<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Industrial Organization</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Industrial Organization</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 11:08:35 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Caught In The Middle: The Bias Against Startup Innovation With Technical And Commercial Challenges</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16862</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andrea Fosfuri, Ashish Arora, Thomas Rønde.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> Startups in IT and life sciences appear to be flourishing. However, startups in other sectors, such as new materials, automation, and eco-innovations, which are often called "deep tech", seem to struggle. We argue that innovations with both technical and commercial challenges, typical of deep tech innovations, are especially disadvantaged in a startup-based innovation system. We develop an analytical model where startups are more efficient at solving technical challenges and incumbents are more efficient at solving commercial challenges. We find that the startup-based system works better for "specialized" innovations, where only one type of challenges is significant. Startups which face both technical and commercial challenges are disadvantaged because they capture a smaller fraction of the value they create. We discuss the implications for various public policies that have been proposed to encourage deep tech.]]></description><author>Andrea Fosfuri, Ashish Arora, Thomas Rønde</author><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16862</guid></item><item><title>Optimal Information Disclosure in Auctions</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16858</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Eyal Winter, Constantine Sorokin, Stephen Morris, Tibor Heumann, Dirk Bergemann.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> We characterize the revenue-maximizing information structure in the second price auction. The seller faces a classic economic trade-off: providing more information improves the efficiency of the allocation but also creates higher information rents for bidders. The information disclosure policy that maximizes the revenue of the seller is to fully reveal low values (where competition will be high) but to pool high values (where competition will be low). The size of the pool is determined by a critical quantile that is independent of the distribution of values and only dependent on the number of bidders. We discuss how this policy provides a rationale for conflation in digital advertising.]]></description><author>Eyal Winter, Constantine Sorokin, Stephen Morris, Tibor Heumann, Dirk Bergemann</author><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16858</guid></item><item><title>Efficient Industrial Policy for Innovation: Standing on the shoulders of Hidden Giants</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16850</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Charlotte Guillard, Dennis Verhoeven, Pierre Mohnen, Catherine Thomas, Ralf Martin.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Research and development is underprovided whenever it creates knowledge spillovers that drive a wedge between its total and private economic returns. Heterogeneity in the intensity of this market failure across technological areas provides an argument to vertically target public support for R&D. This paper examines potential welfare gains of such vertical industrial policy for innovation. It develops measures of private and spillover value of patented innovations using global data on patents and their citations. Our new method identifies a large number `Hidden Giants' - i.e. innovations scoring higher on our new spillover measure than on the traditional forward citation count measure - which are shown to be particularly prevalent among patents applied for by universities. The estimated distributions of private values by technology area are then used to parameterize a structural model of innovation. The model permits estimation of the marginal returns to technology-area-specific subsidies that reduce innovators' R\&D costs. Marginal returns are high when knowledge spillovers in the technology area are valuable, when private innovation costs are low, and when private values in a technology sector are densely distributed around the private cost. The results show large variation in the marginal returns to subsidy and suggest that targeted industrial policy would have helped mitigate underprovision of R\&D over the time period studied. Variation in the extent to which knowledge spillovers are internalized within countries also makes a compelling case for supranational policy coordination, especially among smaller countries.]]></description><author>Charlotte Guillard, Dennis Verhoeven, Pierre Mohnen, Catherine Thomas, Ralf Martin</author><pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16850</guid></item><item><title>Information Choice in Auctions</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16832</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nina Bobkova.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> The choice of an auction mechanism influences which object characteristics bidders learn about and whether the object is allocated efficiently. Some object characteristics are valued equally by all bidders and thus are inconsequential for the efficient allocation. Others matter only to certain bidders, and thus determine the bidder with the highest object value. I show that the efficient auction is the second-price auction: it induces bidders to learn exclusively about object characteristics which matter only to them. An independent private value framework arises endogenously.]]></description><author>Nina Bobkova</author><pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16832</guid></item><item><title>Acquisitions, innovation, and the entrenchment of monopoly</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16826</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michele Polo, Vincenzo Denicolò.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We analyze a dynamic model of repeated innovation where inventors may be acquired by an incumbent or else challenge its leadership. In the short run, acquisitions always spur innovation because of the invention-for-buyout effect. In the long-run, however, acquisitions may stifle innovation because of a countervailing effect, the entrenchment of monopoly. The entrenchment-of-monopoly effect arises when the incumbent's dominance depends on its past activity levels and thus is reinforced by repeated acquisitions over time. We show that if the entrenchment-of-monopoly effect is sufficiently strong, forward-looking policymakers should prohibit acquisitions in the anticipation of their long-run negative impact on innovation. This argument provides a new theory of harm that can be used to block acquisitions that might otherwise go unchallenged.]]></description><author>Michele Polo, Vincenzo Denicolò</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16826</guid></item><item><title>Information, Intermediaries, and International Migration</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Job seekers often face substantial information frictions related to potential job quality. This is especially true in international labor markets, where intermediaries match prospective migrants with employers abroad. We conducted a randomized trial in Indonesia to explore how information about intermediary quality shapes migration choices and outcomes. Information reduces the migration rate, lowering use of low-quality intermediaries. However, workers who migrate receive better pre-departure preparation and have higher-quality job experiences abroad, despite no change in occupation or destination. Information does not change intentions to migrate or beliefs about the return to migration or intermediary quality. Nor does selection explain the improved outcomes for workers who choose to migrate with the information. Together, our findings are consistent with an increase in the option value of search: with better ability to differentiate offer quality, workers become choosier and ultimately have better migration experiences. This offers a new perspective on the importance of information and matching frictions in global labor markets.]]></description><author>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</guid></item><item><title>Keeping the Agents in the Dark: Private Disclosures in Competing Mechanisms</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16807</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alessandro Pavan, Thomas Mariotti, Eloisa Campioni, Andrea Attar.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Abstract N/A]]></description><author>Alessandro Pavan, Thomas Mariotti, Eloisa Campioni, Andrea Attar</author><pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16807</guid></item><item><title>Price-Cost Margins and Fixed Costs</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16796</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Werner Roeger, Jozef Konings, Yannick Bormans, Filip Abraham.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper provides a new method to estimate price-cost margins in the presence of fixed costs of production. We exploit properties of the primal and dual revenue based and cost based Solow residual. Ignoring fixed costs in production underestimates price-cost margins and overestimates excess profit margins. Using a 30 year panel of Belgian firms we estimate price cost margins of 25.9% on average, with fixed costs as a fraction of sales of 23.4%. Fixed costs as well as price-cost margins have declined in the last three decades, pushing excess profit margins close to zero, suggesting competitive markets. The presence of fixed costs implies that price-cost margins might change not only due to a change in firms' market power, but also due to changes in the production process (i.e., the mix between variable and fixed costs) or even due to a combination of both. Our novel methodology is able to distinguish these underlying mechanisms, thereby providing an additional layer of insight to the ongoing academic and policy debate on firms' market power.]]></description><author>Werner Roeger, Jozef Konings, Yannick Bormans, Filip Abraham</author><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16796</guid></item><item><title>Information hierachies</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16790</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Emir Kamenica, Alexander Frankel, Benjamin A Brooks.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> If experiment A is Blackwell more informative than experiment B, it is always possible that A and B are induced by signals A' and B' such that A' is a refinement of B', that is, A' entails observing B' plus some additional information. We first show that this result does not extend beyond pairs of experiments: There exist collections of experiments that cannot be induced by a collection of signals so that whenever two experiments are Blackwell ordered, the associated signals are refinement ordered. In other words, sometimes it is impossible for more informed agents to know everything that less informed agents know. More broadly, define an information hierarchy to be a partially ordered set that ranks experiments in terms of informativeness. Is it the case that for any choice of experiments indexed on the hierarchy such that higher experiments are Blackwell more informative, there are signals that induce these experiments with higher signals being refinements of lower signals? We show that the answers is affirmative if and only if the undirected graph of the information hierarchy is a forest.]]></description><author>Emir Kamenica, Alexander Frankel, Benjamin A Brooks</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16790</guid></item><item><title>Price Dispersion in Wines</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16784</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pierre Regibeau, Olivier Gergaud, Jean-Marie Cardebat, Kate Rockett.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We investigate price dispersion in restaurant sales of wine.  We measure empirically the change in price dispersion as competition varies, finding that price dispersion increases with competition.   We then propose a spatial model capturing the unique features of restaurant dining to explain this empirical regularity.  The model reveals an indirect effect flowing through the price of food, which is announced and known by customers, to the price of wine, which is only revealed once the customer enters the restaurant and receives the wine list.  The results add to the literature on "add ons" and price dispersion in bundled good markets.]]></description><author>Pierre Regibeau, Olivier Gergaud, Jean-Marie Cardebat, Kate Rockett</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16784</guid></item><item><title>Network Externalities and Market Dominance</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16783</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Luis Rayo, Richard Holden, Robert Akerlof.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Many of the largest publicly traded companies--for example, Amazon, Google, and Facebook--operate in "new economy" markets with large network externalities where demand need not be downward sloping and there can be multiple equilibria in demand.  Modeling these increasingly important--but not yet fully understood--markets requires taking a stance on the shape of the demand curve and on when firms will be "in" or "out."  In an attempt to make further progress, we propose a framework with an intuitively-appealing demand curve (which we micro-found) and a new focality concept, based upon level-k thinking, that is both tractable and flexible enough to accommodate heterogeneous consumers.
 Under this focality concept, consumers' "impulses"--or level-0 thinking--determine the level of demand.  We show that firms may compete for the market itself rather than for the marginal consumer, and that a novel form of limit pricing arises in this case.  We characterize how competition changes with firms' technologies, consumers' impulses, and the strength of network externalities, and discuss how our theory informs debates on regulation of the new economy.]]></description><author>Luis Rayo, Richard Holden, Robert Akerlof</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16783</guid></item><item><title>Individual and Collective Information Acquisition: An Experimental Study</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16782</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Wing Suen, Jimmy Chan, Leeat Yariv, Alessandro Lizzeri, Pellumb Reshidi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Many committees---juries, political task forces, etc.---spend time gathering costly information before reaching a decision. We report results from lab experiments focused on such information-collection processes. We consider decisions governed by individuals and groups and compare how voting rules affect outcomes. We also contrast static information collection, as in classical hypothesis testing, with dynamic collection, as in sequential hypothesis testing. Several insights emerge. Static information collection is excessive, and sequential information collection is non-stationary, producing declining decision accuracies over time. Furthermore, groups using majority rule yield especially hasty and inaccurate decisions. Nonetheless, sequential information collection is welfare enhancing relative to static collection, particularly when unanimous rules are used.]]></description><author>Wing Suen, Jimmy Chan, Leeat Yariv, Alessandro Lizzeri, Pellumb Reshidi</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16782</guid></item><item><title>The Welfare Effects of Law Enforcement in the Illegal Money Lending Market</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16779</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christoph Walsh, Nicola Pavanini, Huailu Li, Kaiwen Leong.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We estimate a structural model of borrowing and lending in the illegal money lending market using a unique panel survey of 1,090 borrowers taking out 11,032 loans from loan sharks. We use our model to estimate the welfare effects of a large enforcement crackdown that occurred during our sample period. The crackdown raised interest rates, lowered the volume of loans, and lowered the welfare of borrowers. The welfare of lenders that conduct harassment more frequently fell, but less-harsh lenders gained through the higher interest rates. We compare this strategy to an alternative policy of targeting borrowers. We find that targeting borrowers with medium ability to repay is more effective at lowering lender welfare than targeting those with low or high repayment ability.]]></description><author>Christoph Walsh, Nicola Pavanini, Huailu Li, Kaiwen Leong</author><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16779</guid></item><item><title>Product Market Competition, Creative Destruction and Innovation </title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16763</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John Van Reenen, Rachel Griffith.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> We examine the economic analysis of the relationship between innovation and product market competition. First, we give a brief tour of the intellectual history of the area. Second, we examine how the Aghion-Howitt framework has influenced the development of the literature theoretically and (especially) empirically, with an emphasis on the "inverted U": the idea that innovation rises and then eventually falls as the intensity of competition increases. Thirdly, we look at recent applications and development of the framework in the areas of competition policy, international trade and structural Industrial Organization.]]></description><author>John Van Reenen, Rachel Griffith</author><pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16763</guid></item><item><title>Poor Substitutes? Counterfactual methods in IO and Trade compared</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16762</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Thierry Mayer, Keith Head.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Constant elasticity of substitution (CES) demand for monopolistically competitive firm-varieties is 
a standard  tool for models in international trade and macroeconomics. Inter-variety substitution in this 
model follows a simple share proportionality rule. In contrast, the 
standard toolkit in industrial organization (IO)  estimates a demand system in which cross-elasticities 
depend on similarity in observable attributes. The gain in realism from the IO approach comes at the 
expense of requiring richer data and greater computational challenges. This paper uses the dataset of 
Berry et al. (1995),  who established the modern IO  method, to simulate counterfactual trade policy 
experiments. We use the CES model  as an approximation of the more 
complex underlying demand system and market structure. Although the CES model omits key elements 
of the data generating process, the errors are offsetting, leading to reasonably accurate counterfactual predictions. 
For aggregate outcomes, it turns out that incorporating non-unitary pass-through matters more than fixing 
over-simplified substitution patterns. We do so by extending the commonly used methods of Exact Hat Algebra 
and tariff elasticity estimation to take into account oligopoly.]]></description><author>Thierry Mayer, Keith Head</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16762</guid></item><item><title>Price Authority and Information Sharing with Competing Principals</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16753</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Enrique Andreu, Salvatore Piccolo, Damien J Neven.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> We characterize the degree of price discretion that competing principals award their agents in a
framework where the latter are informed about demand, while the former learn it probabilistically
and may exchange this information on a reciprocal basis. Partial delegation equilibria exist with and
without information sharing and feature binding price caps (list prices) that prevent agents to pass on
their distribution costs to consumers. Yet, these equilibria are more likely to occur with information
sharing than without. Moreover, while principals exchange information when products are sufficiently
differentiated and downstream distribution costs are neither too high nor too low, expected prices are
unambiguously lower with than without information sharing. Finally, we also argue why, and how, an
information-sharing agreement can be implemented by a simple communication protocol according to
which principals disclose their price intentions.]]></description><author>Enrique Andreu, Salvatore Piccolo, Damien J Neven</author><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16753</guid></item></channel></rss>