<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR International Macroeconomics and Finance</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR International Macroeconomics and Finance</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 13:53:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The impact of common law on the volume of legal services: An international study</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16565</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We show that the heavy use of legal services relative to output in the US is not a peculiarity of the country but applies to common law countries in general. It stems largely from better ability to contract and easier access to justice. Yet in close association, common law also offers lawyers potentially more room for rent-Â¬seeking than civil law. Thereby the costs could outweigh the benefits. Both real GDP per capita and openness emerge as further factors making room for lawyers.]]></description><author>Dia, Enzo &amp; Melitz, Jacques</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16565</guid></item><item><title>Exchange Rate Disconnect and the General Equilibrium Puzzle</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16555</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper conducts general equilibrium (GE) estimation to evaluate the empirical contributions of macroeconomic shocks in explaining the exchange rate disconnect, excess volatility, and the uncovered interest parity (UIP) puzzles. We embed stochastic volatilities and limits-to-international arbitrage in a two-country New Keynesian model and estimate the GE system for the US and Euro area using higher-order approximation and full-information Bayesian methods. Assessing the roles of level vs. volatility shocks and linear vs. higher-order approximations, we find that shocks to macroeconomic fundamentals together with their uncertainties can account for a sizable portion-over 40%-of the observed exchange rate variations. Using the GE estimates, we then evaluate whether the fundamental shocks in our model can deliver the UIP relationship observed in the data, and more importantly, whether the results may differ conditionally vs. unconditionally. In line with findings in previous literature, several fundamental shocks individually can indeed generate patterns consistent with data. However, their contributions unconditionally in the GE setting are quantitatively insufficient to resolve the UIP puzzle. The presence of multiple shocks, their potential interactions, and the need for estimators to fit empirical dynamics of all observables beyond just the exchange rate are all likely reasons behind this "General Equilibrium Puzzle," which underscores the importance of GE estimation beyond simulations or partial-equilibrium analyses.]]></description><author>Chen, Yu-Chin &amp; Fujiwara, Ippei &amp; Hirose, Yasuo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16555</guid></item><item><title>On the Benefits of Repaying</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16539</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper studies whether countries benefit from servicing their debts during times of widespread sovereign defaults. Colombia is typically regarded as the only large Latin American country that did not default in the 1980s. Using archival research and formal econometric estimates of Colombia's probability of default, we show that in the early 1980s Colombia's fundamentals were not significantly different from those of the Latin American countries that defaulted on their debts. We also document that the different path chosen by Colombia was due to the authorities' belief that maintaining a good reputation in the international capital market would have substantial long-term payoffs. We show that the case of Colombia is more complex than what is commonly assumed. Although Colombia had to re-profile its debts, high-level political support from the US allowed Colombia do to so outside the standard framework of an IMF program. Our counterfactual analysis shows that in the short to medium run, Colombia benefited from avoiding an explicit default. Specifically, we find that GDP growth in the 1980s was higher than that of a counterfactual in which Colombia behaved like its neighboring countries. We also test whether Colombia's behavior in the 1980s led to long-term reputational benefits. Using an event study based on a large sudden stop, we find no evidence for such long-lasting reputational gains.]]></description><author>Caselli, Francesca &amp; Faralli, Matilde &amp; Manasse, Paolo &amp; Panizza, Ugo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16539</guid></item><item><title>The Aftermath of Debt Surges</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16537</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Debt in emerging market and developing economies (EMDEs) is at its highest level in half a century. In about nine out of 10 EMDEs, debt is higher now than it was in 2010 and, in half of the EMDEs, debt is more than 30 percentage points of gross domestic product higher. Historically, elevated debt levels increased the incidence of debt distress, particularly in EMDEs and particularly when financial market conditions turned less benign. This paper reviews an encompassing menu of options that have, in the past, helped lower debt burdens. Specifically, it examines orthodox options (enhancing growth, fiscal consolidation, privatization, and wealth taxation) and heterodox options (inflation, financial repression, debt default and restructuring). The mix of feasible options depends on country characteristics and the type of debt. However, none of these options comes without political, economic, and social costs. Some options may ultimately be ineffective unless vigorously implemented. Policy reversals in difficult times have been common. The challenges associated with debt reduction raise questions of global governance, including to what extent advanced economies can cast their net wider to cushion prospective shocks to EMDEs.]]></description><author>Kose, Ayhan &amp; Ohnsorge, Franziska &amp; Reinhart, Carmen M. &amp; Rogoff, Kenneth</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16537</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Market Expectations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16520</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Asset prices are a valuable source of information about financial market participants' expectations about key macroeconomic variables. However, the presence of time-varying risk premia requires an adjustment of market prices to obtain the market's rational assessment of future price and policy developments. This paper reviews empirical approaches for recovering market-based expectations. It starts by laying out the two canonical modeling frameworks that form the backbone for estimating risk premia and highlights the proliferation of risk pricing factors that result in a wide range of different asset-price-based expectation measures. It then describes a key methodological innovation to evaluate the empirical plausibility of risk premium estimates and to identify the most accurate market-based expectation measure. The usefulness of this general approach is illustrated for price expectations in the global oil market. Then, the paper provides an overview of the body of empirical evidence for monetary policy and inflation expectations with a special emphasis on market-specific characteristics that complicate the quest for the best possible market-based expectation measure. Finally, it discusses a number of economic applications where market expectations play a key role for evaluating economic models, guiding policy analysis, and deriving shock measures.]]></description><author>Baumeister, Christiane</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16520</guid></item><item><title>Measuring credit procyclicality: a new database</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16519</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Today, the data available to estimate the credit cycle involve a trade-off between country coverage and frequency. In addition, there are pending methodological issues to estimate credit trend and cyclical components. To address these limits, we build a new database on credit metrics that relaxes the trade-off  and includes credit procyclicality measures along three alternative methods- HP filter, the modified HP filter and basic SSA. The credit gaps in our database are statistically consistent with bank credit gaps estimated with BIS data and they have the advantage of being available for 163 countries instead of 43 countries. Armed with this new and expanded data, we revisit classic empirical questions in the literature.]]></description><author>Bouvatier, Vincent &amp; Delatte, Anne-Laure &amp; Rehault, Pierre-Nicolas</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16519</guid></item><item><title>Distrust or speculation? The socioeconomic drivers of U.S. cryptocurrency investments</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16518</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Employing representative data from the U.S. Survey of Consumer Payment Choice, we disprove the hypothesis that cryptocurrency investors are motivatedby distrust in fiat currencies or regulated finance. Compared with the general population, investors show no differences in their level of security concerns with either cash or commercial banking services. We find that cryptocurrency investors tend to be educated, young and digital natives. In recent years, a gap in ownership of cryptocurrencies across genders has emerged. We examine how investor characteristics vary across cryptocurrencies and show that owners of cryptocurrencies increasingly tend to hold their investment for longer periods.]]></description><author>Auer, Raphael &amp; Tercero Lucas, David</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16518</guid></item><item><title>An Equilibrium Theory of Nominal Exchange Rates</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16517</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper proposes an equilibrium theory of nominal exchange rates, which offers a new perspective 
 on various issues in open economy macroeconomics.
 The nominal exchange rate and portfolio choices are jointly determined in equilibrium, 
thus providing a new approach to overcoming the indeterminacy results in Kareken and Wallace (1981).
The distinctive features of this theory are that the nominal exchange rate is determined in international financial markets,
that the risk premium and UIP deviations are fully endogenous equilibrium objects and that the real exchange rate inherits its properties from the nominal exchange rate. 
In terms of policy, this novel theory implies that a country with an exchange rate peg and free asset mobility faces a tetralemma and not a trilemma, because it loses not only monetary policy independence but also fiscal policy independence.]]></description><author>Hagedorn, Marcus</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16517</guid></item><item><title>Growing Apart or Moving Together? Synchronization of Informal and Formal Economy Cycles</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16498</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study the degree of synchronization between formal- and informal-economy business cycles. Using a comprehensive database of informal activity that covers a wide range of informality measures from almost 160 countries over the 1990-2018 period, we report two major results. First, fluctuations in informal-sector output are strongly positively correlated with those in formal-sector output. In contrast, fluctuations in informal employment are largely uncorrelated with those in formal-sector output. Second, movements in the formal economy tend to spillover to the informal economy. Using a novel set of instrumental variables, we show that fluctuations in formal-sector output "cause" movements in informal-sector output.]]></description><author>Elgin, Ceyhun &amp; Kose, Ayhan &amp; Ohnsorge, Franziska &amp; Yu, Shu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16498</guid></item><item><title>Understanding Informality</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16497</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper introduces a comprehensive database of informal economic activity. The database focuses on measures that have strong cross-country and over time coverage: it includes both model-based and survey-based measures of informality and covers more than 160 economies for the period 1990-2018. The paper illustrates two applications of the database. First, it distills stylized facts of informal activity, including its declining trend and pervasiveness in emerging market and developing economies (EMDEs). Second, it documents the cyclical features of the informal economy. Overall, informal economy recessions (recoveries) do not differ significantly from those of formal economy. Like formal-economy business cycles, informal-economy business cycles tend to be shallower in advanced economies than in EMDEs. Informal employment in both advanced economies and EMDEs appears to be largely acyclical.]]></description><author>Elgin, Ceyhun &amp; Kose, Ayhan &amp; Ohnsorge, Franziska &amp; Yu, Shu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16497</guid></item><item><title>A Tale of Two Global Monetary Policies</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16485</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> US monetary policy is not the only one with a global reach. We compare the international financial spillovers of the unconventional monetary policies of the Fed and the ECB. Monetary policy tightenings in both areas are followed by a global retrenchment in capital flows, a fall in global stock markets, and a rise in global risk measures. Thus, ECB and Fed monetary policies propagate internationally through equivalent transmission channels. ECB monetary policy shocks also affect significantly the US business and financial cycles. We produce tentative evidence that links the strength of the ECB international spillovers to the â?¬ exposure for both trade invoicing and the pricing of financial transactions.]]></description><author>Miranda-Agrippino, Silvia &amp; Nenova, Tsvetelina</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16485</guid></item><item><title>Selective Default Expectations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16474</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Sovereign governments often discriminate between creditors during debt default episodes. This paper explores how expectations of selective default affect sovereign bond trading and sovereign risk premia based on a historical laboratory: the German external default of the 1930s. We exploit a unique feature of the interwar sovereign bond market: identical German government bonds were traded on different creditor countries' secondary debt markets but investors expected creditors from various countries to be treated differently in case of default. We show that, when creditor countries' secondary debt markets are integrated, selective default expectations are not reflected in bond yields but affect the volume of bonds traded across markets. By contrast, when creditors' debt markets are geographically segmented, a large selective risk premium can be priced in sovereign bonds. This premium accounted for up to half of the total risk premium on German external bonds during the 1930s. We establish that creditor countries' seniority ranks can be explained by their economic power over the debtor government.]]></description><author>Accominotti, Olivier &amp; Albers, Thilo &amp; Oosterlinck, Kim</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16474</guid></item><item><title>Demographics, Wealth, and Global Imbalances in the Twenty-First Century</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16470</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We use a sufficient statistic approach to quantify the general equilibrium effects of population aging on wealth accumulation, expected asset returns, and global imbalances. Combining population forecasts with household survey data from 25 countries, we measure the compositional effect of aging: how a changing age distribution affects wealth-to-GDP, holding the age profiles of assets and labor income fixed. In a baseline overlapping generations model this statistic, in conjunction with cross-sectional information and two standard macro parameters, pins down general equilibrium outcomes. Since the compositional effect is positive, large, and heterogeneous across countries, our model predicts that population aging will increase wealth-to-GDP ratios, lower asset returns, and widen global imbalances through the twenty-first century. These conclusions extend to a richer model in which bequests, individual savings, and the tax-and-transfer system all respond to demographic change.]]></description><author>Auclert, Adrien &amp; Malmberg, Hannes &amp; Martenet, Frederic &amp; Rognlie, Matthew</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16470</guid></item><item><title>Financial crises: A survey</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16450</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Financial crises have large deleterious effects on economic activity, and as such have been the focus of a large body of research. This study surveys the existing literature on financial crises, exploring how crises are measured, whether they are predictable, and why they are associated with economic contractions. Historical narrative techniques continue to form the backbone for measuring crises, but there have been exciting developments in using quantitative data as well. Crises are predictable with growth in credit and elevated asset prices playing an especially important role; recent research points convincingly to the importance of behavioral biases in explaining such predictability. The negative consequences of a crisis are due to both the crisis itself but also to the imbalances that precede a crisis. Crises do not occur randomly, and, as a result, an understanding of financial crises requires an investigation into the booms that precede them.]]></description><author>Sufi, Amir &amp; Taylor, Alan M.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16450</guid></item><item><title>Sharing Asymmetric Tail Risk: Smoothing, Asset Pricing and Terms of Trade</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16443</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Crises and tail events have asymmetric effects across borders, raising the value of arrangements improving insurance of macroeconomic risk. Using a two-country DSGE model, we provide an analytical and quantitative analysis of the channels through which countries gain from  sharing (tail) risk. Riskier countries gain in smoother consumption but lose in relative wealth and average consumption. Safer countries benefit from higher wealth and better average terms of trade. Calibrated using the empirical distribution of moments of GDP-growth across countries, the model suggests significant quantitative effects. We offer an algorithm for the correct solution of the equilibrium using DSGE models under complete markets, at higher order of approximation.]]></description><author>Corsetti, Giancarlo &amp; Lipinska, Anna &amp; Lombardo, Giovanni</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16443</guid></item><item><title>Ageing and welfare-state policy making: Macroeconomic Perspective</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16442</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> It has been well recognized that population ageing could generate structural changes centered around the dwindling labor force, on one hand, and the expanding dependency on the generosity of the welfare state, on the other hand. Ageing-related welfare state policy entails both fiscal issues and migration issues. The paper employs a general-equilibrium model with a policy-making focus, to help  understand the  mechanism governing the provision of social benefits, labor income taxation, capital income taxation, migration curbs on low skilled and high skilled, driven by the ageing of the  population. Greater generosity of the welfare state comes together with policy of a more liberal migration policy -- incentive compatible with the interests of the majority voters.]]></description><author>Razin, Assaf &amp; Schwemmer, Alexander</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16442</guid></item><item><title>Globalization, Freedoms and Economic Convergence: An empirical exploration of a trivariate relationship using a large panel</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16436</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Using a large panel for 95 countries and the 1972-2014 period, this paper analyses the interactions among globalization, political & civil rights and economic convergence, through a simultaneous estimation technique. We use a multi-dimensional, de facto, and continuous measures of Freedoms and Globalization. We find a two-way positive relationship between civil liberties & political rights and economic, political and social Globalization, as well as significant two-way relationships with the economic convergence (using as a proxy the ratio of GDP per capita to the US). In this way, we extend the test for the two-way relationship between Democracy and Globalization put forward by Eichengreen and Leblang (2008). Overall, we also find a virtuous cycle between Globalization, Freedoms and Economic convergence, except for non-OECD countries at early intermediate stages of development. This positive systemic effect can be put into question by the recent negative shocks on Globalization and Freedoms related to the Covid-19 pandemic.]]></description><author>Braga de Macedo, Jorge &amp; Oliveira Martins, Joaquim &amp; Tovar Jalles, João</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16436</guid></item><item><title>Dash for Dollars</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16415</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Within-firm variation of corporate bond spreads around the Covid-19 outbreak shows that US dollar-denominated bonds experienced larger increases in spreads relative to non-dollar bonds, especially at short maturities. Differently, in the non-dollar sample it was the spreads of longer maturity bonds that widened more markedly. Price pressures arising from a liquidity-driven dash for cash alone cannot rationalize these findings. Instead, the patterns we uncover suggest a `dash for dollars', in which investors sold their dollar-denominated assets first, with a consequent impact on prices. We link these dynamics to the dominant role of the US dollar in the international financial system.]]></description><author>Cesa-Bianchi, Ambrogio &amp; Eguren Martin, Fernando</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16415</guid></item><item><title>The Odious Haitian Independence Debt</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16413</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This article introduces the Haitian Independence Debt of 1825 to the odious debt and sovereign debt literatures. We argue that the legal doctrine of odious debt is surprisingly and perhaps indefensibly narrow possibly because of historical contingency rather than any underlying logic or principle. The story of the Haitian Independence Debt of 1825 serves as an illustrative case study.  In the context of telling that story, we provide estimates of the evolution of Haiti's external debt-to-GDP ratio over 1825-2020, and discuss the implications of the independence debt for the economy of Haiti. We conclude by discussing the implications of Haiti's Independence Debt for the doctrine of odious debt and the possibilities for Haiti to recover compensation.]]></description><author>Gulati, Mitu &amp; Oosterlinck, Kim &amp; Panizza, Ugo &amp; Weidemaier, Mark</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16413</guid></item><item><title>Carbon Taxation and Inflation: Evidence from the European and Canadian Experience</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16396</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> What is the effect of climate policies on inflation and economic activity? Answering this question is critical for central banks trying to achieve price stability. This paper studies the experience from existing Co2 taxes in Canada and Europe, introduced over the last 30 years. Based on two separate empirical approaches, we find that carbon taxes do not have to be inflationary and may even have deflationary effects. In particular, our evidence suggests that the increase in energy prices was more than offset by a fall in the prices of services and other non-tradables. Our results are robust for Europe and Canada, as well as a number of different country groupings. At least in case of British Columbia, a contraction in household incomes and expenditures, in particular among the richer households, could explain the deflationary effect.]]></description><author>Konradt, Maximilian &amp; Weder di Mauro, Beatrice</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16396</guid></item><item><title>Financial 'Side Effects' of QE and Conventional Monetary Policy Compared</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16395</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We explore the size of financial 'side effects' of QE relative to those of conventional monetary policy for the Euro Area, UK and US. Following previous work for conventional monetary policy we examine the effects on private credit imbalances, financial market risk and asset valuation. We adopt an agnostic Bayesian VAR approach, identifying QE and conventional monetary policy shocks with four different identification schemes and two different measures of unconventional monetary policy. We compare the size of each side effect by the amount of inflation generated by each policy, as all three of these central banks were targeting inflation during this time. The relative size of these effects is at the heart of the current debate about the financial stability and wealth inequality consequences of accommodative monetary policy. While both, conventional monetary policy and QE, generate some financial 'side effects', there is no statistical evidence that the effect of QE on these variables is consistently larger than the effect of conventional monetary policy.]]></description><author>Weale, M &amp; Wieladek, Tomasz</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16395</guid></item><item><title>Pricing Ethics in the Foreign Exchange Market: Environmental, Social and Governance Ratings and Currency Premia</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16392</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We examine the cross-sectional predictive ability of the Refinitiv Environmental, Social and Governance (ESG) score for returns in the foreign exchange market, using ESG scores aggregated at the national level, and find that ESG is a strong negative predictor of currency returns. Intuitively, investors require a premium for financing low-ESG countries while high-ESG countries offer lower returns and provide a hedge in the bad state of the world. We show that ESG is priced in the cross-section of currency returns. We also consider the different components of ESG and show that its predictability is driven by the environmental pillar of the ESG ratings. The profitability of the ESG currency strategy is not driven by the carry trade and is robust to transaction costs.]]></description><author>Filippou, Ilias &amp; Taylor, Mark</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16392</guid></item><item><title>Expectations' Anchoring and Inflation Persistence</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16391</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Understanding the sources of inflation persistence is crucial for monetary policy. This paper provides an  assessment of the influence of inflation expectations' anchoring on the persistence of inflation. We construct an index of inflation expectations' anchoring using survey-based inflation forecasts for 45 economies since 1989. We then study the response of consumer prices to terms-of-trade shocks and find that these shocks have a significant and persistent effect on consumer price inflation when expectations are poorly anchored. By contrast, inflation reacts by less and returns quickly to its pre-shock level when expectations are strongly anchored.]]></description><author>Bems, Rudolfs &amp; Caselli, Francesca &amp; Grigoli, Francesco &amp; Gruss, Bertrand</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16391</guid></item><item><title>The Global Capital Market Reconsidered</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16375</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> While the globalization of production has been a prominent target of anti-globalization backlash, globalized finance has seemed to be much less in the public bull's-eye. The blueprint for the postwar international economy agreed at Bretton Woods in 1944 envisioned nothing like today's extensive and fluid global capital market. The demise of the 1946-1973 fixed exchange rate system, however, also brought a progressive dismantling of barriers to international financial flows motivated by special-interest politics, national economic competition, and ideology â?? alongside the benign desire for a more efficient international allocation of capital. Unfortunately, free cross-border financial capital mobility can compromise governments' capacities to attain domestic economic and social goals in several ways. This essay links the dynamics of financial liberalization to the Teflon-like resilience of finance to backlash so far, and suggests that stronger backlash could emerge if national governments fail to enhance multilateral cooperation to manage the financial commons.]]></description><author>Obstfeld, Maurice</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16375</guid></item></channel></rss>