<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR Public Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR Public Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 14:04:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The impact of common law on the volume of legal services: An international study</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16565</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We show that the heavy use of legal services relative to output in the US is not a peculiarity of the country but applies to common law countries in general. It stems largely from better ability to contract and easier access to justice. Yet in close association, common law also offers lawyers potentially more room for rent-Â¬seeking than civil law. Thereby the costs could outweigh the benefits. Both real GDP per capita and openness emerge as further factors making room for lawyers.]]></description><author>Dia, Enzo &amp; Melitz, Jacques</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16565</guid></item><item><title>Complexity and the Reform Process</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16562</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Reform processes commonly involve professional bureaucrats drafting policies to be adopted by political decision makers. Conflicts of interest between these two groups may give rise to pandering in policymaking. We expand the standard pandering setup in two directions. First,  we allow for policies to differ in their complexity. Second, we model the dynamic consequences of reforms, where a complex (simple) policy complexifies (simplifies) the legislative environment in which subsequent policies are drafted. We show that pandering motivates inefficient complex policies, which beget complexity in the legislative environment. We derive conditions under which the complexity build-up is bounded. Stabilization around an intermediate level of complexity is achieved under high uncertainty around the type of policy reform suited to current conditions and around the bureaucracy's capacity to implement it. When complex reforms are expected to be the right ones but bureaucratic capacity is uncertain, the legislative environment may enter a trap of ever increasing complexity.]]></description><author>Foarta, Dana &amp; Morelli, Massimo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16562</guid></item><item><title>The Welfare Economics of Reference Dependence</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16560</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Empirical evidence suggests individuals often evaluate options relative to a reference point, especially seeking to avoid losses. We analyze welfare under reference dependence. We describe how welfare effects of policies depend on normative judgments about whether reference dependence reflects a bias or normative preference. Lowering reference points generally improves welfare, absent countervailing externalities or biases. Conversely, welfare effects of price changes depend strongly on normative judgments. We apply our theory to reference dependence exhibited in German workers' retirement decisions. Our results suggest positive welfare effects of increasing the Normal Retirement Age but ambiguous effects of financial incentives to postpone retirement.]]></description><author>Reck, Daniel &amp; Seibold, Arthur</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16560</guid></item><item><title>Monetary Policy, Labor Income Redistribution and the Credit Channel: Evidence from Matched Employer-Employee and Credit Registers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16549</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper documents the redistributive effects of monetary policy on labor market outcomes via
the credit channel. For identification, we exploit matched administrative datasets in Portugal
- employee-employer and credit registers - and monetary policy since the Eurozone creation
in 1999. We find that softer monetary policy improves worker labor market outcomes (wages,
hours worked and firm employment) more in small and young firms, which are more financially
constrained. Within small and young firms, the wage effects accrue to incumbent workers,
in line with the back-loaded wage mechanism. Consistent with the capital-skill complementarity
mechanism, we document an increase in skill premium and show that financially constrained
firms increase both physical and human capital investment by most. Our findings uncover
a central role for both the firm-balance sheet and the bank lending channels of the monetary
policy transmission to labor income inequality, with state-dependent effects that are substantially
stronger during crisis times. Importantly, we do not find any redistributive effects for firms
without bank credit.]]></description><author>Jasova, Martina &amp; Mendicino, Caterina &amp; Panetti, Ettore &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Supera, Dominik</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16549</guid></item><item><title>The Affordable Care Act After a Decade: Its Impact on the Labor Market and the Macro Economy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16530</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The Affordable Care Act (ACA) is one of the most important reforms of the US health insurance system since the introduction of Medicare. Since employment is a main source of health insurance for the working age population in the United States, this sweeping health insurance reform also has important implications for the labor market and the macro economy. In this paper, we survey the prototype models that are used in the macro and labor literature, extended to integrate health and health insurance, to study the short- and long-run consequences of the ACA. We also suggest open areas for future research.]]></description><author>Fang, Hanming &amp; Krueger, Dirk</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16530</guid></item><item><title>Perceptions of Racial Gaps, their Causes, and Ways to Reduce Them</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16529</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Using new large-scale survey and experimental data, we investigate how respondents perceive racial inequities between Black and white Americans, what they believe causes them, and what interventions, if any, they think should be implemented to reduce them. We intentionally oversample Black respondents, cover many US cities, and survey both adults and young people of ages 13 through 17. In the experimental parts, we consider the causal impact of information on racial inequities (such as the evolution of the Black-white earnings gap or the differences in mobility for Black and white children) and explanations for these inequities (i.e., the deep-seated roots and long-lasting consequences of systemic racism) on respondents' views. Although there is heterogeneity in how respondents perceive the magnitude of current racial gaps in economic conditions and opportunities, the biggest discrepancies are in how they explain them. There is a stark partisan gap among white respondents, particularly in the perceived causes of racial inequities and what should be done about them. White Democrats and Black respondents are much more likely to attribute racial inequities to adverse past and present circumstances and want to act on them with race-targeted and general redistribution policies. White Republicans are more likely to attribute racial gaps to individual actions. These views are already deeply entrenched in teenagers, based on their race and their parents' political affiliation. A policy
decomposition shows that the perceived causes of racial inequities correlate most strongly with support for race-targeted or general redistribution policies, a finding confirmed by the experimental results.]]></description><author>Ferroni, Matteo &amp; Stantcheva, Stefanie</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16529</guid></item><item><title>Shrinking capitalism: Components of a new political economy paradigm</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16515</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The climate emergency, rising inequality, and pandemic diffusion have raised the question: for what purpose is capitalism fit? Implementing new policies and institutions to meet these challenges will require a realignment of political forces on a scale similar to that achieved by neoliberal policies and ideas over the past four decades. We suggest that a successful new paradigm must provide the basis of a dynamic and sustainable economy and be constituted by a synergistic set of ethical commitments, economic models, emblematic policies, and a new vernacular economics by which people understand and seek to improve their livelihoods and futures. We illustrate these four components by reference to the classical liberal, Keynesian-social democratic, and neoliberal paradigms. Using an expanded space for policies and institutions that integrates markets, states, and civil society, we propose elements of a new paradigm, including diminished space for capitalism and greater equality not only of economic endowments but also of dignity and voice.]]></description><author>Bowles, Samuel &amp; Carlin, Wendy</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16515</guid></item><item><title>Expansionary Austerity: Reallocating Credit Amid Fiscal Consolidation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16511</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We show expansionary fiscal austerity via reallocation of credit supply, but with a raise in poverty.
For identification, we exploit the introduction of a Mexican law limiting the debt of subnational
governments along with matched credit register, firm, bank, and state datasets. After the law,
states with higher ex ante public debt grow substantially faster, despite larger fiscal consolidation
(higher taxes and lower public expenditure). Banks operating in more indebted states reallocate
credit supply away from local governments into private firms, with stronger effects for banks with
higher exposure to local public debt, consistent with lowering crowding out. Effects only happen
after the law, not before, and there are strong firm-level real effects associated. The reduction of
crowding out is stronger for financially constrained firms and for firms operating in states with
higher ex ante public spending on social services over infrastructure projects. In states more
affected by the law, despite better economic effects, extreme poverty increases--especially in
states with higher ex ante public spending on social services over infrastructure--consistent with
a strong reduction for social services during the fiscal consolidation.]]></description><author>Morais, Bernardo &amp; Perez-Estrada, Javier &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Ruiz-Ortega, Claudia</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16511</guid></item><item><title>Organizational capacity and profit shifting</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16502</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper analyses the effect of a firm's organizational capacity on the reported profitability of multinational enterprises (MNEs). Better organizational practices improve productivity and the potential taxable profits of firms. However, higher adoption of these practices may also enable more efficient allocation of profits across tax jurisdictions, lowering actual taxable profits. We present new evidence that MNE subsidiaries with better such practices, when located in high-tax countries, report significantly lower profits and have a higher incidence of bunching around zero returns on assets. We show these results are driven by patterns consistent with profit-shifting behavior. Further, using an event study design, we find that firms with better practices are more responsive to corporate tax rate changes. Our results suggest organizational capacity, especially monitoring-related practices, enables firms to engage in shifting profits away from their high-tax subsidiaries.]]></description><author>Bilicka, Katarzyna &amp; Scur, Daniela</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16502</guid></item><item><title>Behavioral Barriers and the Socioeconomic Gap in Child Care Enrollment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16501</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Children with lower socioeconomic status (SES) tend to benefit more from early child care, but are substantially less likely to be enrolled. We study whether reducing behavioral barriers in the application process increases enrollment in child care for lower-SES children. In our RCT in Germany with highly subsidized child care (n > 600), treated families receive application information and personal assistance for applications. For lower-SES families, the treatment increases child care application rates by 21 pp and enrollment rates by 16 pp. Higher-SES families are not affected by the treatment. Thus, alleviating behavioral barriers closes half of the SES gap in early child care enrollment.]]></description><author>Hermes, Henning &amp; Lergetporer, Philipp &amp; Peter, Frauke &amp; Wiederhold, Simon</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16501</guid></item><item><title>Media and Social Capital</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16500</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We survey the empirical literature in economics on the impact of media technologies on social capital. Motivated by a simple model of information and collective action, we cover a range of different outcomes related to social capital, from social and political participation to interpersonal trust, in its benign and destructive manifestations. The impact of media technologies hinges on their content ("information" vs "entertainment"), their effectiveness in fostering coordination, and the networks they create, as well as individual characteristics and media consumption choices]]></description><author>Campante, Filipe &amp; Durante, Ruben &amp; Tesei, Andrea</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16500</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Channel of Wage Rigidity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16499</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> I propose a financial channel of wage rigidity. In recessions, rather than propping up marginal (new hires') costs of labor, rigid average wages squeeze cash flows, forcing firms to cut hiring due to financial constraints. Indeed, empirical cash flows and profits would turn acyclical if wages were only moderately more procyclical. I study this channel in a search and matching model with financial constraints and rigid wages among incumbent workers, while new hires' wages are flexible. Individually, each feature generates no amplification. By contrast, their interaction can account for much of the empirical labor market fluctuations--breaking the neutrality of incumbents' wages for hiring, and showing that financial amplification of business cycles requires wage rigidity.]]></description><author>Schoefer, Benjamin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16499</guid></item><item><title>Countering misinformation with targeted messages: Experimental evidence using mobile phones</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16492</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Widespread misconceptions can be critical, especially in times of crisis. Through a field experiment, we study how to address such wrong or inaccurate beliefs using messages delivered to individual citizens using mobile phones. We focus on misinformation related to the COVID-19 pandemic in a hard-to-reach population â?? India's slum residents. We randomly allocate participants to receive voice and video messages introduced by a local citizen, the messenger, and in which medical practitioners debunk misconceptions. To understand the role of targeting, we randomly vary the signaled religious identity of the messenger into either Muslim or Hindu, guaranteeing exogenous variation in religion concordance between messenger and recipient. Doctor messages are effective at increasing knowledge of, and compliance with, COVID-19 policy guidelines. Changes in misconceptions are observed only when there is religion concordance and mainly for religious-salient misconceptions. Correcting misconceptions with information requires targeting messages to specific populations and tailoring them to individual characteristics.]]></description><author>Armand, Alex &amp; Augsburg, Britta &amp; Bancalari, Antonella &amp; Kameshwara, Kalyan Kumar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16492</guid></item><item><title>Who Cares More? Allocation with Diverse Preference Intensities</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16491</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Goods and services---public housing, medical appointments, schools---are often allocated to individuals who rank them similarly but differ in their preference intensities. We characterize optimal allocation rules when individual preferences are known and when they are not. Several insights emerge. First-best allocations may involve assigning some agents "lotteries" between high- and low-ranked goods. When preference intensities are private information, second-best allocations always involve such lotteries and, crucially, may coincide with first-best allocations. Furthermore, second-best allocations may entail disposal of services. We discuss a market-based alternative and show how it differs.]]></description><author>Ortoleva, Pietro &amp; Safonov, Evgenii &amp; Yariv, Leeat</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16491</guid></item><item><title>Perceived Inequality and Preferences for Redistribution Among High Earners: Do Reference Groups Matter?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16489</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Understanding attitudes towards inequality among the ``working rich" matters for any policy aimed at increasing the level of redistribution in society. We investigate this question using a unique sample of nearly 1,000 graduates from a highly ranked MBA program and a representative sample of Americans. We first show that high-earning MBAs are far more likely to know their rank in the income distribution. We then explore whether and how comparisons with peers or others (i.e. reference groups) shape their preferences for redistribution. Asking them to rank within their family, colleagues or classmates leads to an average 18\% drop in the income share allocated to the richest 1\% but has no discernible effect on their taxation preferences. We discuss the respective contribution of the comparative and normative functions of reference groups as potential mechanisms.]]></description><author>Bellet, Clement &amp; Glover, Dylan &amp; Stabile, Mark</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16489</guid></item><item><title>Stable marriage, household consumption and unobserved match quality</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16483</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We present a methodology for the structural empirical analysis of household consumption and time use behaviour under marital stability. Our approach is of the revealed preference type and non-parametric, meaning that it does not require a prior functional specification of individual utilities. Without making use of the transferable utility assumption, but still allowing for monetary transfers, our method can identify individuals' unobserved match qualities and quantify them in money metric terms. We can include both preference factors, affecting individuals' preferences over private and public goods, and match quality factors, driving differences in unobserved match quality. We demonstrate the practical usefulness of our methodology through an application to the Belgian MEqIn data. Our results reveal intuitive patterns of unobserved match quality that allow us to rationalise both the observed matches and the within-household allocations of time and money.]]></description><author>Browning, Martin &amp; Cherchye, Laurens &amp; De Rock, Bram &amp; Demuynck, Thomas &amp; Vermeulen, Frederic</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16483</guid></item><item><title>Feed the children</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16482</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> To understand the household decision-making process regarding food expenditures for children in poor households in Nairobi, we conduct an experiment with 424 married couples. In the experiment, the spouses (individually and jointly) allocated money between themselves and nutritious meals for one of their children. First, we find strong empirical support for individual rationality and cooperative behavior. Second, our results suggest that women do not have stronger preferences for children's meals than men. Third, the spouses' respective bargaining positions derived from consumption patterns strongly correlate with more traditional indicators. Finally, we document significant heterogeneity both between individuals and intra-household decision processes.]]></description><author>Cherchye, Laurens &amp; Chiappori, Pierre-André &amp; De Rock, Bram &amp; Ringdal, Charlotte &amp; Vermeulen, Frederic</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16482</guid></item><item><title>Cartels and Bribes</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16481</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study the relationship between collusion and corruption in a stylized model of repeated procurement where the cost of reporting corrupt bureaucrats gives rise to a free riding problem. Cooperation among honest suppliers alleviates free-riding in reporting. However, it also facilitates collusion in bidding by increasing the value of the collusive rent. In turn, bidding collusion facilitates cooperation in reporting by increasing the value of having honest bureaucrats, generating a trade-off between collusion and corruption.]]></description><author>Burguet, Roberto &amp; Iossa, Elisabetta &amp; Spagnolo, Giancarlo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16481</guid></item><item><title>Collective Action and Intra-group Conflict with Fixed Budgets</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16472</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study collective action under adverse incentives: each member of the group has a given budget ('use-it-or-lose-it') that is his private information and that can be used for contributions to make the group win a prize and for internal fights about this very prize. Even in the face of such rivalry in resource use, the group often succeeds to overcome the collective action problem in non-cooperative equilibrium. One type of equilibrium has group members who both contribute, the other type has volunteers who make full stand-alone contributions. Both types of equilibrium exist for larger and partially overlapping parameter ranges.]]></description><author>Konrad, Kai A. &amp; Morath, Florian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16472</guid></item><item><title>Let's stay together: the effects of repeated student-teacher matches on academic achievement</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16471</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We explore the effectiveness of repeating the student-teacher match on test scores, for the universe of 8th graders in Chile using information on all student-teacher matches across multiple subjects and years, and a national, anonymous measure of test scores. Also, we exploit a plausibly exogenous source of variation in the process of repeating matches generated by a discontinuity in teacher retention at the legal retirement age. Repeating matches has a robust positive effect on test scores which aggregates up to the student, class, and school-level. As channels, we report a positive effect on attendance, progression, student behaviour and teacher expectations.]]></description><author>Albornoz-Crespo, Facundo &amp; Contreras, David &amp; Upward, Richard</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16471</guid></item><item><title>Local Shocks and Internal Migration: The Disparate Effects of Robots and Chinese Imports in the US</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16460</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Migration has long been considered one of the key mechanisms through which labor markets adjust to economic shocks. In this paper, we analyze the migration response of American workers to two of the most important shocks that hit US manufacturing since the late 1990s - Chinese import competition and the introduction of industrial robots. Exploiting plausibly exogenous variation in exposure across US local labor markets over time, we show that robots caused a sizable reduction in population size, while Chinese imports did not. We rationalize these results in two steps. First, we provide evidence that negative employment spillovers outside manufacturing, caused by robots but not by Chinese imports, are an important mechanism for the different migration responses triggered by the two shocks. Next, we present a model where workers are geographically mobile and compete with either machines or foreign labor in the completion of tasks. The model highlights that two key dimensions along which the shocks differ - the cost savings they provide and the degree of complementarity between directly and indirectly exposed industries - can explain their disparate employment effects outside manufacturing and, in turn, the differential migration response.]]></description><author>Faber, Marius &amp; Sarto, Andres &amp; Tabellini, Marco</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16460</guid></item><item><title>Shifting Punishment on Minorities: Experimental Evidence of Scapegoating</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16453</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper provides experimental evidence showing that members of a majority group systematically shift punishment on innocent members of an ethnic minority.  We develop a new incentivized task, the Punishing the Scapegoat Game, to measure how injustice affecting a member of one's own group shapes punishment of an unrelated bystander ("a scapegoat"). We manipulate the ethnic identity of the scapegoats and study interactions between the majority group and the Roma minority in Slovakia. We find that when no harm is done, there is no evidence of discrimination against the ethnic minority. In contrast, when a member of one's own group is harmed, the punishment "passed" on innocent individuals more than doubles when they are from the minority, as compared to when they are from the dominant group. These results illuminate how individualized tensions can be transformed into a group conflict, dragging minorities into conflicts in a way that is completely unrelated to their behavior.]]></description><author>Želinský, Tomáš &amp; Bauer, Michal &amp; Cahlikova, Jana &amp; Chytilova, Julie &amp; Roland, Gérard</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16453</guid></item><item><title>OECD Pension Reform: it is the business cycle, not the demography!</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16451</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Using a new real-time dataset from Beetsma et al. (2020) containing all pension reform measures in 23 OECD countries between 1970 and 2017, we demonstrate that, in contrast to what one might a priori expect, the timing of pension reform measures coincides with business cycle shocks and not with current or projected demographic shocks. We rationalise this finding using a political-economy model with two-sided adjustment costs to explain a lack of response of pension reform measures to changes in demographic indicators.]]></description><author>Beetsma, Roel &amp; Romp, Ward E</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16451</guid></item><item><title>Corrective Regulation with Imperfect Instruments</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16448</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the optimal design of second-best corrective regulation, when some agents or activities cannot be perfectly regulated. We show that policy elasticities and Pigouvian wedges are sufficient statistics to characterize the marginal welfare impact of regulatory policies in a large class of environments. We show that the optimal second-best policy is determined by a subset of policy elasticities: leakage elasticities, and characterize the marginal value of relaxing regulatory constraints. We apply our results to scenarios with unregulated agents/activities and with uniform regulation across agents/activities. We illustrate our results in several applications.]]></description><author>Davila, Eduardo &amp; Walther, Ansgar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16448</guid></item><item><title>Efficiency and equity in a society-economy integrated model</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16446</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> A model that only focuses on economic relations, and in which efficiency and equity are defined in terms of resource allocation may miss an important part of the picture. We propose an integrated model that embeds economic activities in a larger game of social interactions, and define comprehensive notions of efficiency and equity. Social interactions provide additional sources of inefficiencies and inequalities, including through the mere lack of coordination between the regulation mechanisms of the economic sphere and the social sphere. Remedies may require more than market solutions and redistribution of resources. In particular, social norms are likely to play an important role.]]></description><author>Fleurbaey, Marc &amp; Kanbur, Ravi &amp; Snower, Dennis</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16446</guid></item><item><title>Judging Under Public Pressure</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16427</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Individuals who engage in "judging" - that is, rendering a determination in a dispute or contest between two parties - might be influenced by public pressure to favor one of the parties. Many rules and arrangements seek to insulate such individuals from public pressure or to address the effects of such pressure. We study this subject empirically, investigating the circumstances in which public pressure is more and less likely to affect judging.

Using detailed data from the Bundesliga, Germany's top soccer league, our analysis of how crowd pressure affects the decisions of referees yields two key insights. First, we show that crowd pressure biases referee's decisions in favor of the home team for those decisions that cannot be unambiguously identified as erroneous but not for those decisions that can. In particular, a referee exhibits a bias in favor of the home team with respect to more subjective decisions such as the showing of yellow cards (cautions), which is based on the referee's judgment, but not with respect to more objective decisions such as validating goals and awarding penalty kicks, where live TV coverage often allows for objective identification of errors.

Second, we show that the effect of crowd pressure on referee decisions depends on the extent to which such pressure is viewed by the referee as understandable or reasonable (or even justified). Specifically, a referee's bias in favor of the home team in yellow card issuance is strengthened after the referee makes an objectively identifiable error against the home team and thus might view crowd heckling as understandable. This effect is stronger when the referee's error is costlier to the home team because the game is more important or the error is more consequential due to the closeness of the game at the time of the error.

The introduction of VAR (Video Assistant Referee) technology in 2017 and the restrictions imposed due to Covid-19 pandemic, which caused games to be played without crowds, allow us to test our results under three different regimes (pre-VAR, VAR, and VAR/no-crowd). Inspection of the results under these three different regimes serves to reinforce them. As expected, VAR reduces the number of referee errors, but the pattern of no bias with respect to errors is preserved. VAR has no effect on the number of yellow cards, or on the number of goals. Once the crowd disappears, so does the home advantage in goals. Referee errors are unaffected, but the home bias with respect to yellow cards disappears as well. This confirms the effect that the crowd has on referees' more subjective decisions.]]></description><author>Cohen, Alma</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16427</guid></item><item><title>How to Communicate the Nudge: A Real-World Policy Experiment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16426</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Disclosure-based Nudges are being increasingly utilized by governments around the world to achieve policy goals related to health, safety, employment, environmental protection, retirement savings, credit, debt and more. And, yet, a critical aspect of these Nudge-type policy interventions-the mode of communication-remains unexplored. What is the best way to communicate information to individuals-by letter, by phone call (or voice message), by email, by text message or video message? We begin to answer this basic question using a real-world policy experiment on debt collection procedures. Debtors often lack adequate information about the debt, the judgment, and the enforcement and collection procedures. As a result, the process of debt collection is often harmful to the debtor and ineffective in securing repayment. We conducted a study (N = 36,362), in cooperation with the Israeli Ministry of Justice, to improve communication with debtors and to evaluate the effect of such improved communication strategies on collection procedures and outcomes. A novelty of this study is our focus on the choice of medium-telephone, regular mail, text message and video message-holding fixed the content of the communication. We found that digital communication strategies, specifically communicating via text message, were the most cost-effective, significantly improving outcomes for both debtors and creditors. Our results should inform the choice of communication mediums in the many settings in which disclosure-based Nudge policies are employed.]]></description><author>Bar-Gill, Oren &amp; Cohen, Alma</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16426</guid></item><item><title>Should We Insure Workers or Jobs During Recessions?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16421</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> What is the most efficient way to respond to recessions in the labor market?
To this question, policymakers on both sides of the pond gave two diametrically
opposed answers during the recent crisis. In the US, the focus was on insuring
workers, by aggressively increasing the generosity of unemployment insurance
(UI). In Europe, to the contrary, policies were concentrated on saving job matches,
with the massive use of labor hoarding subsidies through short-time-work (STW)
programs, on which so little is actually known. In this article, we try to understand
who got it right. Building on the vast literature on UI and on a recent stream of
papers on STW, we first provide a framework to determine the relative welfare
effects of STW versus UI. We then show that UI offers more insurance value than
STW, but tends to exhibit larger fiscal externalities, due to moral hazard. We finally
focus on how STW and UI affect labor market equilibrium and how this interacts
with inefficiencies in the labor market. We review recent evidence showing that
STW can be an effective way to reduce socially costly layoffs in recessions. Overall,
we conclude that STW is an important and useful addition to the labor market
policy-toolkit during recessions, with strong and positive complementarities with
UI.]]></description><author>Giupponi, Giulia &amp; Landais, Camille &amp; Lapeyre, Alice</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16421</guid></item><item><title>Retirement Consumption and Pension Design</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16420</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper develops and implements a framework that leverages consumption
data to evaluate the welfare effects of pension reforms. Several countries have reformed
their pension profiles to incentivize later retirement. Using administrative
data in Sweden, we find that such pension reforms entail substantial consumption
smoothing costs. On average, individuals retiring later have higher consumption
levels than those retiring earlier, implying that recent pension reforms redistributed
from low- to high-consumption households. We show that the differences
in retirement consumption are mostly driven by differential changes in consumption
around retirement, and also that the marginal propensities to consume are
the lowest for late retirees. Accounting for selection on health and life expectancy
further increases the redistributive cost of recent reforms. The cost of incentivizing
later retirement is, however, lowest between the early and normal retirement
age, where we document a striking non-monotonicity in consumption levels. We
find similar patterns in consumption data from other countries, including the nonmonotonicity,
suggesting our findings are not unique to Sweden.]]></description><author>Kolsrud, Jonas &amp; Landais, Camille &amp; Reck, Daniel &amp; Spinnewijn, Johannes</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16420</guid></item><item><title>Mothers at Work: How Mandating Paid Maternity Leave Affects Employment, Earnings and Fertility</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16418</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> In July 2005, Switzerland introduced the first federal paid maternity leave mandate, offering 14 weeks of leave with 80% of pre-birth earnings. We study the mandate's impact on women's employment and earnings around the birth of their first child, as well as on their subsequent fertility by exploiting unique, rich administrative data in a difference-in-differences set-up. Women covered by the mandate worked and earned more during pregnancy, and also had temporarily increased job continuity with their pre-birth employer after birth. Estimated effects on other labor market outcomes are small or absent, and all dissipate by five years after birth. The mandate instead persistently increased subsequent fertility: affected women were three percentage points more likely to have a second child in the next nine years. Women living in regions that had greater early child care availability experienced a larger increase in subsequent fertility following the mandate, suggesting that child care complements paid maternity leave in helping women balance work and family.]]></description><author>Lalive, Rafael</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16418</guid></item><item><title>Career Effects of Mental Health</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16401</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This paper investigates the career effects of mental health, focusing on depression,
schizophrenia, and bipolar disorder (BD). Individual-level registry data from Denmark show
that these disorders carry large earnings penalties, ranging from 34 percent for depression and
38 percent for BD to 74 percent for schizophrenia. To investigate the causal effects of mental
health on a person's career, we exploit the approval of lithium as a maintenance treatment for
BD in 1976. Baseline estimates compare career outcomes for people with and without access
in their 20s, the typical age of onset for BD. These estimates show that access to treatment
eliminates one third of the earnings penalty associated with BD and greatly reduces the risks
of low or no earnings. Importantly, access to treatment closes more than half of the disability
risk associated with BD.]]></description><author>Biasi, Barbara &amp; Dahl, Michael S &amp; Moser, Petra</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16401</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Costs of Child Maltreatment in UK</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16397</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Child maltreatment is a major public health problem with significant consequences for individual victims and for society. In this paper we quantify for the first time the economic costs of fatal and non-fatal child maltreatment in the UK in relation to several short-, medium-, and
long-term outcomes ranging from physical and mental health problems, to labour market outcomes and welfare use. We combine novel regression analysis of rich data from the National Child Development Study and the English Longitudinal Study of Ageing with secondary evidence to produce an incidence-based estimate of the lifetime costs of child maltreatment from a societal perspective. The discounted average lifetime incidence cost of non-fatal child maltreatment by a primary caregiver is estimated at Â£89,390 (95% uncertainty interval Â£44,896 to Â£145,508); the largest contributors to this are costs from social care, short-term health and long-term labour market outcomes. The discounted lifetime cost per death from child maltreatment is estimated at Â£940,758, comprising health care and lost productivity costs. Our estimates provide the first comprehensive benchmark to quantify the costs of child maltreatment in the UK and the benefits of interventions aimed at reducing or preventing it.]]></description><author>Conti, Gabriella &amp; Melnychuk, Mariya &amp; Morris, Steve &amp; Pizzo, Elena</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16397</guid></item><item><title>Lobbying Behind the Frontier</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16390</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This chapter investigates the non-market response of firms to international trade shocks increasing the level of competition in U.S. industries. Lobbying expenditures increase as a consequence of import changes related to the China shock. The effect on lobbying is not homogeneous across firms and it concentrates particularly in those producers which are behind the technological frontier. We discuss theoretical mechanisms driving lobbying of firms away from the technological frontier: not only the cost-benefit trade-off between innovation and lobbying is relatively less appealing for low productivity firms, but the collective action ability of low productivity firms improves after a competitive shock.]]></description><author>Bombardini, Matilde &amp; Cutinelli-Rendina, Olimpia &amp; Trebbi, Francesco</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16390</guid></item><item><title>Mandatory Advance Notice of Layoff: Evidence and Efficiency Considerations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16387</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We investigate a prevalent, but understudied, employment protection policy: mandatory advance notice (MN), requiring employers to notify employees of forthcoming layoffs. MN increases future production, as notified workers search on the job, but reduces current production as they supply less effort. Our theoretical model captures this trade-off and predicts that MN improves production efficiency by increasing information sharing, whereas large production losses can be avoided by worker-firm agreements on side-payments â?? severance pay â?? in lieu of MN. We provide evidence of such severance increases in response to an extension of MN using novel Swedish administrative data. We then estimate the production gain of MN: extending the MN period leads to shorter non-employment duration and higher reemployment wages, plausibly driven by on-the-job search. Using variation in notice duration across firms, we estimate the productivity loss of notice. The estimates of benefits and costs suggest that MN has a positive net impact on production, offering an empirically-grounded efficiency argument for mandating notice.]]></description><author>Cederlöf, Jonas &amp; Fredriksson, Peter &amp; Nekoei, Arash &amp; Seim, David</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16387</guid></item><item><title>Teacher Compensation and Structural Inequality: Evidence from Centralized Teacher School Choice in Peru</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16386</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This paper studies how increasing teacher compensation at hard-to-staff schools can reduce inequality in access to qualified teachers. Leveraging an unconditional change in the teacher compensation structure in Peru, we first show causal evidence that increasing salaries at less desirable locations attracts better quality applicants and improves student test scores. We then estimate a model of teacher preferences over local amenities, school characteristics, and wages using geocoded job postings and rich application data from the nationwide centralized teacher assignment system. Our estimated model suggests that the current policy is both ineâ??cient and not large enough to effectively undo the inequality of initial conditions that hard-to-staffâ??schools and their communities face. Counterfactual analyses that incorporate equilibrium sorting effects characterize alternative wage schedules and quantify the cost of reducing structural inequality in the allocation of teacher talent across schools.]]></description><author>Bobba, Matteo &amp; Ederer, Tim &amp; León-Ciliotta, Gianmarco &amp; Neilson, Christopher &amp; Nieddu, Marco</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16386</guid></item><item><title>Machine Learning and Mobile Phone Data Can Improve the Targeting of Humanitarian Assistance</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16385</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic has devastated many low- and middle-income countries (LMICs), causing widespread food insecurity and a sharp decline in living standards. In response to this crisis, governments and humanitarian organizations worldwide have mobilized targeted social assistance programs. Targeting is a central challenge in the administration of these programs: given available data, how does one rapidly identify the individuals and families with the greatest need? This challenge is particularly acute in the large number of LMICs that lack recent and comprehensive data on household income and wealth. Here we show that non-traditional "big" data from satellites and mobile phone networks can improve the targeting of anti-poverty programs. Our approach uses traditional survey-based measures of consumption and wealth to train machine learning algorithms that recognize patterns of poverty in non-traditional data; the trained algorithms are then used to prioritize aid to the poorest regions and mobile subscribers. We evaluate this approach by studying Novissi, Togo's flagship emergency cash transfer program, which used these algorithms to determine eligibility for a rural assistance program that disbursed millions of dollars in COVID-19 relief aid. Our analysis compares outcomes â?? including exclusion errors, total social welfare, and measures of fairness â?? under different targeting regimes. Relative to the geographic targeting options considered by the Government of Togo at the time, the machine learning approach reduces errors of exclusion by 4-21%. Relative to methods that require a comprehensive social registry (a hypothetical exercise; no such registry exists in Togo), the machine learning approach increases exclusion errors by 9-35%. These results highlight the potential for new data sources to contribute to humanitarian response efforts, particularly in crisis settings when traditional data are missing or out of date.]]></description><author>Aiken, Emily &amp; Bellue, Suzanne &amp; Blumenstock, Joshua &amp; Karlan, Dean S. &amp; Udry, Christopher</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16385</guid></item><item><title>Pandemic Lockdown: The Role of Government Commitment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16384</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This paper studies lockdown policy in a dynamic economy without government commitment. Lockdown imposes a cap on labor supply, which improves health prospects at the cost of economic output and consumption. A government would like to commit to the extent of future lockdowns in order to guarantee an economic outlook that supports efficient levels of investment into intermediate inputs. However, such a commitment is not credible, since investments are sunk at the time when the government chooses a lockdown. As a result, lockdown under lack of commitment deviates from the optimal policy. Rules that limit a government's lockdown discretion can improve social welfare, even in the presence of noncontractible information. Quantitatively, lack of commitment causes lockdown to be significantly more severe than is socially optimal. The output and consumption loss due to lack of commitment is greater for higher intermediate input shares, higher discount rates, higher values of life, higher disease transmission rates at and outside of work, and longer vaccine arrival times.]]></description><author>Moser, Christian &amp; Yared, Pierre</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16384</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Pay Gap: Micro Sources and Macro Consequences</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16383</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We document that a large share of the gender pay gap in Brazil is due to women working at lower-paying employers. However, compared with that of men, women's revealed-preference ranking of employers is less increasing in pay. To interpret these facts, we develop an empirical equilibrium search model with endogenous gender differences in pay, amenities, and recruiting intensities across employers. The estimated model suggests that compensating differentials explain one-fifth of the gender pay gap, that there are significant output and welfare gains from eliminating gender differences, and that equal-treatment policies fail to close the gender pay gap.]]></description><author>Morchio, Iacopo &amp; Moser, Christian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16383</guid></item><item><title>Gay Politics Goes Mainstream: Democrats, Republicans, and Same-Sex Relationships</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16382</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Attitudes towards same-sex relationships in the US have changed radically over a
relatively short period of time. After remaining fairly constant for over two decades,
opinions became more favorable starting in 1992 - a presidential election year in which
the Democratic and Republican parties took opposing stands over the status of gay
people in society. What roles did political parties and their leaders play in this process
of cultural change? Using a variety of techniques including machine learning, we show
that the partisan opinion gap emerged substantially prior to 1992 -- in the mid 1980s
-- and did not increase as a result of the political debates in 1992-'93. Furthermore,
we identify people with a college-and-above education as the potential "leaders" of the
process of partisan divergence.]]></description><author>Fernández, Raquel &amp; Parsa, Sahar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16382</guid></item><item><title>Progressive Pensions as an Incentive for Labor Force Participation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16380</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> In this paper, we challenge the conventional idea that an increase in the progressivity of old-age pensions unanimously distorts the labor supply decision of households. So far, the literature has argued that higher pension progressivity leads to more redistribution and insurance provision on the one hand, but increases implicit taxes and therefore distorts labor supply choices on the other. In contrast, we show that a well-designed reform of the pension system has the potential to encourage labor force participation. We propose a progressive pension component linked to the employment decision of households,  which implicitly subsidizes employment of the productivity poor. A simulation analysis in a quantitative stochastic overlapping generations model with productivity and longevity risk indicates that this positive employment effect can be sizable and welfare enhancing.]]></description><author>Kindermann, Fabian &amp; Pueschel, Veronika</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16380</guid></item><item><title>Strategic or Confused Firms? Evidence from &amp;quot;Missing&amp;quot; Transactions in Uganda</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16379</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Are firms sophisticated maximizers, or do they consistently make errors? Using transaction-level data from Ugandan value-added tax (VAT) returns, we show that sellers and buyers report different amounts 79% of the time, despite invoices being easily cross-checked. We estimate that 25% of firms are disadvantageous misreporters-they systematically misreport own sales and purchases such that their tax liability increases-while 75% are advantageous misreporters. Many firms-especially disadvantageous misreporters-fail to report imported inputs they themselves reported at Customs, increasing their VAT liability. On net, unilateral VAT misreporting cost Uganda about US$384 million in foregone 2013-2016 tax revenue.]]></description><author>Almunia, Miguel &amp; Hjort, Jonas &amp; Knebe, Justine &amp; Tian, Lin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16379</guid></item></channel></rss>