<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR &lt;built-in method strip of str object at 0x7f7719148c10&gt;</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR &lt;built-in method strip of str object at 0x7f7719148c10&gt;</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 16:12:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Production Networks and War</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16759</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexey Makarin Vasily Korovkin.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> How do severe shocks such as war alter the economy? We study how a country's production network is affected by a devastating but localized conflict. Using unique transaction-level data on Ukrainian railway shipments, we uncover several novel indirect effects of conflict on firms. First, we document substantial propagation effects on interfirm trade---trade declines even between partners outside the conflict areas if one of them had traded with those areas before the start of the war. The magnitude of such second-degree effect of conflict is one-third of the first-degree effect. Ignoring this propagation would lead to an underestimate of the total impact of conflict on trade by about 67%. Second, war induces sudden changes in the production-network structure that influence firm performance. Specifically, we find that firms that exogenously became more central---after the conflict practically cut off certain regions from the rest of Ukraine---received a relative boost to their revenues and profits. Finally, in a production-network model, we separately estimate the effects of the exogenous firm removal and the subsequent endogenous network adjustment on firm revenue distribution. At the median, network adjustment compensates for 80% of the network-destruction effect a year after the conflict onset.]]></description><author>Alexey Makarin Vasily Korovkin</author><pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16759</guid></item></channel></rss>