<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Macroeconomics and Growth</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Macroeconomics and Growth</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 21:30:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Effects of Automation on Labor Demand: A Survey of the Recent Literature</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16868</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Xavier Jaravel, Simon Bunel, Céline Antonin, Philippe Aghion.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> In this article, we survey the recent literature and discuss two contrasting views on the impacts of automation on labor demand. A first view predicts that firms that automate reduce employment, even if this may ultimately result in job creations taking advantage of the lower equilibrium wage induced by job destructions. A second approach emphasizes the market size and business stealing effects of automation. Automating firms become more productive, which enables them to lower their quality-adjusted prices, and therefore to increase the demand for their products. The resulting increase in scale translates into higher employment by automating firms, potentially at the expense of their competitors through business stealing. Drawing from our empirical work on French firm-level data and a growing literature covering multiple countries, we provide empirical support for this second view: automation has a positive effect on labor demand at the firm level, which remains positive at the industry level as it is not fully offset by business stealing effects. We discuss the implications of these results for the taxation of automation technologies such as robots.]]></description><author>Xavier Jaravel, Simon Bunel, Céline Antonin, Philippe Aghion</author><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16868</guid></item><item><title>Inequality and Creative Destruction</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16867</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Otto Toivanen, Xavier Jaravel, Richard William Blundell.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> In this article we review recent evidence showing how market forces and policies shape the rate and direction of innovation, with various implications for inequality. First, we characterize several market mechanisms whereby higher rates of innovation lead to higher inequality. Second, we highlight channels whereby inequality acts as an impediment to innovation and growth. Third, we highlight policies that can help achieve better outcomes for both innovation and inequality. We show that two types of policies, which are not traditionally viewed as part of innovation policy, play a key role to achieve the goal of enhancing innovation while reducing inequality: education and competition policy.]]></description><author>Otto Toivanen, Xavier Jaravel, Richard William Blundell</author><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16867</guid></item><item><title>Nonparametric Measurement of Long-Run Growth in Consumer Welfare</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16866</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Danial Lashkari, Xavier Jaravel.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> How should we measure long-run changes in consumer welfare? This paper proposes a
nonparametric approach with arbitrary observable preference heterogeneity, e.g. when expenditure
shares vary with income. Our approach only requires data on the consumption
baskets of a cross-section of consumers facing a common set of prices. We take nominal expenditures
under a constant set of prices as our money-metric for real consumption (welfare),
and we derive a consistent measure of its growth in terms of a correction to the conventional
quantity indices. Our correction accounts for the cross-sectional dependence of price indices
on consumer income and any obserable source of preference heterogeneity. We use
nonparametric methods to approximate these corrections and provide bounds on the resulting
approximation errors that hold under arbitrary underlying preferences. Applying our
methodology to the measurement of growth in real consumption per capita in the United
States, we find a sizable correction to standard measures of growth in the postwar eraâ??a period
of fast growth combined with substantial inflation gaps across income groups]]></description><author>Danial Lashkari, Xavier Jaravel</author><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16866</guid></item><item><title>Labor Share, Markups, and Input-Output Linkages - Evidence from the National Accounts</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16857</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin Bridgman, Berthold Herrendorf.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> The literature has suggested so many reasons for the decrease in the aggregate labor share that together they "explain" a multiple of the overall decrease [Grossman and Oberfield (2021)].  We study key causal forces and amplifying and offsetting effects in a multi-sector model with input-output linkages.  We find that the decrease in the U.S. labor share reflects both sectoral forces, which can be identified with micro or NIPA data, and aggregation effects, which can be identified only with NIPA data.  Specifically, the main force behind the decrease in the labor share was a similar increase in sectoral markups, which input-output linkages amplified importantly.]]></description><author>Benjamin Bridgman, Berthold Herrendorf</author><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16857</guid></item><item><title>Occupational Choice and the Intergenerational Mobility of Welfare</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16854</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Danial Lashkari, Corina Boar.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> Based on responses in the General Social Survey, we construct an index that captures non-monetary qualities of occupations, such as respect, learning, and work hazards, relevant to the well-being of workers. Using the Panel Study of Income Dynamics and National Longitudinal Survey of Youth data, we document that the children of richer US parents are more likely to select into occupations that rank higher in terms of this index. We rationalize this fact by introducing occupational choice with preferences over the intrinsic qualities of occupations into a standard theory of intergenerational mobility. Estimating the model allows us to infer the equivalent monetary compensation each worker receives from the intrinsic qualities of their chosen occupation. Earnings adjusted to reflect this additional compensation show substantially larger persistence of income from parents to children. Our model further predicts that the trends in the composition of labor demand in the US over the past three decades decreased intergenerational persistence, and also led to higher growth in the welfare of the average worker than that implied by observed earnings.]]></description><author>Danial Lashkari, Corina Boar</author><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16854</guid></item><item><title>Discovering the True Schumpeter - New Insights into the Finance and Growth Nexus</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16851</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Fabian Mayer, Thomas Haas, Lisa Geißendörfer, Peter Bofinger.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Joseph A. Schumpeter is one of the most famous economists of the 20th century and the 'patron saint' of the finance and growth literature. We have discovered that the prevailing literature has, however, misinterpreted Schumpeter, which leads to puzzling empirical results and difficulties in explaining even fundamental relationships. We argue that this is due to a misrepresentation of the role of banks and liquidity creation and the role of household saving. After a critical discussion of the literature, we provide our own empirical analysis using a panel of 43 countries to explore the relationships between the important variables of the finance and growth literature. Our empirical analysis above all supports Schumpeter's view that credit growth supports GDP growth while saving is irrelevant for credit growth and GDP growth. In sum, a correct interpretation of Schumpeter helps to overcome the theoretical and empirical challenges which confront the prevailing literature.]]></description><author>Fabian Mayer, Thomas Haas, Lisa Geißendörfer, Peter Bofinger</author><pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16851</guid></item><item><title>Before the Dawn: English Medieval Living Standards and Economic Growth 1200-1800</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16847</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Maximilian P McComb, Gregory Clark.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> If pre-industrial England was a Malthusian society, we should observe trendless living standards before 1800. Recent studies have claimed major gains in living standards 1270-1800 in northwest Europe, including England, implying the Malthusian era there had ended before 1350. Here we examine the claim that medieval English living standards were significantly lower than in 1800 using a variety of new metrics: human heights, measures of housing quality, the character of food consumption, the share of wages paid in food when workers were fed at work, and factor shares in agriculture. These all show the continued viability of the Malthusian interpretation: the medieval world was often richer than England of 1800.]]></description><author>Maximilian P McComb, Gregory Clark</author><pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16847</guid></item><item><title>Consolidating the Covid Debt</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16846</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jacob Stevens, Julian Johs, Christian Keuschnigg.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> One of the main functions of public debt is to smooth taxes and spending over time. In the Covid crisis, the Maastricht deficit restrictions were temporarily suspended to allow for large temporary deficits. As recovery sets in, countries are confronted with the task of consolidating the Covid debt. This paper explores a fiscal consolidation strategy combined with growth enhancing tax and expenditure reform. We quantitatively illustrate that this reform based strategy, by reaping substantial efficiency gains and inducing strong growth, eliminates the Covid debt, protects per capita social entitlements and yet avoids increasing tax rates. With slow consolidation, marginal tax rates are reduced right from the beginning.]]></description><author>Jacob Stevens, Julian Johs, Christian Keuschnigg</author><pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16846</guid></item><item><title>Women's Liberation, Household Revolution</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16838</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hosny Zoabi, David Weiss, Moshe Hazan.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> How does women's empowerment affect fertility and children's education? In a dramatic revolution, U.S. states gave economic rights to married women between 1850-1920. Prior to this "women's liberation," married women were subject to the laws of coverture, which granted the husband virtually unlimited power of the purse within the household. Women's legal identities were subsumed (or covered) by their husbands. We show that granting women economic rights led to less fertility and more education. We employ an event study using the full count U.S. census and contiguous county-border pairs in bordering states that gave rights at different times. Additionally, rights were not retroactive, implying differences between those married before/after reforms. This alternative identification strategy confirms our findings and illuminates mechanisms. Quantitatively, women's empowerment can account for 15% (20%) of the decline (increase) in fertility (education) during the U.S. demographic transition. We find that shifting bargaining power accounts for these results with the underlying spousal disagreement relating to maternal mortality risk. Wealthier families decreased their fertility by more than other families, consistent with the notion that differences in control over wealth are responsible for our results. Articles from the New York Times confirm that people were aware of the implications of the legal changes. We provide evidence to negate mechanisms besides bargaining power shifts to explain our findings. Considering that the U.S. was a developing country at the time, our findings may be relevant for policy in developing countries today, where maternal mortality is still high and women are economically disadvantaged.]]></description><author>Hosny Zoabi, David Weiss, Moshe Hazan</author><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16838</guid></item><item><title>Minimum Wages and Insurance within the Firm</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16823</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Emircan Yurdagul, Omar Rachedi, Francesco Manaresi, Effrosyni Adamopoulou.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Minimum wages alter the allocation of firm-idiosyncratic risk across workers. To establish this result, we focus on Italy, and leverage employer-employee data matched to firm balance sheets and hand-collected wage floors.  We find a relatively larger pass-through of firm-specific labor-demand shocks into wages for the workers whose earnings are far from the floors, but who are employed by establishments intensive in minimum-wage workers. We study the welfare implications of this fact using an incomplete-market model. The asymmetric pass-through uncovers a novel channel which tilts the benefits of removing minimum wages toward high-paid employees at the expense of low-wage workers.]]></description><author>Emircan Yurdagul, Omar Rachedi, Francesco Manaresi, Effrosyni Adamopoulou</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16823</guid></item><item><title>Cities and Technological Waves</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16794</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruben Gaetani, Enrico Berkes, Martí Mestieri.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We develop a spatial model of economic growth to study the effect of changes in the technological landscape on the spatial distribution of economic activity. We use this framework to study the evolution of the U.S. economic geography over the twentieth century. In the model, innovation via frictional idea diffusion makes cities trajectories sensitive to "technological waves," defined as long-term shifts in the importance of different knowledge fields. We calibrate the model using a new dataset of historical geolocated patents, and find that cities differential exposure to technological waves explains between 15% and 20% of the variation in local population growth over the twentieth century. Counterfactual experiments suggest large and heterogeneous geographical effects of future technological scenarios.]]></description><author>Ruben Gaetani, Enrico Berkes, Martí Mestieri</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16794</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Origins of Non-Fundamental Risk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16793</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sanjay R. Singh, Keshav Dogra, Sushant Acharya.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We formalize the idea that the financial sector can be a source of non-fundamental risk. Households' desire to hedge against price volatility can generate price volatility in equilibrium, even absent fundamental risk. Fearing that asset prices may fall, risk-averse households demand safe assets from leveraged intermediaries, whose issuance of safe assets exposes the economy to self-fulfilling fire sales. Policy can eliminate non-fundamental risk by (i) increasing the supply of publicly backed safe assets, through issuing government debt or bailing out intermediaries, or (ii) reducing the demand for safe assets, through social insurance or by acting as a market maker of last resort.]]></description><author>Sanjay R. Singh, Keshav Dogra, Sushant Acharya</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16793</guid></item><item><title>Time Use and Gender in Africa in Times of Structural Transformation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16792</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Liwa Rachel Ngai, Taryn Dinkelman.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Many African countries are still in the early stages of structural transformation. Typically, as economies move through the structural transformation, activities once conducted within the household are outsourced to the market. This has particular implications for women's time use. In this paper, we document that current patterns of female time use in home production in several African countries closely resemble historical time use patterns in the US. We highlight two stylized facts about women's time use in Africa. First, in North Africa, women spend very few hours in market work and female labor force participation overall is extremely low. Second, although extensive margin participation of women is high in sub-Saharan Africa, women tend to work in the market for only a few hours each week, with the rest of their work hours spent in home production. These two facts suggest two types of constraints that could slow down the reallocation of female
time from home to market as economies grow: Social norms related to women's market work, and a lack of infrastructure (e.g. household infrastructure and childcare facilities) to facilitate marketizing home production. We discuss recent empirical evidence related to each set of constraints and highlight new avenues for research.]]></description><author>Liwa Rachel Ngai, Taryn Dinkelman</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16792</guid></item><item><title>Larger transfers financed with more progressive taxes? On the optimal design of taxes and transfers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16781</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Oliko Vardishvili, Gaston  Navarro, Philipp Grübener, Axelle Ferriere.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study the optimal joint design of targeted transfers and progressive income taxes. We develop a simple analytical model and demonstrate an optimally negative relation between transfers and income-tax progressivity, due to both efficiency and redistribution concerns. That is, higher transfers should be financed with lower income-tax progressivity. We next quantify the optimal fiscal plan in a rich dynamic model calibrated to the U.S. economy. Transfers should be generous and financed with moderate income-tax progressivity. To redistribute while preserving efficiency, average tax-and-transfer rates should be more progressive than marginal rates. Transfers, even if lump-sum, precisely allow to disentangle average from marginal rates. Targeted transfers further implement non-monotonic marginal rates, but generate only modest additional gains relative to a lump-sum transfer. Quantitatively, the left tail of the income distribution determines the optimal size of the transfer, while the right tail drives the optimal income-tax progressivity.]]></description><author>Oliko Vardishvili, Gaston  Navarro, Philipp Grübener, Axelle Ferriere</author><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16781</guid></item><item><title>Adams and Eves: The Gender Gap in Economics Majors</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16767</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marina Murat, Luca Bonacini, Graziella Bertocchi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the gender gap in Economics among bachelor's and master's graduates in Italy between 2010 and 2019. First we establish that being female exerts a negative impact on the choice to major in Economics: at the bachelor level, only 73 women graduate in Economics for every 100 men, with the mathematical content of high school curricula as the key driver of the effect and a persistence of the gap at the master level. Second, within a full menu of major choices, Economics displays the largest gap, followed by STEM and then Business Economics. Third, decomposition analyses expose a unique role for the math background in driving the Economics gender gap relative to other fields. Fourth, a triple difference analysis of a high school reform shows that an increase in the math content of traditionally low math curricula caused an increase in the Economics gender gap among treated students.]]></description><author>Marina Murat, Luca Bonacini, Graziella Bertocchi</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16767</guid></item></channel></rss>