<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR &lt;built-in method strip of str object at 0x7f771914f2d0&gt;</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR &lt;built-in method strip of str object at 0x7f771914f2d0&gt;</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 16:12:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Poor Substitutes? Counterfactual methods in IO and Trade compared</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16762</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Thierry Mayer Keith Head.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Constant elasticity of substitution (CES) demand for monopolistically competitive firm-varieties is 
a standard  tool for models in international trade and macroeconomics. Inter-variety substitution in this 
model follows a simple share proportionality rule. In contrast, the 
standard toolkit in industrial organization (IO)  estimates a demand system in which cross-elasticities 
depend on similarity in observable attributes. The gain in realism from the IO approach comes at the 
expense of requiring richer data and greater computational challenges. This paper uses the dataset of 
Berry et al. (1995),  who established the modern IO  method, to simulate counterfactual trade policy 
experiments. We use the CES model  as an approximation of the more 
complex underlying demand system and market structure. Although the CES model omits key elements 
of the data generating process, the errors are offsetting, leading to reasonably accurate counterfactual predictions. 
For aggregate outcomes, it turns out that incorporating non-unitary pass-through matters more than fixing 
over-simplified substitution patterns. We do so by extending the commonly used methods of Exact Hat Algebra 
and tariff elasticity estimation to take into account oligopoly.]]></description><author>Thierry Mayer Keith Head</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16762</guid></item></channel></rss>