<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Financial Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Financial Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 10:48:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Macro-financial policy in an international financial centre: the United Kingdom experience since the global financial crisis</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16860</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rhiannon Sowerbutts, Dennis Reinhardt, Simon Lloyd, Thorsten Beck.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> We describe the macroprudential and monetary policy environment in the United Kingdom (UK). We highlight the UK's position as an international financial centre, and the implications for inward and outward spillover effects of monetary and prudential policy actions. These spillovers pose particular opportunities and challenges for policymakers, and we explain how they have motivated specific developments to the Bank of England's modelling framework. We also present novel empirical evidence that monetary policy actions in the UK have outward spillover effects through cross-border lending that can, in part, be mitigated by macroprudential actions in receiving countries.]]></description><author>Rhiannon Sowerbutts, Dennis Reinhardt, Simon Lloyd, Thorsten Beck</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16860</guid></item><item><title>The Purpose of a Finance Professor</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16845</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alex Edmans.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> The academic finance profession has the potential to be uniquely purposeful due to four characteristics â?? the freedom to take risks and work on what we're passionate about, the loyalty to our profession rather than just our institution, the collaborative nature of the creation and dissemination of knowledge, and the magnitude of our potential impact. However, what the profession currently values, and its current social norms, are significant barriers to the fulfilment of this potential. This article highlights the special features of our profession that we often take for granted and ignore, and proposes ideas to make it not only more impactful and relevant, but also more collegial and fun.]]></description><author>Alex Edmans</author><pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16845</guid></item><item><title>Creditor Rights, Implicit Covenants, and the Quality of Accounting Information</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16844</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yishay Yafeh, Nadav Steinberg, Ruth Rooz, Yevgeny Mugerman, Assaf Hamdani.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study a 2013 court decision that enhanced creditor control rights in Israeli firms by allowing them to force companies into bankruptcy. We find that the market expected the court ruling to benefit creditors: bond (equity) prices of companies affected by the new rule responded positively (negatively). We attribute this to the ability of creditors to initiate bankruptcy procedures earlier than in the period before the court ruling. We also observe a pronounced increase in the reported net worth of the firms affected by the new rule. We find evidence suggesting that some firms affected by the new rule increased their net worth by raising more equity. We also find, however, that firms changed their accounting practices, as reflected by an increase in long-term discretionary accruals and a decrease in accounting conservatism. As a result of these accounting changes, we document a decline in the informativeness of the treated firms' financial reports. We conclude that the benefits from creditor control rights may be mitigated by unintended consequences in the form of increased incentives for firms to adopt aggressive accounting practices and, as a result, a reduction in the informativeness of firms' financial reporting.]]></description><author>Yishay Yafeh, Nadav Steinberg, Ruth Rooz, Yevgeny Mugerman, Assaf Hamdani</author><pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16844</guid></item><item><title>Banking Regulation (Long) before Basel: Evidence from Discount Limits at the Austro-Hungarian Bank</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16841</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clemens Jobst, Kilian Rieder.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We show that central banks used credit limits for discount window loans as a means to enforce supervisory standards at a time when they had no formal regulatory powers. Drawing on novel micro data from the Austro-Hungarian Bank's archives, we document that credit limits were binding in normal times and that their size was contingent on counterparties' liquidity and capital position. We also exploit the heterogeneous exposure of counterparties to an exogenous liquidity shock to evidence that the Bank relaxed credit limits during crises to fulfill its role as a lender of last resort.]]></description><author>Clemens Jobst, Kilian Rieder</author><pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16841</guid></item><item><title>Investment and Contagion Tradeoffs between Fair Value and Historical Cost  Accounting</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16835</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rangarajan K Sundaram, Saptarshi Mukherjee, Viral Acharya.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We examine the effects of fair-value accounting (FVA) and historical-cost accounting (HCA) regimes on the ex-ante financing of projects by external investors. We formulate a model highlighting the relative merits and demerits of each accounting regime, in particular the sub-optimal continuations under the HCA regime and contagion-induced sub-optimal liquidations under the FVA regime. We show that
under homogeneous beliefs about future cash-flows, FVA regime is superior with greater ex-ante financing, even during periods of high market illiquidity, when the failure of some banks leads to adverse spillovers on surviving financial institutions. However, if disclosures under the FVA regime leads to distorted beliefs about future success probabilities, ex-ante financing may suffer under the FVA regime, and
it may no longer be superior relative to the HCA regime. In this setting we also analyze the impact on ex-ante financing of (i) ex-post redemption gates, which restrict the extent of investor liquidation under stress, and (ii) government guarantees, which limit the spillovers ex post but may incentivize excessive risk-taking ex ante.]]></description><author>Rangarajan K Sundaram, Saptarshi Mukherjee, Viral Acharya</author><pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16835</guid></item><item><title>A Wake-Up Call Theory of Contagion</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16809</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christoph Bertsch, Toni Ahnert.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We offer a theory of financial contagion based on the information choice of investors after observing a financial crisis elsewhere. We study global coordination games of regime change in two regions linked by an initially unobserved macro shock. A crisis in region 1 is a wake-up
call to investors in region 2. It induces them to reassess the regional fundamental and acquire information about the macro shock. Contagion can occur even after investors learn that region 2 has no ex-post exposure to region 1. We explore normative and testable implications of
the model. In particular, our results rationalize evidence about contagious currency crises and bank runs after wake-up calls and provide some guidance for future empirical work.]]></description><author>Christoph Bertsch, Toni Ahnert</author><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16809</guid></item><item><title>Superstar Returns</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16806</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Moritz Schularick, Martin Dohmen, Sebastian Kohl, Francisco Amaral.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study long-term returns on residential real estate in 27 "superstar" cities in 15 countries over 150 years. We find that total returns in superstar cities are close to 100 basis points lower per year than in the rest of the country. House prices tend to grow faster in the superstars, but rent returns are substantially greater outside the big agglomerations, resulting in higher long-run total returns. The excess returns outside the superstars can be rationalized as a compensation for risk, especially for higher co-variance with income growth and lower liquidity. Superstar real estate is comparatively safe.]]></description><author>Moritz Schularick, Martin Dohmen, Sebastian Kohl, Francisco Amaral</author><pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16806</guid></item><item><title>Skewness and Time-Varying Second Moments in a Nonlinear Production Network: Theory and Evidence</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16804</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andrea Vedolin, Alireza Tahbaz-Salehi, Ian Dew-Becker.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies asymmetry in economic activity over the business cycle. It develops a tractable multisector model of the economy in which complementarity across inputs causes aggregate activity to be left skewed with countercyclical volatility. We then examine implications of the model regarding the time-series skewness of activity at the sector level, cyclicality of dispersion and skewness across sectors, and the conditional covariances of sector growth rates, finding support for each in the data. The empirical skewness of employment growth, industrial production growth, and stock returns increases with the level of aggregation, which is consistent with the model's implication that it is the nonlinearity in the production structure of the economy that generates the skewness. Other prominent models of asymmetry are not able to simultaneously match the range of empirical facts that the production network model can.]]></description><author>Andrea Vedolin, Alireza Tahbaz-Salehi, Ian Dew-Becker</author><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16804</guid></item><item><title>The Real Effects of Banking the Poor: Evidence from Brazil</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16798</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Matray, Julia Fonseca.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We use a large expansion of government-owned banks in cities with extremely low bank branch coverage and data on the universe of formal-sector employees in Brazil over 2000-2014 to study how financial development affects economic development and wage inequality. We find that higher financial development fosters firm creation and firm expansion, which increases labor demand and leads to higher average wages, especially for cities initially located in banking deserts. The gains produced by higher financial development are not shared equally, but instead monotonically increase with workers' productivity, which leads to a substantial increase in inequality. This increase is concentrated in cities where the initial supply of skilled workers is low, showing that talent scarcity is an important driver of how financial development affects inequality.]]></description><author>Adrien Matray, Julia Fonseca</author><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16798</guid></item><item><title>The Premia on State-Contingent Sovereign Debt Instruments</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16795</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Antoine Levy, Taehoon Kim, Deniz Igan.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> State-contingent debt instruments such as GDP-linked warrants have garnered attention as a potential tool to help debt-stressed economies smooth repayments over business cycles, yet very few studies of the empirical properties of these instruments exist. This paper develops a general framework to estimate the time-varying risk premium of a state-contingent sovereign debt instrument. Our estimation framework applied to GDP-linked warrants issued by Argentina, Greece, and Ukraine reveals three stylized facts: (i) the risk premium in state-contingent
instruments is high and persistent; (ii) the risk premium exhibits a pro-cyclical pattern; and (iii) the liquidity premium is higher and more volatile than that for plain-vanilla government bonds issued by the same sovereign. We then present a model in which investors fear ambiguity and that can account for the cyclical properties of the risk premium.]]></description><author>Antoine Levy, Taehoon Kim, Deniz Igan</author><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16795</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Origins of Non-Fundamental Risk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16793</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sanjay R. Singh, Keshav Dogra, Sushant Acharya.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We formalize the idea that the financial sector can be a source of non-fundamental risk. Households' desire to hedge against price volatility can generate price volatility in equilibrium, even absent fundamental risk. Fearing that asset prices may fall, risk-averse households demand safe assets from leveraged intermediaries, whose issuance of safe assets exposes the economy to self-fulfilling fire sales. Policy can eliminate non-fundamental risk by (i) increasing the supply of publicly backed safe assets, through issuing government debt or bailing out intermediaries, or (ii) reducing the demand for safe assets, through social insurance or by acting as a market maker of last resort.]]></description><author>Sanjay R. Singh, Keshav Dogra, Sushant Acharya</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16793</guid></item><item><title>The Welfare Effects of Law Enforcement in the Illegal Money Lending Market</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16779</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christoph Walsh, Nicola Pavanini, Huailu Li, Kaiwen Leong.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We estimate a structural model of borrowing and lending in the illegal money lending market using a unique panel survey of 1,090 borrowers taking out 11,032 loans from loan sharks. We use our model to estimate the welfare effects of a large enforcement crackdown that occurred during our sample period. The crackdown raised interest rates, lowered the volume of loans, and lowered the welfare of borrowers. The welfare of lenders that conduct harassment more frequently fell, but less-harsh lenders gained through the higher interest rates. We compare this strategy to an alternative policy of targeting borrowers. We find that targeting borrowers with medium ability to repay is more effective at lowering lender welfare than targeting those with low or high repayment ability.]]></description><author>Christoph Walsh, Nicola Pavanini, Huailu Li, Kaiwen Leong</author><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16779</guid></item><item><title>Carbon Emissions and the Bank-Lending Channel</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16778</link><description><![CDATA[<i>José Luis Peydró, Marcin Kacperczyk.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study how firm-level carbon emissions affect bank lending and, through this channel, real, financial, and environmental outcomes in a sample of global firms with syndicated loans. For identification, we use bank-level commitments to carbon neutrality to proxy for changes in banks' green preferences and, via these bank commitments, shocks to firms with previous credit from these banks. We find that firms with higher (lower) scope-1 emission levels previously borrowing from banks making commitments subsequently receive less (more) total bank credit. The economic mechanism at play is bank credit supply, and results are consistent with bank preferences for green rather than differential response to an increased firm risk. The reduction in bank lending to brown firms triggers the reduction in these firms' total debt, leverage, total assets, and real investments. The effects are non-linear, with a strong cut (increase) in lending and investments for brown (green) firms, and mild effects for other firms. Despite the real and financial effects, we find no improvement in hard firm-level environmental scores for brown firms, but only evidence consistent with firms' greenwashing. Overall, our results suggest that banks affect carbon emissions via credit reallocation (from brown to green firms) rather than via providing loans to brown firms for the investment necessary to reduce carbon emissions.]]></description><author>José Luis Peydró, Marcin Kacperczyk</author><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16778</guid></item><item><title>Identifying Empty Creditors with a Shock and Micro-Data</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16773</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Steven Ongena, Kuchulain O'Flynn, Yalin Gündüz, Hans Degryse.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Firms with credit-default swaps (CDS) traded on their debt may face "empty creditors" as hedged creditors have less incentive to participate in firm restructuring. We test for the existence of empty creditors by employing an exogenous change to the bankruptcy code in Germany that effectively removes their potential impact on CDS firms. Using a unique dataset on bank-firm CDS net notional and credit exposures we find that the probability of default for CDS firms drops when the effect of empty creditors is removed. This effect increases in the average CDS hedge position of a firm's creditors and in the concentration of the firm's debt. Firms with longer credit relationships, with higher average collateral ratios of their debt, and financially safer firms are less affected by empty creditors. Banks that are not capital constrained and that are liquidity constrained embed the empty creditor effect into their probability of default estimates of affected firms to a larger extent. So do banks that monitor their creditors less and that earn a smaller portion of their income from interest activities.]]></description><author>Steven Ongena, Kuchulain O'Flynn, Yalin Gündüz, Hans Degryse</author><pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16773</guid></item><item><title>Distributed Ledgers and the Governance of Money</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16752</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Cyril Monnet, Hyun Song Shin, Raphael Auer.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Blockchain technology breathes new life into the classical analysis of money as a substitute for a ledger of all past transactions. While it involves updating the ledger through a decentralized consensus on the unique truth, the robustness of the equilibrium that supports this consensus depends on who has access to the ledger and how it can be updated. To find the optimal solution, Buterin's "scalability trilemma" needs to be addressed, so that a workable balance can be found between decentralization, security (i.e. a robust consensus), and scale (the efficient volume of transactions). Using a global game analysis of an exchange economy with credit, we solve for the optimal ledger design that balances the three objectives of this trilemma. We characterize the optimal number of validators, supermajority threshold, fees and transaction size. When intertemporal incentives are strong, a centralized ledger is always optimal. Otherwise, decentralization may be optimal, and validators need to be selected from the set of users of the system.]]></description><author>Cyril Monnet, Hyun Song Shin, Raphael Auer</author><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16752</guid></item><item><title>Non-Standard Errors</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16751</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christian C P Wolff, Utz Weitzel, Michael Razen, Sebastian Neusüess, Michael Kirchler, Magnus Johannesson, Juergen Huber, Felix Holzmeister, Anna Dreber, Albert Menkveld.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> In statistics, samples are drawn from a population in a data generating process (DGP). Standard errors measure the uncertainty in sample estimates of population parameters. In science, evidence is generated to test hypotheses in an evidence generating process (EGP). We claim that EGP variation across researchers adds uncertainty: non-standard errors. To study them, we let 164 teams test six hypotheses on the same sample. We find that non-standard errors are sizeable, on par with standard errors. Their size (i) co-varies only weakly with team
merits, reproducibility, or peer rating, (ii) declines significantly after peer-feedback, and (iii) is underestimated by participants.]]></description><author>Christian C P Wolff, Utz Weitzel, Michael Razen, Sebastian Neusüess, Michael Kirchler, Magnus Johannesson, Juergen Huber, Felix Holzmeister, Anna Dreber, Albert Menkveld</author><pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16751</guid></item><item><title>Sovereign Risk and Financial Risk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16750</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Egon Zakrajšek, Vivian Yue, Bin Wei, Simon Gilchrist.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we study the interplay between sovereign risk and global financial risk. We show that a substantial portion of the comovement among sovereign spreads is accounted for by changes in global financial risk. We construct bond-level sovereign spreads for dollar-denominated bonds issued by over 50 countries from 1995 to 2020 and use various indicators to measure global financial risk. Through panel regressions and local projection analysis, we find that an increase in global financial risk causes a large and persistent widening of sovereign bond spreads. These effect are strongest when measuring global risk using the excess bond premium -- a measure of the risk-bearing
capacity of U.S. financial intermediaries. The spillover effects of global financial risk are more pronounced for speculative-grade sovereign bonds.]]></description><author>Egon Zakrajšek, Vivian Yue, Bin Wei, Simon Gilchrist</author><pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16750</guid></item><item><title>Ambiguity with Machine Learning: An Application to Portfolio Choice</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16748</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Steve Raymond, Yan Qian, Eric Ghysels.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> To characterize ambiguity we use machine learning to impose guidance and discipline on the formulation of expectations in a data-rich environment. In addition, we use the bootstrap to generate plausible synthetic samples of data not seen in historical real data to create statistics of interest pertaining to uncertainty.  While our approach is generic we focus on robust portfolio allocation problems as an application and study the impact of risk versus uncertainty in a dynamic mean-variance setting. We show that a mean-variance optimizing investor achieves economically meaningful wealth gains (33%) across our sample from 1996-2019 by internalizing our uncertainty measure during portfolio formation.]]></description><author>Steve Raymond, Yan Qian, Eric Ghysels</author><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16748</guid></item><item><title>The Geography of Investor Attention</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16747</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pierpaolo Pattitoni, stefano mengoli, Marco Pagano.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Retail investors pay over twice as much attention to local companies than non-local ones, based on Google searches. News volume and volatility amplify this attention gap. Attention appears causally related to perceived proximity: first, acquisition by a nonlocal company is associated with less attention by locals, and more by nonlocals close to the acquirer; second, COVID-19 travel restrictions correlate with a drop in relative attention to nonlocal companies, especially in locations with fewer flights after the outbreak. Finally, local attention predicts volatility, bid-ask spreads and nonlocal attention, not viceversa. These findings are consistent with local investors having an information-processing advantage.]]></description><author>Pierpaolo Pattitoni, stefano mengoli, Marco Pagano</author><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16747</guid></item><item><title>Carbon Taxes and the Geography of Fossil Lending</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16745</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexander Popov, Luc Laeven.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Using data on syndicated loans, we find that the introduction of a carbon tax is associated with an increase in domestic banks' lending to coal, oil, and gas companies in foreign countries. This effect is particularly pronounced for banks with large prior fossil-lending exposures, while bank capital and profitability do not play a role. In addition, banks reallocate a relatively larger share of their fossil loan portfolio to countries without a carbon tax. Our findings speak to the importance of a global carbon tax to prevent the reallocation of carbon emissions across national borders via financial markets.]]></description><author>Alexander Popov, Luc Laeven</author><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16745</guid></item><item><title>CDS and Credit: After the Bangs Cheaper Credit Insurance, More Lending and Hedging</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16744</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yuejuan Yu, Günseli Tümer-Alkan, Steven Ongena, Yalin Gündüz.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Does the cost of credit insurance affect the availability of credit? To answer this question, we couple comprehensive bank-firm level CDS trading data from DTCC to the German credit register containing bilateral bank-firm credit exposures. We assess the differential impact on market participants of the "Big Bang" and "Small Bang" standardization across CDS markets. We find that after the Bangs, the cost of buying CDS contracts becomes lower for non-dealer banks, and that â?? because of this decrease in insurance cost â?? these banks extend more credit to CDS traded and affected firms, and also hedge more effectively.]]></description><author>Yuejuan Yu, Günseli Tümer-Alkan, Steven Ongena, Yalin Gündüz</author><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16744</guid></item></channel></rss>