<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Macroeconomics and Growth</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Macroeconomics and Growth</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 18:11:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Cities and Technological Waves</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16794</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruben Gaetani, Enrico Berkes, Martí Mestieri.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We develop a spatial model of economic growth to study the effect of changes in the technological landscape on the spatial distribution of economic activity. We use this framework to study the evolution of the U.S. economic geography over the twentieth century. In the model, innovation via frictional idea diffusion makes cities trajectories sensitive to "technological waves," defined as long-term shifts in the importance of different knowledge fields. We calibrate the model using a new dataset of historical geolocated patents, and find that cities differential exposure to technological waves explains between 15% and 20% of the variation in local population growth over the twentieth century. Counterfactual experiments suggest large and heterogeneous geographical effects of future technological scenarios.]]></description><author>Ruben Gaetani, Enrico Berkes, Martí Mestieri</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16794</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Origins of Non-Fundamental Risk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16793</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sanjay R. Singh, Keshav Dogra, Sushant Acharya.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We formalize the idea that the financial sector can be a source of non-fundamental risk. Households' desire to hedge against price volatility can generate price volatility in equilibrium, even absent fundamental risk. Fearing that asset prices may fall, risk-averse households demand safe assets from leveraged intermediaries, whose issuance of safe assets exposes the economy to self-fulfilling fire sales. Policy can eliminate non-fundamental risk by (i) increasing the supply of publicly backed safe assets, through issuing government debt or bailing out intermediaries, or (ii) reducing the demand for safe assets, through social insurance or by acting as a market maker of last resort.]]></description><author>Sanjay R. Singh, Keshav Dogra, Sushant Acharya</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16793</guid></item><item><title>Time Use and Gender in Africa in Times of Structural Transformation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16792</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Liwa Rachel Ngai, Taryn Dinkelman.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Many African countries are still in the early stages of structural transformation. Typically, as economies move through the structural transformation, activities once conducted within the household are outsourced to the market. This has particular implications for women's time use. In this paper, we document that current patterns of female time use in home production in several African countries closely resemble historical time use patterns in the US. We highlight two stylized facts about women's time use in Africa. First, in North Africa, women spend very few hours in market work and female labor force participation overall is extremely low. Second, although extensive margin participation of women is high in sub-Saharan Africa, women tend to work in the market for only a few hours each week, with the rest of their work hours spent in home production. These two facts suggest two types of constraints that could slow down the reallocation of female
time from home to market as economies grow: Social norms related to women's market work, and a lack of infrastructure (e.g. household infrastructure and childcare facilities) to facilitate marketizing home production. We discuss recent empirical evidence related to each set of constraints and highlight new avenues for research.]]></description><author>Liwa Rachel Ngai, Taryn Dinkelman</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16792</guid></item><item><title>Larger transfers financed with more progressive taxes? On the optimal design of taxes and transfers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16781</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Oliko Vardishvili, Gaston  Navarro, Philipp Grübener, Axelle Ferriere.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study the optimal joint design of targeted transfers and progressive income taxes. We develop a simple analytical model and demonstrate an optimally negative relation between transfers and income-tax progressivity, due to both efficiency and redistribution concerns. That is, higher transfers should be financed with lower income-tax progressivity. We next quantify the optimal fiscal plan in a rich dynamic model calibrated to the U.S. economy. Transfers should be generous and financed with moderate income-tax progressivity. To redistribute while preserving efficiency, average tax-and-transfer rates should be more progressive than marginal rates. Transfers, even if lump-sum, precisely allow to disentangle average from marginal rates. Targeted transfers further implement non-monotonic marginal rates, but generate only modest additional gains relative to a lump-sum transfer. Quantitatively, the left tail of the income distribution determines the optimal size of the transfer, while the right tail drives the optimal income-tax progressivity.]]></description><author>Oliko Vardishvili, Gaston  Navarro, Philipp Grübener, Axelle Ferriere</author><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16781</guid></item><item><title>Adams and Eves: The Gender Gap in Economics Majors</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16767</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marina Murat, Luca Bonacini, Graziella Bertocchi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the gender gap in Economics among bachelor's and master's graduates in Italy between 2010 and 2019. First we establish that being female exerts a negative impact on the choice to major in Economics: at the bachelor level, only 73 women graduate in Economics for every 100 men, with the mathematical content of high school curricula as the key driver of the effect and a persistence of the gap at the master level. Second, within a full menu of major choices, Economics displays the largest gap, followed by STEM and then Business Economics. Third, decomposition analyses expose a unique role for the math background in driving the Economics gender gap relative to other fields. Fourth, a triple difference analysis of a high school reform shows that an increase in the math content of traditionally low math curricula caused an increase in the Economics gender gap among treated students.]]></description><author>Marina Murat, Luca Bonacini, Graziella Bertocchi</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16767</guid></item></channel></rss>