<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for Macroeconomics and Growth</title><link>a link</link><description>a feed</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 20:56:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Barriers to Creative Destruction: Large Firms and Non-Productive Strategies</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16570</link><description>This chapter reviews recent empirical evidence on large firms and non-productive
strategies that hinder creative destruction and reallocation. The focus is on three
types of non-productive strategies: political connections, non-productive patenting,
and anti-competitive acquisitions. Across different contexts using granular micro
data sets, we overwhelmingly see that as firms gain market shares, they rely more
on non-productive strategies but reduce their productive, innovation-based strategies.
I discuss theoretical channels, aggregate implications, and potentials for some
policies.</description><author>Baslandze, Salomé</author></item><item><title>Measuring Robot Quality: Has Quality Improvement Slowed Down?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16556</link><description>This paper measures the extent to which the quality of robots has improved in Japan between 1990 and 2018, by using data from the "Production and Shipments of Manipulators and Robots" of the Japan Robot Association and the "Corporate Goods Price Index" of the Bank of Japan. We first calculate quality-unadjusted robot price indices applying three approaches: the traditional index number approach, the stochastic approach in the spirits of Edgeworth and Jevons, the structural approach. Then, we compute robot quality by dividing quality-unadjusted prices by the quality-adjusted industrial robot price index produced by the Bank of Japan. Based on the three approaches, significant decline in improvement in the quality of robots in the last decade is found. The differences in the growth rates of robot quality between the 2000s and 2010s show substantially negative values of around -3 percentage points per annum.</description><author>Fujiwara, Ippei &amp; Kimoto, Ryo &amp; Shiratsuka, Shigenori &amp; Shirota, Toyoichiro</author></item><item><title>Mitigating Climate Change: Growth-Friendly Policies to Achieve Net Zero Emissions by 2050</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16553</link><description>The paper examines climate mitigation strategies to reach net-zero emissions by mid-century, focusing on smoothing macroeconomic costs in the short- to medium-term-the horizon relevant for policymakers. It explores a comprehensive policy package, which complements carbon pricing with an initial green fiscal stimulus, consisting of green public investment and subsidies to renewables production. Model simulations show that thanks to the green public spending, the policy package boosts global output relative to the baseline for the first 15 years of the low-carbon transition. Subsequent transitional output costs resulting from further increases in carbon prices are moderate of the order of 1 percent of baseline global GDP by 2050. The findings suggest that upfront green fiscal packages could help smooth the transition to a low-carbon economy. In the current context of the Covid-19 economic crisis, they would help support the recovery from the crisis and put the global economy on a greener, more sustainable path.</description><author>Jaumotte, Florence &amp; Liu, Weifeng &amp; McKibbin, Warwick</author></item><item><title>The Long-Term Effects of Industrial Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16534</link><description>This paper provides causal evidence of the impact of industrial policy on firms' long-term performance and quantifies industrial policy's long-term welfare effects. Using a natural experiment and unique historical data during the Heavy and Chemical Industry (HCI) Drive in South Korea, we find large and persistent effects of firm-level subsidies on firm size. Subsidized firms are larger than those never subsidized even 30 years after subsidies ended. Motivated by this empirical finding, we build a quantitative heterogeneous firm model that rationalizes these persistent effects through a combination of learning-by-doing (LBD) and financial frictions that hinder firms from internalizing LBD. The model is calibrated to firm-level micro data, and its key parameters are disciplined with the econometric estimates. Cost-benefit analysis implies that the industrial policy generated larger benefits than costs. If the industrial policy had not been implemented, South Korea's welfare would have been 22-31% lower, depending on how long-lived are the productivity benefits of LBD. Between one-half and two-thirds of the total welfare difference comes from the long-term effects of the policy.</description><author>Choi, Jaedo &amp; Levchenko, Andrei A.</author></item><item><title>The Affordable Care Act After a Decade: Its Impact on the Labor Market and the Macro Economy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16530</link><description>The Affordable Care Act (ACA) is one of the most important reforms of the US health insurance system since the introduction of Medicare. Since employment is a main source of health insurance for the working age population in the United States, this sweeping health insurance reform also has important implications for the labor market and the macro economy. In this paper, we survey the prototype models that are used in the macro and labor literature, extended to integrate health and health insurance, to study the short- and long-run consequences of the ACA. We also suggest open areas for future research.</description><author>Fang, Hanming &amp; Krueger, Dirk</author></item><item><title>Harms of AI</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16524</link><description>This essay discusses several potential economic, political and social costs of the current path of AI technologies. I argue that if AI continues to be deployed along its current trajectory and remains unregulated, it may produce various social, economic and political harms. These include: damaging competition, consumer privacy and consumer choice; excessively automating work, fueling inequality, inefficiently pushing down wages, and failing to improve worker productivity; and damaging political discourse, democracy's most fundamental lifeblood. Although there is no conclusive evidence suggesting that these costs are imminent or substantial, it may be useful to understand them before they are fully realized and become harder or even impossible to reverse, precisely because of AI's promising and wide-reaching potential. I also suggest that these costs are not inherent to the nature of AI technologies, but are related to how they are being used and developed at the moment - to empower corporations and governments against workers and citizens. As a result, efforts to limit and reverse these costs may need to rely on regulation and policies to redirect AI research. Attempts to contain them
just by promoting competition may be insufficient.</description><author>Acemoglu, Daron</author></item><item><title>Spending a Windfall</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16523</link><description>We study the effect of the discovery of precious metals in America on international trade from 1500 to 1810. Around 1500, there was a simultaneous discovery of precious metals and new trading routes. We construct a counterfactual scenario of new routes but no precious metals. The discovery of precious metals was a windfall to Europe. It increased the stock of precious metals in the world more than tenfold. Compared with the case of no trade routes and no precious metals, Euro-Asian trade increases up to 20 times. We find that American precious metals were at least as important as the new trading routes as a cause of observed trade patterns.</description><author>Palma, Nuno Pedro G. &amp; Silva, André</author></item><item><title>The Neoclassical Model and the Welfare Costs of Selection</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16522</link><description>This paper embeds firm dynamics into the Neoclassical model and provides a simple framework to solve for the transitional dynamics of economies moving towards more selection. As in the Neoclassical model, markets are perfectly competitive, there is only one good and two production factors (capital and labor). At equilibrium, aggregate technology is Neoclassical, but the average quality of capital and the depreciation rate are both endogenous and positively related to selection. At steady state, output per capita and welfare both raise with selection. However, the selection process generates transitional welfare losses that may reduce in around 60% long term (consumption equivalent) welfare gains. The same property is shown to be true in a standard general equilibrium model with entry and fixed production costs.</description><author>Collard, Fabrice &amp; Licandro, Omar</author></item><item><title>Economics and family structures</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16516</link><description>Household decisions are one of the key elements impacting many dimensions of any economy. In this paper, we review the economic literature on family types, focusing on nuclear, stem, and complex families. We show that family types are heterogeneous across and within countries, both in the past and in present times. We argue that economists have focused too much their analysis on nuclear families, which may limit our capacity to analyze the impact of institutional phenomena or public policies. We establish how each family type could relate to the basic ingredients of standard structural models of household decisions. We believe this overview sets the stage for an interesting research avenue to improve the structural models of household decision making.</description><author>Baudin, Thomas &amp; De Rock, Bram &amp; Gobbi, Paula</author></item><item><title>Expansionary Austerity: Reallocating Credit Amid Fiscal Consolidation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16511</link><description>We show expansionary fiscal austerity via reallocation of credit supply, but with a raise in poverty.
For identification, we exploit the introduction of a Mexican law limiting the debt of subnational
governments along with matched credit register, firm, bank, and state datasets. After the law,
states with higher ex ante public debt grow substantially faster, despite larger fiscal consolidation
(higher taxes and lower public expenditure). Banks operating in more indebted states reallocate
credit supply away from local governments into private firms, with stronger effects for banks with
higher exposure to local public debt, consistent with lowering crowding out. Effects only happen
after the law, not before, and there are strong firm-level real effects associated. The reduction of
crowding out is stronger for financially constrained firms and for firms operating in states with
higher ex ante public spending on social services over infrastructure projects. In states more
affected by the law, despite better economic effects, extreme poverty increases--especially in
states with higher ex ante public spending on social services over infrastructure--consistent with
a strong reduction for social services during the fiscal consolidation.</description><author>Morais, Bernardo &amp; Perez-Estrada, Javier &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Ruiz-Ortega, Claudia</author></item><item><title>Organizational capacity and profit shifting</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16502</link><description>This paper analyses the effect of a firm's organizational capacity on the reported profitability of multinational enterprises (MNEs). Better organizational practices improve productivity and the potential taxable profits of firms. However, higher adoption of these practices may also enable more efficient allocation of profits across tax jurisdictions, lowering actual taxable profits. We present new evidence that MNE subsidiaries with better such practices, when located in high-tax countries, report significantly lower profits and have a higher incidence of bunching around zero returns on assets. We show these results are driven by patterns consistent with profit-shifting behavior. Further, using an event study design, we find that firms with better practices are more responsive to corporate tax rate changes. Our results suggest organizational capacity, especially monitoring-related practices, enables firms to engage in shifting profits away from their high-tax subsidiaries.</description><author>Bilicka, Katarzyna &amp; Scur, Daniela</author></item><item><title>Play for the Rich and Work for the Poor? The Optimal Distribution of Saving and Work in the Heterogeneous Agents Neoclassical Growth Model</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16479</link><description>In an economy with un-insurable idiosyncratic labor income risk, how should saving and work hours be distributed across income and wealth? To answer this question, we study a planner who cannot complete asset markets, but dictates how much individuals must work and save. With a U.S. calibration, the planner raises total savings but not hours, driving up aggregate wages which re-distributes income toward the consumption-poor. Across the distribution, the productive (high wage earners) should save more; the wealthy should work more; the poor should keep their work hours unchanged and take advantage of the indirect transfers from higher wages.</description><author>Shanker, Akshay &amp; Wolf, Martin</author></item><item><title>Productivity slowdown: reducing the measure of our ignorance</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16478</link><description>Growth accounting suggests that the bulk of the  post-2004 slowdown in output growth in the U.S. is  attributed to a residual called TFP. In this paper we provide a tractable accounting framework with firm heterogeneity to link this residual to innovations, markup dispersion, and potential measurement errors. Theories of creative destruction offer rich testable predictions of how the quality upgrading of products, the process efficiency of different firms, and markup dispersion in the market interact and therefore constitute a key approach to shed light on the slowdown in TFP growth. Surveying the  literature on measurement, we conclude that measurement errors is unlikely to explain the recent deceleration in TFP growth.</description><author>Boppart, Timo &amp; Li, Huiyu</author></item><item><title>The Elusive Explanation for the Declining Labor Share</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16473</link><description>A vast literature seeks to measure and explain the apparent decline in the labor share in national income that has occurred in recent times in the United States and elsewhere. The culprits include technological change, increased globalization and the rise of China, the enhanced exercise of market power by large firms in concentrated product markets, the decline in unionization rates and the erosion in the bargaining power of workers in labor markets, and the changing composition of the workforce due to a slowdown in population growth and a rise in educational attainment. We review this literature, with special emphasis on the pitfalls associated with using cross-sectional data to assess this phenomenon and the reasons why the body of papers collectively explains the phenomenon many times over.</description><author>Grossman, Gene M. &amp; Oberfield, Ezra</author></item><item><title>Local Shocks and Internal Migration: The Disparate Effects of Robots and Chinese Imports in the US</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16460</link><description>Migration has long been considered one of the key mechanisms through which labor markets adjust to economic shocks. In this paper, we analyze the migration response of American workers to two of the most important shocks that hit US manufacturing since the late 1990s - Chinese import competition and the introduction of industrial robots. Exploiting plausibly exogenous variation in exposure across US local labor markets over time, we show that robots caused a sizable reduction in population size, while Chinese imports did not. We rationalize these results in two steps. First, we provide evidence that negative employment spillovers outside manufacturing, caused by robots but not by Chinese imports, are an important mechanism for the different migration responses triggered by the two shocks. Next, we present a model where workers are geographically mobile and compete with either machines or foreign labor in the completion of tasks. The model highlights that two key dimensions along which the shocks differ - the cost savings they provide and the degree of complementarity between directly and indirectly exposed industries - can explain their disparate employment effects outside manufacturing and, in turn, the differential migration response.</description><author>Faber, Marius &amp; Sarto, Andres &amp; Tabellini, Marco</author></item><item><title>Oil Price Shocks and Conflict Escalation: Onshore vs. Offshore</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16454</link><description>We reconsider the relationship between oil and conflict, focusing on the location of oil resources. In a panel of 132 countries over the period 1962-2009, we show that oil windfalls escalate conflict in onshore-rich countries, while they de-escalate conflict in offshore-rich countries. We use a model to illustrate how these opposite effects can be explained by a fighting capacity mechanism, whereby the government can use offshore oil income to increase its fighting capacity, while onshore oil may be looted by oppositional groups to finance a rebellion. We provide empirical evidence supporting this interpretation: we find that oil price windfalls increase both the number and strength of active rebel groups in onshore-rich countries, while they strengthen the government in offshore-rich ones.</description><author>Juel Andersen, Jørgen &amp; Nordvik, Frode Martin &amp; Tesei, Andrea</author></item><item><title>OECD Pension Reform: it is the business cycle, not the demography!</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16451</link><description>Using a new real-time dataset from Beetsma et al. (2020) containing all pension reform measures in 23 OECD countries between 1970 and 2017, we demonstrate that, in contrast to what one might a priori expect, the timing of pension reform measures coincides with business cycle shocks and not with current or projected demographic shocks. We rationalise this finding using a political-economy model with two-sided adjustment costs to explain a lack of response of pension reform measures to changes in demographic indicators.</description><author>Beetsma, Roel &amp; Romp, Ward E</author></item><item><title>Serial Entrepreneurs and the Macroeconomy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16449</link><description>Are serial entrepreneurs â?? owners of multiple firms -- important for understanding the sources and aggregate consequences of business dynamism? Using unique administrative data, we show that -- compared to other businesses -- firms of serial entrepreneurs are larger, more productive, grow faster, exit less often and disproportionately contribute to aggregate job creation and productivity growth. Moreover, even the very first firms of serial entrepreneurs feature these ``premia'', suggesting an important role of innate abilities, rather than luck or learning. Finally, we show theoretically and quantitatively that serial entrepreneurship is also important for understanding and modelling of top income inequality.</description><author>Felix, Sonia &amp; Karmakar, Sudipto &amp; Sedlacek, Petr</author></item><item><title>Pandemic Shock and Economic Divergence: Political Economy Before and After the Black Death</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16447</link><description>We document how the Black Death activated politics and led to economic divergence within Europe. Before the pandemic, economic development was similar in Eastern and Western German cities despite greater political fragmentation in the West. The pandemic precipitated a divergence that coincided with prior differences in politics.  After the pandemic, construction and manufacturing fell by 1/3 in the East relative to underlying trends and the Western path. Politics institutionalizing local self-government advanced in the West, but not in the East. This divergence is observed across otherwise similar cities along historic borders and foreshadows a subsequent divergence in agriculture.</description><author>Bosshart, Luis &amp; Dittmar, Jeremiah</author></item><item><title>How Much Do Norms Matter for Quantity and Quality of Children?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16445</link><description>This paper quantifies the effect of social norms on fertility and children's education in Pakistan using a quantity-quality trade-off model augmented with the role of norms. The structural parameters of the theoretical model are estimated using stylized facts from an auxiliary econometric model. Quantitative analyses show that norms explain 49% of the variation in fertility and 31% of the variation in investment in the education of children among the households that differ in the mother's educational background and social class. The influence of norms is the weakest in households where women have tertiary education. The policies that provide economic incentives to encourage the education of children and control the population growth are less effective in the presence of norms. The cost of these policies is substantially lower when households are unaffected by norms, and the decline in cost varies with the education of the mothers in the target households.</description><author>Iftikhar, Zainab</author></item><item><title>The Effects of Biased Labor Market Expectations on Consumption, Wealth Inequality, and Welfare</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16444</link><description>Idiosyncratic labor risk is a prevalent phenomenon with important implications for individual choices. In labor market research it is commonly assumed that agents have rational expectations and therefore they correctly assess the risk they face in the labor market. We analyze survey data for the U.S. and document a substantial optimistic bias of households in their subjective expectations about future labor market transitions. Furthermore, we analyze the heterogeneity in the bias across different demographic groups and we find that high-school graduates tend to be vastly over-optimistic about their labor market prospects, whereas college graduates have rather precise beliefs. In the context of a quantitative heterogenous agents lifecycle model we show that the optimistic bias has a quantitatively sizable negative effect on the life-cycle allocation of income, consumption and wealth and implies a substantial loss in individual welfare compared to the allocation under full information. Moreover, we establish that the heterogeneity in the bias leads to pronounced differences in the accumulation of assets across individuals, and is thereby a quantitatively important driver of inequality in wealth.</description><author>Balleer, Almut &amp; Duernecker, Georg &amp; Forstner, Susanne &amp; Goensch, Johannes</author></item><item><title>Monetary Policy in the Age of Automation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16416</link><description>We provide a framework in which monetary policy affects firms' automation decisions (i.e. how intensively capital and labor are used in production). This new feature has far-reaching consequences for monetary policy. Monetary expansions can increase output by inducing firms to invest and automate more, while having little impact on inflation and employment. A protracted period of weak demand might translate into less investment and de-automation, rather than into deflation and involuntary unemployment. Running the economy hot, through expansionary monetary and fiscal policies, may have a positive long run impact on labor productivity and wages. Technological advances that increase the scope for automation may give rise to persistent unemployment, unless they are accompanied by expansionary macroeconomic policies.</description><author>Fornaro, Luca &amp; Wolf, Martin</author></item><item><title>Catholic Censorship and the Demise of Knowledge Production in Early Modern Italy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16409</link><description>Censorship makes new ideas less available to others, but also reduces the share of people choosing a non-compliant activity. We propose a new method to measure the effect of censorship on knowledge growth,  accounting for the endogenous selection of agents into compliant vs. non-compliant ideas. We apply our method to the Catholic Church's censorship of books written by members of Italian universities and academies over the period 1400-1750. We highlight two new facts: once censorship was introduced, censored authors were of better quality than the non-censored authors, but this gap shrunk over time, and the intensity of censorship decreased over time. These facts are used to identify the deep parameters of a novel endogenous growth model linking censorship to knowledge diffusion and occupational choice. We conclude that censorship reduced by 30% the average log publication per scholar in Italy. Interestingly, half of this drop stems from the induced reallocation of talents towards compliant activities, while the other half arises from the direct effect of censorship on book availability.</description><author>Blasutto, Fabio &amp; de la Croix, David</author></item><item><title>The Risks of Safe Assets</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16407</link><description>How much safety and liquidity can the US government provide? Should it accommodate demand for these attributes because high convenience yields in Treasuries lower its borrowing cost? We evaluate a novel fiscal risk channel limiting the government's capacity to issue debt through the lens of a general equilibrium asset pricing model with a rich fiscal sector. Expanding safe asset supply lowers safety premia and improves liquidity in financial markets, but creates  tax and consumption volatility, raising risk premia, credit spreads, and firms' cost of capital. Our  model predicts that this risk channel leads to depressed growth prospects, rising Treasury yields, and elevated consumption risk, for which we find strong empirical evidence. We use our model to quantitatively evaluate current proposals on stimulus and stabilization packages and find that the risk channel is exacerbated in times of fiscal stress. Increasing safe asset supply can thus be risky, and have a significant fiscal cost.</description><author>Liu, Yang &amp; Schmid, Lukas &amp; Yaron, Amir</author></item><item><title>Carbon Taxation and Inflation: Evidence from the European and Canadian Experience</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16396</link><description>What is the effect of climate policies on inflation and economic activity? Answering this question is critical for central banks trying to achieve price stability. This paper studies the experience from existing Co2 taxes in Canada and Europe, introduced over the last 30 years. Based on two separate empirical approaches, we find that carbon taxes do not have to be inflationary and may even have deflationary effects. In particular, our evidence suggests that the increase in energy prices was more than offset by a fall in the prices of services and other non-tradables. Our results are robust for Europe and Canada, as well as a number of different country groupings. At least in case of British Columbia, a contraction in household incomes and expenditures, in particular among the richer households, could explain the deflationary effect.</description><author>Konradt, Maximilian &amp; Weder di Mauro, Beatrice</author></item><item><title>Propagation and Amplification of Local Productivity Spillovers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16388</link><description>Abstract This paper shows that local productivity spillovers propagate throughout the economy through the plant-level networks of multi-region firms. Using confidential Census plant-level data, we show that large manufacturing plant openings not only raise the productivity of local plants but also of distant plants hundreds of miles away, which belong to multi-region firms that are exposed to the local productivity spillover through one of their plants. To quantify the significance of plant-level networks for the propagation and amplification of local productivity shocks, we develop and estimate a quantitative spatial model in which plants of multi-region firms are linked through shared knowledge. Our model features heterogeneous regions, which interact through goods trade and labor markets, as well as within-location, across-plant heterogeneity in productivity, wages, and employment. Counterfactual exercises show that while knowledge sharing through plant-level networks amplifies the aggregate effects of local productivity shocks, it widens economic disparities between individual workers and regions in the economy.</description><author>Giroud, Xavier &amp; Lenzu, Simone &amp; Maingi, Quinn &amp; Mueller, Holger M</author></item><item><title>Pandemic Lockdown: The Role of Government Commitment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16384</link><description>This paper studies lockdown policy in a dynamic economy without government commitment. Lockdown imposes a cap on labor supply, which improves health prospects at the cost of economic output and consumption. A government would like to commit to the extent of future lockdowns in order to guarantee an economic outlook that supports efficient levels of investment into intermediate inputs. However, such a commitment is not credible, since investments are sunk at the time when the government chooses a lockdown. As a result, lockdown under lack of commitment deviates from the optimal policy. Rules that limit a government's lockdown discretion can improve social welfare, even in the presence of noncontractible information. Quantitatively, lack of commitment causes lockdown to be significantly more severe than is socially optimal. The output and consumption loss due to lack of commitment is greater for higher intermediate input shares, higher discount rates, higher values of life, higher disease transmission rates at and outside of work, and longer vaccine arrival times.</description><author>Moser, Christian &amp; Yared, Pierre</author></item><item><title>The Gender Pay Gap: Micro Sources and Macro Consequences</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16383</link><description>We document that a large share of the gender pay gap in Brazil is due to women working at lower-paying employers. However, compared with that of men, women's revealed-preference ranking of employers is less increasing in pay. To interpret these facts, we develop an empirical equilibrium search model with endogenous gender differences in pay, amenities, and recruiting intensities across employers. The estimated model suggests that compensating differentials explain one-fifth of the gender pay gap, that there are significant output and welfare gains from eliminating gender differences, and that equal-treatment policies fail to close the gender pay gap.</description><author>Morchio, Iacopo &amp; Moser, Christian</author></item><item><title>Progressive Pensions as an Incentive for Labor Force Participation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16380</link><description>In this paper, we challenge the conventional idea that an increase in the progressivity of old-age pensions unanimously distorts the labor supply decision of households. So far, the literature has argued that higher pension progressivity leads to more redistribution and insurance provision on the one hand, but increases implicit taxes and therefore distorts labor supply choices on the other. In contrast, we show that a well-designed reform of the pension system has the potential to encourage labor force participation. We propose a progressive pension component linked to the employment decision of households,  which implicitly subsidizes employment of the productivity poor. A simulation analysis in a quantitative stochastic overlapping generations model with productivity and longevity risk indicates that this positive employment effect can be sizable and welfare enhancing.</description><author>Kindermann, Fabian &amp; Pueschel, Veronika</author></item><item><title>Bayesian Learning</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16377</link><description>We survey work using Bayesian learning in macroeconomics, highlighting common themes and new directions. First, we present many of the common types of learning problems agents face -- signal extraction problems -- and trace out their effects on macro aggregates, in different strategic settings. Then we review different perspectives on how agents get their information. Models differ in their motives for information acquisition and the cost of information, or learning technology. Finally, we survey the growing literature on the data economy, where economic activity generates data and the information in data feeds back to affect economic activity.</description><author>Baley, Isaac &amp; Veldkamp, Laura</author></item></channel></rss>