<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: International Macroeconomics and Finance</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: International Macroeconomics and Finance</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 23:16:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Superstar Returns</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16806</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Moritz Schularick, Martin Dohmen, Sebastian Kohl, Francisco Amaral.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study long-term returns on residential real estate in 27 "superstar" cities in 15 countries over 150 years. We find that total returns in superstar cities are close to 100 basis points lower per year than in the rest of the country. House prices tend to grow faster in the superstars, but rent returns are substantially greater outside the big agglomerations, resulting in higher long-run total returns. The excess returns outside the superstars can be rationalized as a compensation for risk, especially for higher co-variance with income growth and lower liquidity. Superstar real estate is comparatively safe.]]></description><author>Moritz Schularick, Martin Dohmen, Sebastian Kohl, Francisco Amaral</author><pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16806</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of Rising Oil Prices on U.S. Inflation and Inflation Expectations in 2020-23</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16776</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Xiaoqing Zhou, Lutz Kilian.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Predictions of oil prices reaching $100 per barrel during the winter of 2021/22 have raised fears of persistently high inflation and rising inflation expectations for years to come. We show that these concerns have been overstated. A $100 oil scenario of the type discussed by many observers, would only briefly raise monthly headline inflation, before fading rather quickly. However, the short-run effects on headline inflation would be sizable. For example, on a year-over-year basis, headline PCE inflation would increase by 1.8 percentage points at the end of 2021 under this scenario, and by 0.4 percentage points at the end of 2022. In contrast, the impact on measures of core inflation such as trimmed mean PCE inflation is only 0.4 and 0.3 percentage points in 2021 and 2022, respectively. These estimates already account for any increases in inflation expectations under the scenario. The peak response of the 1-year household inflation expectation would be 1.2 percentage points, while that of the 5-year expectation would be 0.2 percentage points.]]></description><author>Xiaoqing Zhou, Lutz Kilian</author><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16776</guid></item><item><title>What Has Been the Impact of COVID-19 on Debt? Turning a Wave into a Tsunami</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16775</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Naotaka Sugawara, Franziska Ohnsorge, Peter Nagle, M. Ayhan Kose.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper presents a comprehensive analysis of the impact of COVID-19 on debt, puts recent debt developments and prospects in historical context, and analyzes new policy challenges associated with debt resolution. The paper reports three main results. First, even before the pandemic, a rapid buildup of debt in emerging market and developing economies-dubbed the "fourth wave" of debt-had been underway. Because of the sharp increase in debt during the pandemic-induced global recession of 2020, the fourth wave of debt has turned into a tsunami and become even more dangerous. Second, five years after past global recessions, global government debt continued to increase. In light of this historical record, and given large financing gaps and significant investment needs in many countries, debt levels will likely continue to rise in the near future. Third, debt resolution has become more complicated because of a highly fragmented creditor base, a lack of transparency in debt reporting, and a legacy stock of government debt without collective action clauses. National policy makers and the global community need to act rapidly and forcefully ensure that the fourth wave does not end with a string of debt crises in emerging market and developing economies as earlier debt waves did.]]></description><author>Naotaka Sugawara, Franziska Ohnsorge, Peter Nagle, M. Ayhan Kose</author><pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16775</guid></item><item><title>Can Sticky Portfolios Explain International Capital Flows and Asset Prices?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16772</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Eric van Wincoop, Margaret Davenport, Philippe Bacchetta.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Recently portfolio choice has become an important element of many DSGE open economy models. Yet, a substantial body of evidence is inconsistent with standard frictionless portfolio choice models. In this paper we introduce a quadratic cost of changes in portfolio allocation into a two-country DSGE model. We investigate the level of portfolio frictions most consistent with the data and the impact of portfolio frictions on asset prices and net capital flows. We find the portfolio friction accounts for (i) micro evidence of portfolio inertia by households, (ii) macro evidence of the price impact of financial shocks and related disconnect of asset prices from fundamentals, (iii) a broad set of moments related to the time series behavior of saving, investment and net capital flows, and (iv) other phenomena relating to excess return dynamics. Financial and saving shocks each account for close to half of the variance of net capital flows.]]></description><author>Eric van Wincoop, Margaret Davenport, Philippe Bacchetta</author><pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16772</guid></item><item><title>Distributed Ledgers and the Governance of Money</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16752</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Cyril Monnet, Hyun Song Shin, Raphael Auer.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Blockchain technology breathes new life into the classical analysis of money as a substitute for a ledger of all past transactions. While it involves updating the ledger through a decentralized consensus on the unique truth, the robustness of the equilibrium that supports this consensus depends on who has access to the ledger and how it can be updated. To find the optimal solution, Buterin's "scalability trilemma" needs to be addressed, so that a workable balance can be found between decentralization, security (i.e. a robust consensus), and scale (the efficient volume of transactions). Using a global game analysis of an exchange economy with credit, we solve for the optimal ledger design that balances the three objectives of this trilemma. We characterize the optimal number of validators, supermajority threshold, fees and transaction size. When intertemporal incentives are strong, a centralized ledger is always optimal. Otherwise, decentralization may be optimal, and validators need to be selected from the set of users of the system.]]></description><author>Cyril Monnet, Hyun Song Shin, Raphael Auer</author><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16752</guid></item><item><title>Sovereign Risk and Financial Risk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16750</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Egon Zakrajšek, Vivian Yue, Bin Wei, Simon Gilchrist.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we study the interplay between sovereign risk and global financial risk. We show that a substantial portion of the comovement among sovereign spreads is accounted for by changes in global financial risk. We construct bond-level sovereign spreads for dollar-denominated bonds issued by over 50 countries from 1995 to 2020 and use various indicators to measure global financial risk. Through panel regressions and local projection analysis, we find that an increase in global financial risk causes a large and persistent widening of sovereign bond spreads. These effect are strongest when measuring global risk using the excess bond premium -- a measure of the risk-bearing
capacity of U.S. financial intermediaries. The spillover effects of global financial risk are more pronounced for speculative-grade sovereign bonds.]]></description><author>Egon Zakrajšek, Vivian Yue, Bin Wei, Simon Gilchrist</author><pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16750</guid></item><item><title>What Types of Capital Flows Help Improve International Risk Sharing?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16749</link><description><![CDATA[<i>M. Ayhan Kose, Ergys Islamaj.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Cross-border capital flows are expected to lead to increased international risk sharing by facilitating borrowing and lending in global financial markets. This paper examines risk-sharing outcomes of various types of capital flows (foreign direct investment, portfolio equity, debt, remittance, and aid flows) in a large sample of emerging market and developing economies. The results suggest that remittances and aid flows are associated with increased international risk sharing. Other types of capital flows are not consistently correlated with better risk-sharing outcomes. These findings are robust to the use of different econometric specifications, country-specific characteristics, and other controls.]]></description><author>M. Ayhan Kose, Ergys Islamaj</author><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16749</guid></item><item><title>The Travel Shock</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16738</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gian Maria Milesi Ferretti.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic has led to a collapse in international travel and tourism. This paper explores how the cross-country impact of the pandemic relates to countries' dependence on these activities as a source of revenue. It first documents the size of the shock to net revenues from international travel and tourism for the balance of payments. For the median highly tourism-dependent economy the shock exceeded 10 percentage points of GDP, leading to a sizable current account deterioration. Indeed, empirical evidence suggests that current account adjustment in 2020 relative to pre-crisis forecasts was driven to an important extent by the collapse in revenues and expenditures on international travel as well as by the collapse in oil prices. On the economic growth front, the paper shows that the share of tourism activities in GDP is the single most important predictor of the growth shortfall in 2020 triggered by the COVID-19 crisis across the world as well as within the eurozone, even when compared to a variety of measures of the severity of the pandemic.]]></description><author>Gian Maria Milesi Ferretti</author><pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16738</guid></item></channel></rss>