<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: International Trade and Regional Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: International Trade and Regional Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 20:54:29 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Idiosyncratic Shocks and Aggregate Fluctuations in an Emerging Market</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16824</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Damiano Sandri, Emiliano Luttini, Francesco Grigoli.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper provides the first assessment of the contribution of idiosyncratic shocks to aggregate fluctuations in an emerging market using confidential data on the universe of Chilean firms. We find that idiosyncratic shocks account for more than 40 percent of the volatility of aggregate sales. Although quite large, this contribution is smaller than documented in previous studies based on advanced economies, despite a higher degree of market concentration in Chile. We show that this finding is explained by larger firms being less volatile and by weaker propagation effects across Chilean firms.]]></description><author>Damiano Sandri, Emiliano Luttini, Francesco Grigoli</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16824</guid></item><item><title>Supply shocks in supply chains: Evidence from the early lockdown in China</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16813</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Isabelle Mejean, Raphael Lafrogne-Joussier, Julien Martin.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> How do firms in global value chains react to input shortages? We examine micro-level adjustments to supply chain shocks, building on the COVID-19 pandemic as a case study. French firms sourcing inputs from China just before the early lockdown in the country experienced a drop in imports between February and April 2020 that is 7% larger than firms sourcing their inputs from elsewhere. This shock on input purchases transmits to the rest of the supply chain through exposed firms' domestic and export sales. Between February and April, firms exposed to the Chinese early lockdown experienced a 5.7% drop in domestic sales and a 5% drop in exports, in relative terms. The drop in foreign sales is entirely attributable to a lower volume of exports driven by a reduction in the number of markets served. We then evaluate whether mitigation strategies adopted by some exposed firms helped them weather the shock. Whereas the ex-ante geographic diversification of inputs does not seem to mitigate the impact of the shock, firms with relatively high inventories have been able to absorb the supply shock better.]]></description><author>Isabelle Mejean, Raphael Lafrogne-Joussier, Julien Martin</author><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16813</guid></item><item><title>Information, Intermediaries, and International Migration</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Job seekers often face substantial information frictions related to potential job quality. This is especially true in international labor markets, where intermediaries match prospective migrants with employers abroad. We conducted a randomized trial in Indonesia to explore how information about intermediary quality shapes migration choices and outcomes. Information reduces the migration rate, lowering use of low-quality intermediaries. However, workers who migrate receive better pre-departure preparation and have higher-quality job experiences abroad, despite no change in occupation or destination. Information does not change intentions to migrate or beliefs about the return to migration or intermediary quality. Nor does selection explain the improved outcomes for workers who choose to migrate with the information. Together, our findings are consistent with an increase in the option value of search: with better ability to differentiate offer quality, workers become choosier and ultimately have better migration experiences. This offers a new perspective on the importance of information and matching frictions in global labor markets.]]></description><author>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</guid></item><item><title>Superstar Returns</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16806</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Moritz Schularick, Martin Dohmen, Sebastian Kohl, Francisco Amaral.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study long-term returns on residential real estate in 27 "superstar" cities in 15 countries over 150 years. We find that total returns in superstar cities are close to 100 basis points lower per year than in the rest of the country. House prices tend to grow faster in the superstars, but rent returns are substantially greater outside the big agglomerations, resulting in higher long-run total returns. The excess returns outside the superstars can be rationalized as a compensation for risk, especially for higher co-variance with income growth and lower liquidity. Superstar real estate is comparatively safe.]]></description><author>Moritz Schularick, Martin Dohmen, Sebastian Kohl, Francisco Amaral</author><pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16806</guid></item><item><title>Cities and Technological Waves</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16794</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruben Gaetani, Enrico Berkes, Martí Mestieri.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We develop a spatial model of economic growth to study the effect of changes in the technological landscape on the spatial distribution of economic activity. We use this framework to study the evolution of the U.S. economic geography over the twentieth century. In the model, innovation via frictional idea diffusion makes cities trajectories sensitive to "technological waves," defined as long-term shifts in the importance of different knowledge fields. We calibrate the model using a new dataset of historical geolocated patents, and find that cities differential exposure to technological waves explains between 15% and 20% of the variation in local population growth over the twentieth century. Counterfactual experiments suggest large and heterogeneous geographical effects of future technological scenarios.]]></description><author>Ruben Gaetani, Enrico Berkes, Martí Mestieri</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16794</guid></item><item><title>Trade and Inequality in Europe and the US</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16780</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Peter Levell, David Dorn.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> The share of low-income countries in global exports nearly tripled between 1990 and 2015, driven largely by the rapid emergence of China as an exporting powerhouse. While research in economics had long acknowledged that trade with lower-income countries could raise income inequality in Europe and the US, empirical estimates indicated only a modest contribution of trade to growing national skill premia. However, if workers are not highly mobile across firms, industries and locations, then the unequal impacts of trade can manifest along different margins. Recent evidence from countries across Europe and the US shows that growing import competition from China differentially reduced earnings and employment rates for workers in more trade-exposed industries, and for the residents of more trade-exposed geographic regions. These adverse impacts were often largest for lower-skilled individuals. We show that domestic manufacturing employment declined much more in countries that saw a large growth of net imports from China (such as the UK and the US), than in countries that maintained relatively balanced trade with China (such as Germany and Switzerland). Drawing on a new analysis for the UK, we further show that trade with China contributed to job loss in manufacturing, but also to substantial declines in consumer prices. However, while the adverse labour market impacts were concentrated on specific groups of workers and regions, the consumer benefits from trade were widely dispersed in the population, and appear similarly large for high-income and low-income households. Globalisation has thus created pockets of losers, and recent evidence indicates that in addition to financial losses, residents of regions with greater exposure to import competition also suffer from higher crime rates, a deterioration of health outcomes, and a dissolution of traditional family structures. We argue that new import tariffs such as those imposed by the US in 2018 and 2019 are unlikely to help the losers from globalisation. Instead, displaced workers may be better supported by a combination of transfers to avert financial hardship, skills training that facilitate reintegration into the labour market, and place-based policies that stimulate job creation in depressed locations.]]></description><author>Peter Levell, David Dorn</author><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16780</guid></item><item><title>Controlling Irregular Migration: Can a Market for Temporary Foreign Work Permits Help?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16777</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tiffanie Perrault, Alice Mesnard, Emmanuelle Auriol.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study how temporary visa schemes can be designed to drive smugglers out of business while meeting labor market demand in host countries. The policy trade-off between migration control and ending human smuggling can be overcome by combining internal and external controls with a regulated market for temporary visas. In this market, visa duration and price are set at "eviction" levels, designed to throttle smuggling activity. We use information on irregular migration from Senegal to Spain and the Democratic Republic of Congo to South Africa to calibrate the eviction prices of visas for these two routes. Our results highlight important constraints for governments seeking to prevent temporary workers from overstaying, especially on South-North routes such as Senegal to Spain. We suggest combining a regulated market for visas with tighter sanctions against employers of undocumented workers as a new way forward.]]></description><author>Tiffanie Perrault, Alice Mesnard, Emmanuelle Auriol</author><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16777</guid></item><item><title>Poor Substitutes? Counterfactual methods in IO and Trade compared</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16762</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Thierry Mayer, Keith Head.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Constant elasticity of substitution (CES) demand for monopolistically competitive firm-varieties is 
a standard  tool for models in international trade and macroeconomics. Inter-variety substitution in this 
model follows a simple share proportionality rule. In contrast, the 
standard toolkit in industrial organization (IO)  estimates a demand system in which cross-elasticities 
depend on similarity in observable attributes. The gain in realism from the IO approach comes at the 
expense of requiring richer data and greater computational challenges. This paper uses the dataset of 
Berry et al. (1995),  who established the modern IO  method, to simulate counterfactual trade policy 
experiments. We use the CES model  as an approximation of the more 
complex underlying demand system and market structure. Although the CES model omits key elements 
of the data generating process, the errors are offsetting, leading to reasonably accurate counterfactual predictions. 
For aggregate outcomes, it turns out that incorporating non-unitary pass-through matters more than fixing 
over-simplified substitution patterns. We do so by extending the commonly used methods of Exact Hat Algebra 
and tariff elasticity estimation to take into account oligopoly.]]></description><author>Thierry Mayer, Keith Head</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16762</guid></item><item><title>Production Networks and War</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16759</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexey Makarin, Vasily Korovkin.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> How do severe shocks such as war alter the economy? We study how a country's production network is affected by a devastating but localized conflict. Using unique transaction-level data on Ukrainian railway shipments, we uncover several novel indirect effects of conflict on firms. First, we document substantial propagation effects on interfirm trade---trade declines even between partners outside the conflict areas if one of them had traded with those areas before the start of the war. The magnitude of such second-degree effect of conflict is one-third of the first-degree effect. Ignoring this propagation would lead to an underestimate of the total impact of conflict on trade by about 67%. Second, war induces sudden changes in the production-network structure that influence firm performance. Specifically, we find that firms that exogenously became more central---after the conflict practically cut off certain regions from the rest of Ukraine---received a relative boost to their revenues and profits. Finally, in a production-network model, we separately estimate the effects of the exogenous firm removal and the subsequent endogenous network adjustment on firm revenue distribution. At the median, network adjustment compensates for 80% of the network-destruction effect a year after the conflict onset.]]></description><author>Alexey Makarin, Vasily Korovkin</author><pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16759</guid></item><item><title>A Primer on Trade and Inequality</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16742</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Dani Rodrik.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> In the public imagination globalization's adverse effects have loomed large, contributing significantly to the backlash against the political mainstream and the rise of far-right populism. The literature on trade and inequality is in fact exceptionally rich, with important theoretical insights as well as extensive empirical findings that sheds light on this recent experience. Some of the key results of this literature, discussed here, are as follows: Redistribution is the flip side of the gains from trade, and it becomes larger relative to net gains from trade in the advanced stages of globalization. Compensation is difficult for both economic and political reasons. International trade often differs from other market exchanges, raising fairness concerns in ways that domestic markets do not. The economic benefits of deep integration are generally ambiguous. Dynamic or growth gains from trade are uncertain.]]></description><author>Dani Rodrik</author><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16742</guid></item><item><title>Globalization and the Ladder of Development: Pushed to the Top or Held at the Bottom?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16741</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Masao Fukui, Arnaud Costinot, David Atkin.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> We study the relationship between international trade and development in a model where countries differ in their capability, goods differ in their complexity, and capability growth is a function of a country's pattern of specialization. Theoretically, we show that it is possible for international trade to increase capability growth in all countries and, in turn, to push all countries up the development ladder. This occurs because: (i) the average complexity of a country's industry mix raises its capability growth, and (ii) foreign competition is tougher in less complex sectors for all countries. Empirically, we provide causal evidence consistent with (i) using the entry of countries into the World Trade Organization as an instrumental variable for other countries' patterns of specialization. The opposite of (ii), however, appears to hold in the data. Through the lens of our model, these two empirical observations imply dynamic welfare losses from trade that are small for the median country, but pervasive and large among a number of African countries.]]></description><author>Masao Fukui, Arnaud Costinot, David Atkin</author><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16741</guid></item></channel></rss>