<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR Monetary Economics and Fluctuations</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR Monetary Economics and Fluctuations</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 15:35:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Diverse Policy Committees Can Reach Underrepresented Groups</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16563</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Increasing the diversity of policy committees has taken center stage worldwide, but whether and why diverse committees are more effective is still unclear. In a randomized control trial that varies the salience of female and minority representation on the Federal Reserve's monetary policy committee, the FOMC, we test whether diversity affects how Fed information influences consumers' subjective beliefs. Women and Black respondents form unemployment expectations more in line with FOMC forecasts and trust the Fed more after this intervention. Women are also more likely to acquire Fed-related information when associated with a female official. White men, who are overrepresented on the FOMC,  do not react negatively. Heterogeneous taste for diversity can explain these patterns better than homophily. Our results suggest more diverse policy committees are better able to reach underrepresented groups without inducing negative reactions by others, thereby enhancing the effectiveness of policy communication and public trust in the institution.]]></description><author>D'Acunto, Francesco &amp; Fuster, Andreas &amp; Weber, Michael</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16563</guid></item><item><title>Estimating Hysteresis Effects</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16558</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> In this paper we identify demand shocks that can have a permanent effect on output through hysteresis effects. We call these shocks permanent demand shocks. They are found to be quantitatively important in the United States, in particular when the Great Recession is included in the sample. Recessions driven by permanent demand shocks lead to a permanent decline in employment and investment (including R&D investment), while output per worker is largely unaffected. We find strong evidence that hysteresis transmits through a rise in long-term unemployment and a decline in labor force participation and disproportionately affects the least productive workers.]]></description><author>Furlanetto, Francesco &amp; Lepetit, Antoine &amp; Robstad, Ørjan &amp; Rubio-Ramírez, Juan Francisco &amp; Ulvedal, Pal-bergset</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16558</guid></item><item><title>Central Banks and Inflation: Where Do We Stand and How Did We Get Here?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16557</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The inability of central banks to attain their target inflation rates in recent years has raised questions about the extent to which central banks can control the inflation process. This paper discusses the evolution of thought and evidence since the 1960s on the determinants of inflation and the role that should be played by central banks. The paper highlights the roles played by two streams of thought associated with Milton Friedman: Monetarist theories predicting a key role for monetary aggregates in determining inflation and the rise in popularity of the expectations-augmented Phillips curve. We discuss influence of the latter in determining the modern consensus on central bank institutions and the relative roles for fiscal and monetary policies. We conclude with a discussion of macroeconomic developments of the past decade and current policy options to stimulate the economy and restore inflation to its target levels, including the merits of "helicopter money".]]></description><author>Whelan, Karl</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16557</guid></item><item><title>Monetary Policy, Labor Income Redistribution and the Credit Channel: Evidence from Matched Employer-Employee and Credit Registers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16549</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper documents the redistributive effects of monetary policy on labor market outcomes via
the credit channel. For identification, we exploit matched administrative datasets in Portugal
- employee-employer and credit registers - and monetary policy since the Eurozone creation
in 1999. We find that softer monetary policy improves worker labor market outcomes (wages,
hours worked and firm employment) more in small and young firms, which are more financially
constrained. Within small and young firms, the wage effects accrue to incumbent workers,
in line with the back-loaded wage mechanism. Consistent with the capital-skill complementarity
mechanism, we document an increase in skill premium and show that financially constrained
firms increase both physical and human capital investment by most. Our findings uncover
a central role for both the firm-balance sheet and the bank lending channels of the monetary
policy transmission to labor income inequality, with state-dependent effects that are substantially
stronger during crisis times. Importantly, we do not find any redistributive effects for firms
without bank credit.]]></description><author>Jasova, Martina &amp; Mendicino, Caterina &amp; Panetti, Ettore &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Supera, Dominik</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16549</guid></item><item><title>The Elusive State of Full Employment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16535</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> During the expansion phase of the business cycle unemployment declines towards levels that are usually associated to the natural rate of unemployment. Unfortunately, those low levels of unemployment are short lived. In the last 60 years, the US has not witnessed a long period of stable and low unemployment. We argue that this result is consistent with an asymmetric view of the business cycles (as in Friedman's plucking model) where many expansions are unfinished business, they end too early. The speed of labor market recovery is too slow and before the economy reaches full employment a recession starts, either because of imbalances or bad luck. Our analysis has implications for how we think about labor market slack and potential output. From a policy perspective it calls for a focus on faster recoveries while avoiding the type of imbalances that can be the seed of the next crisis.]]></description><author>Fatás, Antonio</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16535</guid></item><item><title>Commodity Prices and Global Inflation, 1851-1913</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16526</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper uses annual data to study the interaction of consumer and commodity prices in 15 economies over the period 1850-1913. We find that consumer price inflation in all 15 countries co-moves with a broad measure of changes in commodity prices. Consumer prices comove most strongly with changes in metal prices, in particular pig iron prices. Furthermore, changes in pig iron prices and production, which have attracted much attention in the literature on 19th century US business cycles, co-move with the international business cycle, suggesting that pig iron prices offer a transmission channel through which international business cycle movements affect inflation.]]></description><author>Gerlach, Stefan &amp; Stuart, Rebecca</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16526</guid></item><item><title>Central Bank Communication with Non-Experts - A Road to Nowhere?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16525</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Central banks have intensified their communication with non-experts â?? an endeavour which some have argued is bound to fail. This paper studies English and German Twitter traffic about the ECB to understand whether its communication is received by non-experts and how it affects their views. It shows that Twitter traffic is responsive to ECB communication, also for non-experts. For several ECB communication events, Twitter constitutes primarily a channel to relay information: tweets become more factual and the views expressed more moderate and homogeneous. Other communication events, such as former President Draghi's "Whatever it takes" statement, trigger persistent traffic and a divergence in views. Also, ECB-related tweets are more likely to get retweeted or liked if they express stronger or more subjective views. Thus, Twitter also serves as a platform for controversial discussions. The findings suggest that central banks manage to reach non-experts, i.e. their communication is not a road to nowhere.]]></description><author>Ehrmann, Michael &amp; Wabitsch, Alena</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16525</guid></item><item><title>Spending a Windfall</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16523</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the effect of the discovery of precious metals in America on international trade from 1500 to 1810. Around 1500, there was a simultaneous discovery of precious metals and new trading routes. We construct a counterfactual scenario of new routes but no precious metals. The discovery of precious metals was a windfall to Europe. It increased the stock of precious metals in the world more than tenfold. Compared with the case of no trade routes and no precious metals, Euro-Asian trade increases up to 20 times. We find that American precious metals were at least as important as the new trading routes as a cause of observed trade patterns.]]></description><author>Palma, Nuno Pedro G. &amp; Silva, André</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16523</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Market Expectations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16520</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Asset prices are a valuable source of information about financial market participants' expectations about key macroeconomic variables. However, the presence of time-varying risk premia requires an adjustment of market prices to obtain the market's rational assessment of future price and policy developments. This paper reviews empirical approaches for recovering market-based expectations. It starts by laying out the two canonical modeling frameworks that form the backbone for estimating risk premia and highlights the proliferation of risk pricing factors that result in a wide range of different asset-price-based expectation measures. It then describes a key methodological innovation to evaluate the empirical plausibility of risk premium estimates and to identify the most accurate market-based expectation measure. The usefulness of this general approach is illustrated for price expectations in the global oil market. Then, the paper provides an overview of the body of empirical evidence for monetary policy and inflation expectations with a special emphasis on market-specific characteristics that complicate the quest for the best possible market-based expectation measure. Finally, it discusses a number of economic applications where market expectations play a key role for evaluating economic models, guiding policy analysis, and deriving shock measures.]]></description><author>Baumeister, Christiane</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16520</guid></item><item><title>Measuring credit procyclicality: a new database</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16519</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Today, the data available to estimate the credit cycle involve a trade-off between country coverage and frequency. In addition, there are pending methodological issues to estimate credit trend and cyclical components. To address these limits, we build a new database on credit metrics that relaxes the trade-off  and includes credit procyclicality measures along three alternative methods- HP filter, the modified HP filter and basic SSA. The credit gaps in our database are statistically consistent with bank credit gaps estimated with BIS data and they have the advantage of being available for 163 countries instead of 43 countries. Armed with this new and expanded data, we revisit classic empirical questions in the literature.]]></description><author>Bouvatier, Vincent &amp; Delatte, Anne-Laure &amp; Rehault, Pierre-Nicolas</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16519</guid></item><item><title>Distrust or speculation? The socioeconomic drivers of U.S. cryptocurrency investments</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16518</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Employing representative data from the U.S. Survey of Consumer Payment Choice, we disprove the hypothesis that cryptocurrency investors are motivatedby distrust in fiat currencies or regulated finance. Compared with the general population, investors show no differences in their level of security concerns with either cash or commercial banking services. We find that cryptocurrency investors tend to be educated, young and digital natives. In recent years, a gap in ownership of cryptocurrencies across genders has emerged. We examine how investor characteristics vary across cryptocurrencies and show that owners of cryptocurrencies increasingly tend to hold their investment for longer periods.]]></description><author>Auer, Raphael &amp; Tercero Lucas, David</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16518</guid></item><item><title>Capital Controls, Domestic Macroprudential Policy and the Bank Lending Channel of Monetary Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16510</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study how capital controls and domestic macroprudential policy tame credit supply booms, respectively targeting foreign and domestic bank debt. For identification, we exploit the simultaneous introduction of capital controls on foreign exchange (FX) debt inflows and an increase of reserve requirements on domestic bank deposits in Colombia during a strong credit boom, as well as credit registry and bank balance sheet data. Our results suggest that first, an increase in the local monetary policy rate, raising the interest rate spread with the United States, allows more FX-indebted banks to carry trade cheap FX funds with more expensive peso lending, especially toward riskier, opaque firms. Capital controls tax FX debt and break the carry trade. Second, the increase in reserve requirements on domestic deposits directly reduces credit supply, and more so for riskier, opaque firms, rather than enhances the transmission of monetary rates on credit supply. Importantly, different banks finance credit in the boom with either domestic or foreign (FX) financing. Hence, capital controls and domestic macroprudential policy complementarily mitigate the boom and the associated risk-taking through two distinct channels.]]></description><author>Fabiani, Andrea &amp; Lopéz Piñeros, Martha &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Soto, Paul</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16510</guid></item><item><title>Systemic Implications of the Bail-In Design</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16509</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The 2007-2008 financial crisis forced governments to choose between the unattractive alternatives of either bailing out a systemically important bank (SIB) or allowing it to fail disruptively. Bail-in has been put forward as an alternative that potentially addresses the too-big-to-fail and contagion risk problems simultaneously. Though its efficacy has been demonstrated for smaller idiosyncratic SIB failures, its ability to maintain stability in cases of large SIB failures and system-wide crises remains untested. This paper's novelty is to assess the financial-stability implications of bail-in design, explicitly accounting for the multi-layered networked nature of the financial system. We present a model of the European financial system that captures all five of the prevailing contagion channels. We demonstrate that it is essential to understand the interaction of multiple contagion mechanisms and that financial institutions other than banks play an important role. Our results indicate that stability hinges on the bank-specific and structural bail-in design. On one hand, a well-designed bail-in buttresses financial resilience, but on the other hand, an ill-designed bail-in tends to exacerbate financial distress, especially in system-wide crises and when there are large SIB failures. Our analysis suggests that the current bail-in design may be in the region of instability. While policy makers can fix this, the political economy incentives make this unlikely.]]></description><author>Farmer, Doyne &amp; Goodhart, Charles A &amp; Kleinnijenhuis, Alissa M.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16509</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Channel of Wage Rigidity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16499</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> I propose a financial channel of wage rigidity. In recessions, rather than propping up marginal (new hires') costs of labor, rigid average wages squeeze cash flows, forcing firms to cut hiring due to financial constraints. Indeed, empirical cash flows and profits would turn acyclical if wages were only moderately more procyclical. I study this channel in a search and matching model with financial constraints and rigid wages among incumbent workers, while new hires' wages are flexible. Individually, each feature generates no amplification. By contrast, their interaction can account for much of the empirical labor market fluctuations--breaking the neutrality of incumbents' wages for hiring, and showing that financial amplification of business cycles requires wage rigidity.]]></description><author>Schoefer, Benjamin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16499</guid></item><item><title>Nowcasting Tail Risk to Economic Activity at a Weekly Frequency</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16496</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper focuses on nowcasts of tail risk to GDP growth, with a potentially wide array of monthly and weekly information used to produce nowcasts on a weekly basis. We consider diï¬?erent models, consisting of Bayesian mixed frequency regressions with stochastic volatility, Bayesian quantile regressions, and Bayesian partial quantile regression, the last of which incorporates data reduction through a common factor. Our results show that, within some limits, more information helps the accuracy of nowcasts of tail risk to GDP growth. Accuracy typically improves as time moves forward within a quarter, making additional data available, with monthly data more important to accuracy than weekly data. Accuracy also typically improves with the use of ï¬?nancial indicators in addition to a base set of macroeconomic indicators.]]></description><author>Carriero, Andrea &amp; Clark, Todd &amp; Marcellino, Massimiliano</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16496</guid></item><item><title>Financial Stability Policies and Bank Lending: Quasi-experimental Evidence from Federal Reserve Interventions in 1920-1921</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16490</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> I exploit a single natural experiment to estimate the comparative causal effects of different financial stability policies on bank-level credit. In 1920, four Federal Reserve Banks hiked their interest rate indiscriminately to safeguard financial stability. Another four Reserve Banks employed targeted rate action aimed at over-leveraged banks instead. For identification, I draw on border regression discontinuities with the remaining Federal Reserve districts which did not change their stance. The uniform rate hike had counterproductive effects, whereas targeted policy caused credit to contract significantly. The relative strengths of the bank-lending and risk-shifting channels of monetary policy explain these differential outcomes.]]></description><author>Rieder, Kilian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16490</guid></item><item><title>Robust Bayesian Analysis for Econometrics</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16488</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We review the literature on robust Bayesian analysis as a tool for global sensitivity analysis and for statistical decision-making under ambiguity. We discuss the methods proposed in the literature, including the different ways of constructing the set of priors that are the key input of the robust Bayesian analysis. We consider both a general set-up for Bayesian statistical decisions and inference and the special case of set-identified structural models. We provide new results that can be used to derive and compute the set of posterior moments for sensitivity analysis and to compute the optimal statistical decision under multiple priors. The paper ends with a self-contained discussion of three different approaches to robust Bayesian inference for set- identified structural vector autoregressions, including details about numerical implementation and an empirical illustration.]]></description><author>Giacomini, Raffaella &amp; Kitagawa, Toru &amp; Read, Matthew</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16488</guid></item><item><title>A Tale of Two Global Monetary Policies</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16485</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> US monetary policy is not the only one with a global reach. We compare the international financial spillovers of the unconventional monetary policies of the Fed and the ECB. Monetary policy tightenings in both areas are followed by a global retrenchment in capital flows, a fall in global stock markets, and a rise in global risk measures. Thus, ECB and Fed monetary policies propagate internationally through equivalent transmission channels. ECB monetary policy shocks also affect significantly the US business and financial cycles. We produce tentative evidence that links the strength of the ECB international spillovers to the â?¬ exposure for both trade invoicing and the pricing of financial transactions.]]></description><author>Miranda-Agrippino, Silvia &amp; Nenova, Tsvetelina</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16485</guid></item><item><title>Demographics, Wealth, and Global Imbalances in the Twenty-First Century</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16470</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We use a sufficient statistic approach to quantify the general equilibrium effects of population aging on wealth accumulation, expected asset returns, and global imbalances. Combining population forecasts with household survey data from 25 countries, we measure the compositional effect of aging: how a changing age distribution affects wealth-to-GDP, holding the age profiles of assets and labor income fixed. In a baseline overlapping generations model this statistic, in conjunction with cross-sectional information and two standard macro parameters, pins down general equilibrium outcomes. Since the compositional effect is positive, large, and heterogeneous across countries, our model predicts that population aging will increase wealth-to-GDP ratios, lower asset returns, and widen global imbalances through the twenty-first century. These conclusions extend to a richer model in which bequests, individual savings, and the tax-and-transfer system all respond to demographic change.]]></description><author>Auclert, Adrien &amp; Malmberg, Hannes &amp; Martenet, Frederic &amp; Rognlie, Matthew</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16470</guid></item><item><title>Mortgage Pricing and Monetary Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16456</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper provides novel evidence on lenders' mortgage pricing and how central bank policies affected it. Using the universe of mortgages originated in the U.K., we show that lenders seek to segment the market by offering two-part tariffs composed of interest rates and origination fees, and that during recent periods of unconventional monetary policy, such as the U.K.'s Funding for Lending Scheme, lenders decreased interest rates and increased  origination fees. To understand lenders' pricing strategies and their effects on market equilibrium, we develop and estimate a structural discrete-continuous model of mortgage demand and lender competition in which borrowers may have different sensitivities to rates and fees. We use the estimated model to decompose the effects of unconventional monetary policies on mortgage pricing and lending, and find that central bank policies increased borrower surplus and lender profits. Moreover, although origination fees allow lenders to price discriminate and capture surplus, banning fees would lower borrower surplus and aggregate welfare.]]></description><author>Benetton, Matteo &amp; Gavazza, Alessandro &amp; Surico, Paolo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16456</guid></item><item><title>Financial crises: A survey</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16450</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Financial crises have large deleterious effects on economic activity, and as such have been the focus of a large body of research. This study surveys the existing literature on financial crises, exploring how crises are measured, whether they are predictable, and why they are associated with economic contractions. Historical narrative techniques continue to form the backbone for measuring crises, but there have been exciting developments in using quantitative data as well. Crises are predictable with growth in credit and elevated asset prices playing an especially important role; recent research points convincingly to the importance of behavioral biases in explaining such predictability. The negative consequences of a crisis are due to both the crisis itself but also to the imbalances that precede a crisis. Crises do not occur randomly, and, as a result, an understanding of financial crises requires an investigation into the booms that precede them.]]></description><author>Sufi, Amir &amp; Taylor, Alan M.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16450</guid></item><item><title>The Bank Liquidity Channel of Financial (In)stability</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16438</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We examine the system-wide effects of liquidity regulation on banks' balance sheets. In the general equilibrium model, banks have to hold liquid assets, and choose among illiquid assets varying in the extent to which they are difficult to value before maturity, e.g., structured securities. By improving the liquidity of interbank markets, tighter liquidity requirements induce banks to invest in such complex assets. We evaluate the welfare properties of combining liquidity regulation with other financial-stability policies, and show that it can complement ex-ante policies, such as asset-specific taxes, whereas it can undermine the benefits of ex-post interventions, such as quantitative easing.]]></description><author>Bosshardt, Joshua &amp; Kakhbod, Ali &amp; Saidi, Farzad</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16438</guid></item><item><title>The Transmission of Keynesian Supply Shocks</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16430</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Sectoral supply shocks can trigger shortages in aggregate demand when strong sectoral complementarities are at play. US data on sectoral output and prices offer support to this notion of "Keynesian supply shocks" and their underlying transmission mechanism. Demand shocks derived from standard identification schemes using aggregate data can originate from sectoral supply shocks that spillover to other sectors via a Keynesian supply mechanism. This finding is a regular feature of the data and is independent of the effects of the 2020 pandemic. In a New Keynesian model with input-output network calibrated to 3-digit US data, sectoral productivity shocks generate the same pattern for output growth and inflation as observed in the data. The degree of sectoral interconnection, both upstream and downstream, and price stickiness are key determinants of the strength of the mechanism. Sectoral shocks may account for a larger fraction of business cycle fluctuations than previously thought.]]></description><author>Cesa-Bianchi, Ambrogio &amp; Ferrero, Andrea</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16430</guid></item><item><title>Mismatch Cycles</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16423</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the cyclical dynamics of skill mismatch and quantifies its impact
on labor productivity. We build a tractable directed search model, in which workers
differ in skills along multiple dimensions and sort into jobs with heterogeneous skill
requirements. Skill mismatch arises due to information frictions and is prolonged by
search frictions. Estimated to the U.S., the model replicates salient business cycle
properties of mismatch. Job transitions in and out of bottom job rungs, combined with
career mobility, are key to account for the empirical fit. The model provides a novel
narrative for the scarring effect of unemployment.]]></description><author>Baley, Isaac &amp; Figueiredo, Ana &amp; Ulbricht, Robert</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16423</guid></item><item><title>Communicating Data Uncertainty: Multi-Wave Experimental Evidence for U.K. GDP</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16417</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Economic statistics are commonly published without any explicit indication of their uncertainty. To assess if and how the UK public interpret and understand data uncertainty, we conduct two waves of a randomized controlled online experiment. A control group is presented with the headline point estimate of GDP, as emphasized by the statistical office. Treatment groups are then presented with alternative qualitative and quantitative communications of GDP data uncertainty. We find that most of the public understand there is uncertainty inherent in official GDP numbers. But communicating uncertainty information improves understanding. It encourages the public not to take estimates at face-value, but does not decrease trust in the data. Quantitative tools to communicate data uncertainty - notably intervals, density strips and bell curves - are especially beneficial. They reduce dispersion of the public's subjective probabilistic expectations of data uncertainty, improving alignment with objective estimates.]]></description><author>Galvão, Ana Beatriz C &amp; Mitchell, James</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16417</guid></item><item><title>Monetary Policy in the Age of Automation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16416</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We provide a framework in which monetary policy affects firms' automation decisions (i.e. how intensively capital and labor are used in production). This new feature has far-reaching consequences for monetary policy. Monetary expansions can increase output by inducing firms to invest and automate more, while having little impact on inflation and employment. A protracted period of weak demand might translate into less investment and de-automation, rather than into deflation and involuntary unemployment. Running the economy hot, through expansionary monetary and fiscal policies, may have a positive long run impact on labor productivity and wages. Technological advances that increase the scope for automation may give rise to persistent unemployment, unless they are accompanied by expansionary macroeconomic policies.]]></description><author>Fornaro, Luca &amp; Wolf, Martin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16416</guid></item><item><title>Can Monetary Policy Create Fiscal Capacity?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16414</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Governments around the world have gone on a massive fiscal expansion in response to the Covid crisis, increasing government debt to levels not seen in 75 years. How will this debt be repaid?  What role do conventional and unconventional monetary policy play? We  investigate debt sustainability in a New Keynesian model with an intermediary sector, realistic fiscal and monetary policy, endogenous convenience yields, and substantial risk premia. When conventional monetary policy is constrained by the ZLB during an economic crisis, increased government spending and lower tax revenue lead to a large rise in government debt and raise the risk of future tax increases. We find that quantitative easing (QE), forward guidance, and an expansion in government discretionary spending all contribute to lowering debt/GDP ratio and reducing this fiscal risk. A transitory QE policy deployed during a crisis stimulates aggregate demand.]]></description><author>Elenev, Vadim &amp; Landvoigt, Tim &amp; Shultz, Patrick &amp; van Nieuwerburgh, Stijn</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16414</guid></item><item><title>Who Saves More, the Naive or the Sophisticated Agent?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16412</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We consider an additively time-separable life-cycle model for the family of power
period utility functions u such that u'(c) = c^(-theta) for resistance to inter-temporal
substitution of theta > 0. The utility maximization problem over life-time consumption
is dynamically inconsistent for almost all specifications of effective discount factors.
Pollak (1968) shows that the savings behavior of a sophisticated agent and her naive
counterpart is always identical for a logarithmic utility function (i.e., for theta = 1). As
an extension of Pollak's result we show that the sophisticated agent saves a greater
(smaller) fraction of her wealth in every period than her naive counterpart whenever
theta > 1 (theta < 1) irrespective of the specification of discount factors. We further show
that this finding extends to an environment with risky returns and dynamically
inconsistent Epstein-Zin-Weil preferences.]]></description><author>Groneck, Max &amp; Ludwig, Alexander &amp; Zimper, Alexander</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16412</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal and monetary policy interactions in a low interest rate world</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16411</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We analyse fiscal and monetary policy interactions when interest rate policy is hampered by the zero lower bound (ZLB) in an environment where expectations are formed with perpetual learning. The ZLB induces a deterioration of economic performance and raises the risk of persistent lowflation that can disanchor inflation expectations and lead to debt deflation. Systematic use of quantitative easing (QE) can partially substitute for interest rate easing and, if sufficiently aggressive, can maintain average inflation in line with the central bank's goal. By compressing term premia on long-term interest rates, QE creates fiscal space that facilitates expansionary fiscal policy and reduces debt-deflation risk. The ZLB can be counteracted with less aggressive QE if mildly negative policy rates are feasible, if more countercyclical fiscal policy can be activated, or if the central bank can credibly communicate a clear inflation goal. Timidity in implementing QE and excessively debt-averse fiscal policies are counterproductive.]]></description><author>Hofmann, Boris &amp; Lombardi, Marco &amp; Mojon, Benoit &amp; Orphanides, Athanasios</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16411</guid></item><item><title>The Treasury Market in Spring 2020 and the Response of the Federal Reserve</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16410</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Treasury yields spiked during the initial phase of COVID. The 10-year yield increased by 64 bps from March 9 to 18, 2020, leading the Federal Reserve to purchase $1T of Treasuries in 2020Q1. Fed purchases were causal for reducing Treasury yields based on the timing of purchases (which increased on March 19), the timing of yield reversal and Fed purchases in the MBS market, and evidence against confounding factors. Treasury-QE worked more via purchases than announcements. The yield spike was driven by liquidity needs of mutual funds, foreign official agencies, and hedge funds that were unaffected by the March 15 Treasury-QE announcement.]]></description><author>Vissing-Jørgensen, Annette</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16410</guid></item><item><title>Consistent Evidence on Duration Dependence of Price Changes</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16404</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We develop an estimator and tests of a discrete time mixed proportional hazard (MPH) model of duration with unobserved heterogeneity.  We allow for competing risks, observable characteristics, and censoring, and we use linear GMM, making estimation and inference straightforward.   With repeated spell data, our estimator is consistent and robust to the unknown shape of the frailty distribution.  We apply our estimator to the duration of price spells in weekly store data from IRI.  We find substantial unobserved heterogeneity, accounting for a large fraction of the decrease in the Kaplan-Meier hazard with elapsed duration.  Still, we show that the estimated baseline hazard rate is decreasing and a homogeneous firm model can accurately capture the response of the economy to a monetary policy shock even if there is significant strategic complementarity in pricing. Using competing risks and spell-specific observable characteristics, we separately estimate the model for regular and temporary price changes and find that the MPH structure describes regular price changes better than temporary ones.]]></description><author>Alvarez, Fernando &amp; Borovicková, Katarína &amp; Shimer, Robert</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16404</guid></item><item><title>Macroeconomic stabilisation and monetary policy effectiveness in a low-interest-rate environment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16403</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> The secular decline in the equilibrium real interest rate observed over the past decades has materially limited the room for policy-rate reductions in recessions, and has led to a marked increase in the incidence of episodes where policy rates are likely to be at, or near, the effective lower bound on nominal interest rates. Using the ECB's New Area-Wide Model, we show that, if unaddressed, the effective lower bound can cause substantial costs in terms of worsened macroeconomic performance, as reflected in negative biases in inflation and economic activity, as well as heightened macroeconomic volatility. These costs can be mitigated by the use of nonstandard instruments, notably the joint use of interest-rate forward guidance and large-scale asset purchases. When considering alternatives to inflation targeting, we find that make-up strategies such as price-level targeting and average-inflation targeting can, if they are well-understood by the private sector, largely undo the negative biases and heightened volatility induced by the effective lower bound.]]></description><author>Coenen, Günter &amp; Montes-Galdon, Carlos &amp; Schmidt, Sebastian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16403</guid></item><item><title>Carbon Taxation and Inflation: Evidence from the European and Canadian Experience</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16396</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> What is the effect of climate policies on inflation and economic activity? Answering this question is critical for central banks trying to achieve price stability. This paper studies the experience from existing Co2 taxes in Canada and Europe, introduced over the last 30 years. Based on two separate empirical approaches, we find that carbon taxes do not have to be inflationary and may even have deflationary effects. In particular, our evidence suggests that the increase in energy prices was more than offset by a fall in the prices of services and other non-tradables. Our results are robust for Europe and Canada, as well as a number of different country groupings. At least in case of British Columbia, a contraction in household incomes and expenditures, in particular among the richer households, could explain the deflationary effect.]]></description><author>Konradt, Maximilian &amp; Weder di Mauro, Beatrice</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16396</guid></item><item><title>Financial 'Side Effects' of QE and Conventional Monetary Policy Compared</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16395</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We explore the size of financial 'side effects' of QE relative to those of conventional monetary policy for the Euro Area, UK and US. Following previous work for conventional monetary policy we examine the effects on private credit imbalances, financial market risk and asset valuation. We adopt an agnostic Bayesian VAR approach, identifying QE and conventional monetary policy shocks with four different identification schemes and two different measures of unconventional monetary policy. We compare the size of each side effect by the amount of inflation generated by each policy, as all three of these central banks were targeting inflation during this time. The relative size of these effects is at the heart of the current debate about the financial stability and wealth inequality consequences of accommodative monetary policy. While both, conventional monetary policy and QE, generate some financial 'side effects', there is no statistical evidence that the effect of QE on these variables is consistently larger than the effect of conventional monetary policy.]]></description><author>Weale, M &amp; Wieladek, Tomasz</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16395</guid></item><item><title>Pandemic Lockdown: The Role of Government Commitment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16384</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This paper studies lockdown policy in a dynamic economy without government commitment. Lockdown imposes a cap on labor supply, which improves health prospects at the cost of economic output and consumption. A government would like to commit to the extent of future lockdowns in order to guarantee an economic outlook that supports efficient levels of investment into intermediate inputs. However, such a commitment is not credible, since investments are sunk at the time when the government chooses a lockdown. As a result, lockdown under lack of commitment deviates from the optimal policy. Rules that limit a government's lockdown discretion can improve social welfare, even in the presence of noncontractible information. Quantitatively, lack of commitment causes lockdown to be significantly more severe than is socially optimal. The output and consumption loss due to lack of commitment is greater for higher intermediate input shares, higher discount rates, higher values of life, higher disease transmission rates at and outside of work, and longer vaccine arrival times.]]></description><author>Moser, Christian &amp; Yared, Pierre</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16384</guid></item><item><title>Bayesian Learning</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16377</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We survey work using Bayesian learning in macroeconomics, highlighting common themes and new directions. First, we present many of the common types of learning problems agents face -- signal extraction problems -- and trace out their effects on macro aggregates, in different strategic settings. Then we review different perspectives on how agents get their information. Models differ in their motives for information acquisition and the cost of information, or learning technology. Finally, we survey the growing literature on the data economy, where economic activity generates data and the information in data feeds back to affect economic activity.]]></description><author>Baley, Isaac &amp; Veldkamp, Laura</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16377</guid></item></channel></rss>