<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR Industrial Organization</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR Industrial Organization</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 15:26:52 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Women in Economics: Europe and the World</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16686</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Based on a data set that we collected from the top research institutions in
economics around the globe (including universities, business schools and other organizations
such as central banks), we document the underrepresentation of women
in economics. For the 238 universities and business schools in the sample, women
hold 25% of senior level positions (full professor, associate professor) and 37% of
junior level positions. In the 82 U.S. universities and business schools, the figures
are 20% on the senior level and 32% on the entry level, while in the 122 European
institutions, the numbers are 27% and 38%, respectively, with some heterogeneity
across countries. The numbers also show that the highest-ranking institutions (in
terms of research output) have fewer women in senior positions. Moreover, in the
U.S., this effect is even present on the junior level. The "leaky pipeline" may hence
begin earlier than oftentimes assumed, and is even more of an issue in the highly
integrated market of the U.S. In Europe, an institution ranked 100 places higher
has three percentage points fewer women in senior positions, but in the U.S. it is
almost 5 percentage points.]]></description><author>Auriol, Emmanuelle &amp; Friebel, Guido &amp; Weinberger, Alisa &amp; Wilhelm, Sascha</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16686</guid></item><item><title>Misdiagnosing Bank Capital Problems</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16680</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Banks' reluctance to repair their balance sheets, combined with deposit insurance and regulatory forbearance in recognizing greater risks and losses, can lead to solvency problems that look like liquidity (bank-run) crises. Regulatory forbearance incentivizes banks to both retain risky loans and reject new good opportunities. With sufficient regulatory forbearance, partially-insured banks act exactly as if they are fully insured. Stress tests certify that uninsured creditors will be paid, not that banks are solvent, and have ambiguous effects on the efficiency of investment.]]></description><author>Bulow, Jeremy &amp; Klemperer, Paul</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16680</guid></item><item><title>Competition and Misconduct</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16678</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Misconduct is widespread; practices such as mis-selling, pump&dump, and money laundering harm counterparties while raising profits. This paper presents a mechanism which can determine what sorts of misconduct can be sustained in competitive equilibrium in concentrated markets, oligopoly settings, and in markets with many small competing firms. The model studied allows general demand and makes a distinction in types of ethical dilemma using current psychological understanding. The paper shows, for example, that markets with many small competing firms are not vulnerable to misconduct if firms respond to entry with niche strategies or if the ethical dilemma draws an emotional response.]]></description><author>Thanassoulis, John</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16678</guid></item><item><title>An Empirical Model of Quantity Discounts with Large Choice Sets</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16666</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We introduce a Generalized Nested Logit model of demand for bundles that can be estimated sequentially and virtually eliminates any challenge of dimensionality related to large choice sets. We use it to investigate quantity discounts for carbonated soft drinks by simulating a counterfactual with linear pricing. The prices of quantities up to 1L decrease by -31.5% while those of larger quantities increase by +14.8%. Purchased quantities decrease by -20.4%, associated added sugar by -23.8%, and industry profit by -20.5%. Consumer surplus however reduces only moderately, suggesting that linear pricing may be effective in limiting added sugar intake.]]></description><author>Iaria, Alessandro &amp; WANG, Ao</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16666</guid></item><item><title>Selecting Valuation Distributions: Non-Price Decisions of Multi-Product Firms</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16655</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper analyzes decisions of multi-product firms regarding product selection, innovation and advertising as choices of consumer valuation distributions. We show that a profit-maximizing monopolist chooses these distributions so as to maximize the dispersion of the valuation differences between goods across consumers. By contrast, she chooses the willingness-to-pay to be maximally or minimally dispersed, depending on the set of available distributions. In our benchmark model with uniform valuation differences, prices are increasing in valuation difference heterogeneity, but in more general settings this is not necessarily true. Moreover, the relation between willingness-to-pay heterogeneity and prices may well be non-monotone. Over wide parameter ranges, the firm's choice of valuation distribution does not maximize net consumer surplus. This problem is exacerbated when the firm has access to strategies that distort valuation heterogeneity or willingness-to-pay heterogeneity.]]></description><author>Bossard, Stefanie &amp; Schmutzler, Armin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16655</guid></item><item><title>Relational Contracts and Trust in a High-Tech Industry</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16653</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We study how informal buyer-supplier relationships in the German automotive industry aï¬?ect procurement. Using unique data from a survey focusing on these, we show that more trust, the belief that the trading partner acts to maintain the mutual relationship, is associated with both higher quality of the automotive parts and more competition among suppliers. Yet both eï¬?ects hold only for parts involving unsophisticated technology, not when technology is sophisticated. We rationalize these ï¬?ndings within a relational contracting model that critically focuses on changes in the bargaining power, due to diï¬?erences in the costs of switching suppliers.]]></description><author>Calzolari, Giacomo &amp; Felli, Leonardo &amp; Koenen, Johannes &amp; Spagnolo, Giancarlo &amp; Stahl, Konrad O</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16653</guid></item><item><title>Are Housing Prices too Low?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16648</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We propose a sufficient statistic to evaluate whether housing prices are inefficiently low for maximizing steady-state household welfare when housing has collateral value. The statistic is based on the insight that at the optimal housing price, the consumption gains
induced by higher housing prices offset the welfare costs of a reduction in housing uses and household leisure. To apply the methodology, we use Italian data over the 1993-2006 period. As a source of exogenous variation for housing prices we rely on a share-shift
instrument exploiting the facts that (i) owing to seminal historical and cultural episodes, foreign nationals have preferences for buying houses in different Italian provinces and (ii) shifts in a country's foreign investment are largely exogenous to the economic performance
of specific Italian provinces. The data indicate that higher housing prices increase local consumption more than they decrease leisure and housing use by locals, suggesting that housing prices were inefficiently low.]]></description><author>Michelacci, Claudio &amp; Pozzi, Andrea</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16648</guid></item><item><title>Identifying State Dependence in Brand Choice: Evidence from Hurricanes</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16632</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We analyze structural state dependence in brand choice using variation from brand switching during stock-outs caused by hurricanes. We derive a simple test for structural state dependence based on the time-series of choice persistence for households affected by the stock-outs that requires fewer assumptions than most previous work. Using data from the bottled water category, we show that demand increases substantially around hurricane events and causes households to purchase different brands. We find that purchase behavior reverts back to its pre-hurricane trajectory immediately after the hurricane and we are not able to reject the null hypothesis of no structural state dependence. We show that our results are not driven by unusual purchases during the hurricane or context-specific purchase behavior.]]></description><author>Levine, Julia &amp; Seiler, Stephan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16632</guid></item><item><title>Revisiting the Anticompetitive Effects of Common Ownership</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16612</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We use data from the U.S. airline industry to test the hypothesis, consistent with the general equilibrium oligopoly model of Azar and Vives (2021), that inter-industry common ownership should be associated with lower prices in product markets. We find that, as the model predicts, increases over time in intra-industry common ownership are associated with higher prices, while increases in inter-industry common ownership are associated with lower prices. The aggregate effect is nil. We also find that common ownership by the "Big Three" (BlackRock, Vanguard and State Street) is associated with lower airline prices, while common ownership by shareholders other than the Big Three is associated with higher prices. The results highlight the limitations of partial equilibrium oligopoly theory in the context of common ownership, and the need to consider a general equilibrium perspective.]]></description><author>Azar, José &amp; Vives, Xavier</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16612</guid></item><item><title>Comparing European healthcare systems</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16602</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We introduce a theoretical framework to analyze the effects on health system performance of health policy choices related to efficiency, quality and competition and use recent data from Eurostat and OECD to verify the predictions. We find that --conditional on healthcare expenditure-- the following efficiency measures lead to improved performance in terms of reduced mortality:  increasing the ratio of nurses over doctors and a well developed primary care sector. Introducing a regulator specifically for healthcare quality and making provider quality reports public are associated with improved outcomes. In terms of competition, allowing patients to choose their provider leads to lower mortality. But in terms of insurer competition, single payer systems tend to do better than multiple insurers, especially in countries where inpatient care is predominantly delivered by public hospitals.]]></description><author>Boone, Jan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16602</guid></item><item><title>How Do Markets Clear Without Price Adjustments? Service Time In Online Grocery</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16601</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper studies how firms use service time to respond to local competition and demand conditions when their prices are uniformly set at the national level. Using comprehensive data collected twice a week over three years from 180 Israeli localities, we first show that  online grocers set identical prices in all markets where they operate. In contrast, service times are shorter in more competitive markets, on low-demand/low-cost days of the week, and for deliveries offered by high-priced grocers. Next, we exploit regional and temporal variation in entry decisions to examine how incumbents respond. We find that incumbents reduce service time when facing entry, but only on low-demand/low-utilization days. This reduction begins shortly before entry and is greater in monopolistic markets and when entrants pose a larger threat to the incumbent. Service time falls also in markets that do not experience entry yet are served by a fulfillment center serving markets facing entry. We use the classic newsvendor problem model to explain our findings, and in doing so emphasize the importance of accounting for both competitive and supply-side considerations when analyzing firms' response, particularly when prices are unresponsive.]]></description><author>Ater, Itai &amp; Shany, Adi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16601</guid></item><item><title>The Rise of Scientific Research in Corporate America</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16592</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Corporate science in America emerged in the interwar period, as some companies set up state-of-the-art corporate laboratories, hired highly skilled scientists, and embarked upon basic research of the kind we would associate today with academic institutions. Using a newly assembled dataset on U.S. companies between 1926 and 1940 combining information on corporate ownership, organization, research and innovation, we attempt to explain the rise of corporate research. We argue that it was driven by companies trying to take advantage of opportunities for innovation made possible by scientific advances and an underdeveloped academic research system in the United States. Measuring field-specific scientific backwardness in several different ways, we find that large firms, business group-affiliated firms, and firms close to the technological frontier were more likely to initiate scientific research. We also find that companies in monopolistic or concentrated industries were more likely to engage in basic research. Corporate research was positively correlated with novel and valuable patents, and with market-to-book ratios. For companies choosing to do so, investment in corporate research seems to have paid off. The results shed light on the link between corporate organization, market structure and corporate science.]]></description><author>Arora, Ashish &amp; Belenzon, Sharon &amp; Kosenko, Konstantin &amp; Suh, Jungkyu &amp; Yafeh, Yishay</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16592</guid></item><item><title>Consumer Search and Prices in the Automobile Market</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16574</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper develops a discrete choice model of demand with optimal sequential consumer search. Consumers first choose a product to search; then, once they learn the utility they get from the searched product, they choose whether to buy it or to keep searching. We characterize the search problem as a standard discrete choice problem and propose a parametric search cost distribution that generates closed-form expressions for the probability of purchasing a product. We propose a method to estimate the model that supplements aggregate product data with individual-specific data which allows for the separate identification of search costs and preferences. We estimate the model using data from the automobile industry and find that search costs have non-trivial implications for elasticities and markups. We study the effects of exclusive dealing regulation and find that firms benefit at the expense of consumers, who face higher search costs and higher prices than would be the case if multi-brand dealerships were used.]]></description><author>Moraga-González, José-Luis &amp; Sándor, Zsolt &amp; Wildenbeest, Matthijs</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16574</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic Strategic Corporate Finance: A Tug of War with Financial Frictions</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16567</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Access to capital markets plays a key role for the evolution of an industry over time. We develop a benchmark theoretical setting that integrates core corporate finance insights about the impact of financial frictions on investment with those from industrial organization on dynamic competition and industry evolution under perfect capital markets. Using state of the art computational tools to systematically detect and evaluate multiple equilibria and to thoroughly explore the parameter space of our model, we show how, depending on key industry characteristics such as market size, financial frictions impact firms' pricing and investment strategies and the degree of industry concentration.]]></description><author>Doraszelski, Ulrich &amp; Gomes, Joao F &amp; Nockher, Felix</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16567</guid></item><item><title>Strategic Leadership in Corporate Social Responsibility</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16564</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We propose a strategic theory of Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR). Shareholder maximizers commit to a mission statement that extends beyond firm value maximiza- tion. This commitment leads firms (either product market competitors or complementors along the value chain) to change their actions in ways that ultimately favor shareholders. We thus provide a formal analysis of the "doing well by doing good" adage. We also pro- vide conditions such that the mission statement game has the nature of a pure coordination game. Our framework thus provides a natural theory of firm leadership in a CSR context: by selecting a CSR mission statement, a first mover effectively leads the industry to a Pareto optimal equilibrium.]]></description><author>Albuquerque, Rui &amp; Cabral, Luís M B</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16564</guid></item><item><title>Evaluating the Impact of Price Caps - Evidence from the European Roam-Like-at-Home Regulation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16554</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The roam-like-at-home regulation (RLAH) eliminated all mobile roaming surcharges to European consumers travelling within the European Economic Area (EEA). We measure the causal impact of the regulation on EEA roaming traffic, using the Rest of the World as a control group. We find large and heterogeneous effects on retail and wholesale traffic volumes and revenues. To evaluate the welfare effects of the regulation, we develop a framework that includes consumer surplus, retail and wholesale profits. The gains in consumer surplus are large, and mainly stem from data services. The consumer gains are proportionately larger in small, open economies and in countries with previously high roaming prices. Finally, total welfare increases considerably, because the consumer surplus gains far outweigh profit losses. As such, the removal of market power more than compensates for a distortion from a possible overconsumption at zero surcharges.]]></description><author>Canzian, Giulia &amp; Mazzararella, Gianluca &amp; Ranchail, Louis &amp; Verboven, Frank &amp; Verzillo, Stefano</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16554</guid></item><item><title>The Competitive Effects of Vertical Integration in Platform Markets</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16545</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We analyze vertical integration between platforms providing operating systems to manufacturers of devices in presence of indirect network effects between buyers of devices and developers of applications. Vertical integration creates market power over non-integrated manufacturers and application developers. That market power provides the merged entity with the ability to coordinate pricing decisions across both sides of the market, which allows to better internalize network effects. Vertical integration does not systematically lead to foreclosure and can benefit all parties, even in the absence of efficiency gains. Its competitive impact depends on the strength and the structure of indirect network effects.]]></description><author>Pouyet, Jérôme &amp; Thomas, Trégouët</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16545</guid></item><item><title>Frictions in Product Markets</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16542</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This is an invited chapter for the forthcoming Volume 4 of the Handbook of Industrial Organization. We focus on markets with frictions, such as transaction costs, asymmetric information, search and matching frictions. We discuss how such frictions affect allocations, favor the emergence of intermediaries or dealers, and potentially create market power. Our focus is mostly on markets with many participants rather than on transactions that are bilateral or involve a small number of players.]]></description><author>Gavazza, Alessandro &amp; Lizzeri, Alessandro</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16542</guid></item><item><title>Harms of AI</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16524</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This essay discusses several potential economic, political and social costs of the current path of AI technologies. I argue that if AI continues to be deployed along its current trajectory and remains unregulated, it may produce various social, economic and political harms. These include: damaging competition, consumer privacy and consumer choice; excessively automating work, fueling inequality, inefficiently pushing down wages, and failing to improve worker productivity; and damaging political discourse, democracy's most fundamental lifeblood. Although there is no conclusive evidence suggesting that these costs are imminent or substantial, it may be useful to understand them before they are fully realized and become harder or even impossible to reverse, precisely because of AI's promising and wide-reaching potential. I also suggest that these costs are not inherent to the nature of AI technologies, but are related to how they are being used and developed at the moment - to empower corporations and governments against workers and citizens. As a result, efforts to limit and reverse these costs may need to rely on regulation and policies to redirect AI research. Attempts to contain them
just by promoting competition may be insufficient.]]></description><author>Acemoglu, Daron</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16524</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic Games in Empirical Industrial Organization</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16514</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This survey is organized around three main topics: models, econometrics, and empirical applications. Section 2 presents the theoretical framework, introduces the concept of Markov Perfect Nash Equilibrium, discusses existence and multiplicity, and describes the representation of this equilibrium in terms of conditional choice probabilities. We also discuss extensions of the basic framework, including models in continuous time, the concepts of oblivious equilibrium and experience-based equilibrium, and dynamic games where firms have non-equilibrium beliefs. In section 3, we first provide an overview of the types of data used in this literature, before turning to a discussion of identification issues and results, and estimation methods. We review different methods to deal with multiple equilibria and large state spaces. We also describe recent developments for estimating games in continuous time and incorporating serially correlated unobservables, and discuss the use of machine learning methods to solving and estimating dynamic games. Section 4 discusses empirical applications of dynamic games in IO. We start describing the first empirical applications in this literature during the early 2000s. Then, we review recent applications dealing with innovation, antitrust and mergers, dynamic pricing, regulation, product repositioning, advertising, uncertainty and investment, airline network competition, dynamic matching, and natural resources. We conclude with our view of the progress made in this literature and the remaining challenges.]]></description><author>Aguirregabiria, Victor &amp; Collard-Wexler, Allan &amp; Ryan, Stephen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16514</guid></item><item><title>An Industrial Organization Perspective on Productivity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16513</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This chapter overviews productivity research from an industrial organization perspective. We focus on what is known and what still needs to be learned about the productivity levels and dynamics of individual producers, but also how these interact through markets and industries to influence productivity aggregates. We overview productivity concepts, facts, data, measurement, analysis, and open questions.]]></description><author>De Loecker, Jan &amp; Syverson, Chad</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16513</guid></item><item><title>Under-promise and Over-Deliver? - Online Product Reviews and Firm Pricing</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16508</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We consider a signaling model capturing the introductory and the mature phase of a product. Information concerning product quality is transmitted between consumers through reviews, which partially depend on the expectations consumers had prior to their purchase. When future sales are sufficiently important, a novel tension arises: High-quality types may want to underpromise and overdeliver by imitating low types in order to get a better review. We show the existence of a Pareto-improving separating equilibrium. Both more informative reviews and price transparency can lead to higher prices. Our analysis reveals a new rationale for loss-leadership.]]></description><author>Martin, Simon &amp; Shelegia, Sandro</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16508</guid></item><item><title>Selling Impressions: Efficiency vs. Competition</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16507</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> In digital advertising, a publisher selling impressions faces a trade-off in deciding how precisely to match advertisers with viewers.  A more precise match generates efficiency gains that the publisher can hope to exploit.  A coarser match will generate a thicker market and thus more competition.  The publisher can control the precision of the match by controlling the amount of information that advertisers have about viewers.  We characterize the optimal trade-off when impressions are sold by auction.  The publisher pools premium matches for advertisers (when there will be less competition on average) but gives advertisers full information about lower quality matches.]]></description><author>Bergemann, Dirk &amp; Heumann, Tibor &amp; Morris, Stephen &amp; Sorokin, Constantine &amp; Winter, Eyal</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16507</guid></item><item><title>All-Pay Auctions with Two Heterogenous Prizes and Partially Asymmetric Players</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16506</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study complete information all-pay contests with n players and two heterogeneous prizes with distinct values. Among the players, n - 1 are symmetric (i.e., they evaluate the prizes in a similar manner), whereas the remaining player has different valuations than his opponents for each of the prizes. Our analysis focuses on the equilibrium profiles and expected payoffs for the case of three players, and we partially extend our analysis for cases with additional players. Our results show that in all-pay auctions with heterogeneous prizes, the ordering of the players according to their expected payoffs in equilibrium might vary significantly, depending on both prizes. In particular, although the values for the first (larger) prize have the greatest effect on the identity of the players with positive expected payoffs, the value of the second prize might have a non-negligible effect.]]></description><author>Cohen, Chen &amp; Lagziel, David &amp; Levi, Ofer &amp; Sela, Aner</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16506</guid></item><item><title>Resource Allocations in Multi-Stage Contests</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16505</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study best-of-k contests (k=2,3) between two players. The players have heterogeneous resource budgets that decrease within the stages proportionally to the resource allocated in the previous stages such that for each resource unit that a player allocates, he loses Î± (the fatigue parameter) units of resources from his budget. We show that in both contest forms, independent of the values of the fatigue parameters, each player allocates his smallest resource in the last stage. In the best-of three contest where there are different fatigue parameters for each of the two first stages, a sufficient condition that the resource allocation in the first stage is larger than in the second one is that the value of the fatigue parameter of the first stage is smaller than or equal to the value of the fatigue parameter of the second stage. We also show that in the best-of-three contest, if the fatigue parameters are sufficiently large (approaches one), both players allocate almost all their resource budgets in the first two stages such that they have no resources left for the last stage in which the winner might be decided.]]></description><author>Sela, Aner</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16505</guid></item><item><title>Subsidy and Taxation in All-Pay Auctions under Incomplete Information</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16504</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study all-pay auctions under incomplete information with n contestants who have non-linear cost functions. The designer may award two kinds of subsidy (taxation): one that decreases (increases) each contestant's marginal cost of effort and another that increases (decreases) each contestant's value of winning. The designer's expected payoff is the contestants' expected total effort minus the cost of subsidy or, alternatively, plus the tax payment. We show that when the resource of subsidy (the marginal taxation rate) is relatively small and the cost function is concave (convex), the designer's expected payoff in all-pay auctions with both kinds of subsidy (taxation) is higher than in the same contest without any subsidy (taxation). We then compare both kinds of subsidy and demonstrate that if the resource of subsidy is relatively small and the cost functions are concave (convex), the cost subsidy is better than prize subsidy for the designer who wishes to maximize his expected payoff.]]></description><author>Minchuk, Yizhaq &amp; Sela, Aner</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16504</guid></item><item><title>Effort Allocations in Elimination Tournaments</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16503</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study elimination tournaments with n stages and 2n symmetric players. The players have heterogeneous effort budgets that decrease within the stages proportionally to the efforts allocated in the previous stages such that for each effort unit that a player allocates, he loses Î± (the fatigue parameter) units of effort from his budget. We show that if the fatigue parameter Î± is larger than (1/n), the players equally allocate their efforts over all the first n-1 stages, and only in the final stage, they exert a lower effort.]]></description><author>Sela, Aner</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16503</guid></item><item><title>Coordination and Continuous Stochastic Choice</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16495</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Players receive a return to investment that is increasing in the proportion of others who invest and the state, and incur a small cost for acquiring information about the state.  Their information is reflected in a stochastic choice rule, specifying the probability of a signal leading to investment.  If discontinuous stochastic choice rules are infinitely costly, there is a unique equilibrium as costs become small, in which actions are a best response to a uniform (Laplacian) belief over the proportion of others investing.  Infeasibility of discontinuous stochastic choice rules captures the idea that it is impossible to perfectly distinguish states that are arbitrarily close together and is both empirically documented and satisfied by many natural micro-founded cost functionals on information.  Our results generalize global game selection results (Carlsson and van Damme (1993) and Morris and Shin (2003)), and establish that they do not depend on the specific additive noise information structure.]]></description><author>Morris, Stephen &amp; Yang, Ming</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16495</guid></item><item><title>Who Cares More? Allocation with Diverse Preference Intensities</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16491</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Goods and services---public housing, medical appointments, schools---are often allocated to individuals who rank them similarly but differ in their preference intensities. We characterize optimal allocation rules when individual preferences are known and when they are not. Several insights emerge. First-best allocations may involve assigning some agents "lotteries" between high- and low-ranked goods. When preference intensities are private information, second-best allocations always involve such lotteries and, crucially, may coincide with first-best allocations. Furthermore, second-best allocations may entail disposal of services. We discuss a market-based alternative and show how it differs.]]></description><author>Ortoleva, Pietro &amp; Safonov, Evgenii &amp; Yariv, Leeat</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16491</guid></item><item><title>Cartels and Bribes</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16481</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study the relationship between collusion and corruption in a stylized model of repeated procurement where the cost of reporting corrupt bureaucrats gives rise to a free riding problem. Cooperation among honest suppliers alleviates free-riding in reporting. However, it also facilitates collusion in bidding by increasing the value of the collusive rent. In turn, bidding collusion facilitates cooperation in reporting by increasing the value of having honest bureaucrats, generating a trade-off between collusion and corruption.]]></description><author>Burguet, Roberto &amp; Iossa, Elisabetta &amp; Spagnolo, Giancarlo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16481</guid></item><item><title>Two-sided Markets, Pricing, and Network Effects</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16480</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The chapter has 9 sections, covering the theory of two-sided markets and related empirical work. Section 1 introduces the reader to the literature. Section 2 covers the case of markets dominated by a single monopolistic firm. Section 3 discusses the theoretical literature on competition for the market, focusing on pricing strategies that firms may follow to prevent entry. Section 4 discusses pricing in markets in which multiple platforms are active and serve both sides. Section 5 presents alternative models of platform competition. Section 6 discusses richer matching protocols whereby platforms price- discriminate by granting access only to a subset of the participating agents from the other side and discusses the related literature on matching design. Section 7 discusses identification in empirical work. Section 8 discusses estimation in empirical work. Finally, Section 9 concludes.]]></description><author>Jullien, Bruno &amp; Pavan, Alessandro &amp; Rysman, Marc</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16480</guid></item><item><title>Information Markets and Nonmarkets</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16459</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> As large amounts of data become available and can be communicated more easily and processed more effectively, information has come to play a central role for economic activity and welfare in our age. This essay overviews contributions to the industrial organization of information markets and nonmarkets, while attempting to maintain a balance between foundational frameworks and more recent developments. We start by reviewing mechanism-design approaches to modeling the trade of information. We then cover ratings, predictions, and recommender systems. We turn to forecasting contests, prediction markets, and other institutions designed for collecting and aggregating information from decentralized participants. Finally, we discuss science as a prototypical information nonmarket with participants who interact in a non-anonymous way to produce and disseminate information. We aim to make the reader familiar with the central notions and insights in this burgeoning literature and also point to some open critical questions that future research will have to address.]]></description><author>Bergemann, Dirk &amp; Ottaviani, Marco</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16459</guid></item><item><title>A model of information security and competition</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16457</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Cyberattacks are a pervasive threat in the digital economy, with the potential to harm firms and their customers. Larger firms constitute more valuable targets to hackers, thereby creating negative network effects. These can be mitigated by investments in security, which play both a deterrent and a protective role. We study equilibrium investment in information security under imperfect competition in a model where consumers differ in terms of security savviness. We show that the competitive implications of security depend on firms' business models: when firms compete in prices, security intensifies competition, which implies that it is always underprovided in equilibrium (unlike in the monopoly case). When firms are advertising-funded, security plays a business-stealing role, and may be overprovided. In terms of policy, we show that both the structure of the optimal liability regime and the efficacy of certification schemes also depend on firms' business model.]]></description><author>de Cornière, Alexandre &amp; Taylor, Greg</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16457</guid></item><item><title>Mortgage Pricing and Monetary Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16456</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper provides novel evidence on lenders' mortgage pricing and how central bank policies affected it. Using the universe of mortgages originated in the U.K., we show that lenders seek to segment the market by offering two-part tariffs composed of interest rates and origination fees, and that during recent periods of unconventional monetary policy, such as the U.K.'s Funding for Lending Scheme, lenders decreased interest rates and increased  origination fees. To understand lenders' pricing strategies and their effects on market equilibrium, we develop and estimate a structural discrete-continuous model of mortgage demand and lender competition in which borrowers may have different sensitivities to rates and fees. We use the estimated model to decompose the effects of unconventional monetary policies on mortgage pricing and lending, and find that central bank policies increased borrower surplus and lender profits. Moreover, although origination fees allow lenders to price discriminate and capture surplus, banning fees would lower borrower surplus and aggregate welfare.]]></description><author>Benetton, Matteo &amp; Gavazza, Alessandro &amp; Surico, Paolo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16456</guid></item><item><title>Consumer Search and Choice Overload</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16440</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We consider a multiproduct seller facing consumers who must search to learn
prices and valuations. The equilibrium features choice overload: the larger
the product line, the fewer consumers start searching. We provide conditions
under which the seller offers too much or too little variety. We then allow
the seller to position products or make recommendations, thereby introducing
the possibility of directed search, and show that the seller may find it
profitable to maintain some noise. Finally, we study the seller's incentive
to disclose product identity and extend our analysis to that of a platform
choosing which sellers to host.]]></description><author>Nocke, Volker &amp; Rey, Patrick</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16440</guid></item><item><title>The impact of the concession of 14 regional Greek airports on passenger traffic</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16435</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Greece implemented an extensive privatization program in the past decade, which included the concession of 14 regional airports for a period of 40 years. The main purpose of this paper is to assess the effects of the concession in terms of passenger traffic. For that purpose, we applied a "difference-in-differences" econometric analysis of passenger traffic before and after the concession, using traffic data from the reports of the Hellenic Civil Aviation Authority. As a control group, we used 24 regional airports that remained under state control. The econometric estimation provided indications that the change in the management model of these airports has contributed significantly to the increase of passenger traffic. In particular, the coefficient of the variable used to interpret the effect of privatisation on passenger traffic indicated that, controlling for heterogeneous trends and effects, passenger volume in the privatised airports was higher by 30% than it would have been under state control. The results indicate that strengthening the private sector involvement in the development and operation of public infrastructure may have positive economic impact, particularly when it involves the entry of an experienced international strategic investor in asset development in a country undergoing a prolonged and deep economic crisis.]]></description><author>Danchev, Svetoslav &amp; Paratsiokas, Nikos &amp; Vettas, Nikolaos</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16435</guid></item><item><title>Epidemics With Behavior</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16429</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study social distancing in an epidemiological model. Distancing reduces the individual's probability of getting infected but comes at a cost. Equilibrium distancing flattens the curve and decreases the final size of the epidemic. We examine the effects of distancing on the outset, the peak, and the final size of the epidemic. Our results suggest that public policies that decrease the transmission rate can lead to unintended negative consequences in the short run but not in the long run. Therefore, it is important to distinguish between the interventions that affect the transmission rate and the interventions that affect contact rates.]]></description><author>Carnehl, Christoph &amp; Fukuda, Satoshi &amp; Kos, Nenad</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16429</guid></item><item><title>Selling Impressions: Efficiency vs. Competition</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16402</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> In digital advertising, a publisher selling impressions faces a trade-off in deciding how precisely to match advertisers with viewers.  A more precise match generates efficiency gains that the publisher can hope to exploit.  A coarser match will generate a thicker market and thus more competition.  The publisher can control the precision of the match by controlling the amount of information that advertisers have about viewers.  We characterize the optimal trade-off when impressions are sold by auction.  The publisher pools premium matches for advertisers (when there will be less competition on average) but gives advertisers full information about lower quality matches.]]></description><author>Bergemann, Dirk &amp; Heumann, Tibor &amp; Morris, Stephen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16402</guid></item><item><title>On the Dynamics of Technology Transfer</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16399</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We study the strategic timing and pace of cost reducing technology transfer by an upstream
monopolist to a downstream market when there is potential competition downstream and the
protection of intellectual property rights is imperfect. The possibility that the downstream firm
may not fully compensate the upstream firm for the benefits that it has received, creates "hold-
up" issues. In equilibrium transfer occurs to the same downstream firm in both periods, however
the contractual relationship is crucially affected by the presence of competitors - in particular,
there is a delay in technology transfer, relative to the vertical integration benchmark. The
upstream firm is trying to limit the downstream firm's bargaining power, in an effort to pay
lower rent or no rent in the subsequent period. Price competition downstream does not fully
eliminate the opportunistic behavior created by the imperfect intellectual property rights.]]></description><author>Kourandi, Frago &amp; Sachtachtinskagia, Sabina &amp; Vettas, Nikolaos</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16399</guid></item><item><title>The Optimality of Upgrade Pricing</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16394</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We consider a multiproduct monopoly pricing model. We provide sufficient conditions under which the optimal mechanism can be implemented via upgrade pricing---a menu of product bundles that are nested in the strong set order. Our approach exploits duality methods to identify conditions on the distribution of consumer types under which  (a) each product is purchased by the same set of buyers as under separate monopoly pricing (though the transfers can be different), and (b) these sets are nested.

We exhibit two distinct sets of sufficient conditions. The first set of conditions is given by a weak version of monotonicity of types and virtual values, while maintaining a regularity assumption, i.e., that the product-by-product revenue curves are single-peaked.   The second set of conditions establishes the optimality of upgrade pricing for type spaces with monotone marginal rates of substitution (MRS)---the relative preference ratios for any two products are monotone across types. The monotone MRS condition allows us to relax the earlier regularity assumption.

Under both sets of conditions, we fully characterize the product bundles and prices that form the optimal upgrade pricing menu. Finally, we show that, if the consumer's types are monotone, the seller can equivalently post a vector of single-item prices: upgrade pricing and separate pricing are equivalent.]]></description><author>Bergemann, Dirk &amp; Bonatti, Alessandro &amp; Haupt, Andreas &amp; Smolin, Alex</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16394</guid></item><item><title>Algorithmic collusion, genuine and spurious</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16393</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We clarify the difference between the asynchronous pricing algorithms analyzed by Asker, Fershtman and Pakes (2021) and those considered in the previous literature. The difference lies in the way the algorithms explore: randomly or mechanically. We reaffirm that with random exploration, asynchronous pricing algorithms learn genuinely collusive strategies.]]></description><author>Calvano, Emilio &amp; Calzolari, Giacomo &amp; Denicolò, Vincenzo &amp; Pastorello, Sergio</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16393</guid></item></channel></rss>