<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Economic History</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Economic History</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 13:02:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Dynamic Consequences of State-Building: Evidence from the French Revolution</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16815</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin Marx, Emeric Henry, Cédric Chambru.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> How do radical reforms of the state shape economic development over time? In 1790, France's first Constituent Assembly overhauled the kingdom's organization to set up new administrative entities and local capitals. In a subset of departments, new capitals were chosen quasi-randomly as the Assembly abandoned its initial plan to rotate administrative functions across multiple cities. We study how exogenous changes in local administrative presence affect the state's coercive and productive capacity, as well as economic development in the ensuing decades. In the short run, proximity to the state increases taxation, conscription, and investments in law enforcement capacity. In the long run, the new local capitals and their periphery obtain more public goods and experience faster economic development. One hundred years after the reform, capitals are 40% more populated than comparable cities in 1790. Our results shed new light on the intertemporal and redistributive impacts of state-building in the context of one of the most ambitious administrative reforms ever implemented.]]></description><author>Benjamin Marx, Emeric Henry, Cédric Chambru</author><pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16815</guid></item><item><title>Opening Heaven’s Door: Public Opinion and Congressional Votes on the 1965 Immigration Act</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16808</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Max Steinhardt, Timothy Hatton, Giovanni Facchini.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> The Immigration Act of 1965 marked a dramatic shift in policy and one with major long term consequences for the volume and composition of immigration to the United States. Here we explore the political economy of a reform that has been overshadowed by the Civil Rights and Great Society programs. We find that public opinion was against expanding immigration, but it was more favorable to abolishing the old country of origin quota system. Votes in the House of Representatives and the Senate were more closely linked to opinion on abolishing the country of origin quotas than to public opinion on the volume of immigration. Support for immigration reform initially followed in the slipstream of civil rights legislation both among members of Congress and their constituents. The final House vote, on a more restrictive version of the bill, was instead more detached from state-level public opinion on civil rights and gained more support from those whose constituents wanted to see immigration decreased.]]></description><author>Max Steinhardt, Timothy Hatton, Giovanni Facchini</author><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16808</guid></item><item><title>Superstar Returns</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16806</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Moritz Schularick, Martin Dohmen, Sebastian Kohl, Francisco Amaral.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study long-term returns on residential real estate in 27 "superstar" cities in 15 countries over 150 years. We find that total returns in superstar cities are close to 100 basis points lower per year than in the rest of the country. House prices tend to grow faster in the superstars, but rent returns are substantially greater outside the big agglomerations, resulting in higher long-run total returns. The excess returns outside the superstars can be rationalized as a compensation for risk, especially for higher co-variance with income growth and lower liquidity. Superstar real estate is comparatively safe.]]></description><author>Moritz Schularick, Martin Dohmen, Sebastian Kohl, Francisco Amaral</author><pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16806</guid></item><item><title>Resilience, Adaptability and Transformability: Danish Butter Factories in the Face of Coal Shortages</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16769</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christian Vedel, Xanthi Tsoukli, Paul Sharp, Sofia Teives Henriques.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Economic historians have debated the importance of energy for economic development. Energy economists would argue that energy systems need to be adaptable in the face of shocks. In this light, we consider the case of Denmark, a country which was almost entirely dependent on imports of coal, and where a long coastline made imports, largely from the UK, cheap and available. Towards the end of the First World War, however, and well into the 1920s, coal imports were cut off or difficult to obtain. We exploit detailed microlevel data from butter factories, covering the period 1900-28. We find that firms were able to adapt and make use of alternative fuels, notably peat, although its availability varied across the country. Employing a difference-in-differences approach, we find significant productivity advantages for creameries closer to available peat fields in the wake of the coal shortage.]]></description><author>Christian Vedel, Xanthi Tsoukli, Paul Sharp, Sofia Teives Henriques</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16769</guid></item><item><title>Rooted to the Soil: The impact of social housing on population in Ireland since 1911</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16743</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ronan Lyons, Alan de Bromhead.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> How does housing policy influence the distribution of population? We examine the impact of the world's first large-scale rural public housing scheme on the long-term dynamics of rural population, specifically the case of Ireland's Labourers Acts. We link detailed data on the location of over 45,000 heavily subsidized cottages for agricultural laborers built 1883-1915 in over 200 districts to decennial Censuses between 1841 and 2002. We examine how the density of this social housing, which effectively halved rents for landless laborers, affected subsequent population change and find significant persistence in the effect of this treatment on the population. These findings are from specifications that include other factors plausibly related to future population growth, including initial housing stock, land values and population density, as well as distance to urban centres. A causal interpretation is supported by an assessment of pre-trends, by no effect of cottages authorized but not built and by an IV approach that exploits a 1906 limit on legal costs. Our findings suggest that deep housing policy interventions can have long-lasting effects on population distribution.]]></description><author>Ronan Lyons, Alan de Bromhead</author><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16743</guid></item><item><title>The Other Great Migration: Southern Whites and the New Right</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16739</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Patrick Testa, Thomas Pearson, Martin Fiszbein, Andreas Ferrara, Samuel Bazzi.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> This paper provides a novel perspective on the Great Migration out of the U.S. South. Using a shift-share identification strategy, we show how millions of Southern white migrants transformed the cultural and political landscape across America. Counties with a larger Southern white share by 1940 exhibited growing support for right-wing politics throughout the 20th century and beyond. Racial animus, religious conservatism, and localist attitudes among the Southern white diaspora hastened partisan realignment as the Republican Party found fresh support for the Southern strategy outside the South. Their congressional representatives were more likely to oppose politically liberal legislation, such as the Civil Rights Act of 1964, and to object to the Electoral College count in 2021. These migrants helped shape institutions that reinforced racial inequity and exclusion, they shared ideology through religious organizations and popular media, and they transmitted an array of cultural norms to non-Southern populations. Together, our findings suggest that Southern white migrants may have forever changed the trajectory of American politics.]]></description><author>Patrick Testa, Thomas Pearson, Martin Fiszbein, Andreas Ferrara, Samuel Bazzi</author><pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16739</guid></item><item><title>Transportation Costs in the Age of Highways: Evidence from United States 1955-2010.</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16734</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexander Klein, Sylvain Barde.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> This paper constructs general road transport costs in the United States between 1955 and 2010 combining stock measures of transportation network with fuel consumption, driving speed, fuel prices, and labour costs. This results in a novel data set of 3105Ã?3105 county-pairs for seven benchmark years. Using a county-level counterfactual analysis, we precisely quantify the reduction of the transport cost generated by Interstate Highway System. We document an inverted U-shape pattern for road transport costs, peaking in 1980, explained by initially increasing labor costs, followed by cost reductions due to trucking industry deregulation and the completion of the IHS.]]></description><author>Alexander Klein, Sylvain Barde</author><pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16734</guid></item></channel></rss>