<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR International Trade and Regional Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR International Trade and Regional Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 17:56:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Trade, Gravity and Aggregation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16552</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Gravity regressions are a common tool in the empirical international trade literature and serve an important function for many policy purposes. We study to what extent micro-level parameters can be recovered from gravity regressions estimated with aggregate data. We show that estimation of gravity equations in their original multiplicative form via Poisson pseudo maximum likelihood (PPML) is more robust to aggregation than estimation of log-linearized gravity equations via ordinary least squares (OLS). In the leading case where regressors do not vary at the micro level, PPML estimates obtained with aggregate data have a clear interpretation as trade-weighted averages of micro-level parameters that is not shared by OLS estimates. However, when regressors vary at the micro level, using disaggregated data
is essential because in this case not even PPML can recover parameters of interest.
We illustrate our results with an application to Baier and Bergstrand's (2007) influential study of the effects of trade agreements on trade flows. We examine how their findings change when estimation is performed at different levels of aggregation, and explore the consequences of aggregation for predicting the effects of trade agreements.]]></description><author>Breinlich, Holger &amp; Novy, Dennis &amp; Santos Silva, JMC</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16552</guid></item><item><title>IT and Urban Polarization</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16540</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We show that differential IT investment across cities has been a key driver of job and wage polarization since the 1980s. Using a novel data set, we establish two stylized facts: IT investment is highest in firms in large and expensive cities, and the decline in routine cognitive occupations is most prevalent in large and expensive cities. To explain these facts, we propose a model mechanism where the substitution of routine workers by IT leads to higher IT adoption in large cities due to a higher cost of living and higher wages. We estimate the spatial equilibrium model to trace out the effects of IT on the labor market between 1990 and 2015. We find that the fall in IT prices explains 50 percent of the rising wage gap between routine and non-routine cognitive jobs. The decline in IT prices also accounts for 28 percent of the shift in employment away from routine cognitive towards non-routine cognitive jobs. Moreover, our estimates show that the impact of IT is uneven across space. Expensive locations have seen a stronger displacement of routine cognitive jobs and a larger widening of the wage gap between routine and non-routine cognitive jobs.]]></description><author>Eeckhout, Jan &amp; Hedtrich, Christoph &amp; Pinheiro, Roberto</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16540</guid></item><item><title>The Long-Term Effects of Industrial Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16534</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper provides causal evidence of the impact of industrial policy on firms' long-term performance and quantifies industrial policy's long-term welfare effects. Using a natural experiment and unique historical data during the Heavy and Chemical Industry (HCI) Drive in South Korea, we find large and persistent effects of firm-level subsidies on firm size. Subsidized firms are larger than those never subsidized even 30 years after subsidies ended. Motivated by this empirical finding, we build a quantitative heterogeneous firm model that rationalizes these persistent effects through a combination of learning-by-doing (LBD) and financial frictions that hinder firms from internalizing LBD. The model is calibrated to firm-level micro data, and its key parameters are disciplined with the econometric estimates. Cost-benefit analysis implies that the industrial policy generated larger benefits than costs. If the industrial policy had not been implemented, South Korea's welfare would have been 22-31% lower, depending on how long-lived are the productivity benefits of LBD. Between one-half and two-thirds of the total welfare difference comes from the long-term effects of the policy.]]></description><author>Choi, Jaedo &amp; Levchenko, Andrei A.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16534</guid></item><item><title>Spending a Windfall</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16523</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the effect of the discovery of precious metals in America on international trade from 1500 to 1810. Around 1500, there was a simultaneous discovery of precious metals and new trading routes. We construct a counterfactual scenario of new routes but no precious metals. The discovery of precious metals was a windfall to Europe. It increased the stock of precious metals in the world more than tenfold. Compared with the case of no trade routes and no precious metals, Euro-Asian trade increases up to 20 times. We find that American precious metals were at least as important as the new trading routes as a cause of observed trade patterns.]]></description><author>Palma, Nuno Pedro G. &amp; Silva, André</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16523</guid></item><item><title>The Backlash of Globalization</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16521</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We review the literature on the globalization backlash, seen as the political shift of voters
and parties in a protectionist and isolationist direction, with substantive implications on
governments' leaning and enacted policies. Using newly assembled data for 23 advanced
democracies, we document a protectionist and isolationist shift in electorates, legislatures,
and executives from the mid-1990s onwards. This is associated with a noticeable protectionist
shift in trade policy â??although with some notable nuancesâ?? especially since the financial
crisis of 2008. We discuss the economics of the backlash. From a theoretical perspective,
we highlight how the backlash may arise within standard trade models when taking into account
the 'social footprint' of globalization. Then, we review the empirical literature on the
drivers of the backlash. Two main messages emerge from our analysis: (1) globalization is a
significant driver of the backlash, by means of the distributional consequences entailed by
rising trade exposure; yet (2) the backlash is only partly determined by trade. Technological
change, crisis-driven fiscal austerity, immigration, and cultural concerns are found to play
an important role in creating politically consequential cleavages. Looking ahead, we discuss
possible future developments, with specific focus on the issue of social mobility.]]></description><author>Colantone, Italo &amp; Ottaviano, Gianmarco &amp; Stanig, Piero</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16521</guid></item><item><title>An Industrial Organization Perspective on Productivity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16513</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This chapter overviews productivity research from an industrial organization perspective. We focus on what is known and what still needs to be learned about the productivity levels and dynamics of individual producers, but also how these interact through markets and industries to influence productivity aggregates. We overview productivity concepts, facts, data, measurement, analysis, and open questions.]]></description><author>De Loecker, Jan &amp; Syverson, Chad</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16513</guid></item><item><title>Road Capacity, Domestic Trade and Regional Outcomes</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16512</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> What is the impact on intra-national trade and regional economic outcomes when the quality and lane-capacity of an existing paved road network is expanded significantly? We investigate this question for the case of Turkey, which undertook a large-scale public investment in roads during the 2000s. Using spatially disaggregated data on road upgrades and domestic transactions, we estimate a large positive impact of reduced travel times on trade as well as local manufacturing employment and wages. A quantitative exercise using a workhorse model of spatial equilibrium implies heterogeneous effects across locations, with aggregate real income gains reaching 2-3 percent in the long-run. Reductions in travel times increased local employment-to-population ratio but had no effect on local population. We extend the model by endogenizing the labor supply decision to capture this finding. The model-implied elasticity of employment rates to travel time reductions captures about one-third of the empirical elasticity.]]></description><author>Cosar, Kerem &amp; Demir, Banu &amp; Ghose, Devaki &amp; Young, Nathaniel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16512</guid></item><item><title>Electing Educated Leaders during Democratization: Evidence from Indonesia</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16486</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Using manufacturing plant-level census data from Indonesia, we show that the effect of democratization on manufacturing performance crucially depends on the education level of the newly elected local leaders. In districts that elect a mayor without college education, employment drops by five percent in the first few years after democratization, while employment stays constant under college-educated mayors. We also identify mechanisms: manufacturing plants in districts with non-college educated mayors face a much larger increase in local taxes, but also worse provision of local infrastructure and no extra spending on other public goods. A novel hand-collected dataset on corruption cases further suggests that democratic mayors without a college degree are more corrupt. Our estimates are plausibly causal since the year of local democratization varies exogenously across districts, and districts with different mayor education levels exhibit parallel trends in manufacturing prior to democratization.]]></description><author>Pelzl, Paul &amp; Poelhekke, Steven</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16486</guid></item><item><title>Place-based policies â?? how to do them and why</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16468</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Place-based policies had a bad reputation for decades, if they received any attention at all. This has recently changed, for two reasons. First, many countries have experienced political backlashes from rising spatial economic disparities. Populist movements received the highest support in economically backward regions, which had been hit by severe local shocks. By trying to foster spatial economic cohesion, regional policies have become an attempt to insure against those political trends and to save liberal democracies altogether. Second, recent theoretical and empirical research has challenged the leading paradigm of spatial equilibrium analysis, according to which place-based policies are an inefficient interference into the market-based resource allocation. In this paper, I review those arguments and how their balance has changed over time. I argue that the demand for place-based policies is likely to increase in the future, as new digital technologies might reinforce urban-rural divides. But even if the general case for place-based policies now seems to be more widely accepted, the question remains what exactly should be done and which type of programs generate the highest return. Digging through the vast evaluation literature, I try to derive some robust lessons how to conduct place-based policies in practise.]]></description><author>Südekum, Jens</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16468</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic Spatial General Equilibrium</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16466</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We develop a dynamic spatial general equilibrium model with forward-looking investment and migration decisions. We characterize analytically the transition path of the spatial distribution of economic activity in response to shocks. We apply our framework to the reallocation of US economic activity from the Rust Belt to the Sun Belt from 1965-2015. We find slow convergence to steady-state, with US states closer to steady-state at the end of our sample period than at its beginning. We find substantial heterogeneity in the effects of local shocks, which depend on capital and labor dynamics, and the spatial and sectoral incidence of these shocks.]]></description><author>Kleinman, Benny &amp; Liu, Ernest &amp; Redding, Stephen J.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16466</guid></item><item><title>Intra-Bloc Tariffs and Preferential Margins in Trade Agreements</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16464</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study, theoretically and empirically, how countries choose intra-bloc tariffs and preferential margins when they form Preferential Trade Agreements (PTAs). Our model indicates that countries should set systematically lower preferential margins when the bloc takes the form of a free trade area (where members set external trade policies independently), relative to a customs union (where members coordinate external tariffs). Moreover, in customs unions (but not necessarily in free trade areas) preferential margins should increase with the supply of partner countries and decrease with the level of preferential imports. These relationships reflect, respectively, the internalization of political-economy goals within the bloc and the desire to curb trade diversion. Using a sample that covers most PTAs formed by Latin American countries in the 1990s, when their popularity in the region shot up, we find empirical support for each of those predictions. These findings make clear that the type of PTA matters significantly for the bloc's tariff structure. Our results carry out important implications for the welfare consequences and the social desirability of different types of PTAs.]]></description><author>Ornelas, Emanuel &amp; Tovar, Patricia</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16464</guid></item><item><title>North-South Displacement Effects of Environmental Regulation: The Case of Battery Recycling</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16463</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This study examines the effect of a tightening of the U.S. air-quality standard for lead in 2009 on the relocation of battery recycling to Mexico and on infant health in Mexico. In the U.S., airborne lead dropped sharply near affected plants, most of which were battery-recycling plants. Exports of used batteries to Mexico rose markedly. In Mexico, production increased at battery-recycling plants, relative to comparable industries, and birth outcomes deteriorated within two miles of those plants, relative to areas slightly farther away. The case provides a salient example of a pollution-haven effect between a developed and a developing country.]]></description><author>Tanaka, Shinsuke &amp; Teshima, Kensuke &amp; Verhoogen, Eric A</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16463</guid></item><item><title>Pork, Infrastructure and Growth: Evidence from the Italian Railway Expansion</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16462</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the role played by politics in shaping the Italian railway network, and its impact on long-run growth patterns. Examining a large state-planned railway expansion that took place during the second half of the 19th century in a recently unified country, we first study how both national and local political processes shaped the planned railway construction. Exploiting close elections, we show that a state-funded railway line is more likely to be planned for construction where the local representative is aligned with the government. Furthermore, the actual path followed by the railways was shaped by local pork-barreling, with towns supporting winning candidates more likely to see a railway crossing their territory. Finally, we explore the long-run effects of the network expansion on economic development. Employing population and economic censuses for the entire 20th century, we show that politics at a critical juncture played a key role in explaining the long-run evolution of local economies.]]></description><author>Bonfatti, Roberto &amp; Facchini, Giovanni &amp; Tarasov, Alexander &amp; Tedeschi, Gianluca &amp; Testa, Cecilia</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16462</guid></item><item><title>A Unified Theory of Cities</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16461</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> How do people arrange themselves when they are free to choose work and residence locations, when commuting is costly, and when increasing returns may affect production? We consider this problem when the location set is discrete and households have heterogenous preferences over workplace-residence pairs. We provide a general characterization of equilibrium throughout the parameter space. The introduction of preference heterogeneity into an otherwise conventional urban model fundamentally changes equilibrium behavior. Multiple equilibria are pervasive although stable equilibria need not exist. Stronger increasing returns to scale need not concentrate economic activity and lower commuting costs need not disperse it. The qualitative behavior of the model as returns to scale increase accords with changes in the patterns of urbanization observed in the Western world between the pre-industrial period and the present.]]></description><author>Thisse, Jacques-François &amp; Turner, Matthew A &amp; Ushchev, Philip</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16461</guid></item><item><title>Local Shocks and Internal Migration: The Disparate Effects of Robots and Chinese Imports in the US</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16460</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Migration has long been considered one of the key mechanisms through which labor markets adjust to economic shocks. In this paper, we analyze the migration response of American workers to two of the most important shocks that hit US manufacturing since the late 1990s - Chinese import competition and the introduction of industrial robots. Exploiting plausibly exogenous variation in exposure across US local labor markets over time, we show that robots caused a sizable reduction in population size, while Chinese imports did not. We rationalize these results in two steps. First, we provide evidence that negative employment spillovers outside manufacturing, caused by robots but not by Chinese imports, are an important mechanism for the different migration responses triggered by the two shocks. Next, we present a model where workers are geographically mobile and compete with either machines or foreign labor in the completion of tasks. The model highlights that two key dimensions along which the shocks differ - the cost savings they provide and the degree of complementarity between directly and indirectly exposed industries - can explain their disparate employment effects outside manufacturing and, in turn, the differential migration response.]]></description><author>Faber, Marius &amp; Sarto, Andres &amp; Tabellini, Marco</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16460</guid></item><item><title>Firm Export Responses to Tariff Hikes</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16455</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study how firms react to unexpected increases in import tariffs. We identify our results from a sudden removal of American preferential tariffs applied on Argentine imports under the Generalized System of Preferences, which reflected American retaliation to a dispute over intellectual property between the two countries. Critical for  identification, the tariff hike affected a third of Argentine exports enjoying preferential access in the American market, but did nothing to the other two thirds. We find that the higher tariffs reduced export participation of affected Argentine firms in the U.S. market, whereas resilient exporters dealt with the cost increase by reshuffling their export baskets away from the products whose tariffs increased. In fact, affected firms were more likely both to drop suspended products from their export basket and to start exporting new (non-suspended) products to the U.S. Interestingly, the extensive margin effects carry over to third markets, where policy did not change: after the policy shock, affected firms selling to the U.S. were less likely to export to other markets. This happened, however, only for firms that also exited the American market. We develop a framework that rationalizes the observed export interdependencies: while the extensive margin and third-country effects require country and product specific fixed costs, the effect on the sub-extensive  and  sub-intensive  margins require diseconomies of scope, where exporting a product increases the marginal cost of exporting the rest of products in the export mix.]]></description><author>Albornoz-Crespo, Facundo &amp; Brambilla, Irene &amp; Ornelas, Emanuel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16455</guid></item><item><title>How COVID-19 vaccine supply chains emerged in the midst of a pandemic</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16428</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Many months after COVID-19 vaccines were first authorized for public use, still limited supplies could only partially reduce the devastating loss of life and economic costs caused by the pandemic. Could additional vaccine doses have been manufactured more quickly some other way? Would alternative policy choices have made a difference? This paper provides a simple analytical framework through which to view the contours of the vaccine value chain. It then creates a new database that maps the COVID-19 vaccines of Pfizer/BioNTech, Moderna, AstraZeneca/Oxford, Johnson & Johnson, Novavax and CureVac to the product- and location-specific manufacturing supply chains that emerged in 2020 and 2021. It describes the choppy process through which dozens of other companies at nearly 100 geographically distributed facilities came together to scale up global manufacturing. The paper catalogues major pandemic policy initiatives - such as the United States' Operation Warp Speed - that are likely to have affected the timing and formation of those vaccine supply chains. Given the data, a final section identifies further questions for researchers and policymakers.]]></description><author>Bollyky, Thomas &amp; Bown, Chad P.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16428</guid></item><item><title>Propagation and Amplification of Local Productivity Spillovers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16388</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Abstract This paper shows that local productivity spillovers propagate throughout the economy through the plant-level networks of multi-region firms. Using confidential Census plant-level data, we show that large manufacturing plant openings not only raise the productivity of local plants but also of distant plants hundreds of miles away, which belong to multi-region firms that are exposed to the local productivity spillover through one of their plants. To quantify the significance of plant-level networks for the propagation and amplification of local productivity shocks, we develop and estimate a quantitative spatial model in which plants of multi-region firms are linked through shared knowledge. Our model features heterogeneous regions, which interact through goods trade and labor markets, as well as within-location, across-plant heterogeneity in productivity, wages, and employment. Counterfactual exercises show that while knowledge sharing through plant-level networks amplifies the aggregate effects of local productivity shocks, it widens economic disparities between individual workers and regions in the economy.]]></description><author>Giroud, Xavier &amp; Lenzu, Simone &amp; Maingi, Quinn &amp; Mueller, Holger M</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16388</guid></item><item><title>Strategic or Confused Firms? Evidence from &amp;quot;Missing&amp;quot; Transactions in Uganda</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16379</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Are firms sophisticated maximizers, or do they consistently make errors? Using transaction-level data from Ugandan value-added tax (VAT) returns, we show that sellers and buyers report different amounts 79% of the time, despite invoices being easily cross-checked. We estimate that 25% of firms are disadvantageous misreporters-they systematically misreport own sales and purchases such that their tax liability increases-while 75% are advantageous misreporters. Many firms-especially disadvantageous misreporters-fail to report imported inputs they themselves reported at Customs, increasing their VAT liability. On net, unilateral VAT misreporting cost Uganda about US$384 million in foregone 2013-2016 tax revenue.]]></description><author>Almunia, Miguel &amp; Hjort, Jonas &amp; Knebe, Justine &amp; Tian, Lin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16379</guid></item><item><title>Trade and Informality in the Presence of Labor Market Frictions and Regulations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=-83459</link><description><![CDATA[<b>January 2021</b> <p> We build an equilibrium model of a small open economy with labor market frictions and imperfectly enforced regulations. Heterogeneous firms sort into the formal or informal sector. We estimate the model using data from Brazil, and use counterfactual simulations to understand how trade affects economic outcomes in the presence of informality. We show that: (1) Trade openness unambiguously decreases informality in the tradable sector, but has ambiguous effects on aggregate informality. (2) The productivity gains from trade are understated when the informal sector is omitted. (3) Trade openness results in large welfare gains even when informality is repressed. (4) Repressing informality increases productivity, but at the expense of employment and welfare. (5) The effects of trade on wage inequality are reversed when the informal sector is incorporated in the analysis. (6) The informal sector works as an "unemployment," but not a "welfare buffer" in the event of negative economic shocks.]]></description><author>Dix-Carneiro, Rafael &amp; Goldberg, Pinelopi Koujianou &amp; Meghir, Costas &amp; Ulyssea, Gabriel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=-83459</guid></item></channel></rss>