<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR International Trade and Regional Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR International Trade and Regional Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 16:24:23 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Institutional Integration and Productivity Growth: Evidence from the 1995 Enlargement of the European Union</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16696</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the productivity effects of integration deepening. The identification
strategy exploits the 1995 European Union (EU) enlargement, when all candidate countries
joined the Single Market but one - Norway - did not join the EU. Our synthetic
difference-in-differences estimates on sectoral and regional data suggest had Norway chosen
deeper integration, the average Norwegian region would have experienced an increase
in yearly productivity growth of about 0.6 percentage points. This method also helps determining
the sources of heterogeneity, apparently inherent to integration, highlighting higher
costs of the missed deeper integration for more peripheral regions and industrial sector.]]></description><author>Campos, Nauro F. &amp; Coricelli, Fabrizio &amp; Franceschi, Emanuele</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16696</guid></item><item><title>Urban Public Works in Spatial Equilibrium: Experimental Evidence from Ethiopia</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16691</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> This paper evaluates Ethiopia's Urban Productive Safety Net Program, which provides employment on local public works to the urban poor, and was rolled out randomly across neighborhoods of Addis Ababa.  We find that the program increased public employment and reduced private labor supply among beneficiaries. We also show that it improved local amenities in treated locations, for both beneficiary and non-beneficiaries. We then develop a spatial equilibrium model and leverage unique data on commuting flows to quantify the effect of exposure to changes in labor supply from treated locations on labor markets across the city. Our estimates imply that once fully rolled out the program increased private wages by 18.6%. Finally, we use the model to compute the welfare gains to the poor: when we include the indirect effects on private wages and local amenities the welfare gains are four times larger than the direct benefits from public employment alone.]]></description><author>Abebe, Girum &amp; Franklin, Simon &amp; Imbert, Clément &amp; Mejia-Mantilla, Carolina</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16691</guid></item><item><title>On the Persistence of the China Shock</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16688</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We evaluate the duration of the China trade shock and its impact on a wide range of outcomes over the period 2000 to 2019. The shock plateaued in 2010, enabling analysis of its effects for nearly a decade past its culmination. Adverse impacts of import competition on manufacturing employment, overall employment-population ratios, and income per capita in more trade-exposed U.S. commuting zones are present out to 2019. Over the full study period, greater import competition implies a reduction in the manufacturing employment-population ratio of 1.54 percentage points, which is 55% of the observed change in the value, and the absorption of 86% of this net job loss via a corresponding decrease in the overall employment rate. Reductions in population headcounts, which indicate net out-migration, register only for foreign-born workers and the native-born 25-39 years old, implying that exit from work is a primary means of adjustment to trade-induced contractions in labor demand. More negatively affected regions see modest increases in the uptake of government transfers, but these transfers primarily take the form of Social Security and Medicare benefits. Adverse outcomes are more acute in regions that initially had fewer college-educated workers and were more industrially specialized. Impacts are qualitatively-but not quantitatively-similar to those caused by the decline of employment in coal production since the 1980s, indicating that the China trade shock holds lessons for other episodes of localized job loss. Import competition from China induced changes in income per capita across local labor markets that are much larger than the spatial heterogeneity of income effects predicted by standard quantitative trade models. Even using higher-end estimates of the consumer benefits of rising trade with China, a substantial fraction of commuting zones appears to have suffered absolute declines in average real incomes.]]></description><author>Autor, David &amp; Dorn, David &amp; Hanson, Gordon</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16688</guid></item><item><title>Business Groups as Knowledge-Based Hierarchies of Firms</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16677</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Hierarchical differentiation is a cornerstone of the organizing process. In this paper, we do three things. First, exploiting a newly assembled dataset, we provide the first worldwide overview of the patterns of hierarchical differentiation across Business Groups (BGs), highlighting the coexistence of different hierarchical shapes. Second, we show how the different shapes can arise as optimal hierarchical structures in a knowledge-based model of BGs when subsidiaries' operations involve ubiquitous problem solving under parents' supervision. Three primitive characteristics of a BG determine its optimal choice of hierarchical structure: production efficiency and two dimensions of problem solving efficiency related to supervising knowledge creation and handling associated communication across subsidiaries. Third, we check the consistency of the model's predictions with the empirical patterns for Europe, the US, and the world. The model successfully passes the consistency test.]]></description><author>Altomonte, Carlo &amp; Ottaviano, Gianmarco &amp; Rungi, Armando &amp; Sonno, Tommaso</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16677</guid></item><item><title>A Note on the Global Distribution of Authorship in Economics Journals</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16676</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Using Fontana et al.'s (2019) database, we analyze levels and trends in the global distribution of authorship in economics journals, disaggregating by country/region, quality of journal, and fields of specialization. We document striking imbalances. While Western and Northern European authors have made substantial gains, the representation of authors based in low-income countries remains extremely low -- an order of magnitude lower than the weight of their countries or regions in the global economy. Developing country representation has risen fastest at journals rated 100th or lower, while it has barely increased in journals rated 25th or higher. Fields such as international or development where global diversification may have been expected have not experienced much increase in developing country authorship. These results are consistent with a general increase in the relative supply of research in the rest of the world. But they also indicate authors from developing countries remain excluded from the profession's top-rated journals.]]></description><author>Greenspon, Jacob &amp; Rodrik, Dani</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16676</guid></item><item><title>Multinationals' Sales and Profit Shifting in Tax Havens</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16675</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We show that U.S. multinationals record sales and the profit from these sales in tax havens, while their goods and services are physically sold in other countries. We propose a framework illustrating the strategy of sales shifting. Our results reveal the importance of tax havens which attract a disproportionate fraction of worldwide sales. Our quantification shows a large contribution of sales shifting to multinationals' profit shifting that amounts to $80bn in 2013. Our findings suggest that international corporate tax rules based on sales may not efficiently address profit shifting if the policy designs are unable to identify sales by destination.]]></description><author>Laffitte, Sébastien &amp; Toubal, Farid</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16675</guid></item><item><title>Alone and Lonely. The economic cost of solitude for regions in Europe</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16674</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Solitude is a rising phenomenon in the western world. The number of people affected by solitude has been rising for some time and the Covid-19 pandemic has brought this trend to the fore. Yet, we know next to nothing about the aggregate subnational economic consequences of the rise in solitude. In this paper we analyse the consequences of solitude on regional economic performance across Europe, distinguishing between two of its key dimensions: alone living, proxied by the regional share of the population in one-person households; and loneliness, proxied by the aggregate share of social interactions. We find that solitude has important implications for economic development, but that these go in different directions. While alone living is a substantial driver of economic growth across European regions, high shares of lonely people undermine it. The connection of loneliness with economic growth is, however, dependent on the frequency of in-person meetings, with large shares of the population meeting others on a weekly basis yielding the best economic returns.]]></description><author>Burlina, Chiara &amp; Rodríguez-Pose, Andrés</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16674</guid></item><item><title>Risks and global supply chains: What we know and what we need to know</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16672</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Recent supply disruptions catapulted the issue of risk in global supply chains (GSCs) to the top of policy agendas and created the impression that shortages would have been less severe if GSCs were either shorter and more domestic, or more diversified. But is this right? We start our answer by reviewing studies that look at risks to and from GSCs, and how GSCs have recovered from past shocks. We then look at whether GSCs are too risky starting with business research on how firms approach the cost-resiliency trade-off. We propose the risk-versus-reward framework from portfolio theory as a good way to evaluate whether anti-risk policy is justified. We then discuss how exposures to foreign shocks are measured and argue that exposure is higher than direct indicators imply. Finally, we consider the future of GSCs in light of current policy proposals and advancing technology before pointing to the rich menu of topics for future research on the risk-GSC nexus.]]></description><author>Baldwin, Richard &amp; Freeman, Rebecca</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16672</guid></item><item><title>Telemigration and development: On the offshorability of teleworkable jobs</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16641</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> The Covid-19 pandemic has introduced huge numbers of employers and employees to remote work. How many of these newly remote jobs will go overseas? We offer a rough quantification based on two observations: 1) offshore work is trade in services, and 2) the number of telemigrants is the volume of this trade divided by the average wage. Combining these with gravity-model estimates, we can roughly predict the number of new telemigrants that would arise from lower barriers to trade in services. Telemigration seems unlikely to be transformative when it comes to the development paths of most emerging economies. The baseline service trade flows are modest, and the standard gravity model restricts modest changes to have modest impacts. There are no tipping points in structural gravity models. Finally, we propose a simple model of telemigration in which small changes can have large consequences. The key is to assume that latent comparative advantage takes a different shape than typically assumed in quantitative trade models. Given this, small changes in trade costs can generate large and asymmetric increases in the exports of service tasks from low-wage nations.]]></description><author>Baldwin, Richard &amp; Dingel, Jonathan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16641</guid></item><item><title>International trade and letters of credit: A double-edged sword in times of crises</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16630</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This study argues that the ability to mitigate risks associated with international trade is particularly important at times of heightened uncertainty, such as the economic crisis caused by the Covid-19 pandemic. Risk mitigation can be achieved through letters of credit (LCs), trade finance instruments providing guarantees to trading partners. As their use varies across products, exports of some products are more resilient than others during times of increased uncertainty. This situation reverses in times of financial crises when distressed banks may limit the supply of LCs. Our analysis using data on US and EU-15 exports during the Covid crisis and the Global Financial Crisis provides empirical support for these hypotheses.]]></description><author>Crozet, Matthieu &amp; Demir, Banu &amp; Javorcik, Beata</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16630</guid></item><item><title>Local institutions and pandemics: City autonomy and the Black Death</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16593</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Local institutions have long been regarded as key drivers of economic development. However, little is known about the role of institutions in preparing places to cope with public health crises and pandemics. This paper sheds light on how the nature of a local institution, city autonomy, influenced variations in the incidence of the Black Death -possibly the worst pandemic ever recorded- across cities in Western Europe between 1347 and 1352. We examine urban autonomy not only because it represented a major political shift in medieval times, but because, more importantly, it also represents a key prototype of modern political institutions. By exploiting data on the spatial variation of Black Death's mortality rates and duration using OLS and 2SLS methods, we uncover that city autonomy reduced mortality rates by, on average, almost 10 percent. Autonomous cities were in a better position to adopt swift and efficient measures against the pandemic than those governed by remote kings and emperors. This relationship has been confirmed by a series of placebo tests and robustness checks. In contrast, there is no evidence to suggest that city autonomy was a factor in reducing the duration of the pandemic in European cities.]]></description><author>Rodríguez-Pose, Andrés &amp; Wang, Han</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16593</guid></item><item><title>Division of Labor and Productivity Advantage of Cities: Theory and Evidence from Brazil</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16590</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Firms are more productive in larger cities. This paper investigates a potential explanation that was first proposed by Adam Smith: Larger cities facilitate greater division of labor within firms. Using a dataset of Brazilian firms, I first document that division of labor is indeed robustly correlated with city size, controlling for firm size. To quantify the importance of division of labor in explaining productivity advantages of cities, I propose and estimate a quantitative model that embeds a theory of firms' choice of the optimal division of labor in a spatial equilibrium framework. In the model, the observed positive correlation between firm's division of labor and city size is generated by both a selection effect -firms endogenously sort across space, choosing different extents of division of labor-and a treatment effect-larger cities increase division of labor for all firms, possibly by reducing costs associated with greater division of labor. Structural estimates derived from the model show that division of labor accounts for 17% of the productivity advantage of larger cities in Brazil, half of which is due to firm sorting and the other half to the treatment effect of larger city size. The theory also generates a set of auxiliary predictions of firms' responses to an exogenous shock to division of labor. Exploiting a quasi-experiment - the gradual roll-out of broadband internet infrastructure - I find causal empirical support for these predictions. Finally, the quasi-experiment also provides out-of-sample validation for the structural estimation: The model is successful in predicting the heterogeneous impacts of the new infrastructure across Brazilian cities.]]></description><author>Tian, Lin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16590</guid></item><item><title>Supply Chain Resilience: Should Policy Promote Diversification or Reshoring?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16588</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Supply chain disruptions, which have become commonplace, are often associated with globalization and trade. Little is known about optimal policy in the face of insecure supply chains. Should governments promote resilience by subsidizing backup sources of input supply? Should they encourage firms to source from closer and presumably safer domestic suppliers? We address these questions in a very simple model of production with a single critical input and with exogenous risks of relationship-specific and country-wide supply disturbances. We follow Matsuyama and Ushchev (2020) in positing a class of preferences that are homothetic with a single aggregator and that obey Marshall's Second Law of Demand. The familiar case of CES preferences is a member of the class, but it imposes restrictions that are important for policy conclusions.We find that, in the CES case, a subsidy for diversification achieves the constrained social optimum and dominates a policy that promotes reshoring or offshoring. When the demand elasticity rises with price, two policy instruments generally are needed to achieve efficient supply chains, private investments in resilience may be socially excessive, and policy that alter incentives to invest at home versus abroad may achieve greater welfare than ones that encourage or discourage diversification.]]></description><author>Grossman, Gene M. &amp; Helpman, Elhanan &amp; Lhuillier, Hugo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16588</guid></item><item><title>Dynamics of Large Multinationals</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16579</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We develop a model of large multinational enterprises, each one producing a continuum of
products. These outsized firms compete as oligopolists in a domestic and foreign market, facing
competitive pressure from single-product firms that engage in monopolistic competition. The
multinational enterprises invest in R&D in order to expand the span of their products and in
foreign direct investment (FDI) in order to expand the range of products manufactured by their
foreign affiliates. We study the dynamic evolution of these markets and characterize transition
dynamics and steady states. In addition to the evolution of product spans, we characterize the
evolution of prices, markups, market shares, and exports relative to subsidiary sales. Furthermore,
we study comparative dynamics that result from changes in trade costs, R&D costs, the
cost of FDI and productivity changes of the multinational firms.]]></description><author>Helpman, Elhanan &amp; Niswonger, Benjamin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16579</guid></item><item><title>Trade, Gravity and Aggregation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16552</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Gravity regressions are a common tool in the empirical international trade literature and serve an important function for many policy purposes. We study to what extent micro-level parameters can be recovered from gravity regressions estimated with aggregate data. We show that estimation of gravity equations in their original multiplicative form via Poisson pseudo maximum likelihood (PPML) is more robust to aggregation than estimation of log-linearized gravity equations via ordinary least squares (OLS). In the leading case where regressors do not vary at the micro level, PPML estimates obtained with aggregate data have a clear interpretation as trade-weighted averages of micro-level parameters that is not shared by OLS estimates. However, when regressors vary at the micro level, using disaggregated data
is essential because in this case not even PPML can recover parameters of interest.
We illustrate our results with an application to Baier and Bergstrand's (2007) influential study of the effects of trade agreements on trade flows. We examine how their findings change when estimation is performed at different levels of aggregation, and explore the consequences of aggregation for predicting the effects of trade agreements.]]></description><author>Breinlich, Holger &amp; Novy, Dennis &amp; Santos Silva, JMC</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16552</guid></item><item><title>IT and Urban Polarization</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16540</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We show that differential IT investment across cities has been a key driver of job and wage polarization since the 1980s. Using a novel data set, we establish two stylized facts: IT investment is highest in firms in large and expensive cities, and the decline in routine cognitive occupations is most prevalent in large and expensive cities. To explain these facts, we propose a model mechanism where the substitution of routine workers by IT leads to higher IT adoption in large cities due to a higher cost of living and higher wages. We estimate the spatial equilibrium model to trace out the effects of IT on the labor market between 1990 and 2015. We find that the fall in IT prices explains 50 percent of the rising wage gap between routine and non-routine cognitive jobs. The decline in IT prices also accounts for 28 percent of the shift in employment away from routine cognitive towards non-routine cognitive jobs. Moreover, our estimates show that the impact of IT is uneven across space. Expensive locations have seen a stronger displacement of routine cognitive jobs and a larger widening of the wage gap between routine and non-routine cognitive jobs.]]></description><author>Eeckhout, Jan &amp; Hedtrich, Christoph &amp; Pinheiro, Roberto</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16540</guid></item><item><title>The Long-Term Effects of Industrial Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16534</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper provides causal evidence of the impact of industrial policy on firms' long-term performance and quantifies industrial policy's long-term welfare effects. Using a natural experiment and unique historical data during the Heavy and Chemical Industry (HCI) Drive in South Korea, we find large and persistent effects of firm-level subsidies on firm size. Subsidized firms are larger than those never subsidized even 30 years after subsidies ended. Motivated by this empirical finding, we build a quantitative heterogeneous firm model that rationalizes these persistent effects through a combination of learning-by-doing (LBD) and financial frictions that hinder firms from internalizing LBD. The model is calibrated to firm-level micro data, and its key parameters are disciplined with the econometric estimates. Cost-benefit analysis implies that the industrial policy generated larger benefits than costs. If the industrial policy had not been implemented, South Korea's welfare would have been 22-31% lower, depending on how long-lived are the productivity benefits of LBD. Between one-half and two-thirds of the total welfare difference comes from the long-term effects of the policy.]]></description><author>Choi, Jaedo &amp; Levchenko, Andrei A.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16534</guid></item><item><title>Spending a Windfall</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16523</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the effect of the discovery of precious metals in America on international trade from 1500 to 1810. Around 1500, there was a simultaneous discovery of precious metals and new trading routes. We construct a counterfactual scenario of new routes but no precious metals. The discovery of precious metals was a windfall to Europe. It increased the stock of precious metals in the world more than tenfold. Compared with the case of no trade routes and no precious metals, Euro-Asian trade increases up to 20 times. We find that American precious metals were at least as important as the new trading routes as a cause of observed trade patterns.]]></description><author>Palma, Nuno Pedro G. &amp; Silva, André</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16523</guid></item><item><title>The Backlash of Globalization</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16521</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We review the literature on the globalization backlash, seen as the political shift of voters
and parties in a protectionist and isolationist direction, with substantive implications on
governments' leaning and enacted policies. Using newly assembled data for 23 advanced
democracies, we document a protectionist and isolationist shift in electorates, legislatures,
and executives from the mid-1990s onwards. This is associated with a noticeable protectionist
shift in trade policy â??although with some notable nuancesâ?? especially since the financial
crisis of 2008. We discuss the economics of the backlash. From a theoretical perspective,
we highlight how the backlash may arise within standard trade models when taking into account
the 'social footprint' of globalization. Then, we review the empirical literature on the
drivers of the backlash. Two main messages emerge from our analysis: (1) globalization is a
significant driver of the backlash, by means of the distributional consequences entailed by
rising trade exposure; yet (2) the backlash is only partly determined by trade. Technological
change, crisis-driven fiscal austerity, immigration, and cultural concerns are found to play
an important role in creating politically consequential cleavages. Looking ahead, we discuss
possible future developments, with specific focus on the issue of social mobility.]]></description><author>Colantone, Italo &amp; Ottaviano, Gianmarco &amp; Stanig, Piero</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16521</guid></item><item><title>An Industrial Organization Perspective on Productivity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16513</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This chapter overviews productivity research from an industrial organization perspective. We focus on what is known and what still needs to be learned about the productivity levels and dynamics of individual producers, but also how these interact through markets and industries to influence productivity aggregates. We overview productivity concepts, facts, data, measurement, analysis, and open questions.]]></description><author>De Loecker, Jan &amp; Syverson, Chad</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16513</guid></item><item><title>Road Capacity, Domestic Trade and Regional Outcomes</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16512</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> What is the impact on intra-national trade and regional economic outcomes when the quality and lane-capacity of an existing paved road network is expanded significantly? We investigate this question for the case of Turkey, which undertook a large-scale public investment in roads during the 2000s. Using spatially disaggregated data on road upgrades and domestic transactions, we estimate a large positive impact of reduced travel times on trade as well as local manufacturing employment and wages. A quantitative exercise using a workhorse model of spatial equilibrium implies heterogeneous effects across locations, with aggregate real income gains reaching 2-3 percent in the long-run. Reductions in travel times increased local employment-to-population ratio but had no effect on local population. We extend the model by endogenizing the labor supply decision to capture this finding. The model-implied elasticity of employment rates to travel time reductions captures about one-third of the empirical elasticity.]]></description><author>Cosar, Kerem &amp; Demir, Banu &amp; Ghose, Devaki &amp; Young, Nathaniel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16512</guid></item><item><title>Electing Educated Leaders during Democratization: Evidence from Indonesia</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16486</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Using manufacturing plant-level census data from Indonesia, we show that the effect of democratization on manufacturing performance crucially depends on the education level of the newly elected local leaders. In districts that elect a mayor without college education, employment drops by five percent in the first few years after democratization, while employment stays constant under college-educated mayors. We also identify mechanisms: manufacturing plants in districts with non-college educated mayors face a much larger increase in local taxes, but also worse provision of local infrastructure and no extra spending on other public goods. A novel hand-collected dataset on corruption cases further suggests that democratic mayors without a college degree are more corrupt. Our estimates are plausibly causal since the year of local democratization varies exogenously across districts, and districts with different mayor education levels exhibit parallel trends in manufacturing prior to democratization.]]></description><author>Pelzl, Paul &amp; Poelhekke, Steven</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16486</guid></item><item><title>Place-based policies â?? how to do them and why</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16468</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Place-based policies had a bad reputation for decades, if they received any attention at all. This has recently changed, for two reasons. First, many countries have experienced political backlashes from rising spatial economic disparities. Populist movements received the highest support in economically backward regions, which had been hit by severe local shocks. By trying to foster spatial economic cohesion, regional policies have become an attempt to insure against those political trends and to save liberal democracies altogether. Second, recent theoretical and empirical research has challenged the leading paradigm of spatial equilibrium analysis, according to which place-based policies are an inefficient interference into the market-based resource allocation. In this paper, I review those arguments and how their balance has changed over time. I argue that the demand for place-based policies is likely to increase in the future, as new digital technologies might reinforce urban-rural divides. But even if the general case for place-based policies now seems to be more widely accepted, the question remains what exactly should be done and which type of programs generate the highest return. Digging through the vast evaluation literature, I try to derive some robust lessons how to conduct place-based policies in practise.]]></description><author>Südekum, Jens</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16468</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic Spatial General Equilibrium</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16466</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We develop a dynamic spatial general equilibrium model with forward-looking investment and migration decisions. We characterize analytically the transition path of the spatial distribution of economic activity in response to shocks. We apply our framework to the reallocation of US economic activity from the Rust Belt to the Sun Belt from 1965-2015. We find slow convergence to steady-state, with US states closer to steady-state at the end of our sample period than at its beginning. We find substantial heterogeneity in the effects of local shocks, which depend on capital and labor dynamics, and the spatial and sectoral incidence of these shocks.]]></description><author>Kleinman, Benny &amp; Liu, Ernest &amp; Redding, Stephen J.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16466</guid></item><item><title>Intra-Bloc Tariffs and Preferential Margins in Trade Agreements</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16464</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study, theoretically and empirically, how countries choose intra-bloc tariffs and preferential margins when they form Preferential Trade Agreements (PTAs). Our model indicates that countries should set systematically lower preferential margins when the bloc takes the form of a free trade area (where members set external trade policies independently), relative to a customs union (where members coordinate external tariffs). Moreover, in customs unions (but not necessarily in free trade areas) preferential margins should increase with the supply of partner countries and decrease with the level of preferential imports. These relationships reflect, respectively, the internalization of political-economy goals within the bloc and the desire to curb trade diversion. Using a sample that covers most PTAs formed by Latin American countries in the 1990s, when their popularity in the region shot up, we find empirical support for each of those predictions. These findings make clear that the type of PTA matters significantly for the bloc's tariff structure. Our results carry out important implications for the welfare consequences and the social desirability of different types of PTAs.]]></description><author>Ornelas, Emanuel &amp; Tovar, Patricia</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16464</guid></item><item><title>North-South Displacement Effects of Environmental Regulation: The Case of Battery Recycling</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16463</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This study examines the effect of a tightening of the U.S. air-quality standard for lead in 2009 on the relocation of battery recycling to Mexico and on infant health in Mexico. In the U.S., airborne lead dropped sharply near affected plants, most of which were battery-recycling plants. Exports of used batteries to Mexico rose markedly. In Mexico, production increased at battery-recycling plants, relative to comparable industries, and birth outcomes deteriorated within two miles of those plants, relative to areas slightly farther away. The case provides a salient example of a pollution-haven effect between a developed and a developing country.]]></description><author>Tanaka, Shinsuke &amp; Teshima, Kensuke &amp; Verhoogen, Eric A</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16463</guid></item><item><title>Pork, Infrastructure and Growth: Evidence from the Italian Railway Expansion</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16462</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the role played by politics in shaping the Italian railway network, and its impact on long-run growth patterns. Examining a large state-planned railway expansion that took place during the second half of the 19th century in a recently unified country, we first study how both national and local political processes shaped the planned railway construction. Exploiting close elections, we show that a state-funded railway line is more likely to be planned for construction where the local representative is aligned with the government. Furthermore, the actual path followed by the railways was shaped by local pork-barreling, with towns supporting winning candidates more likely to see a railway crossing their territory. Finally, we explore the long-run effects of the network expansion on economic development. Employing population and economic censuses for the entire 20th century, we show that politics at a critical juncture played a key role in explaining the long-run evolution of local economies.]]></description><author>Bonfatti, Roberto &amp; Facchini, Giovanni &amp; Tarasov, Alexander &amp; Tedeschi, Gianluca &amp; Testa, Cecilia</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16462</guid></item><item><title>A Unified Theory of Cities</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16461</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> How do people arrange themselves when they are free to choose work and residence locations, when commuting is costly, and when increasing returns may affect production? We consider this problem when the location set is discrete and households have heterogenous preferences over workplace-residence pairs. We provide a general characterization of equilibrium throughout the parameter space. The introduction of preference heterogeneity into an otherwise conventional urban model fundamentally changes equilibrium behavior. Multiple equilibria are pervasive although stable equilibria need not exist. Stronger increasing returns to scale need not concentrate economic activity and lower commuting costs need not disperse it. The qualitative behavior of the model as returns to scale increase accords with changes in the patterns of urbanization observed in the Western world between the pre-industrial period and the present.]]></description><author>Thisse, Jacques-François &amp; Turner, Matthew A &amp; Ushchev, Philip</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16461</guid></item><item><title>Local Shocks and Internal Migration: The Disparate Effects of Robots and Chinese Imports in the US</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16460</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Migration has long been considered one of the key mechanisms through which labor markets adjust to economic shocks. In this paper, we analyze the migration response of American workers to two of the most important shocks that hit US manufacturing since the late 1990s - Chinese import competition and the introduction of industrial robots. Exploiting plausibly exogenous variation in exposure across US local labor markets over time, we show that robots caused a sizable reduction in population size, while Chinese imports did not. We rationalize these results in two steps. First, we provide evidence that negative employment spillovers outside manufacturing, caused by robots but not by Chinese imports, are an important mechanism for the different migration responses triggered by the two shocks. Next, we present a model where workers are geographically mobile and compete with either machines or foreign labor in the completion of tasks. The model highlights that two key dimensions along which the shocks differ - the cost savings they provide and the degree of complementarity between directly and indirectly exposed industries - can explain their disparate employment effects outside manufacturing and, in turn, the differential migration response.]]></description><author>Faber, Marius &amp; Sarto, Andres &amp; Tabellini, Marco</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16460</guid></item><item><title>Firm Export Responses to Tariff Hikes</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16455</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study how firms react to unexpected increases in import tariffs. We identify our results from a sudden removal of American preferential tariffs applied on Argentine imports under the Generalized System of Preferences, which reflected American retaliation to a dispute over intellectual property between the two countries. Critical for  identification, the tariff hike affected a third of Argentine exports enjoying preferential access in the American market, but did nothing to the other two thirds. We find that the higher tariffs reduced export participation of affected Argentine firms in the U.S. market, whereas resilient exporters dealt with the cost increase by reshuffling their export baskets away from the products whose tariffs increased. In fact, affected firms were more likely both to drop suspended products from their export basket and to start exporting new (non-suspended) products to the U.S. Interestingly, the extensive margin effects carry over to third markets, where policy did not change: after the policy shock, affected firms selling to the U.S. were less likely to export to other markets. This happened, however, only for firms that also exited the American market. We develop a framework that rationalizes the observed export interdependencies: while the extensive margin and third-country effects require country and product specific fixed costs, the effect on the sub-extensive  and  sub-intensive  margins require diseconomies of scope, where exporting a product increases the marginal cost of exporting the rest of products in the export mix.]]></description><author>Albornoz-Crespo, Facundo &amp; Brambilla, Irene &amp; Ornelas, Emanuel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16455</guid></item><item><title>How COVID-19 vaccine supply chains emerged in the midst of a pandemic</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16428</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Many months after COVID-19 vaccines were first authorized for public use, still limited supplies could only partially reduce the devastating loss of life and economic costs caused by the pandemic. Could additional vaccine doses have been manufactured more quickly some other way? Would alternative policy choices have made a difference? This paper provides a simple analytical framework through which to view the contours of the vaccine value chain. It then creates a new database that maps the COVID-19 vaccines of Pfizer/BioNTech, Moderna, AstraZeneca/Oxford, Johnson & Johnson, Novavax and CureVac to the product- and location-specific manufacturing supply chains that emerged in 2020 and 2021. It describes the choppy process through which dozens of other companies at nearly 100 geographically distributed facilities came together to scale up global manufacturing. The paper catalogues major pandemic policy initiatives - such as the United States' Operation Warp Speed - that are likely to have affected the timing and formation of those vaccine supply chains. Given the data, a final section identifies further questions for researchers and policymakers.]]></description><author>Bollyky, Thomas &amp; Bown, Chad P.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16428</guid></item><item><title>Propagation and Amplification of Local Productivity Spillovers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16388</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Abstract This paper shows that local productivity spillovers propagate throughout the economy through the plant-level networks of multi-region firms. Using confidential Census plant-level data, we show that large manufacturing plant openings not only raise the productivity of local plants but also of distant plants hundreds of miles away, which belong to multi-region firms that are exposed to the local productivity spillover through one of their plants. To quantify the significance of plant-level networks for the propagation and amplification of local productivity shocks, we develop and estimate a quantitative spatial model in which plants of multi-region firms are linked through shared knowledge. Our model features heterogeneous regions, which interact through goods trade and labor markets, as well as within-location, across-plant heterogeneity in productivity, wages, and employment. Counterfactual exercises show that while knowledge sharing through plant-level networks amplifies the aggregate effects of local productivity shocks, it widens economic disparities between individual workers and regions in the economy.]]></description><author>Giroud, Xavier &amp; Lenzu, Simone &amp; Maingi, Quinn &amp; Mueller, Holger M</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16388</guid></item><item><title>Strategic or Confused Firms? Evidence from &amp;quot;Missing&amp;quot; Transactions in Uganda</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16379</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Are firms sophisticated maximizers, or do they consistently make errors? Using transaction-level data from Ugandan value-added tax (VAT) returns, we show that sellers and buyers report different amounts 79% of the time, despite invoices being easily cross-checked. We estimate that 25% of firms are disadvantageous misreporters-they systematically misreport own sales and purchases such that their tax liability increases-while 75% are advantageous misreporters. Many firms-especially disadvantageous misreporters-fail to report imported inputs they themselves reported at Customs, increasing their VAT liability. On net, unilateral VAT misreporting cost Uganda about US$384 million in foregone 2013-2016 tax revenue.]]></description><author>Almunia, Miguel &amp; Hjort, Jonas &amp; Knebe, Justine &amp; Tian, Lin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16379</guid></item><item><title>Trade and Informality in the Presence of Labor Market Frictions and Regulations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=-83459</link><description><![CDATA[<b>January 2021</b> <p> We build an equilibrium model of a small open economy with labor market frictions and imperfectly enforced regulations. Heterogeneous firms sort into the formal or informal sector. We estimate the model using data from Brazil, and use counterfactual simulations to understand how trade affects economic outcomes in the presence of informality. We show that: (1) Trade openness unambiguously decreases informality in the tradable sector, but has ambiguous effects on aggregate informality. (2) The productivity gains from trade are understated when the informal sector is omitted. (3) Trade openness results in large welfare gains even when informality is repressed. (4) Repressing informality increases productivity, but at the expense of employment and welfare. (5) The effects of trade on wage inequality are reversed when the informal sector is incorporated in the analysis. (6) The informal sector works as an "unemployment," but not a "welfare buffer" in the event of negative economic shocks.]]></description><author>Dix-Carneiro, Rafael &amp; Goldberg, Pinelopi Koujianou &amp; Meghir, Costas &amp; Ulyssea, Gabriel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=-83459</guid></item></channel></rss>