<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR Economic History</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR Economic History</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 17:39:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Great Expansion. The Exceptional Spread of Bank Branches in Interwar France</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16698</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> France during the 1920s was characterized by exceptional expansion of bank branches, with access to banks developing rapidly in rural areas due especially to establishment of temporary branches. However, it did not translate into increased bank assets and deposits as a share of national income. The banking crisis of the Great Depression ended the network expansion and reversed part of it, but the number of bank branches remained four times greater than before the war (though the French population was similar in 1910 and 1930). The distinction between indicators of credit or deposits on GDP and indicators of the density of the banking network challenges the thesis of the Great Reversal and improves understanding of the evolution of the banking system during the interwar period. We argue that inflation and increased competition explain the disconnect between the evolution of branches and the real volume of banking activity.]]></description><author>Bonhoure, Emilie &amp; Clausse, Hadrien &amp; Monnet, Eric &amp; Riva, Angelo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16698</guid></item><item><title>Losing the inflation anchor</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16664</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Inflation has an anchor in people's expectations of what its long-run value will be. If expectations persistently change, then the anchor is adrift; if they differ from the central bank's target, the anchor is lost. This paper uses data on expectations from market prices, from professional surveys, and from the cross-sectional distribution of household surveys to measure shifts in this anchor. Its main application is to the US Great Inflation. The data suggests that the anchor started drifting as early as 1967 and that this could have been spotted well before policymakers did. Using this approach on expectations data from Brazil, Turkey, South Africa, the US in the 1970s, and the US in 2021, confirms their usefulness to measure the inflation anchor in real time.]]></description><author>Reis, Ricardo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16664</guid></item><item><title>A Safe Harbor: Wealth-Income Ratios in Switzerland Over the 20th Century and the Role of Housing Prices</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16660</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We estimate the ratio of private wealth to national income, Î²pt, for Switzerland over the period 1900â??2018. Our results indicate that the development of Î²pt in Switzerland did not follow a U-shaped pattern as in most European countries, but that the evolution was extraordinarily stable, with Î²pt oscillating around 500% over most of the 20th century. However, the wealth-income ratio has been on the rise since the turn of the century to reach 721% in 2017-a level unprecedented in the past. This considerable increase is mainly driven by large capital gains in housing wealth since 2010. We present new cross-country evidence that capital gains in housing wealth have become an important driver of rising wealth-income ratios in a series of developed economies.]]></description><author>Baselgia, Enea &amp; Martínez, Isabel Z.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16660</guid></item><item><title>Wealth and History: An Update</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16631</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper analyzes new evidence on long-run trends in aggregate wealth accumulation and wealth inequality in Western countries. The new findings suggest that wealth-income ratios were lower before World War I than previously claimed, that wealth concentration fell over the past century and has remained low in Europe but increased in the United States, that wealth has changed from being dominated by elite-owned fortunes to consist mainly of popular wealth, and that capital shares in national income have been relatively stable over time, especially in the postwar era. These findings cast doubt on claims that a low-tax, low-regulation capitalism will generate extreme capital accumulation, and that persistent wealth equalization requires large shocks to capital coming from wars or progressive taxation. Instead, institutions that promote household wealth accumulation from below appear to be key for understanding the long-run evolution of wealth in Western societies.]]></description><author>Waldenström, Daniel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16631</guid></item><item><title>Stunting and wasting in a growing economy: biological living standards in Portugal, 1924-1994</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16617</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Portugal's real income per head grew by a factor of eight during the second half of the twentieth century, a period of fast convergence towards Western European standards of living. We use a new sample of about 2,000 children to document trends in the prevalence of stunting and wasting in the city of Lisbon between 1945 and 1994. We find that stunting and wasting fell quickly in the 1950s and 1960s. This happened for males and females, and for infants (0 to 36 months of age) as well as children (2 to 10 years of age). We additionally use a sample of 17,000 young adult males covering the entire country which shows a similar decrease in the incidence of wasting and stunting, with the expected time lag. We discuss these trends in relation to changes in income and public policy which affected the ontogenetic environment of children.]]></description><author>Cermeño, Alexandra &amp; Palma, Nuno Pedro G. &amp; Pistola, Renato</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16617</guid></item><item><title>&amp;quot;Involution&amp;quot; or Seasonality: a New Perspective on the 19-20th Century Chinese Agricultural Development</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16614</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> China's (or East Asian) highly crop-based agriculture generates high seasonality in demand for labor across the year, leading to the rise of agricultural and handicraft side-employment. In contrast to the "involution" thesis which posits a Malthusian trap with diminishing return in Chinese agriculture dictated by deteriorating land-labor ratio, this paper presents stylized empirical facts from 19-20th century Chinese (and Japanese) agriculture and theoretical models to demonstrate that this labor relocation across the seasons contributes to a Boserupian type of growth. It leads to rising commercialization and population density, but not necessarily urbanization, rising productivity and structural change. Ultimately, industrialization and the expansion of markets that occurred outside agriculture pulled China (and Japan) out of the "involution" to embark on modernization.]]></description><author>Ma, Debin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16614</guid></item><item><title>Lessons of Keynes's Economic Consequences in a Turbulent Century</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16610</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Just over a century old, John Maynard Keynes's The Economic Consequences of the Peace (1919) remains a seminal document of the twentieth century. At the time, the book was a prescient analysis of political events to come. In the decades that followed, this still controversial text became an essential ingredient in the unfolding of history. In this essay, we review the arc of experience since 1919 from the perspective of Keynes's influence and his changing understanding of economics, politics, and geopolitics. We identify how he, his ideas, and this text became key reference points during times of turbulence as actors sought to manage a range of shocks. Near the end of his life, Keynes would play a central role in planning the world economy's reconstruction after World War II. We argue that the "global order" that evolved since then, marked by increasingly polarized societies, leaves the community of nations ill prepared to provide key global public goods or to counter critical collective threats.]]></description><author>Clavin, Patricia &amp; Corsetti, Giancarlo &amp; Obstfeld, Maurice &amp; Tooze, Adam</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16610</guid></item><item><title>Persistence, Randomization, and Spatial Noise</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16609</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Historical persistence studies and other regressions using spatial data commonly have severely inflated t statistics, and different standard error adjustments to correct for this return markedly different estimates. This paper proposes a simple randomization inference procedure where the significance level of an explanatory variable is measured by its ability to outperform synthetic noise with the same estimated spatial structure. Spatial noise, in other words, acts as a treatment randomization in an artificial experiment based on correlated observational data. The performance of twenty persistence studies relative to spatial noise is examined.]]></description><author>Kelly, Morgan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16609</guid></item><item><title>Hot Money Inflows and Bank Risk-Taking: Germany from the 1920s to the Great Depression</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16606</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> What is the impact of hot capital inflows on bank risk-taking? In an increasingly financially globalised world this question becomes especially relevant. However few authors have examined it in detail empirically, despite repeated crises in Latin America, East Asia and the Eurozone from the 1980s to the 2010s. In this paper, we collect individual bank data on one of history's most striking examples of a "supply push" in foreign funds: the great inflow of capital from the developed world to Germany in the second half of the 1920s. Bank by bank we examine its effects on decisions related to leverage, lending and liquidity. The specificities of the time period â?? the Dawes Plan of 1924 as well as the relative absence of a Too-Big-to-Fail environment, which we document through extensive historiographical analysis â?? allow us to mitigate endogeneity concerns. We develop a three-step approach in which we run panel regressions including only months of falling interest-rate spreads, and apply a two-stage least-squares model in which initial bank size is used as an instrument. In all our models our results tend to converge: while capital inflows did not seem to impact banks' liquidity decisions, their impact on leverage was non-negligeable. This paper's results thus call for extra prudential oversight whenever cross-border banking flows increase significantly.]]></description><author>Collet, Stéphanie &amp; Postel-Vinay, Natacha</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16606</guid></item><item><title>Social Mobility in Sweden Before the Welfare State</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16595</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We use historical census data to show that Sweden exhibited high levels of intergenerational occupational mobility several decades before the rise of the welfare state. Mobility rates were higher than in other 19th- and 20th-century European countries, closer to those observed in the highly mobile 19th-century United States. We leverage mobility variation across Swedish municipalities to shed light on potential determinants: economic growth and migration are positively correlated with mobility, consistent with the patterns observed across countries.]]></description><author>Berger, Thor &amp; Engzell, Per &amp; Eriksson, Björn &amp; Molinder, Jakob</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16595</guid></item><item><title>The Rise of Scientific Research in Corporate America</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16592</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Corporate science in America emerged in the interwar period, as some companies set up state-of-the-art corporate laboratories, hired highly skilled scientists, and embarked upon basic research of the kind we would associate today with academic institutions. Using a newly assembled dataset on U.S. companies between 1926 and 1940 combining information on corporate ownership, organization, research and innovation, we attempt to explain the rise of corporate research. We argue that it was driven by companies trying to take advantage of opportunities for innovation made possible by scientific advances and an underdeveloped academic research system in the United States. Measuring field-specific scientific backwardness in several different ways, we find that large firms, business group-affiliated firms, and firms close to the technological frontier were more likely to initiate scientific research. We also find that companies in monopolistic or concentrated industries were more likely to engage in basic research. Corporate research was positively correlated with novel and valuable patents, and with market-to-book ratios. For companies choosing to do so, investment in corporate research seems to have paid off. The results shed light on the link between corporate organization, market structure and corporate science.]]></description><author>Arora, Ashish &amp; Belenzon, Sharon &amp; Kosenko, Konstantin &amp; Suh, Jungkyu &amp; Yafeh, Yishay</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16592</guid></item><item><title>It Takes Money to Make MPs: New Evidence from 150 Years of British Campaign Spending</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16586</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study electoral campaigns over the long run, through the lens of their spending. In particular, we ask whether changing media technologies and electoral environments impacted patterns of spending and their correlation with electoral results. To do so, we build a novel exhaustive dataset on general elections in the United Kingdom from 1857 to 2017, which includes information on campaign spending (itemized by expense categories), electoral outcomes and socio-demographic characteristics for 69,042 election-constituency-candidates. We start by providing new insights on the history of British political campaigns, in particular the growing importance of advertising material, including via digital means, to the detriment of paid staff and electoral meetings. We then show that there is a strong positive correlation between expenditures and votes, and that overall the magnitude of this relationship has strongly increased since the 1880s, with a peak in the last quarter of the 20th century. We link these transformations to changes in the conduct of campaigns, and to the introduction of new information technologies. We show in particular that the expansion of local radio and broadband Internet increased the sensitivity of the electoral results to differences in campaign spending. These results encourage greater contextualization in the drafting of campaign finance regulations.]]></description><author>Cagé, Julia &amp; Dewitte, Edgard</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16586</guid></item><item><title>When Interventions Fail: Lessons from the U.S. Experience in Latin America</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16585</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> On August 30, 2021, the United States completed its withdrawal from Afghanistan after a 20-year presence in the country. During the intervention, the Americans had tried to  improve the capacity of the Afghan state, maintain political stability, and end endemic political violence. While the U.S. intervention prevented violent extraconstitutional overthrows, it failed to improve Afghan state capacity or to end the war. The Afghan government fell to Taliban insurgents even before the Americans had fully departed. Afghanistan, however, was not the first American intervention that had these three aims. Over the first third of the 20th century, the U.S. intervened regularly across Latin America. We use this historical experience to test whether these earlier interventions produced similar outcomes and extract lessons. We find that U.S. interventions decreased state capacity but promoted political stability and peace --for only as long as American officials were present. The Afghan experience, despite the rapid fall of the regime, does not appear to be an outlier.]]></description><author>Arroyo Abad, Leticia &amp; Maurer, Noel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16585</guid></item><item><title>Art in Times of Crisis</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16575</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Art is often presented as an investment of last resort or a potential safe haven in times of political or financial distress. Yet, as no study has focused on the performance of art markets in times of crisis, this paper fills this gap by means of unclosing historical auction archives. We trace the long-term performance of the UK art market, which we relate to periods of crisis such as the World Wars, economic recessions, inflationary periods, and changes in monetary policy. By constructing an art price index from 1908 to 2016, we show that the value of British art expanded more than seven-fold over this century. We classify crises into economic & financial crises, systemic ones, and war periods. The results show that art outperformed equities and other financial assets in war times, which implies that it could serve as a hedge against political uncertainties. However, in times of economic and financial crises the art market underperformed the equity market. We also detail changes in art preferences for specific paintings' sizes, art schools, art objects' liquidity, art (price) segments, and art(ist)'s nationality across crises]]></description><author>David, Géraldine &amp; Li, Yuexin &amp; Oosterlinck, Kim &amp; Renneboog, Luc</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16575</guid></item><item><title>The Rise of the Educated Class</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16572</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Recent decades have seen dramatic developments in Western countries, which happened in a number of areas, political, economic and social. These are the growing support for extreme political parties, mainly on the right. A shift in production specialization in the West, mainly in the US, from manufacturing to global services. The third change is the rapid spread of high education, which increased significantly the educated class since the end of WWII. This paper claims that these three processes have strong relations between them and affect one another significantly.]]></description><author>Zeira, Joseph</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16572</guid></item><item><title>Herding, Warfare, and A Culture of Honor: Global Evidence</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16569</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> According to the widely known 'culture of honor'
hypothesis from social psychology, traditional herding practices
are believed to have generated a value system that is conducive to
revenge-taking and violence. We test this idea at a global scale using
a combination of ethnographic records, historical folklore information,
global data on contemporary conflict events, and large-scale surveys.
The data show systematic links between traditional herding practices
and a culture of honor. First, the culture of pre-industrial societies
that relied on animal herding emphasizes violence, punishment, and
revenge-taking. Second, contemporary ethnolinguistic groups that
historically subsisted more strongly on herding have more frequent
and severe conflict today. Third, the contemporary descendants of
herders report being more willing to take revenge and punish unfair
behavior in the globally representative Global Preferences Survey.
In all, the evidence supports the idea that this form of economic
subsistence generated a functional psychology that has persisted until
today and plays a role in shaping conflict across the globe.]]></description><author>Cao, Yiming &amp; Enke, Benjamin &amp; Falk, Armin &amp; Giuliano, Paola &amp; Nunn, Nathan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16569</guid></item><item><title>On the Benefits of Repaying</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16539</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper studies whether countries benefit from servicing their debts during times of widespread sovereign defaults. Colombia is typically regarded as the only large Latin American country that did not default in the 1980s. Using archival research and formal econometric estimates of Colombia's probability of default, we show that in the early 1980s Colombia's fundamentals were not significantly different from those of the Latin American countries that defaulted on their debts. We also document that the different path chosen by Colombia was due to the authorities' belief that maintaining a good reputation in the international capital market would have substantial long-term payoffs. We show that the case of Colombia is more complex than what is commonly assumed. Although Colombia had to re-profile its debts, high-level political support from the US allowed Colombia do to so outside the standard framework of an IMF program. Our counterfactual analysis shows that in the short to medium run, Colombia benefited from avoiding an explicit default. Specifically, we find that GDP growth in the 1980s was higher than that of a counterfactual in which Colombia behaved like its neighboring countries. We also test whether Colombia's behavior in the 1980s led to long-term reputational benefits. Using an event study based on a large sudden stop, we find no evidence for such long-lasting reputational gains.]]></description><author>Caselli, Francesca &amp; Faralli, Matilde &amp; Manasse, Paolo &amp; Panizza, Ugo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16539</guid></item><item><title>The Middle-Eastern Marriage Pattern? Malthusian Dynamics in Nineteenth-Century Egypt</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16538</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Malthus predicted that fertility rises with income and that people regulate fertility via regulating marriage. However, evidence on the Malthusian equilibrium has been mostly confined to Europe and East Asia. We employ Egypt's population censuses in 1848 and 1868 to provide the first evidence on the pre-industrial Malthusian dynamics in the Middle East and North Africa. At the aggregate level, we document rural Egyptian women having a high fertility rate that is close to the Western European level, combined with low age at marriage and low celibacy rate, that are closer to the East Asian levels. This resulted in a uniquely high fertility regime that contributed to the region's lower wages. Next, we provide individual-level evidence on the positive correlation between fertility and income (occupation). We find that the higher fertility of rural Egyptian white-collar men is attributed to the extensive margin of fertility, and not to marital fertility differentials. Specifically, white-collar men's higher polygyny rate explains 70% of their fertility advantage, whereas their higher marriage rate and lower wife's age at marriage explain 30%, suggesting that polygyny led to a steeper income-fertility curve than in Western Europe, by enabling the Egyptian rural bourgeoisie to out-breed the poor.]]></description><author>Kumon, Yuzuru &amp; Saleh, Mohamed</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16538</guid></item><item><title>The Long-Term Effects of Industrial Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16534</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper provides causal evidence of the impact of industrial policy on firms' long-term performance and quantifies industrial policy's long-term welfare effects. Using a natural experiment and unique historical data during the Heavy and Chemical Industry (HCI) Drive in South Korea, we find large and persistent effects of firm-level subsidies on firm size. Subsidized firms are larger than those never subsidized even 30 years after subsidies ended. Motivated by this empirical finding, we build a quantitative heterogeneous firm model that rationalizes these persistent effects through a combination of learning-by-doing (LBD) and financial frictions that hinder firms from internalizing LBD. The model is calibrated to firm-level micro data, and its key parameters are disciplined with the econometric estimates. Cost-benefit analysis implies that the industrial policy generated larger benefits than costs. If the industrial policy had not been implemented, South Korea's welfare would have been 22-31% lower, depending on how long-lived are the productivity benefits of LBD. Between one-half and two-thirds of the total welfare difference comes from the long-term effects of the policy.]]></description><author>Choi, Jaedo &amp; Levchenko, Andrei A.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16534</guid></item><item><title>Commodity Prices and Global Inflation, 1851-1913</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16526</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper uses annual data to study the interaction of consumer and commodity prices in 15 economies over the period 1850-1913. We find that consumer price inflation in all 15 countries co-moves with a broad measure of changes in commodity prices. Consumer prices comove most strongly with changes in metal prices, in particular pig iron prices. Furthermore, changes in pig iron prices and production, which have attracted much attention in the literature on 19th century US business cycles, co-move with the international business cycle, suggesting that pig iron prices offer a transmission channel through which international business cycle movements affect inflation.]]></description><author>Gerlach, Stefan &amp; Stuart, Rebecca</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16526</guid></item><item><title>Spending a Windfall</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16523</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the effect of the discovery of precious metals in America on international trade from 1500 to 1810. Around 1500, there was a simultaneous discovery of precious metals and new trading routes. We construct a counterfactual scenario of new routes but no precious metals. The discovery of precious metals was a windfall to Europe. It increased the stock of precious metals in the world more than tenfold. Compared with the case of no trade routes and no precious metals, Euro-Asian trade increases up to 20 times. We find that American precious metals were at least as important as the new trading routes as a cause of observed trade patterns.]]></description><author>Palma, Nuno Pedro G. &amp; Silva, André</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16523</guid></item><item><title>Financial Stability Policies and Bank Lending: Quasi-experimental Evidence from Federal Reserve Interventions in 1920-1921</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16490</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> I exploit a single natural experiment to estimate the comparative causal effects of different financial stability policies on bank-level credit. In 1920, four Federal Reserve Banks hiked their interest rate indiscriminately to safeguard financial stability. Another four Reserve Banks employed targeted rate action aimed at over-leveraged banks instead. For identification, I draw on border regression discontinuities with the remaining Federal Reserve districts which did not change their stance. The uniform rate hike had counterproductive effects, whereas targeted policy caused credit to contract significantly. The relative strengths of the bank-lending and risk-shifting channels of monetary policy explain these differential outcomes.]]></description><author>Rieder, Kilian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16490</guid></item><item><title>Selective Default Expectations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16474</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Sovereign governments often discriminate between creditors during debt default episodes. This paper explores how expectations of selective default affect sovereign bond trading and sovereign risk premia based on a historical laboratory: the German external default of the 1930s. We exploit a unique feature of the interwar sovereign bond market: identical German government bonds were traded on different creditor countries' secondary debt markets but investors expected creditors from various countries to be treated differently in case of default. We show that, when creditor countries' secondary debt markets are integrated, selective default expectations are not reflected in bond yields but affect the volume of bonds traded across markets. By contrast, when creditors' debt markets are geographically segmented, a large selective risk premium can be priced in sovereign bonds. This premium accounted for up to half of the total risk premium on German external bonds during the 1930s. We establish that creditor countries' seniority ranks can be explained by their economic power over the debtor government.]]></description><author>Accominotti, Olivier &amp; Albers, Thilo &amp; Oosterlinck, Kim</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16474</guid></item><item><title>Forced Labor in Colonial Spanish America</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16467</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The Spanish colonial empire initially faced a trilemma in the New World. First, they needed to incentivize quasi-private Spanish expeditions to subdue, settle, and secure new territories. Second, they needed labor to develop the new territories and provide a stream of rents for the imperial government. Third, they needed to ensure that the Spanish colonists did not grow powerful enough to challenge imperial authority. We show how the Spanish solved this trilemma in three ways, all involving forced labor: (1) transplanting Iberian institutions; (2) repurposing existing pre-Columbian institutions; (3) importing African slaves. We present evidence that over time forced labor in Spanish America underwent an endogenous process of decay as power slowly shifted from the Spanish-American colonial elite to indigenous labor. The end result was the increasing dominance of wage labor on the American mainland, leaving most forced labor arrangement either moribund or in decay by the time the empire collapsed. The commodity boom around the circum-Caribbean combined with geographic factors explains why this process was slower there (and short-circuited entirely in the case of Cuba).]]></description><author>Arroyo Abad, Leticia &amp; Maurer, Noel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16467</guid></item><item><title>Pork, Infrastructure and Growth: Evidence from the Italian Railway Expansion</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16462</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the role played by politics in shaping the Italian railway network, and its impact on long-run growth patterns. Examining a large state-planned railway expansion that took place during the second half of the 19th century in a recently unified country, we first study how both national and local political processes shaped the planned railway construction. Exploiting close elections, we show that a state-funded railway line is more likely to be planned for construction where the local representative is aligned with the government. Furthermore, the actual path followed by the railways was shaped by local pork-barreling, with towns supporting winning candidates more likely to see a railway crossing their territory. Finally, we explore the long-run effects of the network expansion on economic development. Employing population and economic censuses for the entire 20th century, we show that politics at a critical juncture played a key role in explaining the long-run evolution of local economies.]]></description><author>Bonfatti, Roberto &amp; Facchini, Giovanni &amp; Tarasov, Alexander &amp; Tedeschi, Gianluca &amp; Testa, Cecilia</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16462</guid></item><item><title>Financial crises: A survey</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16450</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Financial crises have large deleterious effects on economic activity, and as such have been the focus of a large body of research. This study surveys the existing literature on financial crises, exploring how crises are measured, whether they are predictable, and why they are associated with economic contractions. Historical narrative techniques continue to form the backbone for measuring crises, but there have been exciting developments in using quantitative data as well. Crises are predictable with growth in credit and elevated asset prices playing an especially important role; recent research points convincingly to the importance of behavioral biases in explaining such predictability. The negative consequences of a crisis are due to both the crisis itself but also to the imbalances that precede a crisis. Crises do not occur randomly, and, as a result, an understanding of financial crises requires an investigation into the booms that precede them.]]></description><author>Sufi, Amir &amp; Taylor, Alan M.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16450</guid></item><item><title>Pandemic Shock and Economic Divergence: Political Economy Before and After the Black Death</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16447</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We document how the Black Death activated politics and led to economic divergence within Europe. Before the pandemic, economic development was similar in Eastern and Western German cities despite greater political fragmentation in the West. The pandemic precipitated a divergence that coincided with prior differences in politics.  After the pandemic, construction and manufacturing fell by 1/3 in the East relative to underlying trends and the Western path. Politics institutionalizing local self-government advanced in the West, but not in the East. This divergence is observed across otherwise similar cities along historic borders and foreshadows a subsequent divergence in agriculture.]]></description><author>Bosshart, Luis &amp; Dittmar, Jeremiah</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16447</guid></item><item><title>The Demand for Extraterritoriality: Religious Minorities in Nineteenth-Century Egypt</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16431</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The transplantation of European legal systems in the periphery often occurred via semi-colonial institutions, where Europeans were subject to their own jurisdictions that placed them outside the reach of local courts. In nineteenth-century Egypt, extraterritoriality was extended to local non-Muslims, who could acquire the legal protection of a European polity. Drawing on Egypt's population censuses in 1848 and 1868, we show that locals did not seek extraterritoriality to place themselves under more efficient jurisdictions. Rather, legal protection mitigated uncertainty about which law would apply to any contractual relationship in an environment where multiple legal systems co-existed and overlapped.]]></description><author>Artunç, Cihan &amp; Saleh, Mohamed</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16431</guid></item><item><title>The Odious Haitian Independence Debt</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16413</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This article introduces the Haitian Independence Debt of 1825 to the odious debt and sovereign debt literatures. We argue that the legal doctrine of odious debt is surprisingly and perhaps indefensibly narrow possibly because of historical contingency rather than any underlying logic or principle. The story of the Haitian Independence Debt of 1825 serves as an illustrative case study.  In the context of telling that story, we provide estimates of the evolution of Haiti's external debt-to-GDP ratio over 1825-2020, and discuss the implications of the independence debt for the economy of Haiti. We conclude by discussing the implications of Haiti's Independence Debt for the doctrine of odious debt and the possibilities for Haiti to recover compensation.]]></description><author>Gulati, Mitu &amp; Oosterlinck, Kim &amp; Panizza, Ugo &amp; Weidemaier, Mark</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16413</guid></item><item><title>Catholic Censorship and the Demise of Knowledge Production in Early Modern Italy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16409</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Censorship makes new ideas less available to others, but also reduces the share of people choosing a non-compliant activity. We propose a new method to measure the effect of censorship on knowledge growth,  accounting for the endogenous selection of agents into compliant vs. non-compliant ideas. We apply our method to the Catholic Church's censorship of books written by members of Italian universities and academies over the period 1400-1750. We highlight two new facts: once censorship was introduced, censored authors were of better quality than the non-censored authors, but this gap shrunk over time, and the intensity of censorship decreased over time. These facts are used to identify the deep parameters of a novel endogenous growth model linking censorship to knowledge diffusion and occupational choice. We conclude that censorship reduced by 30% the average log publication per scholar in Italy. Interestingly, half of this drop stems from the induced reallocation of talents towards compliant activities, while the other half arises from the direct effect of censorship on book availability.]]></description><author>Blasutto, Fabio &amp; de la Croix, David</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16409</guid></item><item><title>The Political-Economic Causes of the Soviet Great Famine, 1932-33</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16408</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This study constructs a large new dataset to investigate whether state policy led to ethnic Ukrainians experiencing higher mortality during the 1932-33 Soviet Great Famine. All else equal, famine (excess) mortality rates were positively associated with ethnic Ukrainian population share across provinces, as well as across districts within provinces. Ukrainian ethnicity, rather than the administrative boundaries of the Ukrainian republic, mattered for famine mortality. These and many additional results provide strong evidence that higher Ukrainian famine mortality was an outcome of policy, and suggestive evidence on the political-economic drivers of repression. A back-of-the-envelope calculation suggests that bias against Ukrainians explains up to 77% of famine deaths in the three republics of Russia, Ukraine and Belarus and up to 92% in Ukraine.]]></description><author>Markevich, Andrei &amp; Naumenko, Natalya &amp; Qian, Nancy</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16408</guid></item><item><title>Gay Politics Goes Mainstream: Democrats, Republicans, and Same-Sex Relationships</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16382</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Attitudes towards same-sex relationships in the US have changed radically over a
relatively short period of time. After remaining fairly constant for over two decades,
opinions became more favorable starting in 1992 - a presidential election year in which
the Democratic and Republican parties took opposing stands over the status of gay
people in society. What roles did political parties and their leaders play in this process
of cultural change? Using a variety of techniques including machine learning, we show
that the partisan opinion gap emerged substantially prior to 1992 -- in the mid 1980s
-- and did not increase as a result of the political debates in 1992-'93. Furthermore,
we identify people with a college-and-above education as the potential "leaders" of the
process of partisan divergence.]]></description><author>Fernández, Raquel &amp; Parsa, Sahar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16382</guid></item><item><title>The Global Capital Market Reconsidered</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16375</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> While the globalization of production has been a prominent target of anti-globalization backlash, globalized finance has seemed to be much less in the public bull's-eye. The blueprint for the postwar international economy agreed at Bretton Woods in 1944 envisioned nothing like today's extensive and fluid global capital market. The demise of the 1946-1973 fixed exchange rate system, however, also brought a progressive dismantling of barriers to international financial flows motivated by special-interest politics, national economic competition, and ideology â?? alongside the benign desire for a more efficient international allocation of capital. Unfortunately, free cross-border financial capital mobility can compromise governments' capacities to attain domestic economic and social goals in several ways. This essay links the dynamics of financial liberalization to the Teflon-like resilience of finance to backlash so far, and suggests that stronger backlash could emerge if national governments fail to enhance multilateral cooperation to manage the financial commons.]]></description><author>Obstfeld, Maurice</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16375</guid></item></channel></rss>