<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Labour Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Labour Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 21:00:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Effects of Automation on Labor Demand: A Survey of the Recent Literature</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16868</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Xavier Jaravel, Simon Bunel, Céline Antonin, Philippe Aghion.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> In this article, we survey the recent literature and discuss two contrasting views on the impacts of automation on labor demand. A first view predicts that firms that automate reduce employment, even if this may ultimately result in job creations taking advantage of the lower equilibrium wage induced by job destructions. A second approach emphasizes the market size and business stealing effects of automation. Automating firms become more productive, which enables them to lower their quality-adjusted prices, and therefore to increase the demand for their products. The resulting increase in scale translates into higher employment by automating firms, potentially at the expense of their competitors through business stealing. Drawing from our empirical work on French firm-level data and a growing literature covering multiple countries, we provide empirical support for this second view: automation has a positive effect on labor demand at the firm level, which remains positive at the industry level as it is not fully offset by business stealing effects. We discuss the implications of these results for the taxation of automation technologies such as robots.]]></description><author>Xavier Jaravel, Simon Bunel, Céline Antonin, Philippe Aghion</author><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16868</guid></item><item><title>Inequality and Creative Destruction</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16867</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Otto Toivanen, Xavier Jaravel, Richard William Blundell.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> In this article we review recent evidence showing how market forces and policies shape the rate and direction of innovation, with various implications for inequality. First, we characterize several market mechanisms whereby higher rates of innovation lead to higher inequality. Second, we highlight channels whereby inequality acts as an impediment to innovation and growth. Third, we highlight policies that can help achieve better outcomes for both innovation and inequality. We show that two types of policies, which are not traditionally viewed as part of innovation policy, play a key role to achieve the goal of enhancing innovation while reducing inequality: education and competition policy.]]></description><author>Otto Toivanen, Xavier Jaravel, Richard William Blundell</author><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16867</guid></item><item><title>The Effect of Labor Market Shocks Across the Life Cycle</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16861</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexander Willén, Barton Willage, Kjell G Salvanes.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> Adverse economic shocks occur frequently and may cause individuals to reevaluate key life 
decisions in ways that have lasting consequences for themselves and the broader economy. These 
life decisions are fundamentally tied to specific periods of an individual's career, and economic 
shocks may therefore have substantially different impacts on individuals â?? and the broader 
economy - depending on when they occur. We exploit mass layoffs and establishment closures to 
examine the impact of adverse shocks across the life cycle on labor market outcomes and major 
life decisions: human capital investment, mobility, family structure, and retirement. Our results 
reveal substantial heterogeneity on labor market effects and life decisions in response to economic 
shocks across the life cycle. Individuals at the beginning of their careers invest in human capital
and relocate to new local labor markets, individuals in the middle of their careers reduce fertility
and adjust family formation decisions, and individuals at the end of their careers permanently exit 
the workforce and retire. As a consequence of the differential interactions between economic 
shocks and life decisions, the very long-term career implications of labor shocks vary considerably 
depending on when the shock occurs. We also document important heterogeneity across genders
and education levels, both with respect to the immediate impact as well as the sum total of all these 
effects in the very long-term. We conclude that effects of adverse labor shocks are both more 
varied and more extensive than has previously been recognized, and that focusing on average 
effects among workers across the life cycle misses a great deal.]]></description><author>Alexander Willén, Barton Willage, Kjell G Salvanes</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16861</guid></item><item><title>An intensive, school-based learning camp targeting academic and non-cognitive skills evaluated in a randomized tr</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16859</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Rosholm, Julia Nafziger, Søren Albeck Nielsen, Alexander K Koch, Charlotte Hvidman.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> We evaluate two variants of a school-based, intensive learning camp for pupils who are assessed `not ready' for further education after compulsory school, using a stratified cluster randomized trial involving 15,559 pupils in 264 schools in Denmark. Next to training pupils in Danish and mathematics, the main variant targets non-cognitive skills, while the alternative variant instead uses this time for more training in Danish and math. In the short-run, in the academic areas that are targeted in the camp, we find small positive effects in math and weak evidence for positive effects in Danish. Yet, we find no evidence of lasting effects and we do not find short-run effects on non-targeted areas in math and Danish or on non-cognitive skills. Further, we find no evidence that training of non-cognitive skills affects academic outcomes. 
These results provide a perspective on recent evidence regarding the effects of training non-cognitive skills in schools -- by running such an intervention with older pupils 
and in a comparatively high-resource school system.]]></description><author>Michael Rosholm, Julia Nafziger, Søren Albeck Nielsen, Alexander K Koch, Charlotte Hvidman</author><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16859</guid></item><item><title>Pulled-in and Crowded-out: Heterogeneous Outcomes of Merit-based School Choice</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16853</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kjell G Salvanes, Kai Liu, Antonio Dalla Zuanna.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> We study the effects of changing the rule that defines how students are selected into high schools
in a context where school capacity is fixed. Schools for which demand exceeds supply must necessarily
exclude some students from enrollment. We provide a theoretical framework to analyze the overall
effect of policy changes, taking into account the crowding-out effect. By exploiting a reform that
implemented merit-based allocation in Norway, we show that we can identify the relevant parameters.
The reform had an overall negative effect because of the negative impact on crowded-out students.
Different allocation rules would result in higher average outcomes.]]></description><author>Kjell G Salvanes, Kai Liu, Antonio Dalla Zuanna</author><pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16853</guid></item><item><title>Reducing Sexual-Orientation Discrimination: Experimental Evidence from Basic Information Treatments</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16852</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Lisa Windsteiger, Mathias Dolls, Ralph De Haas, Christopher S. Carpenter, Cevat Aksoy.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> We study basic information treatments regarding sexual orientation using randomized experiments in three countries with strong and widespread anti-gay attitudes: Serbia, Turkey, and Ukraine. Participants who received information about the economic costs to society of sexual-orientation discrimination were significantly more likely than those in a control group to support equal employment opportunities based on sexual orientation. Information that the World Health Organization (WHO) does not regard homosexuality as a mental illness increased social acceptance of sexual minorities, but only for those who reported trust in the WHO. Our results have important implications for policy makers aiming to expand the rights of lesbian, gay, and bisexual people worldwide.]]></description><author>Lisa Windsteiger, Mathias Dolls, Ralph De Haas, Christopher S. Carpenter, Cevat Aksoy</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16852</guid></item><item><title>Scared Straight? Threat and Assimilation of Refugees in Germany</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16849</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marco Tabellini, Sulin Sardoschau, Philipp Jaschke.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the effects of threat on convergence to local culture and on  economic assimilation of refugees, exploiting plausibly exogenous variation in their allocation across German regions between 2013 and 2016. We combine novel survey data on cultural preferences and economic outcomes of refugees with corresponding information on locals, and construct a threat index that integrates contemporaneous and historical variables. On average, refugees assimilate both culturally and economically. However, while refugees assigned to more hostile regions converge to local culture more quickly, they do not exhibit faster economic assimilation. We provide evidence consistent with the hypothesis that refugees exert more assimilation effort in response to local threat, but fail to successfully integrate because of higher discrimination by locals in more hostile regions.]]></description><author>Marco Tabellini, Sulin Sardoschau, Philipp Jaschke</author><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16849</guid></item><item><title>Zero-hours Contracts in a Frictional Labor Market</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16843</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hélène Turon, Etienne Lale, Juan J. Dolado.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We propose a model to evaluate the U.K.'s zero-hours contract (ZHC) â?? a contract that exempts
employers from the requirement to provide any minimum working hours, and allows employees to
decline any workload. We find quantitatively that ZHCs improve welfare by enabling firms with more
volatile business conditions to create additional jobs. While weaker than job creation, substitution
effects â?? some jobs that are otherwise viable under regular contracts are advertised as ZHCs â??
are sizable and likely explain negative reactions against ZHCs. Our model also assesses increased
labor-force participation from ZHCs which appeal to individuals who prefer flexible work schedules.]]></description><author>Hélène Turon, Etienne Lale, Juan J. Dolado</author><pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16843</guid></item><item><title>The Dynamics of Power in Labor Markets: Monopolistic Unions versus Monopsonistic Employers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16834</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexander Willén, Kjell G Salvanes, Samuel Donini.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper brings together the modern literatures on monopsony power and labor unions by empirically examining the effects of unionization on the dynamics of worker earnings across differently concentrated markets. Exploiting tax reforms to union due deductions as exogenous shocks to unionization, we demonstrate that there is a steep unionization gradient over labor market concentration. We show that there is an equally steep gradient in the union wage premium over concentration and that the premium loads almost exclusively on highly concentrated markets. This result implies a potentially important role of unions as alleviating market failures induced by imperfect competition. To validate our findings and examine robustness to different types of shocks, we extend the analysis by exploiting the emergence of import competition from China as an exogenous shock to employer concentration. This analysis suggest that the negative earnings effect of labor market concentration is eliminated upon reaching a union density of approximately 63 percent at the firm.]]></description><author>Alexander Willén, Kjell G Salvanes, Samuel Donini</author><pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16834</guid></item><item><title>Minimum Wages and Insurance within the Firm</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16823</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Emircan Yurdagul, Omar Rachedi, Francesco Manaresi, Effrosyni Adamopoulou.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Minimum wages alter the allocation of firm-idiosyncratic risk across workers. To establish this result, we focus on Italy, and leverage employer-employee data matched to firm balance sheets and hand-collected wage floors.  We find a relatively larger pass-through of firm-specific labor-demand shocks into wages for the workers whose earnings are far from the floors, but who are employed by establishments intensive in minimum-wage workers. We study the welfare implications of this fact using an incomplete-market model. The asymmetric pass-through uncovers a novel channel which tilts the benefits of removing minimum wages toward high-paid employees at the expense of low-wage workers.]]></description><author>Emircan Yurdagul, Omar Rachedi, Francesco Manaresi, Effrosyni Adamopoulou</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16823</guid></item><item><title>Partisan Fertility and Presidental Elections</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16821</link><description><![CDATA[<i>William Mullins, Runjing Lu, Gordon Dahl.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Changes in political leadership drive sharp changes in public policy and partisan beliefs about the future. We exploit the surprise 2016 election of Trump to identify the effects of a shift in political power on one of the most consequential household decisions: whether to have a child. Republican-leaning counties experience a sharp and persistent increase in fertility relative to Democratic counties, a shift amounting to 1.2 to 2.2% of the national fertility rate. In addition, Hispanics see fertility fall relative to non-Hispanics, especially compared to rural or evangelical whites.]]></description><author>William Mullins, Runjing Lu, Gordon Dahl</author><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16821</guid></item><item><title>Forced Displacement and Human Capital: Evidence from Separated Siblings</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16820</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sandra Sequeira, Elias Papaioannou, Stelios Michalopoulos, Giorgio Chiovelli.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We examine the impact of conflict-driven displacement on human capital looking at the Mozambican civil war (1977-1992), during which more than four million civilians fled to the countryside, to cities, and to refugee camps and settlements in neighboring countries. First, we present descriptive patterns linking education and sectoral employment to the various displacement trajectories using the full population census. Second, we compare siblings separated during the war, using those who stayed behind as a counterfactual to one's displacement path. Displacement is associated with increased educational investments, with the largest effects experienced by rural-born children escaping to urban areas. Third, we jointly estimate place-based and uprootedness effects. Both are present, with displacement increasing education and decreasing attachment to agriculture by the same rate as being exposed to an environment approximately one standard deviation more developed than one's birthplace. Fourth, we conduct a survey in Mozambique's largest Northern city, whose population doubled during the civil war. Those displaced to the city have significantly higher education than their siblings who remained in the countryside and they converged to the levels of schooling of non-mover urban born individuals. However, those displaced exhibit significantly lower social/civic capital and have worse mental health, even three decades after the war ended. These findings reveal that displacement shocks can trigger human capital investments, breaking links with subsistence agriculture, but at the cost of long-lasting, social, and psychological traumas.]]></description><author>Sandra Sequeira, Elias Papaioannou, Stelios Michalopoulos, Giorgio Chiovelli</author><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16820</guid></item><item><title>Information, Intermediaries, and International Migration</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Job seekers often face substantial information frictions related to potential job quality. This is especially true in international labor markets, where intermediaries match prospective migrants with employers abroad. We conducted a randomized trial in Indonesia to explore how information about intermediary quality shapes migration choices and outcomes. Information reduces the migration rate, lowering use of low-quality intermediaries. However, workers who migrate receive better pre-departure preparation and have higher-quality job experiences abroad, despite no change in occupation or destination. Information does not change intentions to migrate or beliefs about the return to migration or intermediary quality. Nor does selection explain the improved outcomes for workers who choose to migrate with the information. Together, our findings are consistent with an increase in the option value of search: with better ability to differentiate offer quality, workers become choosier and ultimately have better migration experiences. This offers a new perspective on the importance of information and matching frictions in global labor markets.]]></description><author>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</guid></item><item><title>Randomization for Causality, Ethnography for Mechanisms: Illiquid Savings for Liquor in an Autarkic Society</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16810</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan Zinman, Dean Karlan, Ricardo Godoy.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> What should researchers do when confronted with surprising results? Financial access
innovations usually leave "temptation" spending unaffected or reduced. However, we
found that promotion of savings lockboxes in a largely autarkic society increased alcohol
consumption and blood pressure, despite no one reporting intentions to save for alcohol.
To probe mechanisms that could explain this pattern, we then used ethnographic methods,
including direct observations of drinking ("scans") and debriefing interviews to discuss the
earlier trial results. We learn that sponsoring drinks confers prestige, but the stigma
attached to drinking by outsiders likely discouraged reporting intentions to save for it.]]></description><author>Jonathan Zinman, Dean Karlan, Ricardo Godoy</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16810</guid></item><item><title>Uncovering the Roots of Obesity-based Wage Discrimination: The Role of Job Characteristics </title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16785</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Airam Guerra, Juan J. Dolado.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper investigates the roots of labour market discrimination underlying the negative correlation between body fat percentage and wages. Using a large panel dataset of individuals drawn from the 1997 National Longitudinal Survey of Youth (NLSY97) for the US, we test whether residual wage gaps (once observed differences in productivity related to obesity are controlled for) are due to prejudice (taste-based discrimination) or statistical discrimination. Our main contribution is to examine how these two types of discrimination hinge on a wide range of obese individualsÂ´ specific job and occupational characteristics (drawn from the O * Net Online database). Our analysis sheds light on whether discrimination originates from the attitudes of clients, fellow-workers or employers. We find strong empirical evidence supporting taste-based discrimination against obese females, especially as they become older,  in jobs requiring frequent communication with either clients or employers. The evidence on this issue for males is weaker. These differences may be explained both by an over-representation of males among employers and different image concerns against people of the same gender]]></description><author>Airam Guerra, Juan J. Dolado</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16785</guid></item><item><title>Trade and Inequality in Europe and the US</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16780</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Peter Levell, David Dorn.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> The share of low-income countries in global exports nearly tripled between 1990 and 2015, driven largely by the rapid emergence of China as an exporting powerhouse. While research in economics had long acknowledged that trade with lower-income countries could raise income inequality in Europe and the US, empirical estimates indicated only a modest contribution of trade to growing national skill premia. However, if workers are not highly mobile across firms, industries and locations, then the unequal impacts of trade can manifest along different margins. Recent evidence from countries across Europe and the US shows that growing import competition from China differentially reduced earnings and employment rates for workers in more trade-exposed industries, and for the residents of more trade-exposed geographic regions. These adverse impacts were often largest for lower-skilled individuals. We show that domestic manufacturing employment declined much more in countries that saw a large growth of net imports from China (such as the UK and the US), than in countries that maintained relatively balanced trade with China (such as Germany and Switzerland). Drawing on a new analysis for the UK, we further show that trade with China contributed to job loss in manufacturing, but also to substantial declines in consumer prices. However, while the adverse labour market impacts were concentrated on specific groups of workers and regions, the consumer benefits from trade were widely dispersed in the population, and appear similarly large for high-income and low-income households. Globalisation has thus created pockets of losers, and recent evidence indicates that in addition to financial losses, residents of regions with greater exposure to import competition also suffer from higher crime rates, a deterioration of health outcomes, and a dissolution of traditional family structures. We argue that new import tariffs such as those imposed by the US in 2018 and 2019 are unlikely to help the losers from globalisation. Instead, displaced workers may be better supported by a combination of transfers to avert financial hardship, skills training that facilitate reintegration into the labour market, and place-based policies that stimulate job creation in depressed locations.]]></description><author>Peter Levell, David Dorn</author><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16780</guid></item><item><title>Controlling Irregular Migration: Can a Market for Temporary Foreign Work Permits Help?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16777</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tiffanie Perrault, Alice Mesnard, Emmanuelle Auriol.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study how temporary visa schemes can be designed to drive smugglers out of business while meeting labor market demand in host countries. The policy trade-off between migration control and ending human smuggling can be overcome by combining internal and external controls with a regulated market for temporary visas. In this market, visa duration and price are set at "eviction" levels, designed to throttle smuggling activity. We use information on irregular migration from Senegal to Spain and the Democratic Republic of Congo to South Africa to calibrate the eviction prices of visas for these two routes. Our results highlight important constraints for governments seeking to prevent temporary workers from overstaying, especially on South-North routes such as Senegal to Spain. We suggest combining a regulated market for visas with tighter sanctions against employers of undocumented workers as a new way forward.]]></description><author>Tiffanie Perrault, Alice Mesnard, Emmanuelle Auriol</author><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16777</guid></item><item><title>Discontinuities in the Age-Victimization Profile and the Determinants of Victimization</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16770</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andreea Mitrut, Nadine Ketel, Randi Hjalmarsson, Anna Bindler.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Many rights are conferred on Dutch youth at ages 16 and 18. Using national register data for all reported victimizations, we find sharp and discontinuous increases in victimization rates at these ages: about 13% for both genders at 16 and 9% (15%) for males (females) at 18. These results are comparable across subsamples (based on socio-economic and neighborhood characteristics) with different baseline victimization risks. We assess potential mechanisms using data on offense location, cross-cohort variation in the minimum legal drinking age driven by a 2014 reform, and survey data of alcohol/drug consumption and mobility behaviors. We conclude that the bundle of access to weak alcohol, bars/clubs and smoking increases victimization at 16 and that age 18 rights (hard alcohol, marijuana coffee shops) exacerbate this risk; vehicle access does not play an important role. Finally, we do not find systematic spillover effects onto individuals who have not yet received these rights.]]></description><author>Andreea Mitrut, Nadine Ketel, Randi Hjalmarsson, Anna Bindler</author><pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16770</guid></item><item><title>How education and GDP drive the COVID-19 vaccination campaign</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16757</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Huan H. Nguyen, Toan Luu Duc Huynh, Phuc V. Nguyen, Klaus F. Zimmermann, Vu M. Ngo.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Since vaccination is the decisive factor for controlling the COVID-19 pandemic,  it is  important to understand the process  to vaccination success. We identify a variety of factors playing a crucial role including the availability of vaccines, pandemic pressures, economic strength (GDP), educational development and political regimes. Examining the speed of vaccinations across countries, we find that initially authoritarian countries are slow in the vaccination process, while education is most relevant for scaling up the campaign and financial strength of the economies drive them to higher vaccination rates.]]></description><author>Huan H. Nguyen, Toan Luu Duc Huynh, Phuc V. Nguyen, Klaus F. Zimmermann, Vu M. Ngo</author><pubDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16757</guid></item><item><title>Did The Australian JobKeeper Program Save Jobs by Subsidizing Temporary Layoffs? </title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16755</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jeff Borland, Jennifer Hunt.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> We analyze the JobKeeper lump-sum wage subsidy introduced by the Australian government in response to the COVID-19 pandemic, paying particular attention to the role of temporary layoffs in saving jobs. Although temporary layoffs were widely used, we find that recalls of workers on temporary layoff played only a small role in the early recovery. Of approximately 300,000 temporarily laid off, only about 100,000 were recalled in the initial months of recovery.   In this time total employment grew by 440,000, reversing one-half of losses from the first months of the pandemic. This suggests either that temporary layoffs were very long, or that many workers on temporary layoffs were never recalled.]]></description><author>Jeff Borland, Jennifer Hunt</author><pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16755</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Gap in Preferences: Evidence from 45,397 Facebook Interests</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16740</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín, Klaus Desmet, Ruben Cuevas, Ángel Cuevas.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses information on the frequency of 45,397 Facebook interests to study how the difference in preferences between men and women changes with a country's degree of gender equality. For preference dimensions that are systematically biased toward the same gender across the globe, differences between men and women are larger in more gender-equal countries. In contrast, for preference dimensions with a gender bias that varies across countries, the opposite holds. This finding takes an important step toward reconciling evolutionary psychology and social role theory as they relate to gender.]]></description><author>Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín, Klaus Desmet, Ruben Cuevas, Ángel Cuevas</author><pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16740</guid></item><item><title>The Other Great Migration: Southern Whites and the New Right</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16739</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Patrick Testa, Thomas Pearson, Martin Fiszbein, Andreas Ferrara, Samuel Bazzi.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> This paper provides a novel perspective on the Great Migration out of the U.S. South. Using a shift-share identification strategy, we show how millions of Southern white migrants transformed the cultural and political landscape across America. Counties with a larger Southern white share by 1940 exhibited growing support for right-wing politics throughout the 20th century and beyond. Racial animus, religious conservatism, and localist attitudes among the Southern white diaspora hastened partisan realignment as the Republican Party found fresh support for the Southern strategy outside the South. Their congressional representatives were more likely to oppose politically liberal legislation, such as the Civil Rights Act of 1964, and to object to the Electoral College count in 2021. These migrants helped shape institutions that reinforced racial inequity and exclusion, they shared ideology through religious organizations and popular media, and they transmitted an array of cultural norms to non-Southern populations. Together, our findings suggest that Southern white migrants may have forever changed the trajectory of American politics.]]></description><author>Patrick Testa, Thomas Pearson, Martin Fiszbein, Andreas Ferrara, Samuel Bazzi</author><pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16739</guid></item><item><title>Equilibrium Worker-Firm Allocations and the Deadweight Losses of Taxation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16735</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rune Vejlin, Espen R. Moen, Jesper Bagger.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> We analyse the deadweight losses of tax-induced labor misallocation in an equilibrium model of the labour market where workers search to climb a job ladder and firms post vacancies. Workers differ in abilities. Jobs differ in productivities and amenities. A planner uses affine tax functions to finance lump-sum transfers to all workers and unemployment benefits. The competitive search equilibrium maximizes after-tax utility subject to resource constraints and the tax policy. A higher tax rate distorts search effort, job ranking and vacancy creation. Distortions vary on the job ladder, but always result in deadweight losses. We calibrate the model using matched employer-employee data from Denmark. The marginal deadweight loss is 33 percent of the tax base, and primarily arise from distorted search effort and vacancy creation. Steeply rising deadweight losses from distorted vacancy creation imply that the deadweight loss in the calibrated economy exceeds those incurred by very inequality averse social planners.]]></description><author>Rune Vejlin, Espen R. Moen, Jesper Bagger</author><pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16735</guid></item><item><title>Equilibrium Job Turnover and the Business Cycle</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16733</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Melvyn G Coles, Alex Clymo, Carlos Carrillo-Tudela.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> This paper develops and estimates a fully microfounded equilibrium business cycle model
of the US labor market with aggregate productivity shocks. Those microfoundations are consistent
with evidence regarding the underlying distribution of firm growth rates across firms
[by age and size] and, when aggregated, are consistent with macro-evidence regarding gross
job creation and job destruction flows over the cycle. By additionally incorporating on-the-job
search, we systematically characterise the stochastic relationships between aggregate job creation
and job destruction flows across firms, gross hire and quit flows [churning] by workers
across firms, as well as the persistence and volatility of unemployment and worker job finding
rates over the cycle.]]></description><author>Melvyn G Coles, Alex Clymo, Carlos Carrillo-Tudela</author><pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16733</guid></item></channel></rss>