<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Development Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Development Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 21:44:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Multidimensional pre-marital investments with imperfect commitment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16864</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Junjian Yi, Wenchao Li, Venkataraman Bhaskar.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> We analyze a model of multidimensional parental investments under imperfect marital commitment. Parents choose to invest in their child's human capital and in housing, which is  a public good within marriage. If men are in excess supply in the marriage market, but also enjoy greater bargaining power within marriage, their parents will overinvest in housing to credibly commit to share more resources with potential wives. This may crowd out human capital investment. To test the theory, we use nationally representative Chinese household survey data to examine the effect of a more male-biased local sex ratio upon investments in boys, relative to investments in girls.Parents with boys increase labor supply and migrate more to improve earnings and investments. They increase housing investment while reduce educational investments.]]></description><author>Junjian Yi, Wenchao Li, Venkataraman Bhaskar</author><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16864</guid></item><item><title>The Covid-19 Shock and the Indian Economy – A Cross-Country Comparative Analysis</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16855</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ramya Raghavan, Maitreesh Ghatak.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> To understand the economic and public health impact of the Covid-19 pandemic on India, we take a comparative cross-country perspective as all countries were exposed to this shock and were negatively affected and so, a relative comparison allows us to better assess India's performance in these dimensions. We carry out three sets of exercises. First, we discuss the economic impact of Covid-19 using key macroeconomic indicators â?? gross domestic product and employment. Second, we review the fiscal policy response of the government and use household and individual-level surveys to understand the heterogenous impacts of the pandemic on households in the country. Finally, we compare public health indicators across countries. The analysis suggests that India's record with respect to other countries, including countries that are comparable in economic status, puts it in the lower tail of the distribution â?? both in terms of economic and public health indicators. The fallout on the poorer sections and informal sector was particularly severe and policies to mitigate this were inadequate. We conclude that going forward, improving the public health infrastructure and the social safety net must be the public policy priority for the government.]]></description><author>Ramya Raghavan, Maitreesh Ghatak</author><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16855</guid></item><item><title>Reducing Sexual-Orientation Discrimination: Experimental Evidence from Basic Information Treatments</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16852</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Lisa Windsteiger, Mathias Dolls, Ralph De Haas, Christopher S. Carpenter, Cevat Aksoy.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> We study basic information treatments regarding sexual orientation using randomized experiments in three countries with strong and widespread anti-gay attitudes: Serbia, Turkey, and Ukraine. Participants who received information about the economic costs to society of sexual-orientation discrimination were significantly more likely than those in a control group to support equal employment opportunities based on sexual orientation. Information that the World Health Organization (WHO) does not regard homosexuality as a mental illness increased social acceptance of sexual minorities, but only for those who reported trust in the WHO. Our results have important implications for policy makers aiming to expand the rights of lesbian, gay, and bisexual people worldwide.]]></description><author>Lisa Windsteiger, Mathias Dolls, Ralph De Haas, Christopher S. Carpenter, Cevat Aksoy</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16852</guid></item><item><title>Is Digital Credit Filling a Hole or Digging a Hole? Evidence from Malawi</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16848</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan Robinson, Pascaline Dupas, Valentina Brailovskaya.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Digital credit has expanded rapidly in Africa, mostly in the form of short-term, high-interest loans offered via mobile money. Loan terms are often opaque and consumer financial literacy is low, providing opportunities for predatory lending. A regression discontinuity analysis shows no negative effect of access to digital loans on financial well-being, but the majority of borrowers fail to repay on time and incur high late fees. We randomize exposure to a short phone-based financial literacy intervention. The intervention improved knowledge and marginally improved loan repayment but increased loan demand, increasing overall default risk.]]></description><author>Jonathan Robinson, Pascaline Dupas, Valentina Brailovskaya</author><pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16848</guid></item><item><title>Science as Civil Society:  Implications for a Green Transition</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16840</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Torsten Persson, Tim Besley.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> When scientists care about how they deploy their skills, this influences the relative cost of innovating in green sectors. We study the effects of motivated science in a simple model, where innovation is directed towards green or brown sectors with the latter polluting the environment. Innovation thus determines the relative growth rate for green goods. When we combine the resulting innovation dynamics with cultural dynamics among consumers, the influence of science is extended further. It can now increase the speed of convergence to a green future and may even change the direction of a society's path. Key activities that are (partly) value driven may thus be an important aspect of market economies.]]></description><author>Torsten Persson, Tim Besley</author><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16840</guid></item><item><title>Women's Liberation, Household Revolution</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16838</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hosny Zoabi, David Weiss, Moshe Hazan.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> How does women's empowerment affect fertility and children's education? In a dramatic revolution, U.S. states gave economic rights to married women between 1850-1920. Prior to this "women's liberation," married women were subject to the laws of coverture, which granted the husband virtually unlimited power of the purse within the household. Women's legal identities were subsumed (or covered) by their husbands. We show that granting women economic rights led to less fertility and more education. We employ an event study using the full count U.S. census and contiguous county-border pairs in bordering states that gave rights at different times. Additionally, rights were not retroactive, implying differences between those married before/after reforms. This alternative identification strategy confirms our findings and illuminates mechanisms. Quantitatively, women's empowerment can account for 15% (20%) of the decline (increase) in fertility (education) during the U.S. demographic transition. We find that shifting bargaining power accounts for these results with the underlying spousal disagreement relating to maternal mortality risk. Wealthier families decreased their fertility by more than other families, consistent with the notion that differences in control over wealth are responsible for our results. Articles from the New York Times confirm that people were aware of the implications of the legal changes. We provide evidence to negate mechanisms besides bargaining power shifts to explain our findings. Considering that the U.S. was a developing country at the time, our findings may be relevant for policy in developing countries today, where maternal mortality is still high and women are economically disadvantaged.]]></description><author>Hosny Zoabi, David Weiss, Moshe Hazan</author><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16838</guid></item><item><title>Forced Displacement and Human Capital: Evidence from Separated Siblings</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16820</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sandra Sequeira, Elias Papaioannou, Stelios Michalopoulos, Giorgio Chiovelli.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We examine the impact of conflict-driven displacement on human capital looking at the Mozambican civil war (1977-1992), during which more than four million civilians fled to the countryside, to cities, and to refugee camps and settlements in neighboring countries. First, we present descriptive patterns linking education and sectoral employment to the various displacement trajectories using the full population census. Second, we compare siblings separated during the war, using those who stayed behind as a counterfactual to one's displacement path. Displacement is associated with increased educational investments, with the largest effects experienced by rural-born children escaping to urban areas. Third, we jointly estimate place-based and uprootedness effects. Both are present, with displacement increasing education and decreasing attachment to agriculture by the same rate as being exposed to an environment approximately one standard deviation more developed than one's birthplace. Fourth, we conduct a survey in Mozambique's largest Northern city, whose population doubled during the civil war. Those displaced to the city have significantly higher education than their siblings who remained in the countryside and they converged to the levels of schooling of non-mover urban born individuals. However, those displaced exhibit significantly lower social/civic capital and have worse mental health, even three decades after the war ended. These findings reveal that displacement shocks can trigger human capital investments, breaking links with subsistence agriculture, but at the cost of long-lasting, social, and psychological traumas.]]></description><author>Sandra Sequeira, Elias Papaioannou, Stelios Michalopoulos, Giorgio Chiovelli</author><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16820</guid></item><item><title>The Dynamic Consequences of State-Building: Evidence from the French Revolution</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16815</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin Marx, Emeric Henry, Cédric Chambru.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> How do radical reforms of the state shape economic development over time? In 1790, France's first Constituent Assembly overhauled the kingdom's organization to set up new administrative entities and local capitals. In a subset of departments, new capitals were chosen quasi-randomly as the Assembly abandoned its initial plan to rotate administrative functions across multiple cities. We study how exogenous changes in local administrative presence affect the state's coercive and productive capacity, as well as economic development in the ensuing decades. In the short run, proximity to the state increases taxation, conscription, and investments in law enforcement capacity. In the long run, the new local capitals and their periphery obtain more public goods and experience faster economic development. One hundred years after the reform, capitals are 40% more populated than comparable cities in 1790. Our results shed new light on the intertemporal and redistributive impacts of state-building in the context of one of the most ambitious administrative reforms ever implemented.]]></description><author>Benjamin Marx, Emeric Henry, Cédric Chambru</author><pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16815</guid></item><item><title>Information, Intermediaries, and International Migration</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Job seekers often face substantial information frictions related to potential job quality. This is especially true in international labor markets, where intermediaries match prospective migrants with employers abroad. We conducted a randomized trial in Indonesia to explore how information about intermediary quality shapes migration choices and outcomes. Information reduces the migration rate, lowering use of low-quality intermediaries. However, workers who migrate receive better pre-departure preparation and have higher-quality job experiences abroad, despite no change in occupation or destination. Information does not change intentions to migrate or beliefs about the return to migration or intermediary quality. Nor does selection explain the improved outcomes for workers who choose to migrate with the information. Together, our findings are consistent with an increase in the option value of search: with better ability to differentiate offer quality, workers become choosier and ultimately have better migration experiences. This offers a new perspective on the importance of information and matching frictions in global labor markets.]]></description><author>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</guid></item><item><title>Randomization for Causality, Ethnography for Mechanisms: Illiquid Savings for Liquor in an Autarkic Society</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16810</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan Zinman, Dean Karlan, Ricardo Godoy.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> What should researchers do when confronted with surprising results? Financial access
innovations usually leave "temptation" spending unaffected or reduced. However, we
found that promotion of savings lockboxes in a largely autarkic society increased alcohol
consumption and blood pressure, despite no one reporting intentions to save for alcohol.
To probe mechanisms that could explain this pattern, we then used ethnographic methods,
including direct observations of drinking ("scans") and debriefing interviews to discuss the
earlier trial results. We learn that sponsoring drinks confers prestige, but the stigma
attached to drinking by outsiders likely discouraged reporting intentions to save for it.]]></description><author>Jonathan Zinman, Dean Karlan, Ricardo Godoy</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16810</guid></item><item><title>The Real Effects of Banking the Poor: Evidence from Brazil</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16798</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Matray, Julia Fonseca.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We use a large expansion of government-owned banks in cities with extremely low bank branch coverage and data on the universe of formal-sector employees in Brazil over 2000-2014 to study how financial development affects economic development and wage inequality. We find that higher financial development fosters firm creation and firm expansion, which increases labor demand and leads to higher average wages, especially for cities initially located in banking deserts. The gains produced by higher financial development are not shared equally, but instead monotonically increase with workers' productivity, which leads to a substantial increase in inequality. This increase is concentrated in cities where the initial supply of skilled workers is low, showing that talent scarcity is an important driver of how financial development affects inequality.]]></description><author>Adrien Matray, Julia Fonseca</author><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16798</guid></item><item><title>Time Use and Gender in Africa in Times of Structural Transformation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16792</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Liwa Rachel Ngai, Taryn Dinkelman.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Many African countries are still in the early stages of structural transformation. Typically, as economies move through the structural transformation, activities once conducted within the household are outsourced to the market. This has particular implications for women's time use. In this paper, we document that current patterns of female time use in home production in several African countries closely resemble historical time use patterns in the US. We highlight two stylized facts about women's time use in Africa. First, in North Africa, women spend very few hours in market work and female labor force participation overall is extremely low. Second, although extensive margin participation of women is high in sub-Saharan Africa, women tend to work in the market for only a few hours each week, with the rest of their work hours spent in home production. These two facts suggest two types of constraints that could slow down the reallocation of female
time from home to market as economies grow: Social norms related to women's market work, and a lack of infrastructure (e.g. household infrastructure and childcare facilities) to facilitate marketizing home production. We discuss recent empirical evidence related to each set of constraints and highlight new avenues for research.]]></description><author>Liwa Rachel Ngai, Taryn Dinkelman</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16792</guid></item><item><title>Controlling Irregular Migration: Can a Market for Temporary Foreign Work Permits Help?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16777</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tiffanie Perrault, Alice Mesnard, Emmanuelle Auriol.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study how temporary visa schemes can be designed to drive smugglers out of business while meeting labor market demand in host countries. The policy trade-off between migration control and ending human smuggling can be overcome by combining internal and external controls with a regulated market for temporary visas. In this market, visa duration and price are set at "eviction" levels, designed to throttle smuggling activity. We use information on irregular migration from Senegal to Spain and the Democratic Republic of Congo to South Africa to calibrate the eviction prices of visas for these two routes. Our results highlight important constraints for governments seeking to prevent temporary workers from overstaying, especially on South-North routes such as Senegal to Spain. We suggest combining a regulated market for visas with tighter sanctions against employers of undocumented workers as a new way forward.]]></description><author>Tiffanie Perrault, Alice Mesnard, Emmanuelle Auriol</author><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16777</guid></item><item><title>OPTIMAL ASSIGNMENT OF BUREAUCRATS: EVIDENCE FROM RANDOMLY ASSIGNED TAX COLLECTORS IN THE DRC</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16771</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan Weigel, Gabriel Tourek, John Kabeya Kabeya, Pedro Bessone, Augustin Bergeron.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> The assignment of workers to tasks and teams is a key margin of firm productivity and a potential source of state effectiveness. This paper investigates whether a low-capacity state can increase its tax revenue through the optimal assignment of its tax collectors. We study the two-stage random assignment of property tax collectors (i) into teams and (ii) to neighborhoods in a large Congolese city. The optimal assignment involves positive assortative matching on both dimensions: high (low) ability collectors should be paired together, and high (low) ability teams should be paired with high (low) payment propensity households. Positive assortative matching stems from complementarities in collector-to-collector and collector-to-household match types. We provide evidence that these complementarities reflect in part high-ability collectors exerting greater effort when matched with other high-ability collectors. Implementing the optimal assignment would increase tax compliance by an estimated 37% relative to the status quo (random) assignment. By contrast, to achieve a similar increase under the status quo assignment, the government would have to replace 63% of low-ability collectors with high-ability ones or to increase collectors' performance wages by 69%.]]></description><author>Jonathan Weigel, Gabriel Tourek, John Kabeya Kabeya, Pedro Bessone, Augustin Bergeron</author><pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16771</guid></item><item><title>Production Networks and War</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16759</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexey Makarin, Vasily Korovkin.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> How do severe shocks such as war alter the economy? We study how a country's production network is affected by a devastating but localized conflict. Using unique transaction-level data on Ukrainian railway shipments, we uncover several novel indirect effects of conflict on firms. First, we document substantial propagation effects on interfirm trade---trade declines even between partners outside the conflict areas if one of them had traded with those areas before the start of the war. The magnitude of such second-degree effect of conflict is one-third of the first-degree effect. Ignoring this propagation would lead to an underestimate of the total impact of conflict on trade by about 67%. Second, war induces sudden changes in the production-network structure that influence firm performance. Specifically, we find that firms that exogenously became more central---after the conflict practically cut off certain regions from the rest of Ukraine---received a relative boost to their revenues and profits. Finally, in a production-network model, we separately estimate the effects of the exogenous firm removal and the subsequent endogenous network adjustment on firm revenue distribution. At the median, network adjustment compensates for 80% of the network-destruction effect a year after the conflict onset.]]></description><author>Alexey Makarin, Vasily Korovkin</author><pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16759</guid></item><item><title>Rooted to the Soil: The impact of social housing on population in Ireland since 1911</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16743</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ronan Lyons, Alan de Bromhead.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> How does housing policy influence the distribution of population? We examine the impact of the world's first large-scale rural public housing scheme on the long-term dynamics of rural population, specifically the case of Ireland's Labourers Acts. We link detailed data on the location of over 45,000 heavily subsidized cottages for agricultural laborers built 1883-1915 in over 200 districts to decennial Censuses between 1841 and 2002. We examine how the density of this social housing, which effectively halved rents for landless laborers, affected subsequent population change and find significant persistence in the effect of this treatment on the population. These findings are from specifications that include other factors plausibly related to future population growth, including initial housing stock, land values and population density, as well as distance to urban centres. A causal interpretation is supported by an assessment of pre-trends, by no effect of cottages authorized but not built and by an IV approach that exploits a 1906 limit on legal costs. Our findings suggest that deep housing policy interventions can have long-lasting effects on population distribution.]]></description><author>Ronan Lyons, Alan de Bromhead</author><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16743</guid></item><item><title>Gender inequality and caste:  Field experimental evidence from India</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16736</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yves Zenou, Liang Choon Wang, Soubhagya Sahoo, Debayan Pakrashi, Asadul Islam.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Using a field experiment in India where patients are randomly assigned to rank among a set of physicians of the same gender but with different castes and years of experience, we show that the differences in patients' physician choices are consistent with gender-based statistical discrimination. Labor market experience cannot easily overcome the discrimination that female doctors suffer. Further, we find that gender discrimination is greater for lower caste doctors, who typically suffer from caste discrimination. Given the increasing share of professionals from a lower caste background, our results suggest that the 'intersectionality' between gender and caste leads to increased gender inequality among professionals in India]]></description><author>Yves Zenou, Liang Choon Wang, Soubhagya Sahoo, Debayan Pakrashi, Asadul Islam</author><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16736</guid></item></channel></rss>