<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Organizational Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Organizational Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 17:33:31 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Voice and Political Engagement: Evidence From a Natural Field Experiment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16839</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andreas Stegmann, Christopher Roth, Lukas Hensel, Anselm Hager.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We conduct a natural field experiment with a major European party to test whether giving
party supporters the opportunity to voice their opinions increases their engagement
in the party's electoral campaign. In our experiment, the party asked a random subset
of supporters for their opinions on the importance of different topics. Giving supporters
more opportunities to voice their opinions increases their engagement in the campaign as
measured using behavioral data from the party's smartphone application. Survey data
reveals that our voice treatments also increase other margins of campaign effort as well
as perceived voice. Our evidence highlights that parties can increase their supporters'
investment in the democratic process by implementing policies that increase their voice.]]></description><author>Andreas Stegmann, Christopher Roth, Lukas Hensel, Anselm Hager</author><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16839</guid></item><item><title>Welfare Comparisons for Biased Learning</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16833</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yuhta Ishii, Ryota Iijima, Mira Frick.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study robust welfare comparisons of learning biases, i.e., deviations from correct Bayesian updating. Given a true signal distribution, we deem one bias more harmful than another if it yields lower objective expected payoffs in all decision problems. We characterize this ranking in static (one signal) and dynamic (many signals) settings. While the static characterization compares posteriors signal-by-signal, the dynamic characterization employs an "efficiency index" quantifying the speed of belief convergence. Our results yield welfare-founded
quantifications of the severity of well-documented biases. Moreover, the static and dynamic rankings can disagree, and "smaller" biases can be worse in dynamic settings.]]></description><author>Yuhta Ishii, Ryota Iijima, Mira Frick</author><pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16833</guid></item><item><title>Information Choice in Auctions</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16832</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nina Bobkova.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> The choice of an auction mechanism influences which object characteristics bidders learn about and whether the object is allocated efficiently. Some object characteristics are valued equally by all bidders and thus are inconsequential for the efficient allocation. Others matter only to certain bidders, and thus determine the bidder with the highest object value. I show that the efficient auction is the second-price auction: it induces bidders to learn exclusively about object characteristics which matter only to them. An independent private value framework arises endogenously.]]></description><author>Nina Bobkova</author><pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16832</guid></item><item><title>Communication in the shadow of catastrophe</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16831</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Dezso Szalay, Inga Deimen.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study the role of risk in strategic information transmission. We show that an increased likelihood of extreme states â?? heavier tails â?? decreases the amount of information transmission and makes it optimal to alter the mode of decision-making from communication to simple delegation. Moreover, the worst-case losses under communication increase relative to the worst-case losses under delegation when the tails get heavier.]]></description><author>Dezso Szalay, Inga Deimen</author><pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16831</guid></item><item><title>Information, Intermediaries, and International Migration</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Job seekers often face substantial information frictions related to potential job quality. This is especially true in international labor markets, where intermediaries match prospective migrants with employers abroad. We conducted a randomized trial in Indonesia to explore how information about intermediary quality shapes migration choices and outcomes. Information reduces the migration rate, lowering use of low-quality intermediaries. However, workers who migrate receive better pre-departure preparation and have higher-quality job experiences abroad, despite no change in occupation or destination. Information does not change intentions to migrate or beliefs about the return to migration or intermediary quality. Nor does selection explain the improved outcomes for workers who choose to migrate with the information. Together, our findings are consistent with an increase in the option value of search: with better ability to differentiate offer quality, workers become choosier and ultimately have better migration experiences. This offers a new perspective on the importance of information and matching frictions in global labor markets.]]></description><author>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</guid></item><item><title>Deals That Start When You Sign Them</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16803</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Robert Gibbons.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This essay explores six sentences from Oliver Williamson- five providing context and the sixth the central topic. Decades ago, Williamson asserted that: (a) "substantially the same factors" (1973: 316) create governance issues not only within organizations but also in interactions between organizations; and (b) relational contracting might be useful in addressing these issues in both domains (1979, Figure II). More recently-in an informal conversation in 2002-he suggested a perspective on relational contracting that appears valuable in both of these domains: relational contracts as "deals that start when you sign them." The bulk of this essay explores past, present, and potential research on this perspective.]]></description><author>Robert Gibbons</author><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16803</guid></item><item><title>Building an Equilibrium: Rules versus Principles in Relational Contracts</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16802</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christian Zehnder, Holger Herz, Manuel Grieder, Robert Gibbons.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Effective collaboration within and between organizations requires efficient adaptation to unforeseen change. We study how parties build relational contracts that achieve this goal. We focus on the "clarity problem"-whether parties have a shared understanding of the promises they make each other. Specifically, (a) a buyer and seller play a trading game in several periods, (b) they know their environment will change but do not know how, and (c) before any trading occurs they can reach a non-binding agreement about how to play the entire game. We hypothesize that pairs whose initial agreement defines a broad principle rather than a narrow rule will be more successful in solving the clarity problem and in achieving efficient adaptation after unforeseen change. In our Baseline condition, we indeed observe that pairs who articulated principles achieved significantly higher performance after change occurred. Underlying this correlation, we also find that pairs with principle-based agreements were more likely both to expect and to take actions that were consistent with what their agreement prescribed. To investigate a causal link between principle-based agreements and performance, we implemented a "Nudge" intervention that induced more pairs to articulate principles. The intervention succeeded in co- ordinating more pairs on efficient quality immediately after the unforeseen change, but it failed to coordinate expectations on price, ultimately leading to conflicts and preventing an increase in long-run performance after the shock. Our results suggest that (1) principle-based agreements may improve organizational performance, but that (2) high-performing relational contracts may be difficult to build.]]></description><author>Christian Zehnder, Holger Herz, Manuel Grieder, Robert Gibbons</author><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16802</guid></item><item><title>Cross-verification and Persuasive Cheap Talk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16801</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ludovic Renou, Mehmet Ekmekci, Alp Atakan.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study a cheap-talk game where two experts first choose what information to acquire and then offer advice to a decision-maker whose actions affect the wel- fare of all. The experts cannot commit to reporting strategies. Yet, we show that the decision-maker's ability to cross-verify the experts' advice acts as a commit- ment device for the experts. We prove the existence of an equilibrium, where an expert's equilibrium payoff is equal to what he would obtain if he could commit to truthfully revealing his information.]]></description><author>Ludovic Renou, Mehmet Ekmekci, Alp Atakan</author><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16801</guid></item><item><title>On the Efficiency of Large Resale Networks</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16800</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ludovic Renou, Andrea Galeotti, Daniele Condorelli.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Many goods are allocated via resale networks, reaching their final buyer through a sequence of exchanges. We study a model where a single good is traded by a potentially infinite number of traders who have private valuations for the good and are connected in a random network that determines resale possibilities. Whoever holds the good has bargaining power. We show that large resale networks allocate efficiently in the no-discounting limit, even if resale opportunities are locally-limited. When the network is a stationary random tree, the limiting equilibrium is inefficient if and only if the network is a chain of monopolists.]]></description><author>Ludovic Renou, Andrea Galeotti, Daniele Condorelli</author><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16800</guid></item><item><title>Dispersed Behavior and Perceptions in Assortative Societies</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16789</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yuhta Ishii, Ryota Iijima, Mira Frick.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We formulate a model of social interactions and misinferences by agents who neglect assortativity in their societies, mistakenly believing that they interact with a representative sample of the population. A key component of our approach is the interplay between this bias and agents' strategic incentives. We highlight a mechanism through which assortativity neglect, combined with strategic complementarities in agents' behavior, drives up action dispersion in society (e.g., socioeconomic disparities in education investment). We also show how the combination of assortativity neglect and strategic incentives may help to explain empirically documented misperceptions of income inequality and political
attitude polarization.]]></description><author>Yuhta Ishii, Ryota Iijima, Mira Frick</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16789</guid></item><item><title>Belief Convergence under Misspecified Learning: A Martingale Approach</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16788</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yuhta Ishii, Ryota Iijima, Mira Frick.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We present an approach to analyze learning outcomes in a broad class of misspecified environments, spanning both single-agent and social learning. We introduce a novel "prediction accuracy" order over subjective models, and observe that this makes
it possible to partially restore standard martingale convergence arguments that apply under correctly specified learning. Based on this, we derive general conditions to determine when beliefs in a given environment converge to some long-run belief either locally or globally (i.e., from some or all initial beliefs). We show that these conditions can be applied, first, to unify and generalize various convergence results in previously
studied settings. Second, they enable us to analyze environments where learning is "slow," such as costly information acquisition and sequential social learning. In such environments, we illustrate that even if agents learn the truth when they are correctly specified, vanishingly small amounts of misspecification can generate extreme failures of learning.]]></description><author>Yuhta Ishii, Ryota Iijima, Mira Frick</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16788</guid></item><item><title>The Anatomy of a Hospital System Merger: The Patient Did Not Respond Well to Treatment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16787</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Shruthi Venkatesh, Chad Syverson, Raffaella Sadun, Adam Sacarny, Martin Gaynor.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Despite the continuing US hospital merger wave, it remains unclear how mergers change, or fail to change, hospital behavior and performance. We open the "black box" of hospital practices through a mega-merger between two for-profit chains. Benchmarking the merger's effects against the acquirer's stated aims, we show they achieved some of their goals, harmonizing electronic medical records and sending managers to target hospitals. Post-acquisition managerial processes were similar across the merged chain. However, these interventions failed to drive detectable gains in performance. Our findings demonstrate the importance of organizations for merger research in health care and the economy more generally.]]></description><author>Shruthi Venkatesh, Chad Syverson, Raffaella Sadun, Adam Sacarny, Martin Gaynor</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16787</guid></item><item><title>Individual and Collective Information Acquisition: An Experimental Study</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16782</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Wing Suen, Jimmy Chan, Leeat Yariv, Alessandro Lizzeri, Pellumb Reshidi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Many committees---juries, political task forces, etc.---spend time gathering costly information before reaching a decision. We report results from lab experiments focused on such information-collection processes. We consider decisions governed by individuals and groups and compare how voting rules affect outcomes. We also contrast static information collection, as in classical hypothesis testing, with dynamic collection, as in sequential hypothesis testing. Several insights emerge. Static information collection is excessive, and sequential information collection is non-stationary, producing declining decision accuracies over time. Furthermore, groups using majority rule yield especially hasty and inaccurate decisions. Nonetheless, sequential information collection is welfare enhancing relative to static collection, particularly when unanimous rules are used.]]></description><author>Wing Suen, Jimmy Chan, Leeat Yariv, Alessandro Lizzeri, Pellumb Reshidi</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16782</guid></item><item><title>Organizing Data Analytics</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16768</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Odilon Câmara, Ricardo Alonso.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We develop a theory of credible skepticism in organizations to explain the main trade-offs in organizing data generation, analysis and reporting. In our designer-agent-principal game, the designer selects the information privately observed by the agent who can misreport it at a cost, while the principal can audit the report. We study three organizational levers: tampering prevention, tampering detection and the allocation of the experimental-design task. We show that motivating informative experimentation while discouraging misreporting are often conflicting organizational goals. To incentivize experimentation, the principal foregoes a flawless tampering detection/prevention system and separates the tasks of experimental design and implementation.]]></description><author>Odilon Câmara, Ricardo Alonso</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16768</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Gap at the Top: How Network Size and Composition Impact CEO Pay</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16761</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sharmin Sazedj, José Tavares.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> This paper advances the literature on the gender pay gap amongst top managers, by
explicitly assessing the relevance of professional networks. We use data on the universe of
firms in Portugal, where female top managers earn 25% less than their male counterparts,
conditional on age, education and firm tenure. We estimate that 20% of the above femalemale earnings difference is due to differences in networks across gender. Making use
of Gelbach's decomposition, we find that the network effect can be ascribed to firm
sorting, i.e. well-connected managers tend to be associated to higher paying firms. By
focusing on episodes of transitions between firms, and relying on a propensity score
matching procedure, we estimate that around 90% of the gender pay gap emerges
during the hiring process, and is only slightly aggravated thereafter, due to biased career
progression. Roughly one third of the gender gap can be attributed to firm sorting, two
thirds of which to differences in networks. We then examine the gender composition
of female and male CEOs' networks. While we find no evidence that females benefit
differently from network size, we do find evidence that male connections are more
valuable. If, however, we proxy for the inner circle of a manager, taking into account
the proximity of connections, we conclude that same gender connections gain relevance.
These results suggest that connections between females do play an important role in the
existing corporate framework where males are over-represented. We conclude that policies
furthering female representation in leadership positions can have positive spillover effect
for other women.]]></description><author>Sharmin Sazedj, José Tavares</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16761</guid></item><item><title>Price Authority and Information Sharing with Competing Principals</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16753</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Enrique Andreu, Salvatore Piccolo, Damien J Neven.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> We characterize the degree of price discretion that competing principals award their agents in a
framework where the latter are informed about demand, while the former learn it probabilistically
and may exchange this information on a reciprocal basis. Partial delegation equilibria exist with and
without information sharing and feature binding price caps (list prices) that prevent agents to pass on
their distribution costs to consumers. Yet, these equilibria are more likely to occur with information
sharing than without. Moreover, while principals exchange information when products are sufficiently
differentiated and downstream distribution costs are neither too high nor too low, expected prices are
unambiguously lower with than without information sharing. Finally, we also argue why, and how, an
information-sharing agreement can be implemented by a simple communication protocol according to
which principals disclose their price intentions.]]></description><author>Enrique Andreu, Salvatore Piccolo, Damien J Neven</author><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16753</guid></item></channel></rss>