<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR Financial Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR Financial Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:20:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Dark Side of Stakeholder Influence: The Surprising Effect of Customer Fraud on Suppliers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16701</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Banerjee, Shantanu & Dasgupta, Sudipto & Shi, Rui.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We show that influential stakeholders distort corporate policies when they cannot commit to a long-term relationship. Following the revelation of financial fraud by a major customer, suppliers surprisingly outperform a control group in terms of sales growth, Tobin's Q and survival likelihood over a ten-year period. Our results suggest that, prior to the fraud revelation, managers' short decision horizons and aversion to short-term risk or uncertainty enables influential customers to demand relationship-specific innovation when their bargaining power is stronger, leading to suboptimal diversification. When customer bargaining power weakens, suppliers engage in riskier and novel innovation, which diversifies the customer base.]]></description><author>Banerjee, Shantanu &amp; Dasgupta, Sudipto &amp; Shi, Rui</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16701</guid></item><item><title>Escaping Air Pollution: Do Chinese Students and Immigrants Drive Property Prices and Economic Activity Abroad?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16700</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Chang, Yuk Ying & Dasgupta, Sudipto.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We construct a time-series of news coverage about air pollution in China for the period 1977-2019, and verify that such abnormal news coverage is associated with worse air quality in major Chinese cities, for which information is available for a shorter period. We find that that cross-border migration of Chinese citizens, the number of Chinese students going abroad to study, as well as capital flight from China, increase when there is an unexpected increase in air pollution news coverage. We find that U.S. regions with stronger historical ethnic ties to China experience higher property price growth when the "innovation" in air pollution news coverage is higher. We find similar results for residential prices in international cities.  Air-pollution driven student inflows increase property prices and employment growth in regions that are major destinations of foreign students. Our study suggests that perception of local environmental and climate risk can have major consequences for the cross-border relocation of capital and labor.]]></description><author>Chang, Yuk Ying &amp; Dasgupta, Sudipto</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16700</guid></item><item><title>Bank Credit and Market-based Finance for Corporations: The Effects of Minibond Issuances</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16693</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Ongena, Steven & Pinoli, Sara & Rossi, Paola & Scopelliti, Alessandro Diego.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Does a diversification of funding sources affect the financing conditions for firms? To answer this question we study a regulatory reform which allowed unlisted firms to issue minibonds. Using the Italian Credit Register, we compare new loans granted to issuer firms with new loans concurrently granted to similar non-issuer firms. We find that issuer firms obtain lower interest rates on bank loans of the same maturity than non-issuer firms, suggesting an improvement in their bargaining power with banks. Issuer firms also reduce the amount of used bank credit, expand their total and fixed assets, and raise their leverage.]]></description><author>Ongena, Steven &amp; Pinoli, Sara &amp; Rossi, Paola &amp; Scopelliti, Alessandro Diego</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16693</guid></item><item><title>Too-big-to-strand? Bond versus bank financing in the transition to a low-carbon economy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16692</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Beyene, Winta & De Greiff, Kathrin & Delis, Manthos & Ongena, Steven.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> What is the role market- and bank-based debt play in the climate transition process? We present evidence that bond markets price the risk that assets held by fossil fuel firms strand, while banks in the syndicated loan market seemingly do not price this risk much. Consequently,
to fulfill their financing needs fossil fuel firms increasingly rely less on bonds and more on loans. We can interpret the within-firm bond-to-loan substitution along stranding risk as a contraction in the supply of bond versus bank funding. Within the banking sector especially the big banks are willing to provide cheaper and more financing to fossil fuel firms.]]></description><author>Beyene, Winta &amp; De Greiff, Kathrin &amp; Delis, Manthos &amp; Ongena, Steven</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16692</guid></item><item><title>The Debt Capacity of a Government</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16687</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Dumas, Bernard J & Ehling, Paul & Yang, Chunyu.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In a deterministic overlapping-generations economy with production and physical capital, the price of debt can be positive without any budget surpluses being in the offing, because debt incorporates a rational bubble. Yet the dynamics of debt remain a function of the dynamics of the primary budget deficit. As a way to study their joint behavior, we endogenize a structural deficit in the form of an underfunded social-security scheme. We define debt capacity as the level of debt that can be just sustained without a change of policy all the way to an unstable steady state. When it starts below the capacity, the debt converges to a stable steady state, in which the bubble is sustained. Above capacity the bubble unravels and the deficit cannot be financed. In several realistic scenarios occurring in economies, we calculate the needed policy response, which is the true "fiscal cost" of exceeding debt capacity.]]></description><author>Dumas, Bernard J &amp; Ehling, Paul &amp; Yang, Chunyu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16687</guid></item><item><title>Zombie Lending: Theoretical, International, and Historical Perspectives</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16685</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Acharya, Viral V. & Crosignani, Matteo & Eisert, Tim & Steffen, Sascha.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper surveys the theory on zombie lending incentives and the consequences of zombie lending for the real economy. It also offers a historical perspective by reviewing the growing empirical evidence on zombie lending along three dimensions: (i) the role of under-capitalized banks, (ii) effects on zombie firms, and (iii) spillovers and distortions for non-zombie firms. We then provide an overview of how zombie lending can be attenuated. Finally, we use a sample of U.S. publicly listed firms to compare various measures proposed in the literature to classify firms as ``zombies." We identify definitions of zombie firms that are  adequate to investigate real sector competitive distortions of zombie lending. We find that only definitions that are based on interest rate subsidies are able to detect these spillovers.]]></description><author>Acharya, Viral V. &amp; Crosignani, Matteo &amp; Eisert, Tim &amp; Steffen, Sascha</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16685</guid></item><item><title>The Real Effects of FinTech Lending on SMEs: Evidence from Loan Applications</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16684</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Eça, Afonso & Ferreira, Miguel & Prado, Melissa & Rizzo, A. Emanuele.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We show that FinTech lending affects credit markets and real economic activity using a unique data set of a Peer-to-Business platform for which we have the universe of loan applications and loans granted. We find that FinTech serves the same segment of high quality and creditworthy small businesses as banks. Firms use FinTech loans to reduce bank dependence, especially from less liquid banks. We find that firms that access FinTech lending increase assets, employment, and sales relative to firms that get their loan application rejected. In addition, we find that firms increase leverage as they substitute long-term bank debt with long-term FinTech debt and short-term bank debt. Our findings suggest that FinTech lending reduces financing constraints and spurs investment and firm growth.]]></description><author>Eça, Afonso &amp; Ferreira, Miguel &amp; Prado, Melissa &amp; Rizzo, A. Emanuele</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16684</guid></item><item><title>Misdiagnosing Bank Capital Problems</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16680</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Bulow, Jeremy & Klemperer, Paul.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Banks' reluctance to repair their balance sheets, combined with deposit insurance and regulatory forbearance in recognizing greater risks and losses, can lead to solvency problems that look like liquidity (bank-run) crises. Regulatory forbearance incentivizes banks to both retain risky loans and reject new good opportunities. With sufficient regulatory forbearance, partially-insured banks act exactly as if they are fully insured. Stress tests certify that uninsured creditors will be paid, not that banks are solvent, and have ambiguous effects on the efficiency of investment.]]></description><author>Bulow, Jeremy &amp; Klemperer, Paul</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16680</guid></item><item><title>Competition and Misconduct</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16678</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Thanassoulis, John.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Misconduct is widespread; practices such as mis-selling, pump&dump, and money laundering harm counterparties while raising profits. This paper presents a mechanism which can determine what sorts of misconduct can be sustained in competitive equilibrium in concentrated markets, oligopoly settings, and in markets with many small competing firms. The model studied allows general demand and makes a distinction in types of ethical dilemma using current psychological understanding. The paper shows, for example, that markets with many small competing firms are not vulnerable to misconduct if firms respond to entry with niche strategies or if the ethical dilemma draws an emotional response.]]></description><author>Thanassoulis, John</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16678</guid></item><item><title>A q-theory of banks</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16670</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Begenau, Juliane & Bigio, Saki & Majerovitz, Jeremy & Vieyra, Matias.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We propose a dynamic bank theory with a delayed loss recognition mechanism and a regulatory capital constraint at its core. The estimated model matches four facts about banks' Tobin's Q that summarize bank leverage dynamics. (1) Book and market equity values diverge, especially during crises; (2) Tobin's Q predicts future bank profitability; (3) neither book nor market leverage constraints are binding for most banks; (4) bank leverage and Tobin's Q are mean reverting but highly persistent. We examine a counterfactual experiment where different accounting rules produce a novel policy tradeoff.]]></description><author>Begenau, Juliane &amp; Bigio, Saki &amp; Majerovitz, Jeremy &amp; Vieyra, Matias</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16670</guid></item><item><title>FinTech Lending</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16668</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Berg, Tobias & Fuster, Andreas & Puri, Manju.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we review the growing literature on FinTech lending â??- the provision of credit facilitated by technology that improves the customer-lender interaction or lenders' screening and monitoring of borrowers. FinTech lending has grown rapidly, though in developed economies like the U.S. it still only accounts for a small share of total credit. An increase in convenience and speed appears to have been more central to FinTech lending's growth than improved screening or monitoring, though there is certainly potential for the latter, as is the case for increased financial inclusion. The COVID-19 pandemic has shown potential vulnerabilities of FinTech lenders, although in certain segments they have displayed rapid growth.]]></description><author>Berg, Tobias &amp; Fuster, Andreas &amp; Puri, Manju</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16668</guid></item><item><title>&amp;quot;There is No Planet B&amp;quot;, but for Banks There are &amp;quot;Countries B to Z&amp;quot;: Domestic Climate Policy and Cross-Border Bank Lending</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16665</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Benincasa, Emanuela & Kabas, Gazi & Ongena, Steven.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We provide evidence that banks increase cross-border lending in response to higher climate policy stringency in their home countries. Saturating with granular set of fixed effects and including a rich set of control variables, we show that the increase in cross-border lending is not driven by loan demand and/or other bank home country characteristics. In line with banks use cross-border lending as a regulatory arbitrage tool, the increase in cross-border lending occurs only if banks' home countries have more stringent climate policy compared to their borrowers' countries. The effect is stronger for large, lowly capitalized banks with high NPL ratios and for banks with more experience in cross-border lending. Our results suggest that without a global cooperation, cross-border lending can be a channel that reduces the effectiveness of climate policies.]]></description><author>Benincasa, Emanuela &amp; Kabas, Gazi &amp; Ongena, Steven</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16665</guid></item><item><title>Zombie Lending and Policy Traps</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16658</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Acharya, Viral V. & Lenzu, Simone & Wang, Olivier.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We build a model with heterogeneous firms and banks to analyze how policy can affect
the efficiency of credit allocation and long-term economic outcomes. When transitory
demand or productivity shocks are small, conventional monetary policy can restore
efficient bank lending and production by lowering interest rates. For moderately large
shocks, however, conventional policy may hit the effective lower bound, necessitating
unconventional policy such as regulatory forbearance towards banks to stabilize the
economy. Aggressive unconventional policy runs the risk of introducing zombie lending and a "diabolical sorting", whereby low-capitalization banks extend new credit or
evergreen existing loans to low-productivity firms. In a dynamic setting, policy aimed
at avoiding short-term recessions can be trapped into protracted excessive forbearance due to congestion externalities imposed by zombie lending on healthier firms.
The resulting economic sclerosis transforms transitory shocks into phases of delayed
recovery and potentially permanent output losses. Our model highlights the importance of maintaining a well-capitalized banking system to avoid such policy traps as
not raising capital requirements upfront but raising them significantly upon the arrival
of shocks can also backfire by encouraging zombie lending.]]></description><author>Acharya, Viral V. &amp; Lenzu, Simone &amp; Wang, Olivier</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16658</guid></item><item><title>How Do Acquisitions Affect the Mental Health of Employees?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16657</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Bach, Laurent & Baghai, Ramin P. & Bos, Marieke & Silva, Rui C.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Using employer-employee level data linked to individual health records, we document that the incidence of stress, anxiety, depression, psychiatric medication usage, and even suicide increase following acquisitions. These effects are prevalent among employees from both targets and acquirers, in weak as well as in growing, profitable firms. Employees who experience negative career developments within the merging firms, 'blue-collar' workers, and employees with lower cognitive and non-cognitive skills are most affected. A variety of tests address endogeneity concerns, including an analysis exploiting failed mergers. Our findings point to mental illness as a significant non-pecuniary cost of acquisitions.]]></description><author>Bach, Laurent &amp; Baghai, Ramin P. &amp; Bos, Marieke &amp; Silva, Rui C</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16657</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Fragility of For-profit Hospitals: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16650</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Bai, Ge & Jiménez, Daniel & Phan, Phillip & Quintero, Luis & Rebucci, Alessandro & Sun, Xian.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We estimate the likelihood of financial distress of U.S. hospitals in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic using AHA Annual Survey data for 2011-2019 and smartphone mobility data for 2020. We find that while the average likelihood of distress across all hospitals is 28.53 % in 2020, slightly increasing from 2019, for-profit hospitals are much more likely to be distressed. Their average likelihood of financial distress is 39.13 %---a 6.93 percentage point increase from 2019. For-profit hospitals are the main providers of specialty health care services, such as psychiatric and acute long-term care, so their increased likelihood of distress poses a risk to service provision in these specialty areas, and particularly in rural communities. Our prediction model based on mobility data performs very well in sample against actual data and can potentially help policymakers and hospital administrators to monitor financial distress in real-time when case mixes change, or other large shocks materialize.]]></description><author>Bai, Ge &amp; Jiménez, Daniel &amp; Phan, Phillip &amp; Quintero, Luis &amp; Rebucci, Alessandro &amp; Sun, Xian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16650</guid></item><item><title>The Return Expectations of Public Pension Funds</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16635</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Andonov, Aleksandar & Rauh, Joshua.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The return expectations of public pension funds are positively related to cross-sectional differences in past performance. This positive relation operates through the expected risk premium, rather than the expected risk-free rate or inflation rate. Pension funds act on their beliefs and adjust their portfolio composition accordingly. Persistent investment skills, risk-taking, efforts to reduce costly rebalancing, and fiscal incentives from unfunded liabilities cannot fully explain the reliance of expectations on past performance. The results are consistent with extrapolative expectations, as the dependence on past returns is greater when executives have personally experienced longer performance histories with the fund.]]></description><author>Andonov, Aleksandar &amp; Rauh, Joshua</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16635</guid></item><item><title>Bank Use of Sovereign CDS in the Eurozone Crisis: Hedging and Risk Incentives</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16628</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Acharya, Viral V. & Gündüz, Yalin & Johnson, Tim.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Using a comprehensive dataset from German banks, we document the usage of
sovereign credit default swaps (CDS) during the European sovereign debt crisis of
2008-2013. Banks used the sovereign CDS market to extend, rather than hedge,
their long exposures to sovereign risk during this period. Lower loan exposure to
sovereign risk is associated with greater protection selling in CDS, the effect being
weaker when sovereign risk is high. Bank and country risk variables are mostly
not associated with protection selling. The findings are driven by the actions of
a few non-dealer banks which sold CDS protection aggressively at the onset of
the crisis, but started covering their positions at its height while simultaneously
shifting their assets towards sovereign bonds and loans. Our findings underscore
the importance of accounting for derivatives exposure in building a complete picture
and understanding fully the economic drivers of the bank-sovereign nexus of risk]]></description><author>Acharya, Viral V. &amp; Gündüz, Yalin &amp; Johnson, Tim</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16628</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Access to Small Business Credit: Evidence from the Paycheck Protection Program</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16623</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Howell, Sabrina & Kuchler, Theresa & Snitkof, David & Ströbel, Johannes & Wong, Jun.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We explore the sources of racial disparities in small business lending by studying the $806 billion Paycheck Protection Program (PPP), which was designed to support small business jobs during the COVID-19 pandemic. PPP loans were administered by private lenders but federally guaranteed, largely eliminating unobservable credit risk as a factor in explaining differential lending by race. We document that even after controlling for a firm's zip code, industry, loan size, PPP approval date, and other characteristics, Black-owned businesses were 12.1 percentage points (70% of the mean) more likely to obtain their PPP loan from a fintech lender than a traditional bank. Among conventional lenders, smaller banks were much less likely to lend to Black-owned firms, while the Top-4 banks exhibited little to no disparity after including controls. We use novel data to show that the disparity is not primarily explained by differences in pre-existing bank or credit relationships, firm financial positions, fintech affinity, or borrower application behavior. In contrast, we document that Black-owned businesses' higher rate of borrowing from fintechs compared to smaller banks is particularly large in places with high racial animus, pointing to a potential role for discrimination in explaining some of the racial disparities in small business lending. We find evidence that when small banks automate their lending processes, and thus reduce human involvement in the loan origination process, their rate of PPP lending to Black-owned businesses increases, with larger effects in places with more racial animus.]]></description><author>Howell, Sabrina &amp; Kuchler, Theresa &amp; Snitkof, David &amp; Ströbel, Johannes &amp; Wong, Jun</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16623</guid></item><item><title>What do you think about climate finance?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16622</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Ströbel, Johannes & Wurgler, Jeffrey.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We survey 861 finance academics, professionals, and public sector regulators and policy economists about climate finance topics. They identify regulatory risk as the top climate risk to businesses and investors over the next five years, but they view physical risks as the top risk over the next 30 years. By an overwhelming margin, respondents believe that asset prices underestimate climate risks rather than overestimate them. We also tabulate opinions about the correlation between growth and climate change; social discount rates appropriate for projects that mitigate the effects of climate change; most influential forces for reducing climate risks; and, most important research topics.]]></description><author>Ströbel, Johannes &amp; Wurgler, Jeffrey</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16622</guid></item><item><title>Global Evidence on Profit Shifting: The Role of Intangible Assets</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16615</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Delis, Fotis & Delis, Manthos & Laeven, Luc & Ongena, Steven.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study global variations in profit shifting and the role played therein by firms' intangible assets. Employing nonparametric estimation techniques within a mainstay model of profit shifting, we construct a global database, with subsidiaryâ??year estimates of profit shifting from 95 countries for the period 2009â??17. A key determinant of profit shifting is the subsidiaries' ratio of intangible assets, and this channel is stronger in countries with weaker institutions. Both our new database and our novel findings open important avenues to analyze the sources and effects of profit shifting.]]></description><author>Delis, Fotis &amp; Delis, Manthos &amp; Laeven, Luc &amp; Ongena, Steven</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16615</guid></item><item><title>Dividend Momentum and Stock Return Predictability: A Bayesian Approach</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16613</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Antolin-Diaz, Juan & Petrella, Ivan & Rubio-Ramírez, Juan Francisco.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> A long tradition in macro-finance studies the joint dynamics of aggregate stock returns and dividends using vector autoregressions (VARs), imposing the cross-equation restrictions implied by the Campbell-Shiller (CS) identity to sharpen inference. We take a Bayesian perspective and develop methods to draw from any posterior distribution of a VAR that encodes a priori skepticism about large amounts of return predictability while imposing the CS restrictions. In doing so, we show how a common empirical practice of omitting dividend growth from the system amounts to imposing the extra restriction that dividend growth is not persistent. We highlight that persistence in dividend growth induces a previously overlooked channel for return predictability, which we label "dividend momentum." Compared to estimation based on OLS, our restricted informative prior leads to a much more moderate, but still signiâ??cant, degree of return predictability, with forecasts that are helpful out-of-sample and realistic asset allocation prescriptions with Sharpe ratios that out-perform common benchmarks.]]></description><author>Antolin-Diaz, Juan &amp; Petrella, Ivan &amp; Rubio-Ramírez, Juan Francisco</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16613</guid></item><item><title>Revisiting the Anticompetitive Effects of Common Ownership</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16612</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Azar, José & Vives, Xavier.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We use data from the U.S. airline industry to test the hypothesis, consistent with the general equilibrium oligopoly model of Azar and Vives (2021), that inter-industry common ownership should be associated with lower prices in product markets. We find that, as the model predicts, increases over time in intra-industry common ownership are associated with higher prices, while increases in inter-industry common ownership are associated with lower prices. The aggregate effect is nil. We also find that common ownership by the "Big Three" (BlackRock, Vanguard and State Street) is associated with lower airline prices, while common ownership by shareholders other than the Big Three is associated with higher prices. The results highlight the limitations of partial equilibrium oligopoly theory in the context of common ownership, and the need to consider a general equilibrium perspective.]]></description><author>Azar, José &amp; Vives, Xavier</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16612</guid></item><item><title>Currency Volatility and Global Technological Innovation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16611</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Hsu, Po-Hsuan & Taylor, Mark & Wang, Zigan & Xu, Qi.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the real effects of foreign exchange (FX) volatility on technological innovation. Using a 32-market, three-decade sample, we show that heightened FX volatility associates with significantly lower firm-level R&D expenditures, patents granted, and forward citations. The negative FX volatility-innovation relation can be attributed to precautionary savings needs and trade slowdown. The relationship is stronger for firms with financial constraints, with the use of foreign debt, and in more open economies; it is weaker for firms with derivatives hedging, with higher sales, and in countries with better financial development. We also use FX regime changes and the collapse of the European Exchange Rate Mechanism to support a causal interpretation]]></description><author>Hsu, Po-Hsuan &amp; Taylor, Mark &amp; Wang, Zigan &amp; Xu, Qi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16611</guid></item><item><title>Hot Money Inflows and Bank Risk-Taking: Germany from the 1920s to the Great Depression</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16606</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Collet, Stéphanie & Postel-Vinay, Natacha.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> What is the impact of hot capital inflows on bank risk-taking? In an increasingly financially globalised world this question becomes especially relevant. However few authors have examined it in detail empirically, despite repeated crises in Latin America, East Asia and the Eurozone from the 1980s to the 2010s. In this paper, we collect individual bank data on one of history's most striking examples of a "supply push" in foreign funds: the great inflow of capital from the developed world to Germany in the second half of the 1920s. Bank by bank we examine its effects on decisions related to leverage, lending and liquidity. The specificities of the time period â?? the Dawes Plan of 1924 as well as the relative absence of a Too-Big-to-Fail environment, which we document through extensive historiographical analysis â?? allow us to mitigate endogeneity concerns. We develop a three-step approach in which we run panel regressions including only months of falling interest-rate spreads, and apply a two-stage least-squares model in which initial bank size is used as an instrument. In all our models our results tend to converge: while capital inflows did not seem to impact banks' liquidity decisions, their impact on leverage was non-negligeable. This paper's results thus call for extra prudential oversight whenever cross-border banking flows increase significantly.]]></description><author>Collet, Stéphanie &amp; Postel-Vinay, Natacha</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16606</guid></item><item><title>Exposure, Experience, and Expertise: Why Personal Histories Matter in Economics</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16598</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Malmendier, Ulrike M..</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Personal experiences of economic outcomes, from global financial crises to individual-level job losses, can shape individual beliefs, risk attitudes, and choices for years to come. A growing literature on experience effects shows that individuals act as if past outcomes that they experienced were overly likely to occur again, even if they are fully informed about the actual likelihood. This reaction to past experiences is long-lasting though it decays over time as individuals accumulate new experiences. Modern brain science helps understand these processes. Evidence on neuroplasticity reveals that personal experiences and learning alter the strength of neural connections and fine-tune the brain structure to those past experiences ("use-dependent brain"). I show that experience effects help understand belief formation and decision-making in a wide area of economic applications, including inflation, home purchases, mortgage choices, and consumption expenditures. I argue that experience-based learning is broadly applicable to economic decision-making and discuss topics for future research in education, health, race, and gender economics.]]></description><author>Malmendier, Ulrike M.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16598</guid></item><item><title>Banks' Equity Stakes in Firms: A Blessing or Curse in Credit Markets?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16594</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Fecht, Falko & Peydró, José Luis & Tümer-Alkan, Günseli & Yu, Yuejuan.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We analyze how banks' equity stakes in firms influence their credit supply in crisis times. For identification, we exploit the 2008 Global Financial Crisis and merge unique supervisory data from the German credit register on individual bank-firm credit exposures with the security register data that include banks' equity holdings. We find that a large and ex-ante persistent equity position held by a bank in a firm is associated with a larger credit provision from the respective bank to that firm. In crisis times, however, equity stakes only foster credit supply to ex-ante riskier firms especially from relatively weak banks. This ex-ante risk-taking may be due to better (insider) information by the bank, including a traditional lending relationship over the crisis. However, this ex-ante riskier lending translates also into higher ex-post loan defaults, worse firm-level stock market returns and even more firm bankruptcy or restructuring cases. Our results therefore suggest that banks' equity stakes in their borrowers do not mitigate debt overhang problems of distressed firms in crisis times, but rather foster evergreening of banks' outstanding credit to those (zombie) firms.]]></description><author>Fecht, Falko &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Tümer-Alkan, Günseli &amp; Yu, Yuejuan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16594</guid></item><item><title>Joining Forces: The Spillover Effects of EPA Enforcement Actions and the Role of Socially Responsible Investors</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16584</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Dasgupta, Sudipto & Huynh, Thanh & Xia, Ying.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We show that firms reduce emissions at their local plants following EPA enforcement actions against nearby plants of peer firms operating in the same product market. The emission reductions are larger for plants located close to socially responsible mutual funds (SRMFs) that hold the parent firm's shares, and for plants belonging to firms with high operational flexibility. The close proximity to SRMFs is also associated with adoption of more abatement measures. While plants increase emissions again in the long run, these reversals are prevented for plants located close to SRMFs. We provide evidence that the threat of exit by SRMFs has real consequences for how the local plants respond to the enforcement action The results suggest that local SRMF monitoring complements EPA enforcement.]]></description><author>Dasgupta, Sudipto &amp; Huynh, Thanh &amp; Xia, Ying</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16584</guid></item><item><title>Learning in Bank Runs</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16581</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Schliephake, Eva & Shapiro, Joel.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We examine a model in which depositor learning exacerbates bank runs. Informed depositors can quickly withdraw when the bank has low-quality assets. Uninformed depositors may decide to wait, which allows them to learn by observing informed depositors' actions. However, learning that the bank has low-quality assets will spark a run ex-post, which increases the incentives of uninformed depositors to run ex-ante. Moreover, when there are more informed depositors, uninformed depositors have a fear of missing out, which also makes preemptive runs more likely. Learning may, thus, increase the likelihood of panic runs and decrease surplus.]]></description><author>Schliephake, Eva &amp; Shapiro, Joel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16581</guid></item><item><title>The Global Financial Cycle</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16580</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Miranda-Agrippino, Silvia & Rey, Hélène.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We review the literature on the empirical characteristics of the global financial cycle and associated stylized facts on international capital flows, asset prices, risk aversion and liquidity in the financial system. We analyse the co-movements of global factors in asset prices and capital flows with commodity prices, international trade and world output as well as the sensitivity of different parts of the world to the Global Financial Cycle.  We present evidence of the causal effects of the monetary policies of the US Federal Reserve, the European Central Bank and of the People's Bank of China on the Global Financial Cycle.  We then assess whether the 2008 financial crisis has altered the transmission channels of monetary policies on the Global Financial Cycle. Finally, we discuss the theoretical modelling of the Global Financial Cycle and avenues for future research.]]></description><author>Miranda-Agrippino, Silvia &amp; Rey, Hélène</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16580</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic Strategic Corporate Finance: A Tug of War with Financial Frictions</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16567</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Doraszelski, Ulrich & Gomes, Joao F & Nockher, Felix.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Access to capital markets plays a key role for the evolution of an industry over time. We develop a benchmark theoretical setting that integrates core corporate finance insights about the impact of financial frictions on investment with those from industrial organization on dynamic competition and industry evolution under perfect capital markets. Using state of the art computational tools to systematically detect and evaluate multiple equilibria and to thoroughly explore the parameter space of our model, we show how, depending on key industry characteristics such as market size, financial frictions impact firms' pricing and investment strategies and the degree of industry concentration.]]></description><author>Doraszelski, Ulrich &amp; Gomes, Joao F &amp; Nockher, Felix</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16567</guid></item><item><title>Credit Market Competition and Bank Capitalization</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16566</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Dursun-de-Neef, Havva Özlem & Gehrig, Thomas.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We document that within regional U.S. mortgage markets an increase in competition exerts differential effects on banks with large and small market shares. Large market share banks reduce capitalization and increase risk taking as a response to an increase in the intensity of competition, while small market share banks enhance capitalization and reduce risk taking. These results are tied to market shares and not driven by bank size or the level of concentration within local regional markets.]]></description><author>Dursun-de-Neef, Havva Özlem &amp; Gehrig, Thomas</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16566</guid></item><item><title>The impact of common law on the volume of legal services: An international study</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16565</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Dia, Enzo & Melitz, Jacques.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We show that the heavy use of legal services relative to output in the US is not a peculiarity of the country but applies to common law countries in general. It stems largely from better ability to contract and easier access to justice. Yet in close association, common law also offers lawyers potentially more room for rent-Â¬seeking than civil law. Thereby the costs could outweigh the benefits. Both real GDP per capita and openness emerge as further factors making room for lawyers.]]></description><author>Dia, Enzo &amp; Melitz, Jacques</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16565</guid></item><item><title>Strategic Leadership in Corporate Social Responsibility</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16564</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Albuquerque, Rui & Cabral, Luís M B.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We propose a strategic theory of Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR). Shareholder maximizers commit to a mission statement that extends beyond firm value maximiza- tion. This commitment leads firms (either product market competitors or complementors along the value chain) to change their actions in ways that ultimately favor shareholders. We thus provide a formal analysis of the "doing well by doing good" adage. We also pro- vide conditions such that the mission statement game has the nature of a pure coordination game. Our framework thus provides a natural theory of firm leadership in a CSR context: by selecting a CSR mission statement, a first mover effectively leads the industry to a Pareto optimal equilibrium.]]></description><author>Albuquerque, Rui &amp; Cabral, Luís M B</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16564</guid></item><item><title>Monetary Policy, Labor Income Redistribution and the Credit Channel: Evidence from Matched Employer-Employee and Credit Registers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16549</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Jasova, Martina & Mendicino, Caterina & Panetti, Ettore & Peydró, José Luis & Supera, Dominik.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> This paper documents the redistributive effects of monetary policy on labor market outcomes via
the credit channel. For identification, we exploit matched administrative datasets in Portugal
- employee-employer and credit registers - and monetary policy since the Eurozone creation
in 1999. We find that softer monetary policy improves worker labor market outcomes (wages,
hours worked and firm employment) more in small and young firms, which are more financially
constrained. Within small and young firms, the wage effects accrue to incumbent workers,
in line with the back-loaded wage mechanism. Consistent with the capital-skill complementarity
mechanism, we document an increase in skill premium and show that financially constrained
firms increase both physical and human capital investment by most. Our findings uncover
a central role for both the firm-balance sheet and the bank lending channels of the monetary
policy transmission to labor income inequality, with state-dependent effects that are substantially
stronger during crisis times. Importantly, we do not find any redistributive effects for firms
without bank credit.]]></description><author>Jasova, Martina &amp; Mendicino, Caterina &amp; Panetti, Ettore &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Supera, Dominik</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16549</guid></item><item><title>Dealer Funding and Market Liquidity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16548</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Bruche, Max & Kuong, John Chi-Fong.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We consider a model in which dealers intermediate trades between clients and provide immediacy, or, market liquidity. Dealers can exert unobservable search effort to improve the chance of intermediating profitably.  This moral-hazard friction impairs dealers' ability to raise external finance and hence to compete aggressively with each other in providing liquidity. Market liquidity is limited even for safe assets and more so for assets with higher search cost. To alleviate the financing friction, dealers opt to finance with debt and intermediate in several markets simultaneously. Dealer leverage is therefore endogenous and related to variations in liquidity across otherwise unrelated markets. Our results shed light on how post-crisis regulations influence the provision of immediacy in bond markets.]]></description><author>Bruche, Max &amp; Kuong, John Chi-Fong</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16548</guid></item><item><title>When Green Meets Green</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16536</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Degryse, Hans & Goncharenko, Roman & Theunisz, Carola & Vadasz, Tamas.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We investigate whether and how the environmental consciousness (greenness for short) of firms and banks is reflected in the pricing of bank credit. Using a large international sample of syndicated loans over the period 2011-2019, we find that firms are indeed rewarded for being
green in the form of cheaper loans -- however, only when borrowing from a green consortium of lenders, and only after the ratification of the Paris Agreement in 2015. Thus, we find that environmental attitudes matter "when green meets green." We further construct a simple
stylized theoretical model to show that the green-meets-green pattern emerges in equilibrium as the result of third-degree price discrimination with regard to firms' greenness.]]></description><author>Degryse, Hans &amp; Goncharenko, Roman &amp; Theunisz, Carola &amp; Vadasz, Tamas</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16536</guid></item><item><title>Does Political Partisanship Cross Borders? Evidence from International Capital Flows</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16533</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Kempf, Elisabeth & Luo, Mancy & Schaefer, Larissa & Tsoutsoura, Margarita.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Does partisan perception shape the flow of international capital? We provide evidence from two settings, syndicated corporate loans and equity mutual funds, to show that ideological alignment with foreign governments affects the cross-border capital allocation by U.S. institutional investors. Moreover, we find that ideological alignment with foreign countries also affects investments of non-U.S. investors and can explain patterns in bilateral FDI flows. Our empirical strategy ensures that direct economic effects of foreign elections or bilateral ties between countries are not driving the result. Combined, our findings imply that partisan perception is a global phenomenon and its economic effects transcend national borders.]]></description><author>Kempf, Elisabeth &amp; Luo, Mancy &amp; Schaefer, Larissa &amp; Tsoutsoura, Margarita</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16533</guid></item><item><title>Regulating Insurance Markets: Multiple Contracting and Adverse Selection</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16531</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Attar, Andrea & Mariotti, Thomas & Salanié, François.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies an insurance market on which privately informed consumers can simultaneously trade with several firms operating under a regulation that prohibits cross-subsidies between contracts. The regulated game supports a single equilibrium allocation in which each layer of coverage is fairly priced given the consumer types who purchase it. This competitive allocation cannot be Pareto-improved by a social planner who observes neither consumers' types nor their trades with firms. Public intervention under multiple contracting and adverse selection should thus arguably target firms' pricing strategies, leaving consumers free to choose their preferred amount of coverage.]]></description><author>Attar, Andrea &amp; Mariotti, Thomas &amp; Salanié, François</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16531</guid></item><item><title>On the Instability of Private Intertemporal Liquidity Provision</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16528</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Dietrich, Diemo & Gehrig, Thomas.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We establish that the provision of intertemporal liquidity is fundamentally prone to instability. Not only are banks subject to coordination failures but also asset markets are inherently unstable. These findings challenge the notion of optimal private provision of liquidity.]]></description><author>Dietrich, Diemo &amp; Gehrig, Thomas</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16528</guid></item><item><title>What Alleviates Crowding in Factor Investing?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16527</link><description><![CDATA[<b>DeMiguel, Victor & Martin-Utrera, Alberto & Uppal, Raman.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> The growing number of institutions exploiting factor-investing strategies raises concerns that crowding may increase price-impact costs and erode profits. We identify a mechanism that alleviates crowding -- trading diversification: institutions exploiting different characteristics can reduce each other's price-impact costs even when their rebalancing trades are not negatively correlated. Empirically, trading diversification increases capacity by 45%, optimal investment by 43%, and profits by 22%. Using a game-theoretic model, we show that, while competition to exploit a characteristic erodes its profits because of crowding, competition among institutions exploiting other characteristics alleviates crowding. Using mutual-fund holdings, we provide empirical support for the model's predictions.]]></description><author>DeMiguel, Victor &amp; Martin-Utrera, Alberto &amp; Uppal, Raman</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16527</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Market Expectations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16520</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Baumeister, Christiane.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Asset prices are a valuable source of information about financial market participants' expectations about key macroeconomic variables. However, the presence of time-varying risk premia requires an adjustment of market prices to obtain the market's rational assessment of future price and policy developments. This paper reviews empirical approaches for recovering market-based expectations. It starts by laying out the two canonical modeling frameworks that form the backbone for estimating risk premia and highlights the proliferation of risk pricing factors that result in a wide range of different asset-price-based expectation measures. It then describes a key methodological innovation to evaluate the empirical plausibility of risk premium estimates and to identify the most accurate market-based expectation measure. The usefulness of this general approach is illustrated for price expectations in the global oil market. Then, the paper provides an overview of the body of empirical evidence for monetary policy and inflation expectations with a special emphasis on market-specific characteristics that complicate the quest for the best possible market-based expectation measure. Finally, it discusses a number of economic applications where market expectations play a key role for evaluating economic models, guiding policy analysis, and deriving shock measures.]]></description><author>Baumeister, Christiane</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16520</guid></item><item><title>Distrust or speculation? The socioeconomic drivers of U.S. cryptocurrency investments</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16518</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Auer, Raphael & Tercero Lucas, David.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Employing representative data from the U.S. Survey of Consumer Payment Choice, we disprove the hypothesis that cryptocurrency investors are motivatedby distrust in fiat currencies or regulated finance. Compared with the general population, investors show no differences in their level of security concerns with either cash or commercial banking services. We find that cryptocurrency investors tend to be educated, young and digital natives. In recent years, a gap in ownership of cryptocurrencies across genders has emerged. We examine how investor characteristics vary across cryptocurrencies and show that owners of cryptocurrencies increasingly tend to hold their investment for longer periods.]]></description><author>Auer, Raphael &amp; Tercero Lucas, David</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16518</guid></item><item><title>Expansionary Austerity: Reallocating Credit Amid Fiscal Consolidation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16511</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Morais, Bernardo & Perez-Estrada, Javier & Peydró, José Luis & Ruiz-Ortega, Claudia.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We show expansionary fiscal austerity via reallocation of credit supply, but with a raise in poverty.
For identification, we exploit the introduction of a Mexican law limiting the debt of subnational
governments along with matched credit register, firm, bank, and state datasets. After the law,
states with higher ex ante public debt grow substantially faster, despite larger fiscal consolidation
(higher taxes and lower public expenditure). Banks operating in more indebted states reallocate
credit supply away from local governments into private firms, with stronger effects for banks with
higher exposure to local public debt, consistent with lowering crowding out. Effects only happen
after the law, not before, and there are strong firm-level real effects associated. The reduction of
crowding out is stronger for financially constrained firms and for firms operating in states with
higher ex ante public spending on social services over infrastructure projects. In states more
affected by the law, despite better economic effects, extreme poverty increases--especially in
states with higher ex ante public spending on social services over infrastructure--consistent with
a strong reduction for social services during the fiscal consolidation.]]></description><author>Morais, Bernardo &amp; Perez-Estrada, Javier &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Ruiz-Ortega, Claudia</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16511</guid></item><item><title>Capital Controls, Domestic Macroprudential Policy and the Bank Lending Channel of Monetary Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16510</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Fabiani, Andrea & Lopéz Piñeros, Martha & Peydró, José Luis & Soto, Paul.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study how capital controls and domestic macroprudential policy tame credit supply booms, respectively targeting foreign and domestic bank debt. For identification, we exploit the simultaneous introduction of capital controls on foreign exchange (FX) debt inflows and an increase of reserve requirements on domestic bank deposits in Colombia during a strong credit boom, as well as credit registry and bank balance sheet data. Our results suggest that first, an increase in the local monetary policy rate, raising the interest rate spread with the United States, allows more FX-indebted banks to carry trade cheap FX funds with more expensive peso lending, especially toward riskier, opaque firms. Capital controls tax FX debt and break the carry trade. Second, the increase in reserve requirements on domestic deposits directly reduces credit supply, and more so for riskier, opaque firms, rather than enhances the transmission of monetary rates on credit supply. Importantly, different banks finance credit in the boom with either domestic or foreign (FX) financing. Hence, capital controls and domestic macroprudential policy complementarily mitigate the boom and the associated risk-taking through two distinct channels.]]></description><author>Fabiani, Andrea &amp; Lopéz Piñeros, Martha &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Soto, Paul</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16510</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Channel of Wage Rigidity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16499</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Schoefer, Benjamin.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> I propose a financial channel of wage rigidity. In recessions, rather than propping up marginal (new hires') costs of labor, rigid average wages squeeze cash flows, forcing firms to cut hiring due to financial constraints. Indeed, empirical cash flows and profits would turn acyclical if wages were only moderately more procyclical. I study this channel in a search and matching model with financial constraints and rigid wages among incumbent workers, while new hires' wages are flexible. Individually, each feature generates no amplification. By contrast, their interaction can account for much of the empirical labor market fluctuations--breaking the neutrality of incumbents' wages for hiring, and showing that financial amplification of business cycles requires wage rigidity.]]></description><author>Schoefer, Benjamin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16499</guid></item><item><title>Persuasion in Global Games with Application to Stress Testing</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16484</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Inostroza, Nicolas & Pavan, Alessandro.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> We study robust/adversarial information design in global games, with an application to stress testing. We show that the optimal policy coordinates all market participants on the same course of action. Importantly, while it removes any "strategic uncertainty," it preserves heterogeneity in "structural uncertainty" (that is, in beliefs over payoff fundamentals). We identify conditions under which the optimal policy is a "pass/fail" test, show that the optimal test need not be monotone in fundamentals, but also identify conditions under which it is monotone. Finally, we show how the effects of an increase in market uncertainty on the toughness of the optimal stress test depend on the securities issued by the banks.]]></description><author>Inostroza, Nicolas &amp; Pavan, Alessandro</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16484</guid></item><item><title>Mutual Fund Loyalty and ESG Stock Resilience During the COVID-19 Stock Market Crash</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16477</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Albuquerque, Rui & Koskinen, Yrjo & Santioni, Raffaele.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the trading behavior of U.S. actively-managed equity mutual funds during the COVID-19 market crash. We show that Environmental, Social, and Gover- nance (ESG) funds helped to stabilize the market by contributing to the resiliency of ESG stocks, but interestingly non-ESG funds also provided support for ESG stocks. First, ESG funds reduced net sales during the crash, controlling for fund flows. Sec- ond, all funds experiencing inflows helped to stabilize the market during the crash by increasing net purchases, but the behaviour was more pronounced for ESG funds. Third, funds experiencing outflows also played a key role contributing to the relative stability of ESG stocks as both ESG and non-ESG funds sold more aggressively their non-ESG stocks. We are able to uncover these results because we use monthly holdings data from Morningstar, instead of the commonly used quarterly data.]]></description><author>Albuquerque, Rui &amp; Koskinen, Yrjo &amp; Santioni, Raffaele</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16477</guid></item><item><title>Filing Speed, Information Leakage, and Price Formation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16476</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Callen, Jeffrey L & Kaniel, Ron & Segal, Dan.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> This study investigates the price discovery process in equity markets with informed institutional investors. Consistent with extant theories, we show empirically that institutional investors, in contrast to retail investors, trade based on the leaked sign of unanticipated news and then (partially) reverse their trades when the news become public. We also find that the longer the leakage period for institutional investors to exploit, the less informative is the news when it becomes public. These results are robust to controls for firm press releases and news articles and endogeneity concerns.]]></description><author>Callen, Jeffrey L &amp; Kaniel, Ron &amp; Segal, Dan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16476</guid></item><item><title>Selective Default Expectations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16474</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Accominotti, Olivier & Albers, Thilo & Oosterlinck, Kim.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Sovereign governments often discriminate between creditors during debt default episodes. This paper explores how expectations of selective default affect sovereign bond trading and sovereign risk premia based on a historical laboratory: the German external default of the 1930s. We exploit a unique feature of the interwar sovereign bond market: identical German government bonds were traded on different creditor countries' secondary debt markets but investors expected creditors from various countries to be treated differently in case of default. We show that, when creditor countries' secondary debt markets are integrated, selective default expectations are not reflected in bond yields but affect the volume of bonds traded across markets. By contrast, when creditors' debt markets are geographically segmented, a large selective risk premium can be priced in sovereign bonds. This premium accounted for up to half of the total risk premium on German external bonds during the 1930s. We establish that creditor countries' seniority ranks can be explained by their economic power over the debtor government.]]></description><author>Accominotti, Olivier &amp; Albers, Thilo &amp; Oosterlinck, Kim</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16474</guid></item><item><title>Ripple effects of monetary policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16465</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Boissay, Frederic & Garcia-Appendini, Emilia & Ongena, Steven.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Is conventional monetary policy transmitted through the demand for and supply of intermediate goods in an economy? Analyzing unique US data on corporate linkages, we document that downstream and upstream corporate financial health are instrumental for the transmission of monetary policy. Our estimates suggest that contractionary changes in monetary conditions lead to reductions in both the demand and the supply of all financially constrained business partners, thereby creating bottlenecks, which induce the linked firms themselves to curtail their own activities ("ripple effects''). Overall, our estimates suggest that changes in monetary conditions may have a quantitatively larger impact on firms' operations through the changes in demand and supply induced by constrained business partners than through the firms' own financial conditions.]]></description><author>Boissay, Frederic &amp; Garcia-Appendini, Emilia &amp; Ongena, Steven</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16465</guid></item><item><title>Counterparty Choice, Bank Interconnectedness, and Systemic Risk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16458</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Ellul, Andrew & Kim, Dasol.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> We provide evidence on how banks form network connections and endogenous risk-taking in their non-bank counterparty choices in the OTC derivative markets. We use confidential regulatory data from the Capital Assessment and Stress Testing reports that provide counterparty-level data across a wide range of OTC markets for the most systemically important U.S. banks. We show that banks are more likely to either establish or maintain a relationship, and increase their exposures within an existing relationship, with non-bank counterparties that are already heavily connected and exposed to other banks. Banks in such densely-connected networks are more likely to connect with riskier counterparties for their most material exposures. The effects are strongest in the case of (non-bank) financial counterparties. These findings suggest moral hazard behavior in counterparty choices. Finally, we demonstrate that these exposures are strongly linked to systemic risk. Overall, the results suggest a network formation process that amplifies risk propagation through non-bank linkages in opaque financial markets.]]></description><author>Ellul, Andrew &amp; Kim, Dasol</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16458</guid></item><item><title>Mortgage Pricing and Monetary Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16456</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Benetton, Matteo & Gavazza, Alessandro & Surico, Paolo.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> This paper provides novel evidence on lenders' mortgage pricing and how central bank policies affected it. Using the universe of mortgages originated in the U.K., we show that lenders seek to segment the market by offering two-part tariffs composed of interest rates and origination fees, and that during recent periods of unconventional monetary policy, such as the U.K.'s Funding for Lending Scheme, lenders decreased interest rates and increased  origination fees. To understand lenders' pricing strategies and their effects on market equilibrium, we develop and estimate a structural discrete-continuous model of mortgage demand and lender competition in which borrowers may have different sensitivities to rates and fees. We use the estimated model to decompose the effects of unconventional monetary policies on mortgage pricing and lending, and find that central bank policies increased borrower surplus and lender profits. Moreover, although origination fees allow lenders to price discriminate and capture surplus, banning fees would lower borrower surplus and aggregate welfare.]]></description><author>Benetton, Matteo &amp; Gavazza, Alessandro &amp; Surico, Paolo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16456</guid></item><item><title>Ownership Concentration and Performance of Deteriorating Syndicated Loans</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16452</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Giannetti, Mariassunta & Meisenzahl, Ralf.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Regulation and capital constraints may force banks and collateralized loan obligations (CLOs) to sell deteriorating loans, potentially hampering renegotiation and amplifying the initial negative shock to the borrower. We show that banks and CLOs sell downgraded loans to mutual funds and hedge funds. The reallocation of loan shares favors the syndicate's concentration increasing lenders' incentives to renegotiate. However, syndicates remain less concentrated when potential buyers experience financial constraints and subsequently loans are less likely to be amended and more likely to be downgraded even further. Our findings indicate that existing regulations may amplify shocks to credit quality during periods of generalized distress in the financial system.]]></description><author>Giannetti, Mariassunta &amp; Meisenzahl, Ralf</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16452</guid></item><item><title>Financial crises: A survey</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16450</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Sufi, Amir & Taylor, Alan M..</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Financial crises have large deleterious effects on economic activity, and as such have been the focus of a large body of research. This study surveys the existing literature on financial crises, exploring how crises are measured, whether they are predictable, and why they are associated with economic contractions. Historical narrative techniques continue to form the backbone for measuring crises, but there have been exciting developments in using quantitative data as well. Crises are predictable with growth in credit and elevated asset prices playing an especially important role; recent research points convincingly to the importance of behavioral biases in explaining such predictability. The negative consequences of a crisis are due to both the crisis itself but also to the imbalances that precede a crisis. Crises do not occur randomly, and, as a result, an understanding of financial crises requires an investigation into the booms that precede them.]]></description><author>Sufi, Amir &amp; Taylor, Alan M.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16450</guid></item><item><title>Corrective Regulation with Imperfect Instruments</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16448</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Davila, Eduardo & Walther, Ansgar.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the optimal design of second-best corrective regulation, when some agents or activities cannot be perfectly regulated. We show that policy elasticities and Pigouvian wedges are sufficient statistics to characterize the marginal welfare impact of regulatory policies in a large class of environments. We show that the optimal second-best policy is determined by a subset of policy elasticities: leakage elasticities, and characterize the marginal value of relaxing regulatory constraints. We apply our results to scenarios with unregulated agents/activities and with uniform regulation across agents/activities. We illustrate our results in several applications.]]></description><author>Davila, Eduardo &amp; Walther, Ansgar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16448</guid></item><item><title>Dynamics of Asset Demands with Confidence Heterogeneity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16441</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Buss, Adrian & Uppal, Raman & Vilkov, Grigory.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> To understand the dynamics of investor asset demands, we develop a multiperiod general-equilibrium model driven by a single latent variable, differences in beliefs, resulting from heterogeneity in investors' confidence regarding the return dynamics of assets. Consistent with the data, investors' asset holdings are concentrated and display large and persistent heterogeneity in asset demands across investors. Moreover, demand curves are steeper than with homogeneous beliefs. The time-series and cross-sectional variation in assets' realized and expected returns, as well as their volatilities, are driven by the mean and dispersion of latent demand.]]></description><author>Buss, Adrian &amp; Uppal, Raman &amp; Vilkov, Grigory</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16441</guid></item><item><title>Safe asset shortage and collateral reuse</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16439</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Jank, Stephan & Moench, Emanuel & Schneider, Michael.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> The reuse of collateral can support the efficient allocation of assets in the financial
system. Exploiting a novel dataset, we quantify banks' collateral reuse at the security
level. We show that banks substantially increase their reuse of collateral in response
to scarcity induced by central bank asset purchases. Repo rates are less sensitive
to purchase-induced scarcity at low levels of reuse, when the banking system can
easily supply collateral through reuse. Repo rates are more sensitive to scarcity and
more volatile at high levels of reuse, highlighting the trade-off between the shock
absorption and shock amplification effects of collateral reuse.]]></description><author>Jank, Stephan &amp; Moench, Emanuel &amp; Schneider, Michael</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16439</guid></item><item><title>The Bank Liquidity Channel of Financial (In)stability</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16438</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Bosshardt, Joshua & Kakhbod, Ali & Saidi, Farzad.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> We examine the system-wide effects of liquidity regulation on banks' balance sheets. In the general equilibrium model, banks have to hold liquid assets, and choose among illiquid assets varying in the extent to which they are difficult to value before maturity, e.g., structured securities. By improving the liquidity of interbank markets, tighter liquidity requirements induce banks to invest in such complex assets. We evaluate the welfare properties of combining liquidity regulation with other financial-stability policies, and show that it can complement ex-ante policies, such as asset-specific taxes, whereas it can undermine the benefits of ex-post interventions, such as quantitative easing.]]></description><author>Bosshardt, Joshua &amp; Kakhbod, Ali &amp; Saidi, Farzad</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16438</guid></item><item><title>Do we need dealers in OTC markets?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16437</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Hendershott, Terrence & Livdan, Dmitry & Schürhoff, Norman.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> We examine technology enabling dispersed investors to directly trade with each other in over- the-counter markets via the largest electronic trading platform in corporate bonds starting Open Trading (OT) to allow investor-to-investor trading. Over our six year sample OT steadily grew to win 12% of trades on the platform, with 2% being investor-to-investor trading, 3% being dealers trading with new clients, and 7% being new liquidity providers acting like dealers. This suggests that investors in corporate bonds prefer intermediation to direct trade. However, OT can enable new dealers to compete in liquidity provision. OT's steady growth facilitates measuring its effect on investors, dealers, and competition to provide liquidity using an auction model.]]></description><author>Hendershott, Terrence &amp; Livdan, Dmitry &amp; Schürhoff, Norman</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16437</guid></item><item><title>When Is (Performance-Sensitive) Debt Optimal?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16433</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Edmans, Alex.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Existing theories of debt consider a single contractible performance measure ("output"). In reality, many other performance signals are also available. It may seem that debt is no longer optimal; for example, if the signals are sufficiently positive, the agent should receive a payment even if output is low. This paper shows that debt remains the optimal contract under additional signals -- they only affect the face value of debt, but not the form of the contract. We show how the face value should depend on other signals, providing a theory of performance-sensitive debt.]]></description><author>Edmans, Alex</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16433</guid></item><item><title>Can Monetary Policy Create Fiscal Capacity?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16414</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Elenev, Vadim & Landvoigt, Tim & Shultz, Patrick & van Nieuwerburgh, Stijn.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> Governments around the world have gone on a massive fiscal expansion in response to the Covid crisis, increasing government debt to levels not seen in 75 years. How will this debt be repaid?  What role do conventional and unconventional monetary policy play? We  investigate debt sustainability in a New Keynesian model with an intermediary sector, realistic fiscal and monetary policy, endogenous convenience yields, and substantial risk premia. When conventional monetary policy is constrained by the ZLB during an economic crisis, increased government spending and lower tax revenue lead to a large rise in government debt and raise the risk of future tax increases. We find that quantitative easing (QE), forward guidance, and an expansion in government discretionary spending all contribute to lowering debt/GDP ratio and reducing this fiscal risk. A transitory QE policy deployed during a crisis stimulates aggregate demand.]]></description><author>Elenev, Vadim &amp; Landvoigt, Tim &amp; Shultz, Patrick &amp; van Nieuwerburgh, Stijn</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16414</guid></item><item><title>The Risks of Safe Assets</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16407</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Liu, Yang & Schmid, Lukas & Yaron, Amir.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> How much safety and liquidity can the US government provide? Should it accommodate demand for these attributes because high convenience yields in Treasuries lower its borrowing cost? We evaluate a novel fiscal risk channel limiting the government's capacity to issue debt through the lens of a general equilibrium asset pricing model with a rich fiscal sector. Expanding safe asset supply lowers safety premia and improves liquidity in financial markets, but creates  tax and consumption volatility, raising risk premia, credit spreads, and firms' cost of capital. Our  model predicts that this risk channel leads to depressed growth prospects, rising Treasury yields, and elevated consumption risk, for which we find strong empirical evidence. We use our model to quantitatively evaluate current proposals on stimulus and stabilization packages and find that the risk channel is exacerbated in times of fiscal stress. Increasing safe asset supply can thus be risky, and have a significant fiscal cost.]]></description><author>Liu, Yang &amp; Schmid, Lukas &amp; Yaron, Amir</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16407</guid></item><item><title>Financial 'Side Effects' of QE and Conventional Monetary Policy Compared</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16395</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Weale, M & Wieladek, Tomasz.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> We explore the size of financial 'side effects' of QE relative to those of conventional monetary policy for the Euro Area, UK and US. Following previous work for conventional monetary policy we examine the effects on private credit imbalances, financial market risk and asset valuation. We adopt an agnostic Bayesian VAR approach, identifying QE and conventional monetary policy shocks with four different identification schemes and two different measures of unconventional monetary policy. We compare the size of each side effect by the amount of inflation generated by each policy, as all three of these central banks were targeting inflation during this time. The relative size of these effects is at the heart of the current debate about the financial stability and wealth inequality consequences of accommodative monetary policy. While both, conventional monetary policy and QE, generate some financial 'side effects', there is no statistical evidence that the effect of QE on these variables is consistently larger than the effect of conventional monetary policy.]]></description><author>Weale, M &amp; Wieladek, Tomasz</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16395</guid></item><item><title>Pricing Ethics in the Foreign Exchange Market: Environmental, Social and Governance Ratings and Currency Premia</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16392</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Filippou, Ilias & Taylor, Mark.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> We examine the cross-sectional predictive ability of the Refinitiv Environmental, Social and Governance (ESG) score for returns in the foreign exchange market, using ESG scores aggregated at the national level, and find that ESG is a strong negative predictor of currency returns. Intuitively, investors require a premium for financing low-ESG countries while high-ESG countries offer lower returns and provide a hedge in the bad state of the world. We show that ESG is priced in the cross-section of currency returns. We also consider the different components of ESG and show that its predictability is driven by the environmental pillar of the ESG ratings. The profitability of the ESG currency strategy is not driven by the carry trade and is robust to transaction costs.]]></description><author>Filippou, Ilias &amp; Taylor, Mark</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16392</guid></item><item><title>The Correlation Risk Premium: International Evidence</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16389</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Faria, Gonçalo & Kosowski, Robert & Wang, Tianyu.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> In this paper we carry out the first cross-country analysis of the correlation risk premium. We examine the statistical properties of the implied and realized correlation in European equity markets and relate the resulting premium to US equity market correlation risk and a global correlation risk premium. We find evidence of strong co-movement of correlation risk premiums in European and US equity markets.
Our results support the existence of a strong empirical relationship between the global correlation risk premium and international equity market option returns. We document the dependence of the correlation risk premium on macroeconomic policy uncertainty and related 
 variables.]]></description><author>Faria, Gonçalo &amp; Kosowski, Robert &amp; Wang, Tianyu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16389</guid></item><item><title>Propagation and Amplification of Local Productivity Spillovers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16388</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Giroud, Xavier & Lenzu, Simone & Maingi, Quinn & Mueller, Holger M.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> Abstract This paper shows that local productivity spillovers propagate throughout the economy through the plant-level networks of multi-region firms. Using confidential Census plant-level data, we show that large manufacturing plant openings not only raise the productivity of local plants but also of distant plants hundreds of miles away, which belong to multi-region firms that are exposed to the local productivity spillover through one of their plants. To quantify the significance of plant-level networks for the propagation and amplification of local productivity shocks, we develop and estimate a quantitative spatial model in which plants of multi-region firms are linked through shared knowledge. Our model features heterogeneous regions, which interact through goods trade and labor markets, as well as within-location, across-plant heterogeneity in productivity, wages, and employment. Counterfactual exercises show that while knowledge sharing through plant-level networks amplifies the aggregate effects of local productivity shocks, it widens economic disparities between individual workers and regions in the economy.]]></description><author>Giroud, Xavier &amp; Lenzu, Simone &amp; Maingi, Quinn &amp; Mueller, Holger M</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16388</guid></item><item><title>The real explanation of nominal bond-stock puzzles</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16381</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Chernov, Mikhail & Lochstoer, Lars & Song, Dongo.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> We present evidence that the mix of transitory and permanent shocks to consumption is changing over time. We study implications of this finding for asset prices. The uncovered dynamics of consumption implies modestly upward sloping real bond and equity curves, upward sloping nominal yield curve, and sign-switching correlation between equities and bonds consistent with the stylized facts. This is achieved without relying on the nominal channel too much. That is, as in the data, the variation of inflation in the model is under 40% as a fraction of variation in nominal yields.]]></description><author>Chernov, Mikhail &amp; Lochstoer, Lars &amp; Song, Dongo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16381</guid></item><item><title>Who Owns What? A Factor Model for Direct Stockholding</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16378</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Balasubramaniam, Vimal & Campbell, John Y & Ramadorai, Tarun & Ranish, Benjamin.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> We build a cross-sectional factor model for investors' direct stockholdings, by analogy with standard time-series factor models for stock returns. We estimate the model using data from almost 10 million retail accounts in the Indian stock market. We find that stock characteristics such as firm age and share price have strong investor clienteles associated with them. Similarly, account attributes such as account age, account size, and extreme underdiversification (holding a single stock) are associated with particular characteristic preferences. Coheld stocks tend to have higher return covariance, suggestive of the importance of clientele effects in the stock market.]]></description><author>Balasubramaniam, Vimal &amp; Campbell, John Y &amp; Ramadorai, Tarun &amp; Ranish, Benjamin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16378</guid></item><item><title>Bayesian Learning</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16377</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Baley, Isaac & Veldkamp, Laura.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> We survey work using Bayesian learning in macroeconomics, highlighting common themes and new directions. First, we present many of the common types of learning problems agents face -- signal extraction problems -- and trace out their effects on macro aggregates, in different strategic settings. Then we review different perspectives on how agents get their information. Models differ in their motives for information acquisition and the cost of information, or learning technology. Finally, we survey the growing literature on the data economy, where economic activity generates data and the information in data feeds back to affect economic activity.]]></description><author>Baley, Isaac &amp; Veldkamp, Laura</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16377</guid></item><item><title>Diseconomies of Scale in Active Management: Robust Evidence</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16376</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Pástor, Lubos & Stambaugh, Robert F. & Taylor, Lucian & Zhu, Min.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> We take a deeper look at the robustness of evidence presented by Pastor, Stambaugh, and Taylor (2015) and Zhu (2018), who find that an actively managed mutual fund's returns relate negatively to both fund size and the size of the active mutual fund industry. When we apply robust regression methods, we confirm both studies' inferences about scale diseconomies at the fund and industry levels. Moreover, data errors play no role, as both studies' results are insensitive to applying various error screens and using alternative return benchmarks. We reject constant returns to scale even after dropping 25% of the most extreme return observations. Finally, we caution that asymmetric removal of influential observations delivers biased conclusions about diseconomies of scale.]]></description><author>Pástor, Lubos &amp; Stambaugh, Robert F. &amp; Taylor, Lucian &amp; Zhu, Min</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16376</guid></item><item><title>The Global Capital Market Reconsidered</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16375</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Obstfeld, Maurice.</b> <p> <b>July 2021.</b> <p> While the globalization of production has been a prominent target of anti-globalization backlash, globalized finance has seemed to be much less in the public bull's-eye. The blueprint for the postwar international economy agreed at Bretton Woods in 1944 envisioned nothing like today's extensive and fluid global capital market. The demise of the 1946-1973 fixed exchange rate system, however, also brought a progressive dismantling of barriers to international financial flows motivated by special-interest politics, national economic competition, and ideology â?? alongside the benign desire for a more efficient international allocation of capital. Unfortunately, free cross-border financial capital mobility can compromise governments' capacities to attain domestic economic and social goals in several ways. This essay links the dynamics of financial liberalization to the Teflon-like resilience of finance to backlash so far, and suggests that stronger backlash could emerge if national governments fail to enhance multilateral cooperation to manage the financial commons.]]></description><author>Obstfeld, Maurice</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16375</guid></item></channel></rss>