<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Monetary Economics and Fluctuations</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Monetary Economics and Fluctuations</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 10:02:09 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>A toolkit for computing Constrained Optimal Policy Projections (COPPs)</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16865</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Annukka Ristiniemi, Roberto Motto, Falk Mazelis, Oliver de Groot.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> This paper presents a toolkit for generating optimal policy projections. It makes five contributions. First, the toolkit requires a minimal set of inputs: only a baseline projection for target and instrument variables and impulse responses of those variables to policy shocks. Second, it solves optimal policy projections under commitment, limited-time commitment, and discretion. Third, it handles multiple policy instruments. Fourth, it handles multiple constraints on policy instruments such as a lower bound on the policy rate and an upper bound on asset purchases. Fifth, it allows alternative approaches to address the forward guidance puzzle. The toolkit that accompanies this paper is Dynare compatible, which facilitates its use. Examples replicate existing results in the optimal monetary policy literature and illustrate the usefulness of the toolkit for highlighting policy trade-offs. We use the toolkit to analyse US monetary policy at the height of the Great Financial Crisis. Given the Fed's early-2009 baseline macroeconomic projections, we find the Fed's planned use of the policy rate was close to optimal whereas a more aggressive QE program would have been beneficial.]]></description><author>Annukka Ristiniemi, Roberto Motto, Falk Mazelis, Oliver de Groot</author><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16865</guid></item><item><title>Occupational Choice and the Intergenerational Mobility of Welfare</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16854</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Danial Lashkari, Corina Boar.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> Based on responses in the General Social Survey, we construct an index that captures non-monetary qualities of occupations, such as respect, learning, and work hazards, relevant to the well-being of workers. Using the Panel Study of Income Dynamics and National Longitudinal Survey of Youth data, we document that the children of richer US parents are more likely to select into occupations that rank higher in terms of this index. We rationalize this fact by introducing occupational choice with preferences over the intrinsic qualities of occupations into a standard theory of intergenerational mobility. Estimating the model allows us to infer the equivalent monetary compensation each worker receives from the intrinsic qualities of their chosen occupation. Earnings adjusted to reflect this additional compensation show substantially larger persistence of income from parents to children. Our model further predicts that the trends in the composition of labor demand in the US over the past three decades decreased intergenerational persistence, and also led to higher growth in the welfare of the average worker than that implied by observed earnings.]]></description><author>Danial Lashkari, Corina Boar</author><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16854</guid></item><item><title>Fear of Hiking? Monetary Policy and Sovereign Risk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16837</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leopold Zessner-Spitzenberg, Martin Wolf.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Abstract N/A]]></description><author>Leopold Zessner-Spitzenberg, Martin Wolf</author><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16837</guid></item><item><title>Identifying Monetary Policy Shocks Using the Central Bank’s Information Set</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16836</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Isabel Goedl Hanisch, Eric Sims, Rüdiger Bachmann.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We identify monetary policy shocks by exploiting variation in the central bank's
information set. To be specific, we use differences between nowcasts of the output
gap and inflation with final, revised estimates of these series to isolate movements in
the policy rate unrelated to economic conditions. We then compute the effects of a
monetary policy shock on the aggregate economy using local projection methods. We
find that a contractionary monetary policy shock has a limited negative effect on output
but a persistent negative impact on prices. In contrast to alternative identification
approaches, we do not observe a price puzzle when analyzing the period from 1987
to 2008. Further, we validate the identification approach in a simple New Keynesian
model, augmented by the assumption that the central bank observes the ingredients of
the Taylor rule with error.]]></description><author>Isabel Goedl Hanisch, Eric Sims, Rüdiger Bachmann</author><pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16836</guid></item><item><title>One Scheme Fits All: A Central Fiscal Capacity for the EMU Targeting Eurozone, National and Regional Shocks</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16829</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Josha Spronsen, Jacopo Cimadomo, Roel Beetsma.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper proposes a central fiscal capacity for the euro area that generates transfers in response to eurozone, country, and region-specific shocks. The main novelty of this fiscal capacity is that it allows a joint response to these three types of shock within a single scheme, thus policymakers can decide on the stabilisation of one shock versus the others according to political and economic considerations. Our analysis, based on NUTS3 regional data over the last two decades, shows that - with a limited central budget and a low risk of moral hazard - substantial stabilisation could have been achieved in response to the eurozone and regional shocks, while country-specific shocks were less severe and therefore needed less stabilisation. Aggregating the transfers over the three levels, they are of the order of magnitude of the EU's Recovery and Resilience Facility.]]></description><author>Josha Spronsen, Jacopo Cimadomo, Roel Beetsma</author><pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16829</guid></item><item><title>The Case for a Positive Euro Area Inflation Target: Evidence form France, Germany and Italy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16828</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Henning Weber, Sergio Santoro, Erwan Gautier, Klaus Adam.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Using the micro price data underlying the Harmonized Index of Consumer Prices, we estimate relative price trends over the product
life cycle in France, Germany and Italy. We show that minimizing the welfare consequences of relative price distortions in the presence
of these trends requires targeting a significantly positive inflation rate:the steady-state inflation rate jointly maximizing welfare in all three
countries ranges between 1.1%-1.7%. The optimal target range for individual countries is 1.1%-2.1% in France, 1.2%-2.0% in Germany
and 0.8%-1.0% in Italy. Differences across countries emerge due to systematic differences in the strength of relative price trends. The
welfare costs associated with targeting an inflation rate of zero in the Euro Area, as suggested by standard monetary models without relative
price trends, amount to 4.5% of consumption in present-value terms.]]></description><author>Henning Weber, Sergio Santoro, Erwan Gautier, Klaus Adam</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16828</guid></item><item><title>Monetary Policy and Endogenous Financial Crises</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16825</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Cristina Manea, Jordi Galí, Fabrice Collard, Frederic Boissay.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study whether a central bank should deviate from its objective of price stability to promote financial stability. We tackle this question within a textbook New Keynesian model augmented with capital accumulation and microfounded endogenous financial crises. We compare several interest rate rules, under which the central bank responds more or less forcefully to inflation and aggregate output. Our main findings are threefold. First, monetary policy affects the probability of a crisis both in the short run (through aggregate demand) and in the medium run (through savings and capital accumulation). Second, a central bank can both reduce the probability of a crisis and increase welfare by departing from strict inflation targeting and responding systematically to fluctuations in output. Third, financial crises may occur after a long period of unexpectedly loose monetary policy as the central bank abruptly reverses course.]]></description><author>Cristina Manea, Jordi Galí, Fabrice Collard, Frederic Boissay</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16825</guid></item><item><title>Idiosyncratic Shocks and Aggregate Fluctuations in an Emerging Market</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16824</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Damiano Sandri, Emiliano Luttini, Francesco Grigoli.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper provides the first assessment of the contribution of idiosyncratic shocks to aggregate fluctuations in an emerging market using confidential data on the universe of Chilean firms. We find that idiosyncratic shocks account for more than 40 percent of the volatility of aggregate sales. Although quite large, this contribution is smaller than documented in previous studies based on advanced economies, despite a higher degree of market concentration in Chile. We show that this finding is explained by larger firms being less volatile and by weaker propagation effects across Chilean firms.]]></description><author>Damiano Sandri, Emiliano Luttini, Francesco Grigoli</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16824</guid></item><item><title>The Unattractiveness of Indeterminate Dynamic Equilibria</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16822</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Ellison, Paul Beaudry, Julian Ashwin.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Macroeconomic forces that generate multiple equilibria often support locally-indeterminate dynamic equilibria in which a continuum of perfect foresight paths converge towards the same steady state. The set of rational expectations equilibria (REE) in such environments can be very large, although the relevance of many of them has been questioned on the basis that they may not be learnable. In this paper we document the existence of a learnable REE in such situations. However, we show that the dynamics of this learnable REE do not resemble perturbations around any of the convergent perfect foresight paths. Instead, the learnable REE treats the locally-indeterminate steady state as unstable, in contrast to it resembling a stable attractor under perfect foresight.]]></description><author>Martin Ellison, Paul Beaudry, Julian Ashwin</author><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16822</guid></item><item><title>Monetary Policy Communication: Perspectives from Former Policy Makers at the ECB</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16816</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gillian Phelan, Danielle Kedan, Sarah Holton, Michael Ehrmann.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper reports the results of a survey of former members of the Governing Council of the European Central Bank, which sought their views on monetary policy communication practices, the related challenges and the road ahead. Pronounced differences across the respondent groups are rare, suggesting that there is broad consensus on the various issues. Respondents view enhancing credibility and trust as the most important objective of central bank communication. They judge communication with financial markets and experts as extremely important and adequate, but see substantial room for improvement in the communication with the general public. The central bank objective is widely seen as the most important topic for monetary policy communication, and several respondents perceived a need for clarification of the ECB's inflation aim, citing the ambiguity of the "below, but close to, 2%" formulation that was in place at the time of the survey.]]></description><author>Gillian Phelan, Danielle Kedan, Sarah Holton, Michael Ehrmann</author><pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16816</guid></item><item><title>A Note on Temporary Supply Shocks with Aggregate Demand Inertia</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16814</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ricardo Caballero, Alp Simsek.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study optimal monetary policy during temporary supply contractions, using a simple New Keynesian model with aggregate demand inertia and a Zero-Lower-Bound (ZLB) constraint. In this setting, it is optimal to run the economy hot during the temporary supply contraction. This result follows from an intertemporal breakdown of the "divine coincidence" of monetary policy:  a positive output gap during the low-supply phase shrinks the negative output gap that is expected to emerge once aggregate supply recovers and the ZLB binds. However, our analysis does not suggest that monetary policy should remain loose throughout the low-supply phase. Since aggregate demand has inertia, the central bank should frontload interest rate cuts and then quickly normalize the interest rate once it succeeds in building aggregate demand momentum.]]></description><author>Ricardo Caballero, Alp Simsek</author><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16814</guid></item><item><title>Rational Inattention and the Business Cycle Effects of Productivity and News Shocks</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16812</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Mirko Wiederholt, Bartosz Mackowiak.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We solve a real business cycle model with rational inattention (an RI-RBC model). In the standard model, anticipated fluctuations in productivity fail to cause business cycle comovement. In response to news about higher future productivity, consumption rises but employment and investment fall. Introducing rational inattention helps produce comovement. Agents choose an optimal signal about the state of the economy. The optimal signal turns out to confound current with expected future productivity. Labor and investment demand rise after a news shock, causing an output expansion. Rational inattention also improves the propagation of a standard productivity shock, by inducing persistence.]]></description><author>Mirko Wiederholt, Bartosz Mackowiak</author><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16812</guid></item><item><title>Skewness and Time-Varying Second Moments in a Nonlinear Production Network: Theory and Evidence</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16804</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andrea Vedolin, Alireza Tahbaz-Salehi, Ian Dew-Becker.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies asymmetry in economic activity over the business cycle. It develops a tractable multisector model of the economy in which complementarity across inputs causes aggregate activity to be left skewed with countercyclical volatility. We then examine implications of the model regarding the time-series skewness of activity at the sector level, cyclicality of dispersion and skewness across sectors, and the conditional covariances of sector growth rates, finding support for each in the data. The empirical skewness of employment growth, industrial production growth, and stock returns increases with the level of aggregation, which is consistent with the model's implication that it is the nonlinearity in the production structure of the economy that generates the skewness. Other prominent models of asymmetry are not able to simultaneously match the range of empirical facts that the production network model can.]]></description><author>Andrea Vedolin, Alireza Tahbaz-Salehi, Ian Dew-Becker</author><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16804</guid></item><item><title>Corporate Legacy Debt, Inflation, and the Efficacy of Monetary Policy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16799</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Xuan Wang, Dimitrios P. Tsomocos, M. Udara Peiris, Charles A. E. Goodhart.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic has coincided with a rapid increase in indebtedness. Although the rise in public debt and its policy implications have received much attention recently, the rise in corporate debt has received less so. We argue that high levels of corporate debt may impede the transmission mechanism of monetary policy and make it less effective in controlling inflation. In an environment with working capital financing requirements, when firms' indebtedness is sufficiently high, the income effect of higher nominal interest rates offsets or even dominates its usual negative substitution effect on aggregate demand and is quantitatively important. This mechanism is independent of standard financial and nominal frictions and enhances the trade-off between inflation and output stabilisation.]]></description><author>Xuan Wang, Dimitrios P. Tsomocos, M. Udara Peiris, Charles A. E. Goodhart</author><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16799</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Origins of Non-Fundamental Risk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16793</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sanjay R. Singh, Keshav Dogra, Sushant Acharya.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We formalize the idea that the financial sector can be a source of non-fundamental risk. Households' desire to hedge against price volatility can generate price volatility in equilibrium, even absent fundamental risk. Fearing that asset prices may fall, risk-averse households demand safe assets from leveraged intermediaries, whose issuance of safe assets exposes the economy to self-fulfilling fire sales. Policy can eliminate non-fundamental risk by (i) increasing the supply of publicly backed safe assets, through issuing government debt or bailing out intermediaries, or (ii) reducing the demand for safe assets, through social insurance or by acting as a market maker of last resort.]]></description><author>Sanjay R. Singh, Keshav Dogra, Sushant Acharya</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16793</guid></item><item><title>Would Households Understand Average Inflation Targeting?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16786</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Guido Schultefrankenfeld, Lora Pavlova, Emanuel Moench, Mathias Hoffmann.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Yes, they would. In a randomized control trial, we provide groups of respondents from the Bundesbank Online Panel Households with information about a hypothetical alternative ECB monetary policy regime akin to the Federal Reserve's flexible average inflation targeting
(AIT). Inflation expectations significantly increase for the treated individuals. When provided with additional assumptions about current inflation, individuals update their expected inflation path in line with the central banks' intentions. Individuals with a high trust in the ECB's ability to achieve price stability adjust their inflation expectations particularly strongly. We assess the economic significance of our findings by comparing two model economies under different monetary policy strategies, calibrated to match the difference in medium-term inflation expectations from our survey results. Inflation is substantially less volatile and the frequency of hitting the lower bound of interest rates considerably reduced
under AIT.]]></description><author>Guido Schultefrankenfeld, Lora Pavlova, Emanuel Moench, Mathias Hoffmann</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16786</guid></item><item><title>News and uncertainty about COVID-19: Survey evidence and short-run economic impact</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16766</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Raphael Schoenle, Gernot Müller, Keith Kuester, Alexander Dietrich.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> A tailor-made survey documents consumer perceptions of the U.S.~economy's response to a large shock: the advent of the COVID-19 pandemic.  The survey ran at a daily frequency between March 2020 and July 2021. Consumer perceptions regarding output and inflation react rapidly. Uncertainty is pervasive. A business-cycle model calibrated to the consumer views provides an interpretation. The rise in household uncertainty amplifies the pandemic recession by a factor of three. Different perceptions about monetary policy can explain why consumers and professional forecasters agree on the recessionary impact, but have sharply divergent views about inflation.]]></description><author>Raphael Schoenle, Gernot Müller, Keith Kuester, Alexander Dietrich</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16766</guid></item><item><title>Uncertainty and Information Acquisition: Evidence from Firms and Households</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16765</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Johannes Wohlfart, Samad Sarferaz, Christopher Roth, Heiner Mikosch.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We leverage the small open economy Switzerland as a testing ground for basic premises
of macroeconomic models of endogenous information acquisition, using tailored surveys
of firms and households. First, we show that firms perceive a greater exposure
to exchange rate movements than households, which is reflected in higher levels of
information acquisition and less dispersed beliefs about past and future exchange
rate realizations. Similarly, within the two samples, acquisition of exchange rate information
strongly increases in various proxies for stake size. Second, households
who perceive higher costs of acquiring or processing information acquire less information.
Finally, an exogenous increase in the perceived uncertainty of the exchange
rate increases firms' demand for a report about exchange rate developments, but not
households'. Our findings inform the modeling of information frictions in macroeconomics.]]></description><author>Johannes Wohlfart, Samad Sarferaz, Christopher Roth, Heiner Mikosch</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16765</guid></item><item><title>Macroeconomic Dynamics with Rigid Wage Contracts</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16764</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Erik Öberg, Per Krusell, Karl Harmenberg, Tobias Broer.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Abstract N/A]]></description><author>Erik Öberg, Per Krusell, Karl Harmenberg, Tobias Broer</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16764</guid></item><item><title>Real-Time Forecasting with a (Standard) Mixed-Frequency VAR During a Pandemic</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16760</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Dongho Song, Frank Schorfheide.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> We resuscitated the mixed-frequency vector autoregression (MF-VAR) developed in Schorfheide and Song (2015, JBES) to generate macroeconomic forecasts for the U.S. during the COVID-19 pandemic in real time. The model combines eleven time series observed at two frequencies: quarterly and monthly. We deliberately did not modify the model specification in view of the COVID-19 outbreak, except for the exclusion of crisis observations from the estimation sample. We compare the MF-VAR forecasts to the median forecast from the Survey of Professional Forecasters (SPF). While the MF-VAR performed poorly during 2020:Q2, subsequent forecasts were at par with the SPF forecasts. We show that excluding a few months of extreme observations is a promising way of handling VAR estimation going forward, as an alternative of a sophisticated modeling of outliers.]]></description><author>Dongho Song, Frank Schorfheide</author><pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16760</guid></item><item><title>Inflation Narratives</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16758</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Johannes Wohlfart, Christopher Roth, Ingar Haaland, Peter Andre.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> We provide evidence on the stories that people tell to explain a historically notable rise in inflation using samples of experts, U.S. households, and managers. We document substantial heterogeneity in narratives about the drivers of higher inflation rates. Experts put more emphasis on demand-side factors, such as fiscal and monetary policy, and on supply chain disruptions. Other supply-side factors, such as labor shortages or increased energy costs, are equally prominent across samples. Households and managers are more likely to tell generic stories related
to the pandemic or mismanagement by the government. We also find that households and managers expect the increase in inflation to be more persistent than experts. Moreover, narratives about the drivers of the inflation increase are strongly correlated with beliefs about its persistence. Our findings have implications for understanding macroeconomic expectation formation.]]></description><author>Johannes Wohlfart, Christopher Roth, Ingar Haaland, Peter Andre</author><pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16758</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Multipliers in the COVID19 Recession</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16754</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel P Murphy, Peter McCrory, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Alan J Auerbach.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> In response to the record-breaking COVID19 recession, many governments have adopted unprecedented fiscal stimuli. While countercyclical fiscal policy is effective in fighting conventional recessions, little is known about the effectiveness of fiscal policy in the current environment with widespread shelter-in-place ("lockdown") policies and the associated considerable limits on economic activity. Using detailed regional variation in economic conditions, lockdown policies, and U.S. government spending, we document that the effects of government spending were stronger during the peak of the pandemic recession, but only in cities that were not subject to strong stay-at-home orders. We examine mechanisms that can account for our evidence and place our findings in the context of other recent evidence from microdata.]]></description><author>Daniel P Murphy, Peter McCrory, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Alan J Auerbach</author><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16754</guid></item><item><title>Distributed Ledgers and the Governance of Money</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16752</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Cyril Monnet, Hyun Song Shin, Raphael Auer.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> Blockchain technology breathes new life into the classical analysis of money as a substitute for a ledger of all past transactions. While it involves updating the ledger through a decentralized consensus on the unique truth, the robustness of the equilibrium that supports this consensus depends on who has access to the ledger and how it can be updated. To find the optimal solution, Buterin's "scalability trilemma" needs to be addressed, so that a workable balance can be found between decentralization, security (i.e. a robust consensus), and scale (the efficient volume of transactions). Using a global game analysis of an exchange economy with credit, we solve for the optimal ledger design that balances the three objectives of this trilemma. We characterize the optimal number of validators, supermajority threshold, fees and transaction size. When intertemporal incentives are strong, a centralized ledger is always optimal. Otherwise, decentralization may be optimal, and validators need to be selected from the set of users of the system.]]></description><author>Cyril Monnet, Hyun Song Shin, Raphael Auer</author><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16752</guid></item><item><title>Sovereign Risk and Financial Risk</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16750</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Egon Zakrajšek, Vivian Yue, Bin Wei, Simon Gilchrist.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we study the interplay between sovereign risk and global financial risk. We show that a substantial portion of the comovement among sovereign spreads is accounted for by changes in global financial risk. We construct bond-level sovereign spreads for dollar-denominated bonds issued by over 50 countries from 1995 to 2020 and use various indicators to measure global financial risk. Through panel regressions and local projection analysis, we find that an increase in global financial risk causes a large and persistent widening of sovereign bond spreads. These effect are strongest when measuring global risk using the excess bond premium -- a measure of the risk-bearing
capacity of U.S. financial intermediaries. The spillover effects of global financial risk are more pronounced for speculative-grade sovereign bonds.]]></description><author>Egon Zakrajšek, Vivian Yue, Bin Wei, Simon Gilchrist</author><pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16750</guid></item></channel></rss>