<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for CEPR Labour Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for CEPR Labour Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 17:56:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Herding, Warfare, and A Culture of Honor: Global Evidence</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16569</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> According to the widely known 'culture of honor'
hypothesis from social psychology, traditional herding practices
are believed to have generated a value system that is conducive to
revenge-taking and violence. We test this idea at a global scale using
a combination of ethnographic records, historical folklore information,
global data on contemporary conflict events, and large-scale surveys.
The data show systematic links between traditional herding practices
and a culture of honor. First, the culture of pre-industrial societies
that relied on animal herding emphasizes violence, punishment, and
revenge-taking. Second, contemporary ethnolinguistic groups that
historically subsisted more strongly on herding have more frequent
and severe conflict today. Third, the contemporary descendants of
herders report being more willing to take revenge and punish unfair
behavior in the globally representative Global Preferences Survey.
In all, the evidence supports the idea that this form of economic
subsistence generated a functional psychology that has persisted until
today and plays a role in shaping conflict across the globe.]]></description><author>Cao, Yiming &amp; Enke, Benjamin &amp; Falk, Armin &amp; Giuliano, Paola &amp; Nunn, Nathan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16569</guid></item><item><title>Less School (Costs), More (Female) Education? Lessons from Egypt Reducing Years of Compulsory Schooling</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16568</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Exploiting a unique policy reform in Egypt that reduced the number of years of compulsory schooling, we show that it unexpectedly increased education attainment. This impact is almost entirely driven by girls from more disadvantaged households staying in school longer. Treated women later experienced important positive improvements in labor market opportunity and marriage quality, as measured by bride price received and household bargaining power. We reject changes in school quality as a driving mechanism and attribute the increased investment in girl's human capitcal to adjustments by credit-constrained families when school costs dropped combined with strongly non-linear returns to female education.]]></description><author>Elsayed, Ahmed &amp; Marie, Olivier</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16568</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Gap in Earnings Losses after Job Displacement</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16551</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Existing research has shown that job displacement leads to large and persistent earnings losses for men, but evidence for women is scarce. Using administrative data from Germany, we apply an event study design in combination with propensity score matching and a reweighting technique to directly compare men and women who are displaced from similar jobs and firms. Our results show that after a mass layoff, women's earnings losses are about 35% higher than men's, with the gap persisting five years after job displacement. This is partly explained by a higher propensity of women to take up part-time or marginal employment following job loss, but even full-time wage losses are almost 50% (or 5 percentage points) higher for women than for men. We then show that on the household level there is no evidence of an added worker effect, independent of the gender of the job loser. Finally, we document that parenthood magnifies the gender gap sharply: while fathers of young children have smaller earnings losses than men in general, mothers of young children have much larger earnings losses than other women.]]></description><author>Illing, Hannah &amp; Schmieder, Johannes &amp; Trenkle, Simon</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16551</guid></item><item><title>Student Employment and Education: A Meta-Analysis</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16550</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Educational outcomes have many determinants, but one that most young people can readily control is choosing whether to work while in school. Sixty-nine studies have estimated the effect, but results vary from large negative to positive estimates. We show that the results are systematically driven by context, publication bias, and treatment of endogeneity. Studies ignoring endogeneity suffer from an upward bias, which is almost fully compensated by publication selection in favor of negative estimates. Net of the biases, the literature suggests a negative but economically inconsequential mean effect. The effect is more negative for high-intensity employment and educational outcomes measured as decisions to dropout, but it is positive in Germany. To derive these results we collect 861 previously reported estimates together with 32 variables reflecting estimation context, use recently developed nonlinear techniques to correct for publication bias, and employ Bayesian and frequentist model averaging to assign a pattern to the heterogeneity in the literature.]]></description><author>Havranek, Tomas &amp; Irsova, Zuzana &amp; Kroupova, Katerina</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16550</guid></item><item><title>Monetary Policy, Labor Income Redistribution and the Credit Channel: Evidence from Matched Employer-Employee and Credit Registers</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16549</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper documents the redistributive effects of monetary policy on labor market outcomes via
the credit channel. For identification, we exploit matched administrative datasets in Portugal
- employee-employer and credit registers - and monetary policy since the Eurozone creation
in 1999. We find that softer monetary policy improves worker labor market outcomes (wages,
hours worked and firm employment) more in small and young firms, which are more financially
constrained. Within small and young firms, the wage effects accrue to incumbent workers,
in line with the back-loaded wage mechanism. Consistent with the capital-skill complementarity
mechanism, we document an increase in skill premium and show that financially constrained
firms increase both physical and human capital investment by most. Our findings uncover
a central role for both the firm-balance sheet and the bank lending channels of the monetary
policy transmission to labor income inequality, with state-dependent effects that are substantially
stronger during crisis times. Importantly, we do not find any redistributive effects for firms
without bank credit.]]></description><author>Jasova, Martina &amp; Mendicino, Caterina &amp; Panetti, Ettore &amp; Peydró, José Luis &amp; Supera, Dominik</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16549</guid></item><item><title>The Effect of Wealth on Worker Productivity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16547</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We propose a theory that analyzes how a workers' asset holdings affect their job productivity. In a labor market with uninsurable risk, workers choose to direct their job search trading off productivity and wages against unemployment risk. Workers with low asset holdings have a precautionary job search motive, they direct their search to low productivity jobs because those offer a low risk at the cost of low productivity and a low wage. Our main theoretical contribution shows that the presence of consumption smoothing can reconcile the directed search model with negative duration-dependence on wages, a robust empirical regularity that the canonical directed search model cannot rationalize. We calibrate the infinite horizon economy and find this mechanism to be quantitatively important. We evaluate a tax financed unemployment insurance (UI) scheme and analyze how it affects welfare. Aggregate welfare is inverted U-shaped in benefits: the insurance effect UI dominates the incentive effects for low levels of benefits and vice versa for high benefits. In addition, when UI increases, total production falls in the economy while worker productivity increases. Finally, we compare a one-off severance payment with per-period benefits and find th]]></description><author>Eeckhout, Jan &amp; Sepahsalari, Alireza</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16547</guid></item><item><title>Screening and Signaling Non-Cognitive Skills: Experimental Evidence from Uganda</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16546</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study how employers and job-seekers respond to credible information on skills that are difficult to observe, and how this affects matching in the labor market. We experimentally vary whether certificates on workers' non-cognitive skills are disclosed to both sides of the market during job interviews between young workers and small firms in Uganda. The certificates cause workers to increase their labor market expectations, while high-ability managers revise their assessments of the workers' skills upwards. The reaction in terms of beliefs leads to an increase in positive assortative matching and to higher earnings for workers, conditional on employment.]]></description><author>Bassi, Vittorio &amp; Nansamba, Aisha</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16546</guid></item><item><title>The Cognitive Load of Financing Constraints: Evidence from Large Scale Wage Surveys</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16541</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> In this paper, we take advantage of the implicit cognitive exercise available in standard Labor Force Surveys in order to propose a new indicator of financing constraints that is based on the cognitive load they generate (Mullainathan and Shafir, 2013). Survey respondants are requested to report their monthly wages, which we compare to their administrative, fiscal counterparts. We propose a well defined index of worker-level uncertainty which filters out their potential rounding behavior and reporting biases. We estimate it with (unsupervised) ML/EM techniques and obtain that workers tend to perceive their own wages with a degree of uncertainty of around 10%. Through the lens of a simple rational signal extraction model, this amounts to estimates of workers' attention ranging between 30% and 84% depending on their wage level, education, tenure and gender. Most importantly, we show that the attention of the lowest paid 30% of workers is cyclical and increases steadily (by 17 percentage points) in the ten days preceding payday, before dropping instantaneously at that date, which through the lens of a simple model is indicative of end-of-month financing (liquidity) constraints. This pattern furthermore reveals that the cognitive cost induced by these financing constraints arises from not too concave (or convex) costs of achieving high levels of attention, and convex costs of maintaining it over time.]]></description><author>Berson, Clémence &amp; Lardeux, Raphael &amp; Lelarge, Claire</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16541</guid></item><item><title>Improving Workplace Climate in Large Corporations: A Clustered Randomized Intervention</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16532</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We evaluate the impact of a program aiming at improving the workplace climate in corporations. The program is implemented via a clustered randomized design and evaluated with respect to the prevalence of support networks, antisocial behavior, perceived relational atmosphere, and turnover rate. We find that professionals in treated corporations are less inclined to engage in toxic competition, exhibit higher reciprocity toward each other, report higher workplace satisfaction and a more collegial atmosphere. Treated firms have fewer socially isolated individuals and a lower employee turnover. The program's success in improving leader-subordinate relationships emerges as a likely mechanism to explain these results.]]></description><author>Alan, Sule &amp; Corekcioglu, Gozde &amp; Sutter, Matthias</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16532</guid></item><item><title>The Affordable Care Act After a Decade: Its Impact on the Labor Market and the Macro Economy</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16530</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The Affordable Care Act (ACA) is one of the most important reforms of the US health insurance system since the introduction of Medicare. Since employment is a main source of health insurance for the working age population in the United States, this sweeping health insurance reform also has important implications for the labor market and the macro economy. In this paper, we survey the prototype models that are used in the macro and labor literature, extended to integrate health and health insurance, to study the short- and long-run consequences of the ACA. We also suggest open areas for future research.]]></description><author>Fang, Hanming &amp; Krueger, Dirk</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16530</guid></item><item><title>Perceptions of Racial Gaps, their Causes, and Ways to Reduce Them</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16529</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Using new large-scale survey and experimental data, we investigate how respondents perceive racial inequities between Black and white Americans, what they believe causes them, and what interventions, if any, they think should be implemented to reduce them. We intentionally oversample Black respondents, cover many US cities, and survey both adults and young people of ages 13 through 17. In the experimental parts, we consider the causal impact of information on racial inequities (such as the evolution of the Black-white earnings gap or the differences in mobility for Black and white children) and explanations for these inequities (i.e., the deep-seated roots and long-lasting consequences of systemic racism) on respondents' views. Although there is heterogeneity in how respondents perceive the magnitude of current racial gaps in economic conditions and opportunities, the biggest discrepancies are in how they explain them. There is a stark partisan gap among white respondents, particularly in the perceived causes of racial inequities and what should be done about them. White Democrats and Black respondents are much more likely to attribute racial inequities to adverse past and present circumstances and want to act on them with race-targeted and general redistribution policies. White Republicans are more likely to attribute racial gaps to individual actions. These views are already deeply entrenched in teenagers, based on their race and their parents' political affiliation. A policy
decomposition shows that the perceived causes of racial inequities correlate most strongly with support for race-targeted or general redistribution policies, a finding confirmed by the experimental results.]]></description><author>Ferroni, Matteo &amp; Stantcheva, Stefanie</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16529</guid></item><item><title>Harms of AI</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16524</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This essay discusses several potential economic, political and social costs of the current path of AI technologies. I argue that if AI continues to be deployed along its current trajectory and remains unregulated, it may produce various social, economic and political harms. These include: damaging competition, consumer privacy and consumer choice; excessively automating work, fueling inequality, inefficiently pushing down wages, and failing to improve worker productivity; and damaging political discourse, democracy's most fundamental lifeblood. Although there is no conclusive evidence suggesting that these costs are imminent or substantial, it may be useful to understand them before they are fully realized and become harder or even impossible to reverse, precisely because of AI's promising and wide-reaching potential. I also suggest that these costs are not inherent to the nature of AI technologies, but are related to how they are being used and developed at the moment - to empower corporations and governments against workers and citizens. As a result, efforts to limit and reverse these costs may need to rely on regulation and policies to redirect AI research. Attempts to contain them
just by promoting competition may be insufficient.]]></description><author>Acemoglu, Daron</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16524</guid></item><item><title>Behavioral Barriers and the Socioeconomic Gap in Child Care Enrollment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16501</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Children with lower socioeconomic status (SES) tend to benefit more from early child care, but are substantially less likely to be enrolled. We study whether reducing behavioral barriers in the application process increases enrollment in child care for lower-SES children. In our RCT in Germany with highly subsidized child care (n > 600), treated families receive application information and personal assistance for applications. For lower-SES families, the treatment increases child care application rates by 21 pp and enrollment rates by 16 pp. Higher-SES families are not affected by the treatment. Thus, alleviating behavioral barriers closes half of the SES gap in early child care enrollment.]]></description><author>Hermes, Henning &amp; Lergetporer, Philipp &amp; Peter, Frauke &amp; Wiederhold, Simon</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16501</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Channel of Wage Rigidity</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16499</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> I propose a financial channel of wage rigidity. In recessions, rather than propping up marginal (new hires') costs of labor, rigid average wages squeeze cash flows, forcing firms to cut hiring due to financial constraints. Indeed, empirical cash flows and profits would turn acyclical if wages were only moderately more procyclical. I study this channel in a search and matching model with financial constraints and rigid wages among incumbent workers, while new hires' wages are flexible. Individually, each feature generates no amplification. By contrast, their interaction can account for much of the empirical labor market fluctuations--breaking the neutrality of incumbents' wages for hiring, and showing that financial amplification of business cycles requires wage rigidity.]]></description><author>Schoefer, Benjamin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16499</guid></item><item><title>Perceived Inequality and Preferences for Redistribution Among High Earners: Do Reference Groups Matter?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16489</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Understanding attitudes towards inequality among the ``working rich" matters for any policy aimed at increasing the level of redistribution in society. We investigate this question using a unique sample of nearly 1,000 graduates from a highly ranked MBA program and a representative sample of Americans. We first show that high-earning MBAs are far more likely to know their rank in the income distribution. We then explore whether and how comparisons with peers or others (i.e. reference groups) shape their preferences for redistribution. Asking them to rank within their family, colleagues or classmates leads to an average 18\% drop in the income share allocated to the richest 1\% but has no discernible effect on their taxation preferences. We discuss the respective contribution of the comparative and normative functions of reference groups as potential mechanisms.]]></description><author>Bellet, Clement &amp; Glover, Dylan &amp; Stabile, Mark</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16489</guid></item><item><title>Stable marriage, household consumption and unobserved match quality</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16483</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We present a methodology for the structural empirical analysis of household consumption and time use behaviour under marital stability. Our approach is of the revealed preference type and non-parametric, meaning that it does not require a prior functional specification of individual utilities. Without making use of the transferable utility assumption, but still allowing for monetary transfers, our method can identify individuals' unobserved match qualities and quantify them in money metric terms. We can include both preference factors, affecting individuals' preferences over private and public goods, and match quality factors, driving differences in unobserved match quality. We demonstrate the practical usefulness of our methodology through an application to the Belgian MEqIn data. Our results reveal intuitive patterns of unobserved match quality that allow us to rationalise both the observed matches and the within-household allocations of time and money.]]></description><author>Browning, Martin &amp; Cherchye, Laurens &amp; De Rock, Bram &amp; Demuynck, Thomas &amp; Vermeulen, Frederic</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16483</guid></item><item><title>Feed the children</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16482</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> To understand the household decision-making process regarding food expenditures for children in poor households in Nairobi, we conduct an experiment with 424 married couples. In the experiment, the spouses (individually and jointly) allocated money between themselves and nutritious meals for one of their children. First, we find strong empirical support for individual rationality and cooperative behavior. Second, our results suggest that women do not have stronger preferences for children's meals than men. Third, the spouses' respective bargaining positions derived from consumption patterns strongly correlate with more traditional indicators. Finally, we document significant heterogeneity both between individuals and intra-household decision processes.]]></description><author>Cherchye, Laurens &amp; Chiappori, Pierre-André &amp; De Rock, Bram &amp; Ringdal, Charlotte &amp; Vermeulen, Frederic</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16482</guid></item><item><title>Play for the Rich and Work for the Poor? The Optimal Distribution of Saving and Work in the Heterogeneous Agents Neoclassical Growth Model</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16479</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> In an economy with un-insurable idiosyncratic labor income risk, how should saving and work hours be distributed across income and wealth? To answer this question, we study a planner who cannot complete asset markets, but dictates how much individuals must work and save. With a U.S. calibration, the planner raises total savings but not hours, driving up aggregate wages which re-distributes income toward the consumption-poor. Across the distribution, the productive (high wage earners) should save more; the wealthy should work more; the poor should keep their work hours unchanged and take advantage of the indirect transfers from higher wages.]]></description><author>Shanker, Akshay &amp; Wolf, Martin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16479</guid></item><item><title>The Elusive Explanation for the Declining Labor Share</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16473</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> A vast literature seeks to measure and explain the apparent decline in the labor share in national income that has occurred in recent times in the United States and elsewhere. The culprits include technological change, increased globalization and the rise of China, the enhanced exercise of market power by large firms in concentrated product markets, the decline in unionization rates and the erosion in the bargaining power of workers in labor markets, and the changing composition of the workforce due to a slowdown in population growth and a rise in educational attainment. We review this literature, with special emphasis on the pitfalls associated with using cross-sectional data to assess this phenomenon and the reasons why the body of papers collectively explains the phenomenon many times over.]]></description><author>Grossman, Gene M. &amp; Oberfield, Ezra</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16473</guid></item><item><title>Local Shocks and Internal Migration: The Disparate Effects of Robots and Chinese Imports in the US</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16460</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Migration has long been considered one of the key mechanisms through which labor markets adjust to economic shocks. In this paper, we analyze the migration response of American workers to two of the most important shocks that hit US manufacturing since the late 1990s - Chinese import competition and the introduction of industrial robots. Exploiting plausibly exogenous variation in exposure across US local labor markets over time, we show that robots caused a sizable reduction in population size, while Chinese imports did not. We rationalize these results in two steps. First, we provide evidence that negative employment spillovers outside manufacturing, caused by robots but not by Chinese imports, are an important mechanism for the different migration responses triggered by the two shocks. Next, we present a model where workers are geographically mobile and compete with either machines or foreign labor in the completion of tasks. The model highlights that two key dimensions along which the shocks differ - the cost savings they provide and the degree of complementarity between directly and indirectly exposed industries - can explain their disparate employment effects outside manufacturing and, in turn, the differential migration response.]]></description><author>Faber, Marius &amp; Sarto, Andres &amp; Tabellini, Marco</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16460</guid></item><item><title>Internal Labor Markets: A Worker Flow Approach</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16434</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper develops a new method to study how workers' career and wage profiles are shaped by internal labor markets (ILM) and job hierarchies in firms. Our paper tackles the conceptual challenge of organizing jobs within firms into hierarchy levels by proposing a data-driven ranking method based on observed worker flows between occupations within firms. We apply our method to linked employer-employee data from Norway that records fine-grained occupational codes and tracks contract changes within firms. Our findings confirm existing evidence that is primarily based on case studies for single firms. We expand on this by documenting substantial heterogeneity in the structure and hierarchy of ILMs across a broad range of large firms. Our findings on wage and promotion dynamics in ILMs are consistent with models of careers in organizations.]]></description><author>Huitfeldt, Ingrid &amp; Kostøl, Andreas R. &amp; Nimczik, Jan Sebastian &amp; Weber, Andrea</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16434</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Competition and the Assimilation of Immigrants</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16432</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> In this paper, we show that the wage assimilation of immigrants is the result of the intricate interplay between individual skill accumulation and dynamic equilibrium effects in the labor market. When immigrants and natives are imperfect substitutes, increasing immigrant inflows widen the wage gap between them. Using a simple production function framework, we show that this labor market competition channel can explain about one quarter of the large increase in the average immigrant-native wage gap in the United States between the 1960s and 1990s arrival cohorts. Once competition effects and compositional changes in education and region of origin are accounted for, we find that the unobservable skills of newly arriving immigrants increased over time rather than decreased as traditionally argued in the literature. We corroborate this finding by documenting closely matching patterns for immigrants' English language proficiency.]]></description><author>Albert, Christoph &amp; Glitz, Albrecht &amp; Llull, Joan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16432</guid></item><item><title>The Heterogeneous Value of a Statistical Life: Evidence from U.S. Army Reenlistment Decisions</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16425</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper estimates the value of a statistical life (VSL), or the willingness to trade-off wealth and mortality risk, among 430,000 U.S. Army soldiers choosing whether to reenlist between 2002 and 2010. Using a discrete choice random utility approach and significant variation in retention bonuses and mortality risk, we recover average VSL estimates that range between $500,000 and $900,000, an order of magnitude smaller than U.S. civilian labor market estimates. Additionally, we fulfill Rosen's (1974) vision to recover indifference curves between
wealth and non-market goods (e.g., mortality risk) and document substantial heterogeneity in preferences within and across types. We find the VSL increases rapidly with mortality risk within type, and that soldiers in combat occupations have much lower VSLs than those
in noncombat occupations. We estimate that the quadrupling of mortality risk from the Afghanistan and Iraq wars reduced annual welfare by $2,355 per soldier, roughly 8 percent of pay.]]></description><author>Greenberg, Kyle &amp; Greenstone, Michael &amp; Ryan, Stephen &amp; Yankovich, Michael</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16425</guid></item><item><title>Women's Well-being During a Pandemic and its Containment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16424</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic brought the dual crises of disease and the containment policies designed to mitigate it. Yet, there is little evidence on the impacts of these policies on women, who are likely to be especially vulnerable, in lower-income countries. We conduct a large phone survey and leverage India's geographically-varying containment policies to estimate the association between both the pandemic and its containment policies, and measures of women's well-being, including mental health and food security. On aggregate, the pandemic resulted in dramatic income losses, increases in food insecurity, and declines in female mental health. While potentially crucial to stem the spread of COVID-19 cases, we find that greater prevalence of containment policies is associated with increased food insecurity, particularly for women, and with reduced female mental health. Average containment levels are associated with a 39-40% increase in the likelihood of sadness, depression, and hopelessness among women and with an increase in the likelihood that women feel more worried by 45% of the variable mean. Particularly vulnerable groups of women, those with daughters and those living in female-headed households, experience larger declines in mental health.]]></description><author>Bau, Natalie &amp; Khanna, Gaurav &amp; Low, Corinne &amp; Shah, Manisha &amp; Sharmin, Sreyashi &amp; Voena, Alessandra</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16424</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Returns and the Evolution of Cognitive Skills: Theory and Evidence</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16422</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> A large literature in cognitive science studies the puzzling "Flynn effect" of rising fluid intelligence (reasoning skill) in rich countries. We develop an economic model in which a cohort's mix of skills is determined by different skills' relative returns in the labor market and by the technology for producing skills. We estimate the model using administrative data from Sweden. Combining data from exams taken at military enlistment with earnings records from the tax register, we document an increase in the relative labor market return to logical reasoning skill as compared to vocabulary knowledge. The estimated model implies that changes in labor market returns explain 36 percent of the measured increase in reasoning skill, and can also explain the decline in knowledge. An original survey of parents, an analysis of trends in school curricula, and an analysis of occupational characteristics show evidence of increasing emphasis on reasoning as compared to knowledge.]]></description><author>Hermo, Santiago &amp; Päällysaho, Miika &amp; Seim, David &amp; Shapiro, Jesse</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16422</guid></item><item><title>Should We Insure Workers or Jobs During Recessions?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16421</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> What is the most efficient way to respond to recessions in the labor market?
To this question, policymakers on both sides of the pond gave two diametrically
opposed answers during the recent crisis. In the US, the focus was on insuring
workers, by aggressively increasing the generosity of unemployment insurance
(UI). In Europe, to the contrary, policies were concentrated on saving job matches,
with the massive use of labor hoarding subsidies through short-time-work (STW)
programs, on which so little is actually known. In this article, we try to understand
who got it right. Building on the vast literature on UI and on a recent stream of
papers on STW, we first provide a framework to determine the relative welfare
effects of STW versus UI. We then show that UI offers more insurance value than
STW, but tends to exhibit larger fiscal externalities, due to moral hazard. We finally
focus on how STW and UI affect labor market equilibrium and how this interacts
with inefficiencies in the labor market. We review recent evidence showing that
STW can be an effective way to reduce socially costly layoffs in recessions. Overall,
we conclude that STW is an important and useful addition to the labor market
policy-toolkit during recessions, with strong and positive complementarities with
UI.]]></description><author>Giupponi, Giulia &amp; Landais, Camille &amp; Lapeyre, Alice</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16421</guid></item><item><title>Retirement Consumption and Pension Design</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16420</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper develops and implements a framework that leverages consumption
data to evaluate the welfare effects of pension reforms. Several countries have reformed
their pension profiles to incentivize later retirement. Using administrative
data in Sweden, we find that such pension reforms entail substantial consumption
smoothing costs. On average, individuals retiring later have higher consumption
levels than those retiring earlier, implying that recent pension reforms redistributed
from low- to high-consumption households. We show that the differences
in retirement consumption are mostly driven by differential changes in consumption
around retirement, and also that the marginal propensities to consume are
the lowest for late retirees. Accounting for selection on health and life expectancy
further increases the redistributive cost of recent reforms. The cost of incentivizing
later retirement is, however, lowest between the early and normal retirement
age, where we document a striking non-monotonicity in consumption levels. We
find similar patterns in consumption data from other countries, including the nonmonotonicity,
suggesting our findings are not unique to Sweden.]]></description><author>Kolsrud, Jonas &amp; Landais, Camille &amp; Reck, Daniel &amp; Spinnewijn, Johannes</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16420</guid></item><item><title>Racial Bias in Newspaper Ratings of Professional Football Players</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16419</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We study whether there is a racial bias in ratings of professional football players in Italian newspapers. We find that there is such a bias. Conditional on objective performance indicators black players receive a lower rating than non-black players. This is not a difference across the board but predominantly present at the lower end of the newspaper rating distribution. The best black players are not subject to a racial bias in ratings. We also find that clubs do not have a racial bias in the wages they pay to players. We speculate that for clubs there is sufficient competition to remove racial wage discrimination. Clubs simply want value for money. Newspaper football experts do seem to have a racial bias in their rating of players. We hypothesize that this might be unconscious discrimination related to stereotyping of black players.]]></description><author>Principe, Francesco &amp; van Ours, Jan C.</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16419</guid></item><item><title>Mothers at Work: How Mandating Paid Maternity Leave Affects Employment, Earnings and Fertility</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16418</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> In July 2005, Switzerland introduced the first federal paid maternity leave mandate, offering 14 weeks of leave with 80% of pre-birth earnings. We study the mandate's impact on women's employment and earnings around the birth of their first child, as well as on their subsequent fertility by exploiting unique, rich administrative data in a difference-in-differences set-up. Women covered by the mandate worked and earned more during pregnancy, and also had temporarily increased job continuity with their pre-birth employer after birth. Estimated effects on other labor market outcomes are small or absent, and all dissipate by five years after birth. The mandate instead persistently increased subsequent fertility: affected women were three percentage points more likely to have a second child in the next nine years. Women living in regions that had greater early child care availability experienced a larger increase in subsequent fertility following the mandate, suggesting that child care complements paid maternity leave in helping women balance work and family.]]></description><author>Lalive, Rafael</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16418</guid></item><item><title>Parental Responses to Information About School Quality: Evidence from Linked Survey and Administrative Data</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16406</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Multiple inputs determine children's academic achievement. We study the interaction between family and school inputs by identifying the causal impact of information about school quality on parental time investment into children. Our setting is England, where credible information on school quality is provided by a nationwide school inspection regime. Schools are inspected at short notice, with school ratings using hard and soft information. As such soft information is not necessarily known to parents ex ante, inspection ratings provide news to parents that shifts parental beliefs about school quality, and hence their investment into their children. We study this using household panel data linked to administrative records on school performance and inspection ratings. Within the same academic year, we observe some households being interviewed pre school inspection, and others being interviewed post inspection. Treatment assignment is determined by a household's survey date relative to the school inspection date, and shown to be as good as random. We find that parents receiving good news over school quality significantly decrease time investment into their children (relative to parents that will later receive such good news). Our data and design allow us to provide insights on the distributional and test score impacts of the nationwide inspections regime, through multiple margins of endogenous response of parents and children. Our findings highlight the importance of accounting for interlinked private responses by families to new public information on school quality.]]></description><author>Greaves, Ellen &amp; Hussain, Iftikhar &amp; Rabe, Birgitta &amp; Rasul, Imran</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16406</guid></item><item><title>Career Effects of Mental Health</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16401</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This paper investigates the career effects of mental health, focusing on depression,
schizophrenia, and bipolar disorder (BD). Individual-level registry data from Denmark show
that these disorders carry large earnings penalties, ranging from 34 percent for depression and
38 percent for BD to 74 percent for schizophrenia. To investigate the causal effects of mental
health on a person's career, we exploit the approval of lithium as a maintenance treatment for
BD in 1976. Baseline estimates compare career outcomes for people with and without access
in their 20s, the typical age of onset for BD. These estimates show that access to treatment
eliminates one third of the earnings penalty associated with BD and greatly reduces the risks
of low or no earnings. Importantly, access to treatment closes more than half of the disability
risk associated with BD.]]></description><author>Biasi, Barbara &amp; Dahl, Michael S &amp; Moser, Petra</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16401</guid></item><item><title>The Making of Social Democracy The Economic and Electoral Consequences of Norway's 1936 Folk School Reform</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16398</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> Upon assuming power for the first time in 1935, the Norwegian Labour Party delivered on its promise for a major schooling reform. The reform raised minimum instruction time in less developed rural areas and boosted the resources available to rural schools, reducing
class size and increasing teacher salaries. We document that cohorts more intensively affected by the reform significantly increased their education and experienced higher labor income. Our main result is that the schooling reform also substantially increased support for the Norwegian Labour Party in subsequent elections. This additional support persisted for several decades and was pivotal in maintaining support for the social democratic coalition in Norway. These results are not driven by the direct impact of education and are not explained by higher
turnout, or greater attention or resources from the Labour Party targeted towards the municipalities most affected by the reform. Rather, our evidence suggests that cohorts that benefited from the schooling reform, and their parents, rewarded the party for delivering a major reform
that was beneficial to them.]]></description><author>Acemoglu, Daron &amp; Pekkarinen, Tuomas &amp; Salvanes, Kjell G &amp; Sarvimäki, Matti</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16398</guid></item><item><title>Mandatory Advance Notice of Layoff: Evidence and Efficiency Considerations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16387</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We investigate a prevalent, but understudied, employment protection policy: mandatory advance notice (MN), requiring employers to notify employees of forthcoming layoffs. MN increases future production, as notified workers search on the job, but reduces current production as they supply less effort. Our theoretical model captures this trade-off and predicts that MN improves production efficiency by increasing information sharing, whereas large production losses can be avoided by worker-firm agreements on side-payments â?? severance pay â?? in lieu of MN. We provide evidence of such severance increases in response to an extension of MN using novel Swedish administrative data. We then estimate the production gain of MN: extending the MN period leads to shorter non-employment duration and higher reemployment wages, plausibly driven by on-the-job search. Using variation in notice duration across firms, we estimate the productivity loss of notice. The estimates of benefits and costs suggest that MN has a positive net impact on production, offering an empirically-grounded efficiency argument for mandating notice.]]></description><author>Cederlöf, Jonas &amp; Fredriksson, Peter &amp; Nekoei, Arash &amp; Seim, David</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16387</guid></item><item><title>Teacher Compensation and Structural Inequality: Evidence from Centralized Teacher School Choice in Peru</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16386</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This paper studies how increasing teacher compensation at hard-to-staff schools can reduce inequality in access to qualified teachers. Leveraging an unconditional change in the teacher compensation structure in Peru, we first show causal evidence that increasing salaries at less desirable locations attracts better quality applicants and improves student test scores. We then estimate a model of teacher preferences over local amenities, school characteristics, and wages using geocoded job postings and rich application data from the nationwide centralized teacher assignment system. Our estimated model suggests that the current policy is both ineâ??cient and not large enough to effectively undo the inequality of initial conditions that hard-to-staffâ??schools and their communities face. Counterfactual analyses that incorporate equilibrium sorting effects characterize alternative wage schedules and quantify the cost of reducing structural inequality in the allocation of teacher talent across schools.]]></description><author>Bobba, Matteo &amp; Ederer, Tim &amp; León-Ciliotta, Gianmarco &amp; Neilson, Christopher &amp; Nieddu, Marco</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16386</guid></item><item><title>Pandemic Lockdown: The Role of Government Commitment</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16384</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> This paper studies lockdown policy in a dynamic economy without government commitment. Lockdown imposes a cap on labor supply, which improves health prospects at the cost of economic output and consumption. A government would like to commit to the extent of future lockdowns in order to guarantee an economic outlook that supports efficient levels of investment into intermediate inputs. However, such a commitment is not credible, since investments are sunk at the time when the government chooses a lockdown. As a result, lockdown under lack of commitment deviates from the optimal policy. Rules that limit a government's lockdown discretion can improve social welfare, even in the presence of noncontractible information. Quantitatively, lack of commitment causes lockdown to be significantly more severe than is socially optimal. The output and consumption loss due to lack of commitment is greater for higher intermediate input shares, higher discount rates, higher values of life, higher disease transmission rates at and outside of work, and longer vaccine arrival times.]]></description><author>Moser, Christian &amp; Yared, Pierre</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16384</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Pay Gap: Micro Sources and Macro Consequences</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16383</link><description><![CDATA[<b>July 2021</b> <p> We document that a large share of the gender pay gap in Brazil is due to women working at lower-paying employers. However, compared with that of men, women's revealed-preference ranking of employers is less increasing in pay. To interpret these facts, we develop an empirical equilibrium search model with endogenous gender differences in pay, amenities, and recruiting intensities across employers. The estimated model suggests that compensating differentials explain one-fifth of the gender pay gap, that there are significant output and welfare gains from eliminating gender differences, and that equal-treatment policies fail to close the gender pay gap.]]></description><author>Morchio, Iacopo &amp; Moser, Christian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16383</guid></item><item><title>Trade and Informality in the Presence of Labor Market Frictions and Regulations</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=-83459</link><description><![CDATA[<b>January 2021</b> <p> We build an equilibrium model of a small open economy with labor market frictions and imperfectly enforced regulations. Heterogeneous firms sort into the formal or informal sector. We estimate the model using data from Brazil, and use counterfactual simulations to understand how trade affects economic outcomes in the presence of informality. We show that: (1) Trade openness unambiguously decreases informality in the tradable sector, but has ambiguous effects on aggregate informality. (2) The productivity gains from trade are understated when the informal sector is omitted. (3) Trade openness results in large welfare gains even when informality is repressed. (4) Repressing informality increases productivity, but at the expense of employment and welfare. (5) The effects of trade on wage inequality are reversed when the informal sector is incorporated in the analysis. (6) The informal sector works as an "unemployment," but not a "welfare buffer" in the event of negative economic shocks.]]></description><author>Dix-Carneiro, Rafael &amp; Goldberg, Pinelopi Koujianou &amp; Meghir, Costas &amp; Ulyssea, Gabriel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=-83459</guid></item></channel></rss>