<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by areas: Public Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by areas: Public Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 09:48:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Inequality and Creative Destruction</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16867</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Otto Toivanen, Xavier Jaravel, Richard William Blundell.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> In this article we review recent evidence showing how market forces and policies shape the rate and direction of innovation, with various implications for inequality. First, we characterize several market mechanisms whereby higher rates of innovation lead to higher inequality. Second, we highlight channels whereby inequality acts as an impediment to innovation and growth. Third, we highlight policies that can help achieve better outcomes for both innovation and inequality. We show that two types of policies, which are not traditionally viewed as part of innovation policy, play a key role to achieve the goal of enhancing innovation while reducing inequality: education and competition policy.]]></description><author>Otto Toivanen, Xavier Jaravel, Richard William Blundell</author><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16867</guid></item><item><title>Nonparametric Measurement of Long-Run Growth in Consumer Welfare</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16866</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Danial Lashkari, Xavier Jaravel.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> How should we measure long-run changes in consumer welfare? This paper proposes a
nonparametric approach with arbitrary observable preference heterogeneity, e.g. when expenditure
shares vary with income. Our approach only requires data on the consumption
baskets of a cross-section of consumers facing a common set of prices. We take nominal expenditures
under a constant set of prices as our money-metric for real consumption (welfare),
and we derive a consistent measure of its growth in terms of a correction to the conventional
quantity indices. Our correction accounts for the cross-sectional dependence of price indices
on consumer income and any obserable source of preference heterogeneity. We use
nonparametric methods to approximate these corrections and provide bounds on the resulting
approximation errors that hold under arbitrary underlying preferences. Applying our
methodology to the measurement of growth in real consumption per capita in the United
States, we find a sizable correction to standard measures of growth in the postwar eraâ??a period
of fast growth combined with substantial inflation gaps across income groups]]></description><author>Danial Lashkari, Xavier Jaravel</author><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16866</guid></item><item><title>A Fair Day's Pay for a Fair Day's Work: Optimal Tax Design as Redistributional Arbitrage</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16863</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicolas Werquin, Christian Hellwig.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> We study optimal tax design based on the idea that policy-makers face trade-offs between multiple margins of redistribution. Within a Mirrleesian economy with earnings, consumption and retirement savings, we derive a novel formula for optimal income and savings distortions based on redistributional arbitrage. We establish a sufficient statistics representation of the labor income and capital tax rates on top income earners in dynamic environments, which relies on the observed distributions of both income and consumption. Because consumption has a thinner Pareto tail than income, our quantitative results suggest that it is optimal to shift a substantial fraction of the top earners' tax burden from income to savings.]]></description><author>Nicolas Werquin, Christian Hellwig</author><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16863</guid></item><item><title>Inequalities in the Times of a Pandemic</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16856</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefanie Stantcheva.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> This paper summarizes some of the major inequalities that have been exacerbated by the COVID-
19 pandemic and discusses avenues for policy intervention over the medium and long runs.]]></description><author>Stefanie Stantcheva</author><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16856</guid></item><item><title>The Covid-19 Shock and the Indian Economy – A Cross-Country Comparative Analysis</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16855</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ramya Raghavan, Maitreesh Ghatak.</i> <p> <b>January 1, 2022.</b> <p> To understand the economic and public health impact of the Covid-19 pandemic on India, we take a comparative cross-country perspective as all countries were exposed to this shock and were negatively affected and so, a relative comparison allows us to better assess India's performance in these dimensions. We carry out three sets of exercises. First, we discuss the economic impact of Covid-19 using key macroeconomic indicators â?? gross domestic product and employment. Second, we review the fiscal policy response of the government and use household and individual-level surveys to understand the heterogenous impacts of the pandemic on households in the country. Finally, we compare public health indicators across countries. The analysis suggests that India's record with respect to other countries, including countries that are comparable in economic status, puts it in the lower tail of the distribution â?? both in terms of economic and public health indicators. The fallout on the poorer sections and informal sector was particularly severe and policies to mitigate this were inadequate. We conclude that going forward, improving the public health infrastructure and the social safety net must be the public policy priority for the government.]]></description><author>Ramya Raghavan, Maitreesh Ghatak</author><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16855</guid></item><item><title>Efficient Industrial Policy for Innovation: Standing on the shoulders of Hidden Giants</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16850</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Charlotte Guillard, Dennis Verhoeven, Pierre Mohnen, Catherine Thomas, Ralf Martin.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Research and development is underprovided whenever it creates knowledge spillovers that drive a wedge between its total and private economic returns. Heterogeneity in the intensity of this market failure across technological areas provides an argument to vertically target public support for R&D. This paper examines potential welfare gains of such vertical industrial policy for innovation. It develops measures of private and spillover value of patented innovations using global data on patents and their citations. Our new method identifies a large number `Hidden Giants' - i.e. innovations scoring higher on our new spillover measure than on the traditional forward citation count measure - which are shown to be particularly prevalent among patents applied for by universities. The estimated distributions of private values by technology area are then used to parameterize a structural model of innovation. The model permits estimation of the marginal returns to technology-area-specific subsidies that reduce innovators' R\&D costs. Marginal returns are high when knowledge spillovers in the technology area are valuable, when private innovation costs are low, and when private values in a technology sector are densely distributed around the private cost. The results show large variation in the marginal returns to subsidy and suggest that targeted industrial policy would have helped mitigate underprovision of R\&D over the time period studied. Variation in the extent to which knowledge spillovers are internalized within countries also makes a compelling case for supranational policy coordination, especially among smaller countries.]]></description><author>Charlotte Guillard, Dennis Verhoeven, Pierre Mohnen, Catherine Thomas, Ralf Martin</author><pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16850</guid></item><item><title>Scared Straight? Threat and Assimilation of Refugees in Germany</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16849</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marco Tabellini, Sulin Sardoschau, Philipp Jaschke.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the effects of threat on convergence to local culture and on  economic assimilation of refugees, exploiting plausibly exogenous variation in their allocation across German regions between 2013 and 2016. We combine novel survey data on cultural preferences and economic outcomes of refugees with corresponding information on locals, and construct a threat index that integrates contemporaneous and historical variables. On average, refugees assimilate both culturally and economically. However, while refugees assigned to more hostile regions converge to local culture more quickly, they do not exhibit faster economic assimilation. We provide evidence consistent with the hypothesis that refugees exert more assimilation effort in response to local threat, but fail to successfully integrate because of higher discrimination by locals in more hostile regions.]]></description><author>Marco Tabellini, Sulin Sardoschau, Philipp Jaschke</author><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16849</guid></item><item><title>Consolidating the Covid Debt</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16846</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jacob Stevens, Julian Johs, Christian Keuschnigg.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> One of the main functions of public debt is to smooth taxes and spending over time. In the Covid crisis, the Maastricht deficit restrictions were temporarily suspended to allow for large temporary deficits. As recovery sets in, countries are confronted with the task of consolidating the Covid debt. This paper explores a fiscal consolidation strategy combined with growth enhancing tax and expenditure reform. We quantitatively illustrate that this reform based strategy, by reaping substantial efficiency gains and inducing strong growth, eliminates the Covid debt, protects per capita social entitlements and yet avoids increasing tax rates. With slow consolidation, marginal tax rates are reduced right from the beginning.]]></description><author>Jacob Stevens, Julian Johs, Christian Keuschnigg</author><pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16846</guid></item><item><title>Intergenerational Assimilation of Minorities: The Role of the Majority Group</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16830</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yves Zenou, Yasuhiro Sato, Ryo Itoh.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We develop a dynamic model of assimilation of ethnic minorities that posits a tradeoff between higher productivity and wages and  greater social distance to the  culture of origin. We also highlight the importance  of the assimilation of the past generation  and the role of the majority group in the assimilation of ethnic minorities. First, there is  an inverted $U-$shaped relationship between the degree of tolerance of the  majority individuals and the average level of assimilation in the society. Second, more tolerance from the majority group generates positive externalities for the minority group, while each minority's  individual assimilation effort affects the welfare of the majority individuals differently depending on the initial minority assimilation level. Finally,  the more the majority individuals are tolerant toward the minority group, the more the minority individuals will assimilate to the majority group, while the reverse is not always true. In fact, when there is too much assimilation, the majority group may reduce its degree of tolerance toward the majority group.]]></description><author>Yves Zenou, Yasuhiro Sato, Ryo Itoh</author><pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16830</guid></item><item><title>Partisan Fertility and Presidental Elections</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16821</link><description><![CDATA[<i>William Mullins, Runjing Lu, Gordon Dahl.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Changes in political leadership drive sharp changes in public policy and partisan beliefs about the future. We exploit the surprise 2016 election of Trump to identify the effects of a shift in political power on one of the most consequential household decisions: whether to have a child. Republican-leaning counties experience a sharp and persistent increase in fertility relative to Democratic counties, a shift amounting to 1.2 to 2.2% of the national fertility rate. In addition, Hispanics see fertility fall relative to non-Hispanics, especially compared to rural or evangelical whites.]]></description><author>William Mullins, Runjing Lu, Gordon Dahl</author><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16821</guid></item><item><title>The Dynamic Consequences of State-Building: Evidence from the French Revolution</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16815</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin Marx, Emeric Henry, Cédric Chambru.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> How do radical reforms of the state shape economic development over time? In 1790, France's first Constituent Assembly overhauled the kingdom's organization to set up new administrative entities and local capitals. In a subset of departments, new capitals were chosen quasi-randomly as the Assembly abandoned its initial plan to rotate administrative functions across multiple cities. We study how exogenous changes in local administrative presence affect the state's coercive and productive capacity, as well as economic development in the ensuing decades. In the short run, proximity to the state increases taxation, conscription, and investments in law enforcement capacity. In the long run, the new local capitals and their periphery obtain more public goods and experience faster economic development. One hundred years after the reform, capitals are 40% more populated than comparable cities in 1790. Our results shed new light on the intertemporal and redistributive impacts of state-building in the context of one of the most ambitious administrative reforms ever implemented.]]></description><author>Benjamin Marx, Emeric Henry, Cédric Chambru</author><pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16815</guid></item><item><title>Information, Intermediaries, and International Migration</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Job seekers often face substantial information frictions related to potential job quality. This is especially true in international labor markets, where intermediaries match prospective migrants with employers abroad. We conducted a randomized trial in Indonesia to explore how information about intermediary quality shapes migration choices and outcomes. Information reduces the migration rate, lowering use of low-quality intermediaries. However, workers who migrate receive better pre-departure preparation and have higher-quality job experiences abroad, despite no change in occupation or destination. Information does not change intentions to migrate or beliefs about the return to migration or intermediary quality. Nor does selection explain the improved outcomes for workers who choose to migrate with the information. Together, our findings are consistent with an increase in the option value of search: with better ability to differentiate offer quality, workers become choosier and ultimately have better migration experiences. This offers a new perspective on the importance of information and matching frictions in global labor markets.]]></description><author>Firman Witoelar, Simone Schaner, Lisa Cameron, Samuel Bazzi</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16811</guid></item><item><title>Randomization for Causality, Ethnography for Mechanisms: Illiquid Savings for Liquor in an Autarkic Society</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16810</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan Zinman, Dean Karlan, Ricardo Godoy.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> What should researchers do when confronted with surprising results? Financial access
innovations usually leave "temptation" spending unaffected or reduced. However, we
found that promotion of savings lockboxes in a largely autarkic society increased alcohol
consumption and blood pressure, despite no one reporting intentions to save for alcohol.
To probe mechanisms that could explain this pattern, we then used ethnographic methods,
including direct observations of drinking ("scans") and debriefing interviews to discuss the
earlier trial results. We learn that sponsoring drinks confers prestige, but the stigma
attached to drinking by outsiders likely discouraged reporting intentions to save for it.]]></description><author>Jonathan Zinman, Dean Karlan, Ricardo Godoy</author><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16810</guid></item><item><title>In Medio Stat Virtus? Effective Communication and Preferences for Redistribution in Hard Times</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16805</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anna Rosso, Massimo Morelli, Veronica Grembi, Paola Bertoli.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> This paper evaluates the effects of statistical information on preferences for redistribution of scarce public resources. We refer to scarce resource with reference to the COVID-19 emergency: allocation of the first round of vaccine and the allocation of financial resources provided by the Italian national government to fight the economic emergency triggered by the pandemic. Randomly allocating the information through an online experiment, we show that treated respondents tend to prioritize the group targeted by the information, and they are more likely to do so if they are "in the middle", in terms of age, political preferences, religiosity and education.]]></description><author>Anna Rosso, Massimo Morelli, Veronica Grembi, Paola Bertoli</author><pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16805</guid></item><item><title>Optimal Taxation with Multiple Incomes and Types</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16797</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Floris Zoutman, Sander Renes, Etienne Lehmann, Kevin Spiritus.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We analyze the optimal nonlinear income tax schedule when taxpayers earn multiple incomes and differ along many unobserved dimensions. We derive the necessary conditions for the government's optimum using both a tax perturbation and a mechanism design approach, and show that both methods produce the same results. Our main contribution is to propose a numerical method to find the optimal tax schedule. Applied to the optimal taxation of couples, we find that optimal isotax curves are very close to linear and parallel. The slope of isotax curves is strongly affected by the relative tax-elasticity of male and female income. We make several additional contributions, including a test for Pareto efficiency and a condition on primitives that ensures the government's necessary conditions are sufficient and the solution to the problem is unique.]]></description><author>Floris Zoutman, Sander Renes, Etienne Lehmann, Kevin Spiritus</author><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16797</guid></item><item><title>When Reality Bites: Local Deaths and Vaccine Take-Up</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16791</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yves Zenou, Michael Vlassopoulos, Corrado Giulietti.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> In this study, we investigate whether COVID-19 deaths that occurred before vaccination rollouts impact subsequent vaccination take-ups. We used data on local vaccination rates and COVID-19-related deaths from England measured at high geographic granularity. We found that vaccination take-up as of November 2021 was positively associated with pre-vaccine COVID-19-related deaths, controlling for demographic, economic, and health-related characteristics of the localities, while including  geographic fixed effects. In addition,  the share of ethnic minorities in a locality was negatively associated with vaccination rates, and that localities with a larger share of ethnic minorities increased their vaccination rates if they get exposed to more COVID-related-deaths. Further evidence on vaccination intention at the individual level from a representative sample corroborated these patterns. Overall, our evidence suggests that social proximity to victims of the disease triggers a desire to take protective measures against it.]]></description><author>Yves Zenou, Michael Vlassopoulos, Corrado Giulietti</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16791</guid></item><item><title>Individual and Collective Information Acquisition: An Experimental Study</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16782</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Wing Suen, Jimmy Chan, Leeat Yariv, Alessandro Lizzeri, Pellumb Reshidi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Many committees---juries, political task forces, etc.---spend time gathering costly information before reaching a decision. We report results from lab experiments focused on such information-collection processes. We consider decisions governed by individuals and groups and compare how voting rules affect outcomes. We also contrast static information collection, as in classical hypothesis testing, with dynamic collection, as in sequential hypothesis testing. Several insights emerge. Static information collection is excessive, and sequential information collection is non-stationary, producing declining decision accuracies over time. Furthermore, groups using majority rule yield especially hasty and inaccurate decisions. Nonetheless, sequential information collection is welfare enhancing relative to static collection, particularly when unanimous rules are used.]]></description><author>Wing Suen, Jimmy Chan, Leeat Yariv, Alessandro Lizzeri, Pellumb Reshidi</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16782</guid></item><item><title>Controlling Irregular Migration: Can a Market for Temporary Foreign Work Permits Help?</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16777</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tiffanie Perrault, Alice Mesnard, Emmanuelle Auriol.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We study how temporary visa schemes can be designed to drive smugglers out of business while meeting labor market demand in host countries. The policy trade-off between migration control and ending human smuggling can be overcome by combining internal and external controls with a regulated market for temporary visas. In this market, visa duration and price are set at "eviction" levels, designed to throttle smuggling activity. We use information on irregular migration from Senegal to Spain and the Democratic Republic of Congo to South Africa to calibrate the eviction prices of visas for these two routes. Our results highlight important constraints for governments seeking to prevent temporary workers from overstaying, especially on South-North routes such as Senegal to Spain. We suggest combining a regulated market for visas with tighter sanctions against employers of undocumented workers as a new way forward.]]></description><author>Tiffanie Perrault, Alice Mesnard, Emmanuelle Auriol</author><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16777</guid></item><item><title>Money and Ideology: Evidence from Candidate Manifestos</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16774</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Elisa Mougin, Caroline Le Pennec, Julia Cagé.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> Do campaign contributions influence politicians? In this article, we study the impact of corporate donations on ideology and political discourse. We construct a novel dataset that combines the campaign manifestos issued by every candidate running for a seat in the French parliament with data on the amount and origin of their campaign contributions. We exploit an exogenous historical shock on corporate donations to estimate their causal impact on the content of campaign communication. Combining a difference-in-differences approach with computational text analysis, we show that receiving more donations from corporate donors encourages candidates to advertise their local presence over national politics during the campaign. We also find evidence that donations lead candidates from extreme parties to moderate their rhetoric â?? including shifts in the policy topics they advertise. Our findings may reflect a "quid-pro-quo effect" between donors and politicians, but they may also result from an "electoral effect": receiving expressive contributions from corporate donors affects the content of campaign messages because it changes candidates' perception of which issues matter most to voters. According to our findings, campaign finance regulations may alter the information made available to voters through their impact on candidates' rhetoric.]]></description><author>Elisa Mougin, Caroline Le Pennec, Julia Cagé</author><pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16774</guid></item><item><title>OPTIMAL ASSIGNMENT OF BUREAUCRATS: EVIDENCE FROM RANDOMLY ASSIGNED TAX COLLECTORS IN THE DRC</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16771</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan Weigel, Gabriel Tourek, John Kabeya Kabeya, Pedro Bessone, Augustin Bergeron.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> The assignment of workers to tasks and teams is a key margin of firm productivity and a potential source of state effectiveness. This paper investigates whether a low-capacity state can increase its tax revenue through the optimal assignment of its tax collectors. We study the two-stage random assignment of property tax collectors (i) into teams and (ii) to neighborhoods in a large Congolese city. The optimal assignment involves positive assortative matching on both dimensions: high (low) ability collectors should be paired together, and high (low) ability teams should be paired with high (low) payment propensity households. Positive assortative matching stems from complementarities in collector-to-collector and collector-to-household match types. We provide evidence that these complementarities reflect in part high-ability collectors exerting greater effort when matched with other high-ability collectors. Implementing the optimal assignment would increase tax compliance by an estimated 37% relative to the status quo (random) assignment. By contrast, to achieve a similar increase under the status quo assignment, the government would have to replace 63% of low-ability collectors with high-ability ones or to increase collectors' performance wages by 69%.]]></description><author>Jonathan Weigel, Gabriel Tourek, John Kabeya Kabeya, Pedro Bessone, Augustin Bergeron</author><pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16771</guid></item><item><title>Adams and Eves: The Gender Gap in Economics Majors</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16767</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marina Murat, Luca Bonacini, Graziella Bertocchi.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the gender gap in Economics among bachelor's and master's graduates in Italy between 2010 and 2019. First we establish that being female exerts a negative impact on the choice to major in Economics: at the bachelor level, only 73 women graduate in Economics for every 100 men, with the mathematical content of high school curricula as the key driver of the effect and a persistence of the gap at the master level. Second, within a full menu of major choices, Economics displays the largest gap, followed by STEM and then Business Economics. Third, decomposition analyses expose a unique role for the math background in driving the Economics gender gap relative to other fields. Fourth, a triple difference analysis of a high school reform shows that an increase in the math content of traditionally low math curricula caused an increase in the Economics gender gap among treated students.]]></description><author>Marina Murat, Luca Bonacini, Graziella Bertocchi</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16767</guid></item><item><title>Covid-19 and the Forces Behind Social Unrest</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16756</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Mario Lackner, Uwe Sunde, Rudolf Winter-Ebmer.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> The unprecedented consequences of the Covid-19 pandemic have raised concerns about intensified social unrest, but evidence for such a link and the underlying channels is still lacking. We use a unique combination of nationally representative survey data, event data on social unrest, and data on Covid-19 fatalities and unemployment at a weekly resolution to investigate the forces behind social unrest in the context of the strains on public health and the economy due to the pandemic in the USA. The results show that pandemic-related unemployment and Covid-19 fatalities intensified negative emotional stress and led to a deterioration of economic confidence among individuals. The prevalence of negative emotional stress, particularly in economically strained and politically polarized environments, was, in turn, associated with intensified social unrest as measured by political protests. No such link is found for economic perceptions.]]></description><author>Mario Lackner, Uwe Sunde, Rudolf Winter-Ebmer</author><pubDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16756</guid></item><item><title>The impact of 2020 French municipal elections on the spread of COVID-19</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16746</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marc Sangnier, Guilhem Cassan.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> In the first weeks of the COVID-19 pandemic, the French government decided to maintain the first round of the 2020 municipal elections that was scheduled on March 15, 2020. What has been the impact of these elections on the spread of COVID-19 in France? Answering this question leads to intricate econometric issues as omitted variables may drive both epidemiological dynamics and electoral turnout, and as a national lockdown was imposed almost at the same time as the elections. In order to disentangle the effect of the elections from that of confounding factors, we first predict each dÃ©partement's own epidemiological dynamics using information up to the election to calibrate a standard logistic model. We then take advantage of differences in electoral turnout across dÃ©partements to identify the impact of the election on prediction errors in hospitalizations. We report a detrimental effect of the first round of the election in locations that were at relatively advanced stages of the epidemic by the time of the election. Estimates suggest that elections accounted for at least 3,000 hospitalization,
that is 11% of all hospitalizations by the end of March. This indicates that the health cost of holding elections during an epidemic is important and that promoting ways of voting that lower exposure to contamination is key until the COVID-19 pandemic shows signs of abating.]]></description><author>Marc Sangnier, Guilhem Cassan</author><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16746</guid></item><item><title>Equilibrium Worker-Firm Allocations and the Deadweight Losses of Taxation</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16735</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rune Vejlin, Espen R. Moen, Jesper Bagger.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> We analyse the deadweight losses of tax-induced labor misallocation in an equilibrium model of the labour market where workers search to climb a job ladder and firms post vacancies. Workers differ in abilities. Jobs differ in productivities and amenities. A planner uses affine tax functions to finance lump-sum transfers to all workers and unemployment benefits. The competitive search equilibrium maximizes after-tax utility subject to resource constraints and the tax policy. A higher tax rate distorts search effort, job ranking and vacancy creation. Distortions vary on the job ladder, but always result in deadweight losses. We calibrate the model using matched employer-employee data from Denmark. The marginal deadweight loss is 33 percent of the tax base, and primarily arise from distorted search effort and vacancy creation. Steeply rising deadweight losses from distorted vacancy creation imply that the deadweight loss in the calibrated economy exceeds those incurred by very inequality averse social planners.]]></description><author>Rune Vejlin, Espen R. Moen, Jesper Bagger</author><pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16735</guid></item><item><title>Does Organized Crime Attract EU Funding?  Evidence from the Sicilian Mafia</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16732</link><description><![CDATA[<i>José Tavares, João Pereira dos Santos, Marlene Thomas.</i> <p> <b>November 11, 2021.</b> <p> This study examines the impact of the Sicilian Mafia on the allocation of European Union (EU) funding. Our focus is on the number of EU projects and the amount of EU funds awarded to Sicilian municipalities between 2007 and 2019. Mafia activity is proxied by real estate assets seized from organized crime, and instrumented by either geographical shifters of land value, or geographical pointers of MafiaÂ´s historical roots as of the end of the 19th century. We find that Mafia presence increases the amount of EU funds and the number of EU projects assigned to municipalities. Our results are consistent across instrumental variables used, as well as type of EU projects - namely infrastructure, goods and services, grants to individuals, and incentives to firms, and robust to different tests. Our findings suggest that local institutions â?? including the prevalence of organized crime, affect how place-based policies â?? even those originating in international institutions such as the EU, are allocated.]]></description><author>José Tavares, João Pereira dos Santos, Marlene Thomas</author><pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16732</guid></item><item><title>A Commitment Theory of Populism</title><link>http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16051-2</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Paolo Roberti, Antonio Nicolò, Massimo Morelli.</i> <p> <b>December 12, 2021.</b> <p> When voters' trust in politicians collapses, they demand simple policies that they can easily monitor. Disenchanted citizens therefore prefer committed delegates  to  politicians who propose themselves as competent policy makers but without a specific policy commitment (trustees). In a two-party competition, the unique asymmetric equilibrium is such that voters with lower interest for the common good select a committed delegate, while those with higher interest for the common good appoint a trustee. In this equilibrium, we show that the committed delegate also  chooses all the strategies typically associated with populism in the literature. Hence, this paper puts forward a commitment theory of populism.]]></description><author>Paolo Roberti, Antonio Nicolò, Massimo Morelli</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://cepr.org/active/publications/discussion_papers/dp.php?dpno=16051-2</guid></item></channel></rss>