<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Poverty and Wellbeing</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Poverty and Wellbeing</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 23:00:26 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Schools, Job Flexibility, and Married Women's Labor Supply: Evidence From the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29660</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin Hansen, Joseph J. Sabia, Jessamyn Schaller.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This study explores the effect of school reopenings during the COVID-19 pandemic on married women's labor supply. We proxy for in-person attendance at US K-12 schools using smartphone data from Safegraph and measure female employment, hours, and remote work using the Current Population Survey. Difference-in-differences estimates show that K-12 reopenings are associated with significant increases in employment and hours among married women with school-aged children, with no measurable effects on labor supply in comparison groups. Employment effects of school reopenings are concentrated among mothers of older school-aged children, while remote work may mitigate effects for mothers of younger children.]]></description><author>Benjamin Hansen, Joseph J. Sabia, Jessamyn Schaller</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29660</guid></item><item><title>What Leads to Measurement Errors? Evidence from Reports of Program Participation in Three Surveys</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29652</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pablo A. Celhay, Bruce D. Meyer, Nikolas Mittag.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Measurement errors are often a large source of bias in survey data. Lack of knowledge of the determinants of such errors makes it difficult for data producers to reduce the extent of errors and for data users to assess the validity of analyses using the data. We study the determinants of reporting error using high quality administrative data on government transfers linked to three major U.S. surveys. Our results support several theories of misreporting: Errors are related to event recall, forward and backward telescoping, salience of receipt, the stigma of reporting participation in welfare programs and respondent’s degree of cooperation with the survey overall. We provide evidence on how survey design choices affect reporting errors. Our findings help survey users to gauge the reliability of their data and to devise estimation strategies that can correct for systematic errors, such as instrumental variable approaches. Understanding survey errors allows survey producers to reduce them by improving survey design. Our results indicate that survey producers should take into account that higher response rates as well as collecting more detailed information may have negative effects on survey accuracy.]]></description><author>Pablo A. Celhay, Bruce D. Meyer, Nikolas Mittag</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29652</guid></item><item><title>Urban Mobility and the Experienced Isolation of Students and Adults</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29645</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Cody Cook, Lindsey Currier, Edward L. Glaeser.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Do urban children live more segregated lives than urban adults? Using cellphone location data and following the ‘experienced isolation’ methodology of Athey et al. (2021), we compare the isolation of students over the age of 16—who we identify based on their time spent at a high school—and adults. We find that students in cities experience significantly less integration in their day-to-day lives than adults. The average student experiences 27% more isolation outside of the home than the average adult. Even when comparing students and adults living in the same neighborhood, exposure to devices associated with a different race is 20% lower for students. Looking at more broad measures of urban mobility, we find that students spend more time at home, more time closer to home when they do leave the house, and less time at school than adults spend at work. Finally, we find correlational evidence that neighborhoods with more geographic mobility today also had more intergenerational income mobility in the past. We hope future work will more rigorously test the hypothesis that different geographic mobility patterns for children and adults can explain why urban density appears to boost adult wages but reduce intergenerational income mobility.]]></description><author>Cody Cook, Lindsey Currier, Edward L. Glaeser</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29645</guid></item><item><title>Racial Inequality in Unemployment Insurance Receipt and Take-Up</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29595</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Elira Kuka, Bryan A. Stuart.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies differences in receipt and take-up of unemployment insurance (UI) benefits among white and Black individuals. We combine state-level UI regulations with data containing detailed information on individuals’ work history and UI receipt. Black individuals who separate from a job are 24% less likely to receive UI than whites. The UI receipt gap stems primarily from lower take-up of UI benefits among likely eligible individuals, as opposed to differences in benefit eligibility. Statistical decompositions indicate that about one-half of the take-up gap is explained by Black workers’ lower pre-unemployment earnings and higher tendency to live in the South.]]></description><author>Elira Kuka, Bryan A. Stuart</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29595</guid></item><item><title>Private but Misunderstood? Evidence on Measuring Intimate Partner Violence via Self-Interviewing in Rural Liberia and Malawi</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29584</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Sungho Park, Shilpa Aggarwal, Dahyeon Jeong, Naresh Kumar, Jonathan Robinson, Alan Spearot.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Women may under-report intimate partner violence (IPV) in surveys due to a variety of social and psychological factors. To understand if anonymized interviewing can allay this concern, we conduct a measurement experiment in rural Liberia and Malawi in which women were asked IPV questions via either self-interviewing (SI) or face-to-face interviewing (FTFI) with an enumerator. We find that about a third of women incorrectly answer basic screening questions over SI, and that it generates placebo effects on innocuous questions even for those who "pass" screening. Because the probability of responding "yes" to any specific IPV question is less than 50%, and that IPV is typically reported as an index (reporting yes to at least one question in a category of violence), such misunderstanding will tend to increase IPV reporting. In Malawi, we find that SI dramatically increases reported IPV, with the incidence of any type of IPV increasing by 13 percentage points on a base of 20%; in Liberia, we find an insignificant and modest increase of 4 percentage points on a base of 39%. Our results suggest SI may spuriously increase reported IPV rates.]]></description><author>David Sungho Park, Shilpa Aggarwal, Dahyeon Jeong, Naresh Kumar, Jonathan Robinson, Alan Spearot</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29584</guid></item><item><title>Race and Economic Well-Being in the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29539</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jean-Felix Brouillette, Charles I. Jones, Peter J. Klenow.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We construct a measure of consumption-equivalent welfare for Black and White Americans. Our statistic incorporates life expectancy, consumption, leisure, and inequality, with mortality rates playing a key role quantitatively. According to our estimates, welfare for Black Americans was 43% of that for White Americans in 1984 and rose to 60% by 2019. Going back further in time (albeit with more limited data), the gap was even larger, with Black welfare equal to just 28% of White welfare in 1940. On the one hand, there has been remarkable progress for Black Americans: the level of their consumption-equivalent welfare increased by a factor of 28 between 1940 and 2019, when aggregate consumption per person rose a more modest 5-fold. On the other hand, despite this remarkable progress, the welfare gap in 2019 remains disconcertingly large. Mortality from COVID-19 has temporarily reversed a decade of progress, lowering Black welfare by 17% while reducing White welfare by 10%.]]></description><author>Jean-Felix Brouillette, Charles I. Jones, Peter J. Klenow</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29539</guid></item><item><title>Support for Paid Family Leave among Small Employers Increases during the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29486</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ann P. Bartel, Maya Rossin-Slater, Christopher J. Ruhm, Meredith Slopen, Jane Waldfogel.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The United States is one of the few countries that does not guarantee paid family leave (PFL) to workers. Proposals for PFL legislation are often met with opposition from employer organizations, who fear disruptions to business, especially among small employers. But there has been limited data on employers’ views. We surveyed firms with 10-99 employees in New York and New Jersey on their attitudes towards PFL programs before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. We found high support for state PFL programs in 2019 that rose substantially over the course of the pandemic: by the fall of 2020, almost 70% of firms were supportive. Increases in support were larger among firms that had an employee use PFL, suggesting that experience with PFL led to employers becoming more supportive. Thus, concerns about negative impacts on small employers should not impede efforts to expand PFL at the state or federal levels.]]></description><author>Ann P. Bartel, Maya Rossin-Slater, Christopher J. Ruhm, Meredith Slopen, Jane Waldfogel</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29486</guid></item><item><title>Mental Health Therapy as a Core Strategy for Increasing Human Capital: Evidence from Ghana</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the impact of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) for individuals selected from the general population of poor households in rural Ghana. Results from 2-3 months after a randomized intervention show strong impacts on mental and physical health, cognitive and socioemotional skills, and downstream economic outcomes. We find no evidence of heterogeneity by baseline mental distress; we argue that this is because CBT can improve human capital for a general population of poor individuals through two pathways. First, CBT reduces vulnerability to deteriorating mental health; and second, CBT directly improves bandwidth, increasing cognitive and socioemotional skills and hence economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</guid></item><item><title>The Effect of Free School Meals on Household Food Purchases: Evidence from the Community Eligibility Provision</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29395</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michelle M. Marcus, Katherine G. Yewell.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We find evidence that exposure to universal free school meals through the Community Eligibility Provision (CEP) had a meaningful impact on grocery spending for households with children, with monthly food purchases declining by about $11, or 5 percent. For households in zip codes with higher exposure, the decline is as high as $39 per month, or 19 percent. We also show evidence that the composition of food purchases changes, with low income households experiencing an increase in the dietary quality of their food purchases by about 3 percent after CEP. Finally, we show CEP exposure is associated with an 11 percent decline in the percent of households that ran short of money or tried to make their food money go further, and an almost 5 percent decline in households classified as food insecure. Our results on the heterogeneous effects of CEP exposure by prior free/reduced price lunch eligibility reveal large benefits in terms of both spending, dietary composition, and food insecurity for previously eligible low-income families, suggesting that the stigma of free school meals may be declining after universal access.]]></description><author>Michelle M. Marcus, Katherine G. Yewell</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29395</guid></item><item><title>School Food Policy Affects Everyone: Retail Responses to the National School Lunch Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29384</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jessie Handbury, Sarah Moshary.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the private market response to the National School Lunch Program, documenting economically meaningful spillovers to non-recipients. We focus on the Community Eligibility Provision (CEP), an expansion of the lunch program under the 2010 Healthy, Hunger-Free Kids Act. Under the CEP, participating schools offer free lunch to all students. We leverage both the staggered roll-out and eligibility criterion for the CEP, which is limited to schools where at least 40% of students participate in other means-tested welfare programs. We find that local adoption of the CEP causes households with children to reduce their grocery purchases, leading to a 10% decline in grocery sales at large retail chains. Retailers respond with chain-level price adjustments: chains with the most exposure lower prices by 2.5% across all outlets in the years following adoption, so that the program's welfare benefits propagate spatially. Using a stylized model of grocery demand, we estimate that, by 2016, the indirect benefit had reduced grocery costs for the median household by approximately 4.5%.]]></description><author>Jessie Handbury, Sarah Moshary</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29384</guid></item><item><title>Fleshing Out the Olive? On Income Polarization in China</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29383</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Ravallion, Shaohua Chen.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> In a rare example of an explicit national goal for income distribution besides reducing poverty, China’s leadership has recently committed to expanding the middle-income share—moving to a less polarized “olive-shaped” distribution. Recognizing the potential trade-offs, the paper asks whether China’s experience indicates that income-polarization was a by-product of past economic progress, including poverty reduction. The paper does not find robust time-series evidence of polarizing effects alongside either economic growth or population urbanization (including among those below the national median). There was strong co-movement between polarization and inequality. Larger urban-rural gaps in mean incomes are strongly polarizing in China.]]></description><author>Martin Ravallion, Shaohua Chen</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29383</guid></item><item><title>The Anti-Poverty, Targeting, and Labor Supply Effects of the Proposed Child Tax Credit Expansion</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29366</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kevin Corinth, Bruce D. Meyer, Matthew Stadnicki, Derek Wu.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The proposed change under the American Families Plan (AFP) to the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act (TCJA) Child Tax Credit (CTC) would increase maximum benefit amounts to $3,000 or $3,600 per child (up from $2,000 per child) and make the full credit available to all low and middle-income families regardless of earnings or income. We estimate the anti-poverty, targeting, and labor supply effects of the expansion by linking survey data with administrative tax and government program data which form part of the Comprehensive Income Dataset (CID). Initially ignoring any behavioral responses, we estimate that the expansion of the CTC would reduce child poverty by 34% and deep child poverty by 39%. The expansion of the CTC would have a larger anti-poverty effect on children than any existing government program, though at a higher cost per child raised above the poverty line than any other means-tested program. Relatedly, the CTC expansion would allocate a smaller share of its total dollars to families at the bottom of the income distribution—as well as families with the lowest levels of long-term income, education, or health—than any existing means-tested program with the exception of housing assistance. We then simulate anti-poverty effects accounting for labor supply responses. By replacing the TCJA CTC (which contained substantial work incentives akin to the Earned Income Tax Credit) with a universal basic income-type benefit, the CTC expansion reduces the return to working at all by at least $2,000 per child for most workers with children. Relying on elasticity estimates consistent with mainstream simulation models and the academic literature, we estimate that this change in policy would lead 1.5 million workers (constituting 2.6% of all working parents) to exit the labor force. The decline in employment and the consequent earnings loss would mean that child poverty would only fall by 22% and deep child poverty would not fall at all with the CTC expansion.]]></description><author>Kevin Corinth, Bruce D. Meyer, Matthew Stadnicki, Derek Wu</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29366</guid></item><item><title>Early Childhood Development, Human Capital and Poverty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29362</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Orazio Attanasio, Sarah Cattan, Costas Meghir.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Children's experiences during early childhood are critical for their cognitive and socio-emotional development, two key dimensions of human capital. However, children from low income backgrounds often grow up lacking stimulation and basic investments, leading to developmental deficits that are difficult, if not impossible, to reverse later in life without intervention. The existence of these deficits are a key driver of inequality and contribute to the intergenerational transmission of poverty. In this paper, we discuss the framework used in economics to model parental investments and early childhood development and use it as an organizing tool to review some of the empirical evidence on early childhood research. We then present results from various important early childhoods interventions with emphasis on developing countries. Bringing these elements together we draw conclusions on what we have learned and provide some directions for future research.]]></description><author>Orazio Attanasio, Sarah Cattan, Costas Meghir</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29362</guid></item><item><title>The Psychosocial Effects of the Flint Water Crisis on School-Age Children</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29341</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sam Trejo, Gloria Yeomans-Maldonado, Brian Jacob.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Lead poisoning has well-known impacts for the developing brain of young children, with a large literature documenting the negative effects of elevated blood lead levels on academic and behavioral outcomes. In April of 2014, the municipal water source in Flint, Michigan was changed, causing lead from aging pipes to leach into the city’s drinking water. In this study, we use Michigan’s universe of longitudinal, student-level education records, combined with home water service line inspection data containing the location of lead pipes, to empirically examine the effect of the Flint Water Crisis on educational outcomes of Flint public school children. We leverage parallel causal identification strategies, a between-district synthetic control analysis and a within-Flint difference-in-differences analysis, to separate out the direct health effects of lead exposure from the broad effects of living in a community experiencing a crisis. Our results highlight a less well-appreciated consequence of the Flint Water Crisis – namely, the psychosocial effects of the crisis on the educational outcomes of school-age children. These findings suggest that cost estimates which rely only on the negative impact of direct lead exposure substantially underestimate the overall societal cost of the crisis.]]></description><author>Sam Trejo, Gloria Yeomans-Maldonado, Brian Jacob</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29341</guid></item><item><title>Why do people stay poor?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clare A. Balboni, Oriana Bandiera, Robin Burgess, Maitreesh Ghatak, Anton Heil.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> There are two broad views as to why people stay poor. One emphasizes differences in fundamentals, such as ability, talent or motivation. The other, the poverty traps view, differences in opportunities which stem from access to wealth. To test between these two views, we exploit a large-scale, randomized asset transfer and an 11-year panel on 6000 households who begin in extreme poverty. The setting is rural Bangladesh and the asset is cows. The data supports the poverty traps view - we identify a threshold level of initial assets above which households accumulate assets, take on better occupations (from casual labor in agriculture or domestic services to running small livestock businesses) and grow out of poverty. The reverse happens for those below the threshold. Structural estimation of an occupational choice model reveals that almost all beneficiaries are misallocated in the work they do at baseline and that the gains arising from eliminating misallocation would far exceed the program costs. Our findings imply that large transfers which create better jobs for the poor are an effective means of getting people out of poverty traps and reducing global poverty.]]></description><author>Clare A. Balboni, Oriana Bandiera, Robin Burgess, Maitreesh Ghatak, Anton Heil</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</guid></item><item><title>The Initial Effects of the Expanded Child Tax Credit on Material Hardship</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zachary Parolin, Elizabeth Ananat, Sophie M. Collyer, Megan Curran, Christopher Wimer.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> The transformation of the Child Tax Credit (CTC) into a more generous, inclusive monthly payment marks a historic (temporary) shift in U.S. treatment of low-income families. To investigate the initial impact of these payments, we apply a series of difference-in-difference estimates using Census Household Pulse Survey microdata collected from April 14 through August 16, 2021. Our findings offer three primary conclusions regarding the initial effects of the monthly CTC. First, payments strongly reduced food insufficiency: the initial payments led to a 7.5 percentage point (25 percent) decline in food insufficiency among low-income households with children. Second, the effects on food insufficiency are concentrated among families with 2019 pre-tax incomes below $35,000, and the CTC strongly reduces food insufficiency among low-income Black, Latino, and White families alike. Third, increasing the CTC coverage rate would be required in order for material hardship to be reduced further. Self-reports suggest the lowest-income households were less likely than higher-income families to receive the first CTC payments. As more children receive the benefit in future months, material hardship may decline further. Even with imperfect coverage, however, our findings suggest that the first CTC payments were largely effective at reducing food insufficiency among low-income families with children.]]></description><author>Zachary Parolin, Elizabeth Ananat, Sophie M. Collyer, Megan Curran, Christopher Wimer</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285</guid></item><item><title>The Consequences of Chronic Pain in Mid-Life: Evidence from the National Child Development Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29278</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Using data from all those born in a single week in 1958 in Britain we track the consequences of short pain and chronic pain in mid-life (age 44) on health, wellbeing and labor market outcomes in later life.  We examine data taken at age 50 in 2008, when the Great Recession hit and then five years later at age 55 in 2013.  We find those suffering both short-term and chronic pain at age 44 continue to report pain and poor general health in their 50s.  However, the associations are much stronger for those with chronic pain.  Furthermore, chronic pain at age 44 is associated with a range of poor mental health outcomes, pessimism about the future and joblessness at age 55 whereas short-duration pain at age 44 is not.  Uniquely, we also show that pain experienced in childhood, at ages 11 and 16, reported by a parent and a teacher respectively, collected decades earlier, predicts pain in mid-life, indicating just how persistent pain can be over the life-course.]]></description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29278</guid></item></channel></rss>