<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Experimental Design</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Experimental Design</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 23:04:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>State-building on the Margin: An Urban Experiment in Medellín</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29692</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher Blattman, Gustavo Duncan, Benjamin Lessing, Santiago Tobon.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Medellín's government wanted to raise its efficacy, legitimacy, and control. The city identified 80 neighborhoods with weak state presence and competing armed actors. In half, they increased non-police street presence tenfold for two years, offering social services and dispute resolution. In places where the state was initially weakest, the intervention did not work, mainly because the government struggled to deliver on its promises. Where the state began stronger, the government raised opinions of its services and legitimacy. If there are indeed low marginal returns to investing in capacity in the least-governed areas, this could produce increasing returns to state-building.]]></description><author>Christopher Blattman, Gustavo Duncan, Benjamin Lessing, Santiago Tobon</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29692</guid></item><item><title>Private but Misunderstood? Evidence on Measuring Intimate Partner Violence via Self-Interviewing in Rural Liberia and Malawi</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29584</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Sungho Park, Shilpa Aggarwal, Dahyeon Jeong, Naresh Kumar, Jonathan Robinson, Alan Spearot.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Women may under-report intimate partner violence (IPV) in surveys due to a variety of social and psychological factors. To understand if anonymized interviewing can allay this concern, we conduct a measurement experiment in rural Liberia and Malawi in which women were asked IPV questions via either self-interviewing (SI) or face-to-face interviewing (FTFI) with an enumerator. We find that about a third of women incorrectly answer basic screening questions over SI, and that it generates placebo effects on innocuous questions even for those who "pass" screening. Because the probability of responding "yes" to any specific IPV question is less than 50%, and that IPV is typically reported as an index (reporting yes to at least one question in a category of violence), such misunderstanding will tend to increase IPV reporting. In Malawi, we find that SI dramatically increases reported IPV, with the incidence of any type of IPV increasing by 13 percentage points on a base of 20%; in Liberia, we find an insignificant and modest increase of 4 percentage points on a base of 39%. Our results suggest SI may spuriously increase reported IPV rates.]]></description><author>David Sungho Park, Shilpa Aggarwal, Dahyeon Jeong, Naresh Kumar, Jonathan Robinson, Alan Spearot</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29584</guid></item><item><title>The Effects of Letters of Recommendation in the Youth Labor Market</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29579</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sara B. Heller, Judd B. Kessler.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Youth employment has been near historic lows in recent years, and racial gaps persist. This paper tests whether information frictions limit young people's labor market success with a field experiment involving over 43,000 youth in New York City. We build software that allows employers to quickly and easily produce letters of recommendation for randomly selected youth who worked under their supervision during a summer youth employment program. We then send these letters to nearly 9,000 youth over two years. Being sent a letter generates a 3 percentage point (4.5 percent) increase in employment the following year, with both employment and earnings increases persisting over the two-year follow-up period. By posting our own job advertisement, we document that while treatment youth do use the letters in applications, there is no evidence of other supply-side responses (i.e., no increased job search, motivation, or confidence); effects appear to be driven by the demand side. Labor market benefits accrue primarily to racial and ethnic minorities, suggesting frictions may contribute to racial employment gaps. But improved employment may also hamper on-time high school graduation. Additional evidence indicates that letters help improve job match quality. Results suggest that expanding the availability credible signals about young workers—particularly for those not on the margin of graduating high school—could improve the efficiency of the youth labor market.]]></description><author>Sara B. Heller, Judd B. Kessler</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29579</guid></item><item><title>Individual and Collective Information Acquisition: An Experimental Study</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29557</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pëllumb Reshidi, Alessandro Lizzeri, Leeat Yariv, Jimmy H. Chan, Wing Suen.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Many committees—juries, political task forces, etc.—spend time gathering costly information before reaching a decision. We report results from lab experiments focused on such information-collection processes. We consider decisions governed by individuals and groups and compare how voting rules affect outcomes. We also contrast static information collection, as in classical hypothesis testing, with dynamic collection, as in sequential hypothesis testing. Several insights emerge. Static information collection is excessive, and sequential information collection is non-stationary, producing declining decision accuracies over time. Furthermore, groups using majority rule yield especially hasty and inaccurate decisions. Nonetheless, sequential information collection is welfare enhancing relative to static collection, particularly when unanimous rules are used.]]></description><author>Pëllumb Reshidi, Alessandro Lizzeri, Leeat Yariv, Jimmy H. Chan, Wing Suen</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29557</guid></item><item><title>Salary History and Employer Demand: Evidence from a Two-Sided Audit</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29460</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Amanda Y. Agan, Bo Cowgill, Laura K. Gee.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study how salary history disclosures affect employer demand by using a novel, two-sided field experiment featuring hundreds of recruiters reviewing over 2000 job applications. We randomize the presence of salary history questions as well as candidates' disclosures. We find that employers make negative inferences about non-disclosing candidates, and view salary history as a stronger signal about competing options than worker quality. Disclosures by men (and other highly-paid candidates) yield higher salary offers, however they are negative signals of value (net of salary), and thus yield fewer callbacks. Male wage premiums are regarded as a weaker signal of quality than other sources (such as the premiums from working at higher paying firms, or being well-paid compared to peers). Recruiters correctly anticipate that women are less likely to disclose salary history at any level, and punish women less than men for silence. In our simulation of bans, we find no evidence that bans affect the gender ratio of callback choices, but find large reductions in gender inequality in salary offers among candidates called back. However, salary offers are lower overall (especially for men). A theoretical framework shows how these effects may differ by key properties of labor markets.]]></description><author>Amanda Y. Agan, Bo Cowgill, Laura K. Gee</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29460</guid></item><item><title>It All Starts with Beliefs: Addressing the Roots of Educational Inequities by Shifting Parental Beliefs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29394</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John A. List, Julie Pernaudet, Dana Suskind.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Socioeconomic inequalities in child development crystallize at early stages, with associated disparities in parental investment in children. A key to understanding the data patterns is to document the sources underlying the observed inequalities. We first show that there are dramatic differences in parental beliefs across socioeconomic backgrounds (SES), with parents of higher SES being more likely to believe that parental investments impact child development. We then use two field experiments targeted to low-SES families to explore the mutability of such beliefs and their link to parental investments. In both cases, we find that parental beliefs about child development are malleable. The less intensive version of the program based on educational videos changes parental beliefs, but fails to lastingly increase parental investments and child outcomes. By contrast, in the more intensive version of our program combining home visits and feedback, the augmented beliefs are associated with enriched parent-child interactions and improved vocabulary, math, and social-emotional skills for the children. Together, these results suggest that changing parental beliefs can be an important pathway to raising parental investments and reducing socioeconomic gaps in children’s skills, but that simple informational policies may not be sufficient.]]></description><author>John A. List, Julie Pernaudet, Dana Suskind</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29394</guid></item><item><title>Interpreting the Will of the People: A Positive Analysis of Ordinal Preference Aggregation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29389</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sandro Ambuehl, B. Douglas Bernheim.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Collective decision making requires preference aggregation even if no ideal aggregation method exists (Arrow, 1950). We investigate how individuals think groups should aggregate members' ordinal preferences—that is, how they interpret "the will of the people." Our experiment elicits revealed attitudes toward ordinal preference aggregation and classifies subjects according to the rules they implicitly deploy. Majoritarianism is rare while rules that promote compromise are common. People evaluate relative sacrifice by inferring cardinal utility from ordinal ranks. Cluster analysis reveals that our classification encompasses all important aggregation rules. Aggregation methods exhibit stability across domains and across countries with divergent traditions.]]></description><author>Sandro Ambuehl, B. Douglas Bernheim</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29389</guid></item><item><title>A (Dynamic) Investigation of Stereotypes, Belief-Updating, and Behavior</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29382</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Katherine B. Coffman, Paola Ugalde Araya, Basit Zafar.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Many decisions – such as what educational or career path to pursue – are dynamic in nature, with individuals receiving feedback at one point in time and making decisions later. Using a controlled experiment, with two sessions one week apart, we analyze the dynamic effects of feedback on beliefs about own performance and decision-making across two different domains (verbal skills and math). We find significant gender gaps in beliefs and choices before feedback: men are more optimistic about their performance and more willing to compete than women in both domains, but the gaps are significantly larger in math. Feedback significantly shifts individuals' beliefs and choices. Despite this, we see substantial persistence of gender gaps over time. This is particularly true among the set of individuals who receive negative feedback. We find that, holding fixed performance and decisions before feedback, women update their beliefs and choices more negatively than men do after bad news. Our results highlight the challenges involved in overcoming gender gaps in dynamic settings.]]></description><author>Katherine B. Coffman, Paola Ugalde Araya, Basit Zafar</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29382</guid></item><item><title>The Asymmetry in Responsible Investing Preferences</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29288</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jacquelyn Humphrey, Shimon Kogan, Jacob Sagi, Laura Starks.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We design an experiment to understand how social preferences affect investment decisions through stock allocations and probability assessments. The major preference channel is asymmetric in social outcomes – although negative and positive responsible investment (RI) externalities have the same magnitudes, negative externalities have greater impact on investment choices. The effect is persistent, but heterogenous. We also find asymmetries in belief formation and learning constitute a secondary channel. Overall, our results are consistent with important stylized empirical facts and the predictions of recent RI theories that social preferences lead to different investment choices, but our analyses also suggest important future modeling directions.]]></description><author>Jacquelyn Humphrey, Shimon Kogan, Jacob Sagi, Laura Starks</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29288</guid></item><item><title>Memory and Probability</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29273</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pedro Bordalo, John J. Conlon, Nicola Gennaioli, Spencer Yongwook Kwon, Andrei Shleifer.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> People often estimate probabilities, such as the likelihood that an insurable risk will materialize or that an Irish person has red hair, by retrieving experiences from memory. We present a model of this process based on two established regularities of selective recall: similarity and interference. The model accounts for and reconciles a variety of conflicting empirical findings, such as overestimation of unlikely events when these are cued vs. neglect of non-cued ones, the availability heuristic, the representativeness heuristic, as well as over vs. underreaction to information in different situations. The model makes new predictions on how the content of a hypothesis (not just its objective probability) affects probability assessments by shaping the ease of recall. We experimentally evaluate these predictions and find strong experimental support.]]></description><author>Pedro Bordalo, John J. Conlon, Nicola Gennaioli, Spencer Yongwook Kwon, Andrei Shleifer</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29273</guid></item></channel></rss>