<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by programs: Development Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by programs: Development Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 22:11:44 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>On the Dynamics of Human Behavior: The Past, Present, and Future of Culture, Conflict, and Cooperation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29804</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nathan Nunn.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> I provide a theoretically-guided discussion of the dynamics of human behavior, focusing on the importance of culture (socially-learned information) and tradition (transmission of culture across generations). Decision-making that relies on tradition can be an effective strategy and arises in equilibrium. While dynamically optimal, it generates static `mismatch.' When the world changes, since traits evolve slowly, they may not be beneficial in their new environment. I discuss how mismatch helps explain the world around us, presents special challenges and opportunities for policy, and provides important lessons for our future as a human species.]]></description><author>Nathan Nunn</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29804</guid></item><item><title>Democratization, Elite Capture and Economic Development</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29797</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andrew D. Foster, Mark R. Rosenzweig.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We show using a theoretical framework that embeds a voting model in a general-equilibrium model of a rural economy with two interest groups defined by land ownership that the effects of democratization—a shift from control of public resources by the landed elite to a democratic regime with universal suffrage—on the portfolio of public goods is heterogeneous, depending the population landless. In accord with the model and empirical findings from micro data on the differing material interests of the two land classes, we find, based on 30-year panel data describing the democratization of Indian villages, that democratization in villages with a larger landless population share shifted resources away from public irrigation, secondary schools, and electrification and towards programs that increase employment. When the landed farmers have a large population share, public resources were shifted towards irrigation, secondary schools and electrification and away from employment programs.]]></description><author>Andrew D. Foster, Mark R. Rosenzweig</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29797</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Upward Mobility</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29796</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Debraj Ray ⓡ, Garance Genicot.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We develop a measure of upward mobility that distills central features of the relative and absolute approaches to measuring mobility.  The former is embodied in the Growth Progressivity axiom: transfers of instantaneous growth rates from relatively rich to poor individuals increases upward mobility. The latter is embodied in the Growth Alignment axiom: mobility increases with  higher growth for all individuals. These axioms, along with standard auxiliary restrictions, identify a simple one-parameter family of upward mobility measures, linear in individual growth rates and exhibiting geometrically declining weights on baseline incomes. A serendipitous implication of our measure is that it does not rely on panel data, which greatly expands our analytical scope to data-poor settings.]]></description><author>Debraj Ray ⓡ, Garance Genicot</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29796</guid></item><item><title>Gifted Children Programs’ Short and Long-Term Impact: Higher Education, Earnings, and the Knowledge-Economy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29779</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Victor Lavy, Yoav Goldstein.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We estimate the effects of gifted children programs (GCP) in high schools in Israel. We selected a comparison group of equally gifted students from other cities where GCP was not offered at the time. Based on administrative data, we follow 22 cohorts and measure treatment effects on outcomes, ranging from high school to the labor market in their 30s and 40s. We find tiny impact on academic achievements in high school, in contrast to the abundance of educational resources enjoyed by GCP participants. In the longer run, we find meaningful effects of GCP on higher education attainment. GCP participants study more math, computer, and physical sciences but engage less in engineering programs. The net effect on STEM degrees is, therefore, zero. However, a much higher share of GCP participants graduated with two STEM majors. This evidence suggests that GCP enhances the impact of “multipotentiality,” which characterizes many gifted adolescents. The effect on getting a Ph.D. is positive, too. Lastly, we find no effect of GCP on employment and earnings. Nor do we find that GCP participants work more than other equally talented children in the knowledge economy. These results are very similar for females and males gifted children.]]></description><author>Victor Lavy, Yoav Goldstein</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29779</guid></item><item><title>What Gets Measured Gets Managed: Investment and the Cost of Capital</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29775</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhiguo He, Guanmin Liao, Baolian Wang.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We study the impact of government-led incentive systems by examining a staggered reform in the Chinese state-owned enterprise (SOE) performance evaluation policy. To improve capital allocative efficiency, in 2010, regulators switched from using return on equity (ROE) to economic value added (EVA) when evaluating SOE performance. This EVA policy adopts a one-size-fits-all approach by stipulating a fixed cost of capital for virtually all SOEs, ignoring the potential heterogeneity of firm-specific costs of capital. We show that SOEs did respond to the performance evaluation reform by altering their investment decisions, more so when the actual borrowing rate was further away from the stipulated cost of capital. Our paper provides causal evidence that incentive schemes affect real investment and sheds new light on challenges faced by economic reforms in China.]]></description><author>Zhiguo He, Guanmin Liao, Baolian Wang</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29775</guid></item><item><title>How Important are Investment Indivisibilities for Development? Experimental Evidence from Uganda</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29773</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joseph P. Kaboski, Molly Lipscomb, Virgiliu Midrigan, Carolyn Pelnik.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Theoretically, indivisible investments together with financial frictions can lower development, generate poverty traps, and lead agents to become risk-loving. Using experimental cash grants involving a choice between a safer, low payoff and a riskier, large payoff lottery, we find that  27 percent choose the riskier, larger lottery. Small grant winners invest in livestock and business inventory, while large grant winners invest in land, which exhibits high capital gains. Our quantitative model shows that the aggregate effects of financial deepening are sizable if the indivisible investment can be accumulated (e.g., capital) but not if it is in fixed supply (e.g., land).]]></description><author>Joseph P. Kaboski, Molly Lipscomb, Virgiliu Midrigan, Carolyn Pelnik</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29773</guid></item><item><title>Conditional Cash Transfers for Education</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29758</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sandra García, Juan Saavedra.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> This chapter reviews the extensive literature to date on CCTs for education. Section 2 provides background on the origins and expansion of CCTs globally, and describes basic design features and variation in characteristics across programs. Section 3 presents a theory of change and an economic household decision-making model highlighting key comparative statics and empirical predictions for the introduction of an education CCT program. Section 4 discusses key methodological challenges in evaluating the impacts of education CCTs. Section 5 integrates and updates the extensive evidence to date on the impacts of education CCTs on various outcome domains over the life cycle, and provides the most comprehensive view to date on learning impacts by meta-analyzing new evidence from more than 30 studies—substantially more than prior reviews of the literature. Section 6 reviews the evidence on indirect and general equilibrium effects. Section 7 presents a simple model of costs commonly used in the literature, which we extend to analyze cost-effectiveness for a subset of programs. Section 8 concludes and highlights open questions for future research.]]></description><author>Sandra García, Juan Saavedra</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29758</guid></item><item><title>Reinforcing RCTs with Multiple Priors while Learning about External Validity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29756</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Frederico Finan, Demian Pouzo.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> This paper presents a framework for how to incorporate prior sources of information into the design of a sequential experiment. These sources can include previous experiments, expert opinions, or the experimenter's own introspection. We formalize this problem using a multi-prior Bayesian approach that maps each source to a Bayesian model. These models are aggregated according to their associated posterior probabilities. We evaluate a broad of policy rules according to three criteria: whether the experimenter learns the parameters of the payoff distributions, the probability that the experimenter chooses the wrong treatment when deciding to stop the experiment, and the average rewards. We show that our framework exhibits several nice finite sample properties, including robustness to any source that is not externally valid.]]></description><author>Frederico Finan, Demian Pouzo</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29756</guid></item><item><title>Valuing the Time of the Self-Employed</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29752</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel J. Agness, Travis Baseler, Sylvain Chassang, Pascaline Dupas, Erik Snowberg.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> People’s value for their own time is a key input in evaluating public policies: evaluations should account for time taken away from work or leisure as a result of policy. Using rich choice data collected from farming households in western Kenya, we show that households exhibit non-transitive preferences consistent with behavioral features such as loss aversion and self-serving bias. As a result, neither market wages nor standard valuation techniques (such as the Becker-DeGroot-Marschak—BDM—mechanism of Becker et al., 1964) correctly measure participants’ value of time. Using a structural model, we identify the mix of behavioral features driving our choice data. We find that these features distort choices when exchanging cash either for time or for goods. Our model estimates suggest that valuing the time of the self-employed at 60% of the market wage is a reasonable rule of thumb.]]></description><author>Daniel J. Agness, Travis Baseler, Sylvain Chassang, Pascaline Dupas, Erik Snowberg</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29752</guid></item><item><title>Assessing Misallocation in Agriculture: Plots versus Farms</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29749</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Fernando M. Aragón, Diego Restuccia, Juan Pablo Rud.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We assess the extent and cost of misallocation in agriculture in less-developed countries comparing the analysis at the plot and farm levels. Using detailed data from Uganda, we show that the plot-level analysis leads to extremely large estimates of reallocation gains, even after adjusting for measurement error and unobserved heterogeneity. These results reflect two empirical limitations of the plot as unit of analysis: excess measurement error and near constant returns to scale production estimates. We find limited evidence of substantial measurement error at the farm level.]]></description><author>Fernando M. Aragón, Diego Restuccia, Juan Pablo Rud</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29749</guid></item><item><title>Two-way Fixed Effects and Differences-in-Differences Estimators with Several Treatments</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29734</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&#039;Haultfoeuille.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We study regressions with period and group fixed effects and several treatment variables. Under a parallel trends assumption, the coefficient on each treatment identifies the sum of two terms. The first term is a weighted sum of the effect of that treatment in each group and period, with weights that may be negative and sum to one. The second term is a sum of the effects of the other treatments, with weights summing to zero. Accordingly, coefficients in those regressions are not robust to heterogeneous effects, and may be contaminated by the effect of other treatments. We propose alternative differences-in-differences estimators. To estimate, say, the effect of the first treatment, our estimators compare the outcome evolution of a group whose first treatment changes while its other treatments remain unchanged, to control groups whose treatments all remain unchanged, and with the same baseline treatments or treatments' history as the switching group. Those carefully selected comparisons are robust to heterogeneous effects, and do not suffer from the contamination problem.]]></description><author>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&amp;#039;Haultfoeuille</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29734</guid></item><item><title>Empirical Strategies in Economics: Illuminating the Path from Cause to Effect</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29726</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Angrist.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> The view that empirical strategies in economics should be transparent and credible now goes almost without saying. The local average treatment effects (LATE) framework for causal inference helped make this so. The LATE theorem tells us for whom particular instrumental variables (IV) and regression discontinuity estimates are valid. This lecture uses several empirical examples, mostly involving charter and exam schools, to highlight the value of LATE. A surprising exclusion restriction, an assumption central to the LATE interpretation of IV estimates, is shown to explain why enrollment at Chicago exam schools reduces student achievement. I also make two broader points: IV exclusion restrictions formalize commitment to clear and consistent explanations of reduced-form causal effects; compelling applications demonstrate the power of simple empirical strategies to generate new causal knowledge.]]></description><author>Joshua Angrist</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29726</guid></item><item><title>Management and Misallocation in Mexico</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29717</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicholas Bloom, Leonardo Iacovone, Mariana Pereira-Lopez, John Van Reenen.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We argue that greater misallocation is a key driver of the worse management practices in Mexico compared to the US. These management practices are strongly associated with higher productivity, growth, trade, and innovation. One indicator of greater misallocation in Mexico is the weaker size-management relationship compared to the US, particularly in the highly distorted Mexican service sector. Second, the size-management relationship is weaker in smaller markets, measured by distance to the US for manufacturing firms and population density for service firms. Third, municipalities with weaker institutions, measured by contract enforcement, crime, and corruption, have a weaker size-management relation. These results are consistent with frictions lowering aggregate management quality and productivity.]]></description><author>Nicholas Bloom, Leonardo Iacovone, Mariana Pereira-Lopez, John Van Reenen</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29717</guid></item><item><title>Incentive-Compatible Critical Values</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29702</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adam McCloskey, Pascal Michaillat.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Statistically significant results are more rewarded than insignificant ones, so researchers have the incentive to pursue statistical significance. Such p-hacking reduces the informativeness of hypothesis tests by making significant results much more common than they are supposed to be in the absence of true significance. To address this problem, we construct critical values of test statistics such that, if these values are used to determine significance, and if researchers optimally respond to these new significance standards, then significant results occur with the desired frequency. Such incentive-compatible critical values allow for p-hacking so they are larger than classical critical values. Using evidence from the social and medical sciences, we find that the incentive-compatible critical value for any test and any significance level is the classical critical value for the same test with approximately one fifth of the significance level—a form of Bonferroni correction. For instance, for a z-test with a significance level of 5%, the incentive-compatible critical value is 2.31 instead of 1.65 if the test is one-sided and 2.57 instead of 1.96 if the test is two-sided.]]></description><author>Adam McCloskey, Pascal Michaillat</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29702</guid></item><item><title>Traditional Supernatural Beliefs and Prosocial Behavior</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29695</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Etienne Le Rossignol, Sara Lowes, Nathan Nunn.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> In sub-Saharan Africa, traditional supernatural beliefs, including belief in witchcraft, black magic, or fetishism, are widespread. Some have hypothesized that these beliefs help to sustain cooperative behavior in a setting where the state is often absent. Others have documented that, at least at a macro-level, such beliefs are negatively associated with prosocial behavior. We contribute to a better understanding of the causal effects of these traditional supernatural beliefs by using lab-in-the-field experiments in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Participants complete a range of experimental tasks where one player chooses whether to act in a prosocial manner towards another player. Participants are randomly assigned to another player that has either a strong or weak belief in witchcraft, and this information is known by the players. We find that participants act less prosocially towards randomly-assigned partners who believe more strongly in witchcraft. We also find that antisocial behavior is more socially acceptable and prosocial behavior less socially acceptable when playing with a partner who believes more strongly in witchcraft. Our findings suggest that the negative relationship between witchcraft and prosocial outcomes observed in the data may, in fact, be due to the causal effect of the presence of traditional supernatural beliefs on people’s behavior.]]></description><author>Etienne Le Rossignol, Sara Lowes, Nathan Nunn</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29695</guid></item><item><title>State-building on the Margin: An Urban Experiment in Medellín</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29692</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher Blattman, Gustavo Duncan, Benjamin Lessing, Santiago Tobon.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Medellín's government wanted to raise its efficacy, legitimacy, and control. The city identified 80 neighborhoods with weak state presence and competing armed actors. In half, they increased non-police street presence tenfold for two years, offering social services and dispute resolution. In places where the state was initially weakest, the intervention did not work, mainly because the government struggled to deliver on its promises. Where the state began stronger, the government raised opinions of its services and legitimacy. If there are indeed low marginal returns to investing in capacity in the least-governed areas, this could produce increasing returns to state-building.]]></description><author>Christopher Blattman, Gustavo Duncan, Benjamin Lessing, Santiago Tobon</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29692</guid></item><item><title>Two-Way Fixed Effects and Differences-in-Differences with Heterogeneous Treatment Effects: A Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29691</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&#039;Haultfoeuille.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Linear regressions with period and group fixed effects are widely used to estimate policies' effects: 26 of the 100 most cited papers published by the American Economic Review from 2015 to 2019 estimate such regressions. It has recently been show that those regressions may produce misleading estimates, if the policy's effect is heterogeneous between groups or over time, as is often the case. This survey reviews a fast-growing literature that documents this issue, and that proposes alternative estimators robust to heterogeneous effects.]]></description><author>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&amp;#039;Haultfoeuille</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29691</guid></item><item><title>Vaccine Allocation Priorities Using Disease Surveillance and Economic Data</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29682</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anup Malani, Satej Soman, Sabareesh Ramachandran, Alice Chen, Darius N. Lakdawalla.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Vaccination is a critical tool, along with suppression and treatment, for controlling epidemics such as SARS-CoV-2.  To maximize the impact of vaccination, doses should be allocated to the highest value targets, accounting for health and potential economic benefits.  We examine what allocation strategy is optimal and how to translate that strategy into actionable procurement decisions in the context of India.  We compare 3 different allocation strategies (oldest first, highest contact rate first, random order) across 4 outcomes (lives saved, life-years saved, value of statistical lives saved, value of statistical life-years saved).  We make 3 methodological contributions.  First, we estimate the incremental health benefit of vaccination using novel, local seroprevalence data from India.  Second, we estimate the value of statistical life-years using disaggregated, monthly data on consumption during the pandemic.  Third, and most importantly, we estimate social demand curves for vaccines that can practically guide government procurement decisions.  Our analysis yields 4 novel findings.  First, the need to speed-up vaccination does not justify deviation from elderly-first prioritization.  Second, much of the value of vaccination comes from improvements in consumption rather than longevity.  Moreover, vaccination increases the value of a life year because it increases consumption.  Third, social demand for vaccination falls over time as natural immunity from infections increases.  Therefore, the slower a country vaccinates its population, the fewer doses it should procure.  Fourth, there is enough variation in consumption and infection risk that it makes sense to vaccinate some areas before others.  Our approach of connecting epidemiological models and data on health and consumption to economic valuation methods generalizes to other infection control strategies, such as suppression, and public health crises, such as influenza and HIV.]]></description><author>Anup Malani, Satej Soman, Sabareesh Ramachandran, Alice Chen, Darius N. Lakdawalla</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29682</guid></item><item><title>Understanding Rural Households’ Time Use in a Developing Setting: Validating a Low-Cost Time Use Module</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29671</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Erica M. Field, Rohini Pande, Natalia Rigol, Simone G. Schaner, Elena M. Stacy, Charity M. Troyer Moore.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Time use data facilitate deeper understanding of individual labor supply choices, especially for women, who are more likely to engage in unpaid care and home production. However, traditional time use data collection methods are time-consuming, expensive and susceptible to significant attrition. To address these concerns, we develop an abbreviated, low-cost time use survey module designed for low-literacy populations. It captures contextually-determined broad time use categories of interest to researchers - in our case, time allocations across market work, household labor, and leisure. Using survey experiments in the field, we show that, relative to the widely-used assisted diary approach, the new module is lower cost and relatively more accurate in capturing individuals’ average time use. Its primary shortcomings are its limited ability to capture short duration activities and simultaneous activities. Using the example of passive childcare, we show how module design can provide accurate information on multitasking for an identified category of interest.]]></description><author>Erica M. Field, Rohini Pande, Natalia Rigol, Simone G. Schaner, Elena M. Stacy, Charity M. Troyer Moore</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29671</guid></item><item><title>Land Security and Mobility Frictions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29666</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tasso Adamopoulos, Loren Brandt, Chaoran Chen, Diego Restuccia, Xiaoyun Wei.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Developing countries are characterized by frictions that impede the mobility of workers across occupations and space. We disentangle the role of insecure property rights from other labor mobility frictions for the reallocation of labor from agriculture to non-agriculture and from rural to urban areas. We combine rich household and individual-level panel data from China and an equilibrium quantitative framework that features the sorting of workers across locations and occupations. We explicitly model the farming household and the endogenous decisions of who operates the family farm and who potentially migrates, capturing an additional channel of selection within the household. We find that land insecurity has substantial negative effects on agricultural productivity and structural change, raising the share of households operating farms by almost 30 percentage points and depressing agricultural productivity by more than 10 percent. Quantitatively, land insecurity is as important as all other labor mobility frictions. We measure a sharp reduction in overall labor mobility barriers over 2004-2018 in the Chinese economy, all of which can be accounted for by improved land security, consistent with reforms covering rural land in China during the period.]]></description><author>Tasso Adamopoulos, Loren Brandt, Chaoran Chen, Diego Restuccia, Xiaoyun Wei</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29666</guid></item><item><title>A Cross-Country Comparison of Old Age Financial Readiness in Asian Countries vs. the United States: The Case of Japan and the Republic of Korea</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29649</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Isaac Ehrlich, Yong Yin.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We pursue a cross-country comparison of relative financial readiness of older households in Japan and the Republic of Korea relative to the US.  Our comparative analysis, using macro-level and harmonized longitudinal household financial data, covers the principal financial channels of old age support: public and private pension plans, family support, and self-management of private financial portfolios. We find that while all three countries have similar public pension systems, older Americans benefit from more developed and better-funded public and private pension systems, as well as individual management of risky financial portfolios. We find that educational and health attainments of household heads and household wealth lead to a greater tendency to hold and manage risky assets. Our decomposition analysis also shows that the gap in stock ownership in Asian countries relative to the US is attributable to lower development levels of financial and pension markets. However, these gaps are shrinking more recently.]]></description><author>Isaac Ehrlich, Yong Yin</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29649</guid></item><item><title>Technology and Resilience</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29644</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Diego A. Comin, Marcio Cruz, Xavier Cirera, Kyung Min Lee, Jesica Torres.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper estimates the impact of technology sophistication pre-COVID-19 on the performance of firms during the early stages of the pandemic. We exploit a unique data covering firms from Brazil, Senegal, and Vietnam using a treatment effect mediation framework to decompose the results into a direct and an indirect effect. Increasing pre-pandemic technology sophistication by one standard deviation is associated with 3.8pp higher sales. Both effects are positive, but the direct effect is about 5 times larger than the indirect effect. The total effect on sales is markedly nonlinear with significantly smaller estimates of the reduction in sales for firms with more sophisticated pre-pandemic technology. Our results are robust to different measures of digital responses and matching estimators.]]></description><author>Diego A. Comin, Marcio Cruz, Xavier Cirera, Kyung Min Lee, Jesica Torres</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29644</guid></item><item><title>Revealing Corruption: Firm and Worker Level Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29627</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Emanuele Colonnelli, Spyridon Lagaras, Jacopo Ponticelli, Mounu Prem, Margarita Tsoutsoura.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We study how the disclosure of corrupt practices affects the growth of firms involved in illegal interactions with the government using randomized audits of public procurement in Brazil. On average, firms exposed by the anti-corruption program grow larger after the audits, despite experiencing a decrease in procurement contracts. We manually collect new data on the details of thousands of corruption cases, through which we uncover a large heterogeneity in our firm-level effects depending on the degree of involvement in corruption cases. Using investment-, loan-, and worker- level data, we show that the average exposed firms adapt to the loss of government contracts by changing their investment strategy. They increase capital investment and borrow more to finance such investment, while there is no change in their internal organization.  We provide qualitative support to our results by conducting new face-to-face surveys with business owners of government-dependent firms.]]></description><author>Emanuele Colonnelli, Spyridon Lagaras, Jacopo Ponticelli, Mounu Prem, Margarita Tsoutsoura</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29627</guid></item><item><title>Blackouts in the Developing World: The Role of Wholesale Electricity Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29610</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Akshaya Jha ⓡ, Louis Preonas ⓡ, Fiona Burlig ⓡ.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Blackouts impose substantial economic costs in developing countries. This paper advances a new explanation for their continued prevalence: unlike in high-income countries, where regulatory mandates require utilities to satisfy all electricity demand, utilities in developing countries respond to wholesale electricity prices. As a result, misallocation of output across power plants can decrease the quantity of electricity supplied to end-users. We provide empirical support for this explanation using novel data from India, home to the world’s third-largest electricity sector. In contrast to the developed world, we find that Indian wholesale demand is downward-sloping. Reducing supply-side misallocation would increase electricity supply for the average household by 1.7 percent (enough to power 4.6 million additional households). Justifying a mandate that utilities must satisfy all end-use demand would require consumers to value electricity far above the cost of diesel backup generation. However, such a mandate would likely be cost-effective if paired with supply-side reforms.]]></description><author>Akshaya Jha ⓡ, Louis Preonas ⓡ, Fiona Burlig ⓡ</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29610</guid></item><item><title>Innovation Networks and Innovation Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29607</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ernest Liu, Song Ma.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study the optimal allocation of R&amp;D resources in an endogenous growth model with an innovation network, through which one sector’s past innovations may benefit other sectors’ future innovations. First, we provide closed-form sufficient statistics for the optimal path of R&amp;D resource allocation, and we show that planners valuing long-term growth should allocate more R&amp;D toward key sectors that are upstream in the innovation network. Second, we extend to an open-economy setting and illustrate an incentive for countries to free-ride on fundamental technologies: an economy more reliant on foreign knowledge spillovers has less incentive to direct resources toward innovation-upstream sectors, leading to cross-country differences in unilaterally optimal R&amp;D allocations across sectors. Third, we build the global innovation network based on over 30 million global patents and establish its empirical importance for knowledge spillovers. Fourth, we apply the model to evaluate R&amp;D allocations across countries and time. Adopting optimal R&amp;D allocations can generate substantial welfare improvements across the globe. For the United States, R&amp;D misallocation accounts for about 0.68 percentage points of missing annual growth since the 2000s.]]></description><author>Ernest Liu, Song Ma</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29607</guid></item><item><title>Inequality in India Declined During COVID</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29597</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Arpit Gupta, Anup Malani, Bartosz Woda.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We use a large, representative panel data set from India with monthly data on household finances to examine the incidence of economic harms during the COVID pandemic.  We observe a sharp spike in poverty, peaking during India's sharp but short lockdown.  However, there was a striking decrease in income inequality outside the lockdown.  There was a smaller decrease in consumption inequality, likely due to consumption smoothing.  Evidence supports two mechanisms for the decline in income inequality: the capital income of top-quartile earners covaries more with aggregate income, and demand for labor fell more for higher quartiles.]]></description><author>Arpit Gupta, Anup Malani, Bartosz Woda</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29597</guid></item><item><title>International Evidence of Strengthening Taxes and Spending For Sustainable Development</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29594</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Donghyun Park.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We trace the linkages between the episodes of fiscal expansion and consolidation in 72 advanced and emerging and developing economies. The findings suggest that fiscal expansions are positively associated with economic growth, which in turn is positively linked with better sustainable development outcomes. The association between fiscal consolidation and growth as well as the sustainable development indicators, however, is not clear-cut. Jointly, more tax revenues and expenditures, together with better governance help explain the association between economic growth and inclusive development. High-income, high-tax-revenue, and manufacture-exporting economies have made significant progress on reducing disease-linked mortality and improving environment protection along with economic growth. Meanwhile, emerging and developing, low-tax-revenue, and commodity-exporting economies have gained notable improvement in poverty reduction, pre-primary enrolment and access to basic sanitation services and clean cooking fuels and technologies, and lowering bribery incidence. On average, the sampled economies have persistently achieved better primary goals such as sanitation, clean fuels and technologies. Achievements in mortality reduction, and environmental protection goals are shown more recently.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Donghyun Park</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29594</guid></item><item><title>Forced Displacement and Human Capital: Evidence from Separated Siblings</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29589</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Giorgio Chiovelli, Stelios Michalopoulos, Elias Papaioannou, Sandra Sequeira.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We examine the impact of conflict-driven displacement on human capital. We focus on the Mozambican civil war (1977–1992), during which more than four million civilians fled to the countryside, cities, and refugee camps and settlements in neighboring countries. We leverage the full post-war census to compare siblings separated during the war, using those who stayed behind as a counterfactual to one’s displacement path. Uprooted children register higher investments in education. Second, we quantify the relative importance of place-based and displacement effects. The latter increases education and decreases attachment to agriculture by the same rate as being exposed to an environment approximately one standard deviation more developed than one’s birthplace. Third, we conduct a survey in Nampula, whose population doubled during the civil war. Those who fled to the city have significantly higher education than their siblings who remained in the countryside and they converged to the levels of schooling of non-mover urban-born individuals. However, those displaced exhibit significantly lower social/civic capital and have worse mental health, even three decades after the war. These findings reveal that displacement shocks can trigger human capital investments, breaking links with subsistence agriculture, but at the cost of long-lasting, social, and psychological traumas.]]></description><author>Giorgio Chiovelli, Stelios Michalopoulos, Elias Papaioannou, Sandra Sequeira</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29589</guid></item><item><title>Information, Intermediaries, and International Migration</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29588</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Samuel Bazzi, Lisa Cameron, Simone G. Schaner, Firman Witoelar.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Job seekers often face substantial information frictions related to potential job quality. This is especially true in international labor markets, where intermediaries match prospective migrants with employers abroad. We conducted a randomized trial in Indonesia to explore how information about intermediary quality shapes migration choices and outcomes. Information reduces the migration rate, lowering use of low-quality intermediaries. However, workers who migrate receive better pre-departure preparation and have higher-quality job experiences abroad, despite no change in occupation or destination. Information does not change intentions to migrate or beliefs about the return to migration or intermediary quality. Nor does selection explain the improved outcomes for workers who choose to migrate with the information. Together, our findings are consistent with an increase in the option value of search: with better ability to differentiate offer quality, workers become choosier and ultimately have better migration experiences. This offers a new perspective on the importance of information and matching frictions in global labor markets.]]></description><author>Samuel Bazzi, Lisa Cameron, Simone G. Schaner, Firman Witoelar</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29588</guid></item><item><title>Private but Misunderstood? Evidence on Measuring Intimate Partner Violence via Self-Interviewing in Rural Liberia and Malawi</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29584</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Sungho Park, Shilpa Aggarwal, Dahyeon Jeong, Naresh Kumar, Jonathan Robinson, Alan Spearot.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Women may under-report intimate partner violence (IPV) in surveys due to a variety of social and psychological factors. To understand if anonymized interviewing can allay this concern, we conduct a measurement experiment in rural Liberia and Malawi in which women were asked IPV questions via either self-interviewing (SI) or face-to-face interviewing (FTFI) with an enumerator. We find that about a third of women incorrectly answer basic screening questions over SI, and that it generates placebo effects on innocuous questions even for those who "pass" screening. Because the probability of responding "yes" to any specific IPV question is less than 50%, and that IPV is typically reported as an index (reporting yes to at least one question in a category of violence), such misunderstanding will tend to increase IPV reporting. In Malawi, we find that SI dramatically increases reported IPV, with the incidence of any type of IPV increasing by 13 percentage points on a base of 20%; in Liberia, we find an insignificant and modest increase of 4 percentage points on a base of 39%. Our results suggest SI may spuriously increase reported IPV rates.]]></description><author>David Sungho Park, Shilpa Aggarwal, Dahyeon Jeong, Naresh Kumar, Jonathan Robinson, Alan Spearot</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29584</guid></item><item><title>Absenteeism, Productivity, and Relational Contracts Inside the Firm</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29581</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Achyuta Adhvaryu, Jean-François Gauthier, Anant Nyshadham, Jorge A. Tamayo.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study relational contracts among managers using unique data that tracks transfers of workers across teams in Indian ready-made garment factories. We focus on how relational contracts help managers cope with worker absenteeism shocks, which are frequent, often large, weakly correlated across teams, and which substantially reduce team productivity. Together these facts imply gains from sharing workers. We show that managers respond to shocks by lending and borrowing workers in a manner consistent with relational contracting, but many potentially beneficial transfers are unrealized. This is because managers’ primary relationships are with a very small subset of potential partners. A borrowing event study around main trading partners’ separations from the firm reinforces the importance of relationships. We show robustness to excluding worker moves least likely to reflect relational borrowing responses to idiosyncratic absenteeism shocks. Counterfactual simulations reveal large gains to reducing costs associated with forming and maintaining additional relationships among managers.]]></description><author>Achyuta Adhvaryu, Jean-François Gauthier, Anant Nyshadham, Jorge A. Tamayo</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29581</guid></item><item><title>Effect of Health Insurance in India: A Randomized Controlled Trial</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29576</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anup Malani, Phoebe Holtzman, Kosuke Imai, Cynthia Kinnan, Morgen Miller, Shailender Swaminathan, Alessandra Voena, Bartosz Woda, Gabriella Conti.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We report on a large randomized controlled trial of hospital insurance for above-poverty-line Indian households.  Households were assigned to free insurance, sale of insurance, sale plus cash transfer, or control.  To estimate spillovers, the fraction of households offered insurance varied across villages.  The opportunity to purchase insurance led to 59.91% uptake and access to free insurance to 78.71% uptake.  Access increased insurance utilization. Positive spillover effects on utilization suggest learning from peers.  Many beneficiaries were unable to use insurance, demonstrating hurdles to expanding access via insurance.  Across a range of health measures, we estimate no significant impacts on health.]]></description><author>Anup Malani, Phoebe Holtzman, Kosuke Imai, Cynthia Kinnan, Morgen Miller, Shailender Swaminathan, Alessandra Voena, Bartosz Woda, Gabriella Conti</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29576</guid></item><item><title>Is Digital Credit Filling a Hole or Digging a Hole? Evidence from Malawi</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29573</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Valentina Brailovskaya, Pascaline Dupas, Jonathan Robinson.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Digital credit has expanded rapidly in Africa, mostly in the form of short-term, high-interest loans offered via mobile money. Loan terms are often opaque and consumer financial literacy is low, providing opportunities for predatory lending. A regression discontinuity analysis shows no negative effect of access to digital loans on financial well-being, but the majority of borrowers fail to repay on time and incur high late fees. We randomize exposure to a short phone-based financial literacy intervention. The intervention improved knowledge and marginally improved loan repayment but increased loan demand, increasing overall default risk.]]></description><author>Valentina Brailovskaya, Pascaline Dupas, Jonathan Robinson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29573</guid></item><item><title>Time Use and Gender in Africa in Times of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29571</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Taryn Dinkelman, L. Rachel Ngai.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Many African countries are still in the early stages of structural transformation. Typically, as economies move through the structural transformation, activities once conducted within the household are outsourced to the market. This has particular implications for women’s time use. In this paper, we document that current patterns of female time use in home production in several African countries closely resemble historical time use patterns in the US. We highlight two stylized facts about women’s time use in Africa. First, in North Africa, women spend very few hours in market work and female labor force participation overall is extremely low. Second, although extensive margin participation of women is high in sub-Saharan Africa, women tend to work in the market for only a few hours each week, with the rest of their work hours spent in home production. These two facts suggest two types of constraints that could slow down the reallocation of female time from home to market as economies grow: Social norms related to women’s market work, and a lack of infrastructure (e.g. household infrastructure and childcare facilities) to facilitate marketizing home production. We discuss recent empirical evidence related to each set of constraints and highlight new avenues for research.]]></description><author>Taryn Dinkelman, L. Rachel Ngai</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29571</guid></item><item><title>Labor Productivity Growth and Industrialization in Africa</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29570</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Margaret S. McMillan, Albert Zeufack.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Manufacturing has made an important contribution to raising living standards in many parts of the world. Concerns about premature deindustrialization have made some observers skeptical about the potential for manufacturing to play this role in Africa. But employment in African manufacturing has grown rapidly over the past 20 years. These employment gains have been accompanied by: (i) large increases in the number of small manufacturing firms; (ii) limited employment gains in large firms; and (iii) robust labor productivity growth in Africa’s large firms. Limited employment growth in Africa’s large manufacturing firms is partly a result of the capital intensity of the manufacturing sub-sectors in which African countries are most engaged – the processing of resources, and partly a result of rising capital intensity in manufacturing. The potential for manufacturing to raise living standards in Africa depends on indirect job creation by large firms through backward and forward linkages and increasing labor productivity in small firms.]]></description><author>Margaret S. McMillan, Albert Zeufack</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29570</guid></item><item><title>Randomization for Causality, Ethnography for Mechanisms: Illiquid Savings for Liquor in an Autarkic Society</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29566</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ricardo Godoy, Dean Karlan, Jonathan Zinman.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> What should researchers do when confronted with surprising results? Financial access innovations usually leave “temptation” spending unaffected or reduced. However, we found that promotion of savings lockboxes in a largely autarkic society increased alcohol consumption and blood pressure, despite no one reporting intentions to save for alcohol. To probe mechanisms that could explain this pattern, we then used ethnographic methods, including direct observations of drinking (“scans”) and debriefing interviews to discuss the earlier trial results. We learn that sponsoring drinks confers prestige, but the stigma attached to drinking by outsiders likely discouraged reporting intentions to save for it.]]></description><author>Ricardo Godoy, Dean Karlan, Jonathan Zinman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29566</guid></item><item><title>Job Training Through Turmoil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29565</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Adriana D. Kugler, Mikko I. Silliman.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We follow the labor market outcomes of applicants who were randomized into job training a year and a half before the pandemic through the subsequent economic turmoil that resulted from COVID-19. Despite persistently improved labor market outcomes of training participants prior to March 2020, we show that job losses resulting from the pandemic washed away all the benefits of the program. A year and a half after the initial scars of the pandemic, there are no visible signs of recovery of trainees’ labor market outcomes.]]></description><author>Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Adriana D. Kugler, Mikko I. Silliman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29565</guid></item><item><title>Unlocking the Benefits of Credit through Saving</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29542</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sanghamitra W. Mukherjee, Lauren F. Bergquist, Marshall Burke, Edward Miguel.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Access to microcredit has been shown to generate only modest average benefits for recipient households. We study whether other financial market frictions—in particular, lack of access to a safe place to save—might limit credit's benefits. Working with Kenyan farmers, we cross-randomize access to a simple savings product with a harvest-time loan. Among farmers offered a loan, the additional offer of a savings lockbox increased farm investment by 11% and household consumption by 7%. Results suggest that financial market frictions can interact in important ways and that multifaceted financial access programs might unlock dynamic household gains.]]></description><author>Sanghamitra W. Mukherjee, Lauren F. Bergquist, Marshall Burke, Edward Miguel</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29542</guid></item><item><title>“Golden Ages”: A Tale of the Labor Markets in China and the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29523</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hanming Fang, Xincheng Qiu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the labor markets in China and the United States, the two largest economies in the world, by examining the evolution of their cross-sectional age-earnings profiles during the past thirty years. We find that, first, the peak age in the cross-sectional age-earnings profiles, which we refer to as the “golden age,” stayed almost constant at around 45-50 in the U.S., but decreased sharply from 55 to around 35 in China; second, the age-specific earnings grew drastically in China, but stayed almost stagnant in the U.S.; third, the cross-sectional and life-cycle age-earnings profiles were remarkably similar in the U.S., but differed substantially in China. We propose and empirically implement a decomposition framework to infer from the repeated cross-sectional earnings data the experience effect (i.e., human capital accumulation over the life cycle), the cohort effect (i.e., inter-cohort human capital growth), and the time effect (i.e., changes in the human capital rental prices over time), under an identifying assumption that the growth of the experience effect stops at the end of one's working career. The decomposition suggests that China has experienced a much larger inter-cohort productivity growth and higher increase in the rental price to human capital, but lower returns to experience, compared to the U.S. We also use the inferred components to revisit several important and classical applications in macroeconomics and labor economics, including growth accounting and the estimation of TFP growth, and the college wage premium and skill-biased technical change.]]></description><author>Hanming Fang, Xincheng Qiu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29523</guid></item><item><title>Harvesting the Rain: The Adoption of Environmental Technologies in the Sahel</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29518</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jenny C. Aker, Kelsey Jack.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Many agricultural and environmental technologies require large upfront investments in exchange for longer-term benefits. This time profile of costs and benefits makes adoption particularly sensitive to liquidity and credit constraints, which are prevalent in low-income settings. We test the importance of these barriers to the adoption of an agricultural technique that helps reduce land degradation and restore soil fertility in Niger. We find little evidence that liquidity or credit constraints deter adoption: instead, providing farmers with training increases the share of adopters by over 90 percentage points, whereas adding conditional or unconditional cash transfers has no additional effect. Adoption increases agricultural output, reduces land turnover and leads to adoption spillovers up to three years after treatment. These results imply that training can be a cost-effective and scalable means of promoting the adoption of profitable technologies.]]></description><author>Jenny C. Aker, Kelsey Jack</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29518</guid></item><item><title>Learning versus Unlearning: An Experiment on Retractions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29512</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Duarte Gonçalves, Jonathan Libgober, Jack Willis.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Widely discredited ideas nevertheless persist. Why do we fail to "unlearn"? We study one explanation: beliefs are resistant to retractions (the revoking of earlier information). Our experimental design allows us to identify updating from retractions - unlearning - and to compare it with updating from equivalent new information - learning. Across different kinds of retractions - for instance, those consistent or contradictory with the prior, or those occurring when prior beliefs are either extreme or moderate - subjects do not fully unlearn from retractions and update approximately one-third less from them than from equivalent new information. While we document a number of well-known biases in belief updating in our data, our results are inconsistent with any explanation that does not treat retractions as inherently different. Instead, our analysis suggests that retractions are harder to process, for instance, due to the intimate reliance on conditional reasoning.]]></description><author>Duarte Gonçalves, Jonathan Libgober, Jack Willis</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29512</guid></item><item><title>Globalization and the Ladder of Development: Pushed to the Top or Held at the Bottom?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29500</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Atkin, Arnaud Costinot, Masao Fukui.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the relationship between international trade and development in a model where countries differ in their capability, goods differ in their complexity, and capability growth is a function of a country’s pattern of specialization. Theoretically, we show that it is possible for international trade to increase capability growth in all countries and, in turn, to push all countries up the development ladder. This occurs because: (i) the average complexity of a country’s industry mix raises its capability growth, and (ii) foreign competition is tougher in less complex sectors for all countries. Empirically, we provide causal evidence consistent with (i) using the entry of countries into the World Trade Organization as an instrumental variable for other countries’ patterns of specialization. The opposite of (ii), however, appears to hold in the data. Through the lens of our model, these two empirical observations imply dynamic welfare losses from trade that are small for the median country, but pervasive and large among a number of African countries.]]></description><author>David Atkin, Arnaud Costinot, Masao Fukui</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29500</guid></item><item><title>Converging to Convergence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29484</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Kremer, Jack Willis, Yang You.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Empirical tests in the 1990s found little evidence of poor countries catching up with rich - unconditional convergence - since the 1960s, and divergence over longer periods. This stylized fact spurred several developments in growth theory, including AK models, poverty trap models, and the concept of convergence conditional on determinants of steady-state income. We revisit these findings, using the subsequent 25 years as an out-of-sample test, and document a trend towards unconditional convergence since 1990 and convergence since 2000, driven by both faster catch-up growth and slower growth of the frontier. During the same period, many of the correlates of growth - human capital, policies, institutions, and culture - also converged substantially and moved in the direction associated with higher income. Were these changes related? Using the omitted variable bias formula, we decompose the gap between unconditional and conditional convergence as the product of two cross-sectional slopes. First, correlate-income slopes, which remained largely stable since 1990. Second, growth-correlate slopes controlling for income - the coefficients of growth regressions - which remained stable for fundamentals of the Solow model (investment rate, population growth, and human capital) but which flattened substantially for other correlates, leading unconditional convergence to converge towards conditional convergence.]]></description><author>Michael Kremer, Jack Willis, Yang You</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29484</guid></item><item><title>Cooperation in the Commons: Community-based Rangeland Management in Namibia</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29469</link><description><![CDATA[<i>D. Layne Coppock, Lucas Crowley, Susan L. Durham, Dylan Groves, Julian C. Jamison, Dean Karlan, Brien E. Norton, R. Douglas Ramsey.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Classic theories suggest that common pool resources are subject to overexploitation. Community-based resource management approaches may ameliorate “tragedy of the commons” effects. Using a randomized evaluation in Namibia’s communal rangelands, we find that a comprehensive four-year program to support community-based rangeland and cattle management led to persistent and large improvements for eight of thirteen indices of social and behavioral outcomes. Effects on rangeland health, cattle productivity and household economics, however, were either negative or nil. Positive impacts on community resource management may have been offset by communities’ inability to control grazing by non-participating herds and inhibited by an unresponsive rangeland sub-system. This juxtaposition, in which measurable improvements in community resource management did not translate into better outcomes for households or rangeland health, demonstrates the fragility of the causal pathway from program implementation to intended socioeconomic and environmental outcomes. It also points to challenges for improving climate change–adaptation strategies.]]></description><author>D. Layne Coppock, Lucas Crowley, Susan L. Durham, Dylan Groves, Julian C. Jamison, Dean Karlan, Brien E. Norton, R. Douglas Ramsey</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29469</guid></item><item><title>AI-tocracy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29466</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Beraja, Andrew Kao, David Y. Yang, Noam Yuchtman.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Can frontier innovation be sustained under autocracy? We argue that innovation and autocracy can be mutually reinforcing when: (i) the new technology bolsters the autocrat’s power; and (ii) the autocrat’s demand for the technology stimulates further innovation in applications beyond those benefiting it directly. We test for such a mutually reinforcing relationship in the context of facial recognition AI in China. To do so, we gather comprehensive data on AI firms and government procurement contracts, as well as on social unrest across China during the last decade. We first show that autocrats benefit from AI: local unrest leads to greater government procurement of facial recognition AI, and increased AI procurement suppresses subsequent unrest. We then show that AI innovation benefits from autocrats’ suppression of unrest: the contracted AI firms innovate more both for the government and commercial markets. Taken together, these results suggest the possibility of sustained AI innovation under the Chinese regime: AI innovation entrenches the regime, and the regime’s investment in AI for political control stimulates further frontier innovation.]]></description><author>Martin Beraja, Andrew Kao, David Y. Yang, Noam Yuchtman</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29466</guid></item><item><title>Firm-Level Upgrading in Developing Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29461</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Eric Verhoogen.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In principle, firms in developing countries benefit from the fact that advanced technologies and products have already been developed in industrialized countries and can simply be adopted, a process often referred to as industrial upgrading. But for many firms this advantage remains elusive. What is getting in the way? This paper reviews recent firm-level empirical research on the determinants of upgrading in developing countries. The first part focuses on how to define and measure various dimensions of upgrading --- learning, quality upgrading, technology adoption, and product innovation. The second part takes stock of recent micro-empirical evidence on the drivers of upgrading, classifying them as output-side drivers, input-side drivers, or drivers of know-how. The review concludes with some thoughts about promising directions for research in the area.]]></description><author>Eric Verhoogen</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29461</guid></item><item><title>Some Children Left Behind: Variation in the Effects of an Educational Intervention</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29459</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Julie Buhl-Wiggers, Jason T. Kerwin, Juan S. Muñoz-Morales, Jeffrey A. Smith, Rebecca Thornton.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We document substantial variation in the effects of a highly-effective literacy pro-gram in northern Uganda. The program increases test scores by 1.40 SDs on average, but standard statistical bounds show that the impact standard deviation exceeds 1.0SD. This implies that the variation in effects across our students is wider than the spread of mean effects across all randomized evaluations of developing country education interventions in the literature. This very effective program does indeed leave some students behind. At the same time, we do not learn much from our analyses that attempt to determine which students benefit more or less from the program. We reject rank preservation, and the weaker assumption of stochastic increasingness leaves wide bounds on quantile-specific average treatment effects. Neither conventional nor machine-learning approaches to estimating systematic heterogeneity capture more than a small fraction of the variation in impacts given our available candidate moderators.]]></description><author>Julie Buhl-Wiggers, Jason T. Kerwin, Juan S. Muñoz-Morales, Jeffrey A. Smith, Rebecca Thornton</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29459</guid></item><item><title>Does Social Media cause Polarization? Evidence from access to Twitter Echo Chambers during the 2019 Argentine Presidential Debate</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29458</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rafael Di Tella, Ramiro H. Gálvez, Ernesto Schargrodsky.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study how two groups, those inside vs those outside echo chambers, react to a political event when we vary social media status (Twitter). Our treatments mimic two strategies often suggested as a way to limit polarization on social media: they expose people to counter-attitudinal data, and they get people to switch off social media. Our main result is that subjects that started inside echo chambers became more polarized when these two strategies were implemented. The only scenario where they did not become more polarized is when they did not even experience the political event. Interestingly, subjects that were outside echo chambers before our study began experienced no change (or a reduction) in polarization. We also study a group of non-Twitter users in order to have a simple, offline benchmark of the debate’s impact on polarization.]]></description><author>Rafael Di Tella, Ramiro H. Gálvez, Ernesto Schargrodsky</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29458</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Gap in Preferences: Evidence from 45,397 Facebook Interests</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ángel Cuevas, Rubén Cuevas, Klaus Desmet, Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses information on the frequency of 45,397 Facebook interests to study how the difference in preferences between men and women changes with a country's degree of gender equality. For preference dimensions that are systematically biased toward the same gender across the globe, differences between men and women are larger in more gender-equal countries. In contrast, for preference dimensions with a gender bias that varies across countries, the opposite holds. This finding takes an important step toward reconciling evolutionary psychology and social role theory as they relate to gender.]]></description><author>Ángel Cuevas, Rubén Cuevas, Klaus Desmet, Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</guid></item><item><title>FinTech as a Financial Liberator</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Greg Buchak, Jiayin Hu, Shang-Jin Wei.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> A binding interest rate cap on household savings is a common form of financial repression in developing economies and typically benefits banks. Using proprietary data from a leading Chinese FinTech company, we study Fintech's role in ending financial repression in China through the introduction of a money market fund with deposit-like features available through an already widely-adopted household payment platform.  Cities and banks whose depositor base is more exposed to FinTech see greater deposit outflows. Importantly, exposed banks respond to FinTech competition by offering competing products with market interest rates. FinTech thus facilitates a bottom-up interest rate liberalization.]]></description><author>Greg Buchak, Jiayin Hu, Shang-Jin Wei</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</guid></item><item><title>Water Treatment and Child Mortality: Evidence from Kenya</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29447</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Johannes Haushofer, Michael Kremer, Ricardo Maertens, Brandon Joel Tan.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Each year, around 500,000 children under 5 die from diarrhea, making it the third-leading cause of death in this age group. More than 80 percent of these deaths are attributable to unsafe drinking water. Drinking water can be made safe through dilute chlorine solution, but take-up of this technology has been low. Previous work has shown that free community-wide provision of dilute chlorine solution through “dispensers” – reservoirs of chlorine solution at water sources that make chlorination easy and free – increases take-up of chlorination. However, it has remained unclear whether this increase also translates into reduced mortality. Here we show that four years of community-wide provision of dilute chlorine solution in rural Kenya reduces all-cause under-5 mortality by 1.4 percentage points (95% CI: 0.3 pp, 2.5 pp), a 63% reduction relative to control. We estimate that at USD 25 per DALY averted, free provision of chlorine solution is twenty times more cost-effective than the WHO “highly cost-effective” threshold.]]></description><author>Johannes Haushofer, Michael Kremer, Ricardo Maertens, Brandon Joel Tan</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29447</guid></item><item><title>Estimating the Economic Value of Zoning Reform</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29440</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Santosh Anagol, Fernando V. Ferreira, Jonah M. Rexer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We develop a framework to estimate the economic value of a recent zoning reform in the city of Sao Paulo, which altered maximum permitted construction at the city-block level. Using a spatial regression discontinuity design, we find that developers file for more multi-family construction permits in blocks with higher allowable densities. We incorporate these micro-estimates into an equilibrium model of housing supply and demand to estimate the long term impact of zoning changes. Supply responses from the reform produce a 2.2 percent increase in the total housing stock, leading to a 0.5% reduction in prices on average, with substantial heterogeneity across neighborhoods. Consumer welfare gains due to price reductions are small, but increase 4-fold once we account for changes in the built environment, with more gains accruing to college-educated and higher income households. However, nominal house price losses faced by existing homeowners and landlords overshadow all consumer welfare gains.]]></description><author>Santosh Anagol, Fernando V. Ferreira, Jonah M. Rexer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29440</guid></item><item><title>A Note on the Global Distribution of Authorship in Economics Journals</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29435</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jacob Greenspon, Dani Rodrik.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Using Fontana et al.’s (2019) database, we analyze levels and trends in the global distribution of authorship in economics journals, disaggregating by country/region, quality of journal, and fields of specialization. We document striking imbalances. While Western and Northern European authors have made substantial gains, the representation of authors based in low-income countries remains extremely low -- an order of magnitude lower than the weight of their countries or regions in the global economy. Developing country representation has risen fastest at journals rated 100th or lower, while it has barely increased in journals rated 25th or higher. Fields such as international or development where global diversification may have been expected have not experienced much increase in developing country authorship. These results are consistent with a general increase in the relative supply of research in the rest of the world. But they also indicate authors from developing countries remain excluded from the profession’s top-rated journals.]]></description><author>Jacob Greenspon, Dani Rodrik</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29435</guid></item><item><title>Loan Officers Impede Graduation from Microfinance: Strategic Disclosure in a Large Microfinance Institution</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29427</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Natalia Rigol, Benjamin N. Roth.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> One of the most important puzzles in microfinance is the low rate of borrower graduation to larger, more flexible loans. Utilizing observational and experimental data from a large Chilean microfinance institution, we demonstrate that loan officers impede borrower graduation due to common features of their compensation contracts. Our partner lender offers both microloans and larger, more flexible graduation loans, and relies on loan officer endorsements to determine borrower graduation. Loan officers are rewarded for the size of their portfolio and repayment, and so are implicitly penalized when good borrowers graduate. In an experiment designed to isolate strategic disclosure, we modify compensation to reduce this implicit penalty and document that loan officers withheld endorsements of their most qualified borrowers prior to the shift. Graduated borrowers endorsed after the shift are 34% more profitable for our partner lender than those endorsed beforehand. A back-of-the- envelope calculation suggests that strategic behavior of loan officers accounts for $4.8-29.2 billion in lost social value from forgone borrower graduations in microfinance worldwide. Our experimental design may prove useful for other experiments within firms.]]></description><author>Natalia Rigol, Benjamin N. Roth</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29427</guid></item><item><title>Immigration and Occupational Comparative Advantage</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29418</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gordon H. Hanson, Chen Liu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Job choice by high-skilled foreign-born workers in the US correlates strongly with country of origin. We apply a Fréchet-Roy model of occupational choice to evaluate the causes of immigrant sorting. In a gravity specification, we find that revealed comparative advantage in the US is stronger for workers from countries with higher education quality in occupations that are more intensive in cognitive reasoning, and for workers from countries that are more linguistically similar to the US in occupations that are more intensive in communication. Our findings hold for immigrants who arrived in the US at age 18 or older (who received their K-12 education abroad) but not for immigrants who arrived in the US as children (who received their K-12 education domestically). We obtain similar results for immigrant sorting in Canada, which supports our interpretation that origin-country education quality, rather than US immigration policy, is what drives sorting patterns. In counterfactual analysis, we evaluate the consequences of reallocating visas for college-educated immigrants according to origin-country education quality.]]></description><author>Gordon H. Hanson, Chen Liu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29418</guid></item><item><title>Mental Health Therapy as a Core Strategy for Increasing Human Capital: Evidence from Ghana</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the impact of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) for individuals selected from the general population of poor households in rural Ghana. Results from 2-3 months after a randomized intervention show strong impacts on mental and physical health, cognitive and socioemotional skills, and downstream economic outcomes. We find no evidence of heterogeneity by baseline mental distress; we argue that this is because CBT can improve human capital for a general population of poor individuals through two pathways. First, CBT reduces vulnerability to deteriorating mental health; and second, CBT directly improves bandwidth, increasing cognitive and socioemotional skills and hence economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Consequences of the Opium War</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29404</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Wolfgang Keller, Carol H. Shiue.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the economic consequences of the West’s foray into China after the Opium War (1839-42), when Western colonial influence was introduced in dozens of so-called treaty ports. We document a turnaround during the 19th century in the nature of China’s capital markets. Whereas before the Opium War, coastal cities were of relatively minor importance, the treaty port system of the West transformed China into an economy focused on coastal areas and on international trade that aligned with the trading interests of the West. We show, first, that the West had a positive impact on China’s economy during the 19th century. It brought down local interest rates, and regions under Western influence exhibited both higher rates of industry growth and technology adoption. Second, the geographic scope of influence went far beyond the ports, impacting most of China. Interest rates fell by more than a quarter in the immediate vicinity of the ports and still by almost ten percent at distances of 450 kilometers from treaty ports. The development of China was not simply propelled by its own pre-1800 history, or by post-1978 reforms. The nearly 100 years of semi-colonization have shaped China’s economy today as one focused on the coastal areas.]]></description><author>Wolfgang Keller, Carol H. Shiue</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29404</guid></item><item><title>Policy Experimentation in China: the Political Economy of Policy Learning</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29402</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Shaoda Wang, David Y. Yang.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Many governments have engaged in policy experimentation in various forms to resolve uncertainty and facilitate learning. However, little is understood about the characteristics of policy experimentation, and how the structure of experimentation may affect policy learning and policy outcomes. We aim to describe and understand China’s policy experimentation since 1980, among the largest and most systematic in recent history. We collect comprehensive data on policy experimentation conducted in China over the past four decades. We find three main results. First, more than 80% of the experiments exhibit positive sample selection in terms of a locality’s economic development, and much of this can be attributed to misaligned incentives across political hierarchies. Second, local politicians allocate more resources to ensure the experiments’ success, and such effort is not replicable when policies roll out to the entire country. Third, the presence of sample selection and strategic effort is not fully accounted for by the central government, thus affecting policy learning and distorting national policies originating from the experimentation. Taken together, these results suggest that while China’s bureaucratic and institutional conditions make policy experimentation at such scale possible, the complex political environments can also limit the scope and bias the direction of policy learning.]]></description><author>Shaoda Wang, David Y. Yang</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29402</guid></item><item><title>The Human Side of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We document that nearly half of the global decline in agricultural employment during the 20th-century was driven by new cohorts entering the labor market. A newly compiled dataset of policy reforms supports an interpretation of these cohort effects as human capital. Through the lens of a model of frictional labor reallocation, we conclude that human capital growth, both as a mediating factor and as an independent driver, led to a sharp decline in the agricultural labor supply. This decline accounts, at fixed prices, for 40% of the decrease in agricultural employment. This aggregate effect is roughly halved in general equilibrium.]]></description><author>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</guid></item><item><title>Household Credit as Stimulus? Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> From 2011 to 2014, the Brazilian government conducted a heavily advertised major credit expansion program through government banks as part of its effort to stimulate the economy. Using administrative data on individual-level borrowing and spending, we find that the program led to a substantial rise in borrowing by government employees, especially those with low financial literacy. We trace the impact of credit stimulus on borrowers' consumption through the 2011-16 business cycle, and find that the credit stimulus resulted in higher consumption volatility and lower average consumption over the cycle. Our results suggest a potential downside of using household credit as stimulus in emerging markets.]]></description><author>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</guid></item><item><title>Fleshing Out the Olive? On Income Polarization in China</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29383</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Ravallion, Shaohua Chen.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> In a rare example of an explicit national goal for income distribution besides reducing poverty, China’s leadership has recently committed to expanding the middle-income share—moving to a less polarized “olive-shaped” distribution. Recognizing the potential trade-offs, the paper asks whether China’s experience indicates that income-polarization was a by-product of past economic progress, including poverty reduction. The paper does not find robust time-series evidence of polarizing effects alongside either economic growth or population urbanization (including among those below the national median). There was strong co-movement between polarization and inequality. Larger urban-rural gaps in mean incomes are strongly polarizing in China.]]></description><author>Martin Ravallion, Shaohua Chen</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29383</guid></item><item><title>Misallocation in Indian Agriculture</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29363</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marijn A. Bolhuis, Swapnika R. Rachapalli, Diego Restuccia.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We exploit substantial variation in land-market institutions across Indian states and detailed micro household-level panel data to assess the effect of distortions in land rental markets on agricultural productivity. We provide empirical evidence that states with more rental-market activity feature less misallocation and reallocate land more efficiently over time. We develop a model of heterogeneous farms and land rentals to estimate land-market distortions in each state. Land rentals have substantial positive effects on agricultural productivity: an efficient reallocation of land increases agricultural productivity by 38 percent on average and by more than 50 percent in states with highly distorted rental markets. Both farm and state-level land market distortions are quantitatively important, with state-level wedges accounting for a significant fraction of rental market participation differences across states. Land market distortions contribute about one-third to the large differences in agricultural total factor productivity across Indian states.]]></description><author>Marijn A. Bolhuis, Swapnika R. Rachapalli, Diego Restuccia</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29363</guid></item><item><title>Why do people stay poor?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clare A. Balboni, Oriana Bandiera, Robin Burgess, Maitreesh Ghatak, Anton Heil.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> There are two broad views as to why people stay poor. One emphasizes differences in fundamentals, such as ability, talent or motivation. The other, the poverty traps view, differences in opportunities which stem from access to wealth. To test between these two views, we exploit a large-scale, randomized asset transfer and an 11-year panel on 6000 households who begin in extreme poverty. The setting is rural Bangladesh and the asset is cows. The data supports the poverty traps view - we identify a threshold level of initial assets above which households accumulate assets, take on better occupations (from casual labor in agriculture or domestic services to running small livestock businesses) and grow out of poverty. The reverse happens for those below the threshold. Structural estimation of an occupational choice model reveals that almost all beneficiaries are misallocated in the work they do at baseline and that the gains arising from eliminating misallocation would far exceed the program costs. Our findings imply that large transfers which create better jobs for the poor are an effective means of getting people out of poverty traps and reducing global poverty.]]></description><author>Clare A. Balboni, Oriana Bandiera, Robin Burgess, Maitreesh Ghatak, Anton Heil</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</guid></item><item><title>The Economics of the COVID-19 Pandemic in Poor Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29339</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Edward Miguel, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic has upended health and living standards around the world. This article provides an interim overview of these effects, with a particular focus on low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). Economists have explained how the pandemic is likely to have differential consequences for LMICs, and demand distinct policy responses, compared to rich countries. We survey the rapidly expanding body of empirical research that documents its many adverse economic and non-economic effects in terms of living standards, education, health, and gender equality, which appear to be unprecedented in depth and scale. We also review research on successful and failed policy responses, including the failure to ensure widespread vaccine coverage in LMICs, which is needed to end the pandemic. We close with a discussion of implications for public policy in LMICs, and for the institutions of international governance, given the likelihood of future pandemics and other major shocks (e.g., climate).]]></description><author>Edward Miguel, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29339</guid></item><item><title>Creative Destruction, Distance to Frontier, and Economic Development</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29333</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Peters, Fabrizio Zilibotti.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We construct a model of creative destruction with endogenous firm dynamics. We integrate the theory into a general equilibrium multi-country model of technological convergence where countries interact via international spillovers. We derive implications for both firm dynamics and aggregate productivity dynamics. In richer economies, firms are on average larger and the best firms grow larger over time. In poorer economies, there is little creative destruction, low selection, and firms remain small. We estimate the parameters of the model using firm-level data for India and the United States. We study the effect of counterfactual policy reforms. Industrial policy that selectively targets the more productive firms can be beneficial in poor countries while being harmful in countries close to the economic frontier. The findings echo Acemoglu et al. (2006).]]></description><author>Michael Peters, Fabrizio Zilibotti</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29333</guid></item><item><title>Market Size and Spatial Growth - Evidence from Germany’s Post-War Population Expulsions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29329</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Peters.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Virtually all theories of economic growth predict a positive relationship between population size and productivity. In this paper I study a particular historical episode to provide direct evidence for the empirical relevance of such scale effects. In the aftermath of the Second World War about 8m ethnic Germans were expelled from their domiciles in Eastern Europe and transferred to West Germany. This inflow increased the German population by almost 20%. Using variation across counties I show that the settlement of refugees had a large and persistent effect on the size of the local population, manufacturing employment and income per capita. I show that these findings are quantitatively consistent with an idea-based model of spatial growth if population mobility is subject to frictions and productivity spillovers occur locally. The model implies that the refugee settlement increased aggregate income per capita by about 12% after 25 years and that the historical settlement rule triggered persistent industrialization of rural areas.]]></description><author>Michael Peters</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29329</guid></item><item><title>Circles of Trust: Rival Information in Social Networks</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29324</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Petra Persson ⓡ, Nikita Roketskiy ⓡ, Samuel Lee.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We analyze the diffusion of rival information in a social network. In our model, rational agents can share information sequentially, unconstrained by an exogenous protocol or timing. We show how to compute the set of eventually informed agents for any network, and show that it is essentially unique under altruistic preferences. The relationship between network structure and information diffusion is complex because the former shapes both the charity and confidentiality of potential senders and receivers.]]></description><author>Petra Persson ⓡ, Nikita Roketskiy ⓡ, Samuel Lee</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29324</guid></item><item><title>The Role of Trade in Economic Development</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29314</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Atkin, Dave Donaldson.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> This chapter (to appear in the forthcoming Handbook of International Economics, Vol. 5) develops a framework with which to interpret and survey answers to the question: how does increased openness affect aggregate welfare in a typical developing country? We decompose answers into four mechanisms: (i) an effect akin to technological progress that is purely mechanical; (ii) an effect on factoral terms of trade; (iii) a distortion revenue effect that exacerbates or mitigates the consequences of domestic distortions; and (iv) an effect of trade on the magnitude of those distortions themselves. Our focus lies in the last two mechanisms as these are especially important for the study of low-income settings where domestic distortions are thought to be rife. Throughout, we provide both a review of existing work on these topics and quantitative calculations that aim to gauge the magnitudes involved in a global model that is calibrated to match firm- and industry-level data on trade flows, production techniques, and a host of distortions (tariffs, other taxes, markups, bribes, theft, credit constraints, contracting failures, labor regulations, and public utility provision) that have featured in the literature.]]></description><author>David Atkin, Dave Donaldson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29314</guid></item><item><title>Big Loans to Small Businesses: Predicting Winners and Losers in an Entrepreneurial Lending Experiment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We experimentally study the impact of substantially larger enterprise loans, in collaboration with an Egyptian lender. Larger loans generate small average impacts, but machine learning using psychometric data reveals dramatic heterogeneity. Top-performers (i.e., those with the highest predicted treatment effects) substantially increase profits, whereas profits for poor-performers drop. The magnitude of this difference implies that an individual lender’s credit allocation choices matter for aggregate income. Evidence on two fronts suggests large loans would be misallocated: top-performers are predicted by loan officers to have higher default rates; and, top-performers grow less than others when given small loans, implying that allocating larger loans based on prior performance is not efficient. Our results have important implications for credit expansion policy and our understanding of entrepreneurial talent: on the former, the use of psychometric data to identify top-performers suggests a pathway towards better allocation that revolves around entrepreneurial type more than firm type; on the latter, the reversal of fortune for poor-performers, who do well with small loans but not large, indicates a type of entrepreneur that we call a “go-getter” who performs well when constrained but poorly when not.]]></description><author>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</guid></item><item><title>Electoral Violence and Supply Chain Disruptions in Kenya's Floriculture Industry</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29297</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher Ksoll, Rocco Macchiavello, Ameet Morjaria.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Violent conflicts, particularly at election times in Africa, are a common cause of instability and economic disruption. This paper studies how firms react to electoral violence using the case of Kenyan flower exporters during the 2008 post-election violence as an example. The violence induced a large negative supply shock that reduced exports primarily through workers' absence and had heterogeneous effects: larger firms and those with direct contractual relationships in export markets suffered smaller production and losses of workers. On the demand side, global buyers were not able to shift sourcing to Kenyan exporters located in areas not directly affected by the violence nor to neighboring Ethiopian suppliers. Consistent with difficulties in insuring against supply-chain risk disruptions caused by electoral violence, firms in direct contractual relationships ramp up shipments just before the subsequent 2013 presidential election to mitigate risk.]]></description><author>Christopher Ksoll, Rocco Macchiavello, Ameet Morjaria</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29297</guid></item><item><title>Privatization of Public Goods: Evidence from the Sanitation Sector in Senegal</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29295</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua W. Deutschmann, Jared E. Gars, Jean-François Houde, Molly Lipscomb, Laura A. Schechter.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Privatization of a public good (the management of sewage treatment centers in Dakar, Senegal) leads to an increase in the productivity of downstream sewage dumping companies and a decrease in downstream prices of the services they provide to households. We use the universe of legal dumps of sanitation waste from May 2009 to November 2018 to show that legal dumping increased substantially following privatization–on average an increase of 61.7%, or an increase of about 14,000 cubic meters each month. This is due to increased productivity of all trucks, not just those associated with the company managing the treatment centers. Household-level survey data shows that prices of legal sanitary dumping decreased by ten percent following privatization, and DHS data show that diarrhea rates among children under five decreased in Dakar relative to secondary cities in Senegal following privatization with no similar effect on respiratory illness as a placebo.]]></description><author>Joshua W. Deutschmann, Jared E. Gars, Jean-François Houde, Molly Lipscomb, Laura A. Schechter</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29295</guid></item><item><title>Social and Financial Incentives for Overcoming a Collective Action Problem</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29294</link><description><![CDATA[<i>M. Mehrab Bakhtiar, Raymond Guiteras, James A. Levinsohn, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Addressing public health externalities often requires community-level collective action. Each person’s sanitation behavior can affect the health of neighbors. We report on a cluster randomized controlled trial conducted with 19,000 households in rural Bangladesh where we randomized (1) either group financial incentives or a non-financial “social recognition” reward, and (2) asking each household to make either a private pledge or a public pledge to maintain hygienic latrines. The group financial reward has the strongest impact in the short term (3 months), inducing a 7.5-12.5 percentage point increase in hygienic latrine ownership. Getting people to publicly commit to maintaining and using a hygienic latrine in front of their neighbors induced a 4.2-6.1 percentage point increase in hygienic latrine ownership in the short term. In the medium term (15 months), the effect of the financial reward dissipates while the effect of the public commitment persists. Neither social recognition nor private commitments produce effects statistically distinguishable from zero.]]></description><author>M. Mehrab Bakhtiar, Raymond Guiteras, James A. Levinsohn, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29294</guid></item><item><title>Effect of the Jamaica Early Childhood Stimulation Intervention on Labor Market Outcomes at Age 31</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29292</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Paul Gertler, James J. Heckman, Rodrigo Pinto, Susan M. Chang, Sally Grantham-McGregor, Christel Vermeersch, Susan Walker, Amika Wright.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We report the labor market effects of the Jamaica Early Childhood Stimulation intervention at age 31. The study is a small-sample randomized early childhood education stimulation intervention targeting stunted children living in the poor neighborhoods of Kingston, Jamaica. Implemented in 1987-1989, treatment consisted of a two-year home-based intervention designed to improve nutrition and the quality of mother-child interactions to foster cognitive, language and psycho-social skills. The original sample is 127 stunted children between 9 and 24 months old. Our study is able to track and interview 75% of the original sample 30 years after the intervention, both still living in Jamaica and migrated abroad. We find large and statistically significant effects on income and schooling; the treatment group had 43% higher hourly wages and 37% higher earnings than the control group. This is a substantial increase over the treatment effect estimated for age 22 where we observed a 25% increase in earnings. The Jamaican Study is a rare case of a long-term follow up for an early childhood development (ECD) intervention implemented in a less-developed country. Our results confirm large economic returns to an early childhood intervention that targeted disadvantaged families living in poverty in the poor neighborhoods of Jamaica. The Jamaican intervention is being replicated around the world. Our analysis provides justification for expanding ECD interventions targeting disadvantaged children living in poor countries around the world.]]></description><author>Paul Gertler, James J. Heckman, Rodrigo Pinto, Susan M. Chang, Sally Grantham-McGregor, Christel Vermeersch, Susan Walker, Amika Wright</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29292</guid></item></channel></rss>