<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic History of Economic Thought</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic History of Economic Thought</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 15:36:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>O.M.W. Sprague (the Man Who “Wrote the Book” on Financial Crises) meets the Great Depression</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29416</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> When the Great Depression struck the United States, Oliver M.W. Sprague was America’s foremost expert on financial crises. His History of Crises under the National Banking System is a frequently cited classic. Had he diagnosed a banking panic and called for an aggressive response by the Federal Reserve, it might have made a difference; but he did not. Sprague’s misdiagnosis had, I argue, two causes. First, the crisis lacked the symptoms of a panic, such as high short-term interest rates in the New York money market, which Sprague had identified from his studies of previous crises. Second, Sprague’s macro-economic ideas led him to conclude that an expansionary monetary policy would be of little help once a depression was underway. Sprague’s main concern was that abandoning the gold standard would intensify the crisis, a concern that led him to resign his position as advisor to the U.S. Treasury to protest Roosevelt’s gold policy.]]></description><author>Hugh Rockoff</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29416</guid></item><item><title>Mr. Keynes and the “Classics”; A Suggested Reinterpretation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29158</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper revisits and proposes a resolution to an empirical and theoretical controversy between Keynes and the “classics” (or monetarists). The controversy dates to Keynes’s General Theory (1936)—most famously formalized in Hicks’s (1937) classic Econometrica article, in which the IS-LM model is first formally stated. We first replicate empirical tests formulated in the late 1960s and ’70s and show that more recent data have more statistical power and resolve the empirical debate in favor of the Keynesians, at least according to the criteria of the literature at that time. We then show, using a simple dynamic stochastic general equilibrium (DSGE) model, that the empirical tests suffer from the Lucas (1976) critique, as the conclusion fundamentally depends upon the assumed policy regime. Nevertheless, we argue, this new empirical result is useful: it provides evidence for the existence of a “Keynesian policy regime” according to which traditional monetary expansion loses its impact in the absence of a policy regime change, in the sense of Sargent (1982).]]></description><author>Gauti B. Eggertsson, Cosimo Petracchi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29158</guid></item><item><title>Publishing Economics: How Slow? Why Slow? Is Slow Productive? Fixing Slow?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29147</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Publishing in economics proceeds much more slowly on average than in the natural sciences, and more slowly than in other social sciences and finance. It is even relatively slower at the extremes. We demonstrate that much of the lag, especially at the extremes, arises from authors’ dilatory behavior in revising their work. The marginal product of an additional round of re-submission at the top economics journals is productive of additional subsequent citations; but conditional on re-submission, journals taking more time is not productive, and authors spending more time is associated with reduced scholarly impact. We offer several proposals to speed up the publication process. These include no-revisions policies; limits on authors’ time revising articles, and limits on editors waiting for dilatory referees.]]></description><author>Aboozar Hadavand, Daniel S. Hamermesh, Wesley W. Wilson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29147</guid></item></channel></rss>