<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Experimental Design</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Experimental Design</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 14:04:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Memory and Probability</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29273</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>People often estimate probabilities, such as the likelihood that an insurable risk will materialize or that an Irish person has red hair, by retrieving experiences from memory. We present a model of this process based on two established regularities of selective recall: similarity and interference. The model accounts for and reconciles a variety of conflicting empirical findings, such as overestimation of unlikely events when these are cued vs. neglect of non-cued ones, the availability heuristic, the representativeness heuristic, as well as over vs. underreaction to information in different situations. The model makes new predictions on how the content of a hypothesis (not just its objective probability) affects probability assessments by shaping the ease of recall. We experimentally evaluate these predictions and find strong experimental support.]]></description><author>Pedro Bordalo, John J. Conlon, Nicola Gennaioli, Spencer Yongwook Kwon, Andrei Shleifer</author></item><item><title>Experimental Evidence on Semi-structured Bargaining with Private Information</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29265</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>We conduct a laboratory experiment to study a decentralized market where goods are differentiated and evaluations are private. We implement different semi-structured bargaining protocols based on deferred acceptance, and we compare their performance to the benchmark scenario of a sealed-bid auction. We show that bargaining dramatically improves efficiency, mainly to the benefit of players rather than the silent auctioneer. A protocol of unconstrained simultaneous bargaining performs best, doubling the proportion of deals relative to the benchmark. This is because participants seek to reveal information through a gradual bidding-up strategy that favors bargaining environments. Aggregate efficiency nonetheless suffers from the fact that buyers bargain harder than sellers, and that some players over-bargain to appropriate a larger share of the unknown surplus.]]></description><author>Margherita Comola, Marcel Fafchamps</author></item></channel></rss>