<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Energy</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Energy</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 15:36:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Predicting the Oil Market</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29379</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We study the performance of many traditional and novel, text-based variables for in-sample and out-of-sample forecasting of oil spot, futures, and energy company stock returns, and changes in oil volatility, production, and inventories. After controlling for small-sample biases, we find evidence of in-sample predictability. Our text measures, derived using energy news articles, hold their own against traditional variables. While we cannot identify ex-ante rules for selecting successful out-of-sample forecasters, an analysis of all possible two-variable models reveals out-of-sample performance above that expected under random variation. Our findings provide new directions for identifying robust forecasting models for oil markets, and beyond.]]></description><author>Charles W. Calomiris, Harry Mamaysky, Nida Çakır Melek</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29379</guid></item><item><title>Using Satellite Imagery and Machine Learning to Estimate the Livelihood Impact of Electricity Access</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29237</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> In many regions of the world, sparse data on key economic outcomes inhibits the development, targeting, and evaluation of public policy.  We demonstrate how advancements in satellite imagery and machine learning can help ameliorate these data and inference challenges. In the context of an expansion of the electrical grid across Uganda, we show how a combination of satellite imagery and computer vision can be used to develop local-level livelihood measurements appropriate for inferring the causal impact of electricity access on livelihoods. We then show how ML-based inference techniques deliver more reliable estimates of the causal impact of electrification than traditional alternatives when applied to these data. We estimate that grid access improves village-level asset wealth in rural Uganda by 0.17 standard deviations, more than doubling the growth rate over our study period relative to untreated areas.  Our results provide country-scale evidence on the impact of a key infrastructure investment, and provide a low-cost, generalizable approach to future policy evaluation in data sparse environments.]]></description><author>Nathan Ratledge, Gabriel Cadamuro, Brandon De la Cuesta, Matthieu Stigler, Marshall Burke</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29237</guid></item><item><title>Energy and Environmental Markets, Industrial Organization, and Regulation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29235</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper discusses contributions that industrial organization economists have made to our understanding of energy markets and environmental regulation. We emphasize the substantive contributions of recent papers while also highlighting how this literature has adopted and sometimes augmented theoretical and empirical tools from industrial organization. Many of the topics examined by this literature—especially auctions, investment, productivity and innovation, and regulation—also apply to a variety of settings beyond energy and the environment. We also indicate areas where future research is likely to be fruitful, with an emphasis on how industrial organization economists can help inform energy and environmental policies.]]></description><author>Ryan Kellogg, Mar Reguant</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29235</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Market Expectations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29232</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Asset prices are a valuable source of information about financial market participants' expectations about key macroeconomic variables. However, the presence of time-varying risk premia requires an adjustment of market prices to obtain the market's rational assessment of future price and policy developments. This paper reviews empirical approaches for recovering market-based expectations. It starts by laying out the two canonical modeling frameworks that form the backbone for estimating risk premia and highlights the proliferation of risk pricing factors that result in a wide range of different asset-price-based expectation measures. It then describes a key methodological innovation to evaluate the empirical plausibility of risk premium estimates and to identify the most accurate market-based expectation measure. The usefulness of this general approach is illustrated for price expectations in the global oil market. Then, the paper provides an overview of the body of empirical evidence for monetary policy and inflation expectations with a special emphasis on market-specific characteristics that complicate the quest for the best possible market-based expectation measure. Finally, it discusses a number of economic applications where market expectations play a key role for evaluating economic models, guiding policy analysis, and deriving shock measures.]]></description><author>Christiane Baumeister</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29232</guid></item><item><title>Holding Up Green Energy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29154</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Green energy is produced by relationship-specific assets that are vulnerable to hold-up if contracts are not strictly enforced. I study the role of counterparty risk in the procurement of green energy using data on the universe of solar procurement auctions in India. The Indian context allows clean estimates of how risk affects procurement, because solar power plants set up in the same states, by the same firms, are procured in auctions variously intermediated by either risky states themselves or the central government. I find that: (i) the counterparty risk of an average state increases solar energy prices by 10%; (ii) the intermediation of the central government eliminates this risk premium; (iii) higher prices due to risk reduce investment, because state demand for green energy is elastic. The results suggest that the risk of hold-up places developing countries at a disadvantage in the procurement of green energy.]]></description><author>Nicholas Ryan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29154</guid></item><item><title>Soaking Up the Sun: Battery Investment, Renewable Energy, and Market Equilibrium</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29133</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We develop a dynamic competitive equilibrium model of battery adoption and operations to evaluate the social value and adoption trajectory of utility-scale batteries and examine policy counterfactuals. The first battery unit breaks even in 2027 when renewable energy share reaches 52% and expected capital costs are $259/kWh.  While the competitive market will install 10 MWh by 2030, competitive adoption does not reach 5,000 MWh until 2043 because the marginal value of investment sharply declines in aggregate capacity. California's 1,300 MW battery mandate implies subsidies of 49% and creates deadweight losses of $433 million relative to a competitive battery market.]]></description><author>R. Andrew Butters, Jackson Dorsey, Gautam Gowrisankaran</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29133</guid></item></channel></rss>