<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER working group Economics of Crime</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER working group Economics of Crime</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 15:27:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Office-Based Mental Healthcare and Juvenile Arrests</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29465</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We estimate the effect of local access to office-based mental healthcare on juvenile arrest outcomes. We leverage variation in the number of mental healthcare offices within a county over the period 1999 to 2016 in a two-way fixed-effects model. Office-based treatment is the most common modality of mental healthcare received by juveniles. We find that ten additional office-based mental healthcare providers in a county leads a decrease of 2.3% to 2.6% in the per capita costs to society of juvenile arrest. Findings are similar for arrest rates although often less precise, which suggests that accounting for social costs is empirically important. Crime imposes substantial costs on society and individuals, and interventions during early life can have more pronounced effects than those received at later stages, therefore our results imply increased juvenile access to mental healthcare may have an unintended benefit for the current and future generations.]]></description><author>Monica Deza, Thanh Lu, Johanna Catherine Maclean</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29465</guid></item><item><title>Effects of COVID-19 Shutdowns on Domestic Violence in US Cities</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29429</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We empirically investigate the impact of COVID-19 shutdowns on domestic violence using incident-level data on both domestic-related calls for service and crime reports of domestic violence assaults from the 18 major US police departments for which both types of records are available. Although we confirm prior reports of an increase in domestic calls for service at the start of the pandemic, we find that the increase preceded mandatory shutdowns, and there was an incremental decline following the government imposition of restrictions. We find no evidence that domestic violence crimes increased. Rather, domestic violence assaults declined significantly during the initial shutdown period and there was no significant change in intimate partner homicides in these months. Our results fail to support claims that shutdowns increased domestic violence and suggest caution before drawing inference or basing policy on calls data alone.]]></description><author>Amalia R. Miller, Carmit Segal, Melissa K. Spencer</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29429</guid></item><item><title>Red Scare? A Study of Ethnic Prejudice in the Prosecutions under the Economic Espionage Act</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29272</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We empirically test whether the Department of Justice (DOJ) engages in ethnic prejudice against Chinese in its prosecutorial decisions under the Economic Espionage Act (EEA) of 1996. Using data of EEA cases from November 1996 to June 2021, we conduct Becker's outcome test for evidence of ethnic prejudice. We find that Chinese-named defendants were more likely to be dismissed by trial or acquitted by jury, and were found guilty on fewer counts, and on average received harsher indictments. These results are robust regardless of whether we consider all cases or only arguably ``marginal'' cases. We also find that, for those publicly listed victim firms whose trade secrets were allegedly stolen by the charged defendants, the stock market reaction was much more muted to the news on the case filing date if the charged defendants are of Chinese descent. Our study provides the first systematic evidence that the DOJ's prosecutorial decisions in the application of the EEA may have been tainted by ethnic prejudice against Chinese, including American citizens of Chinese descent.]]></description><author>Hanming Fang, Ming Li</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29272</guid></item><item><title>Fragile Algorithms and Fallible Decision-Makers: Lessons from the Justice System</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29267</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Algorithms (in some form) are already widely used in the criminal justice system.  We draw lessons from this experience for what is to come for the rest of society as machine learning diffuses. We find economists and other social scientists have a key role to play in shaping the impact of algorithms, in part through improving the tools used to build them.]]></description><author>Jens Ludwig, Sendhil Mullainathan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29267</guid></item><item><title>Police Officer Assignment and Neighborhood Crime</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29243</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We develop an empirical model of the mechanism used to assign police officers to Chicago districts and examine the efficiency and equity of alternative allocations. We document that the current bidding process, which grants priority based on seniority, results in the assignment of more experienced officers to less violent and high-income neighborhoods. Our empirical model combines estimates of heterogeneous officer preferences underlying the bidding process with causal estimates of the effects of officer experience on neighborhood crime. Equalizing officer seniority across districts would reduce violent crime rate by 4.6 percent and significantly decrease inequality in crime, discretionary arrests, and officer use of force across neighborhoods. Moreover, this assignment can be achieved in a revenue-neutral way while resulting in small welfare gains for police officers, implying that it is more equitable and efficient.]]></description><author>Bocar Ba, Patrick Bayer, Nayoung Rim, Roman Rivera, Modibo Sidibé</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29243</guid></item><item><title>Shifting Punishment on Minorities: Experimental Evidence of Scapegoating</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29157</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper provides experimental evidence showing that members of a majority group systematically shift punishment on innocent members of an ethnic minority.  We develop a new incentivized task, the Punishing the Scapegoat Game, to measure how injustice affecting a member of one’s own group shapes punishment of an unrelated bystander (“a scapegoat”). We manipulate the ethnic identity of the scapegoats and study interactions between the majority group and the Roma minority in Slovakia. We find that when no harm is done, there is no evidence of discrimination against the ethnic minority. In contrast, when a member of one’s own group is harmed, the punishment ”passed” on innocent individuals more than doubles when they are from the minority, as compared to when they are from the dominant group. These results illuminate how individualized tensions can be transformed into a group conflict, dragging minorities into conflicts in a way that is completely unrelated to their behavior.]]></description><author>Michal Bauer, Jana Cahlíková, Julie Chytilová, Gérard Roland, Tomas Zelinsky</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29157</guid></item><item><title>Can Restorative Justice Conferencing Reduce Recidivism? Evidence From the Make-it-Right Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29150</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the effect of a restorative justice intervention targeted at youth ages 13 to 17 facing felony charges of medium severity (e.g., burglary, assault).  Eligible youths were randomly assigned to participate in the Make-it-Right (MIR) restorative justice program or to a control group in which they faced criminal prosecution.  We estimate the effects of MIR on the likelihood that a youth will be rearrested in the four years following randomization. Assignment to MIR reduces the likelihood of a rearrest within six months by 19 percentage points, a 44 percent reduction relative to the control group.  Moreover, the reduction in recidivism persists even four years after randomization.  Thus, our estimates show that juvenile restorative justice conferencing can reduce recidivism among youth charged with relatively serious offenses and can be an effective alternative to traditional criminal justice practices.]]></description><author>Yotam Shem-Tov, Steven Raphael, Alissa Skog</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29150</guid></item></channel></rss>