<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Economic Systems</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Economic Systems</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 11:33:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Other Great Migration: Southern Whites and the New Right</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29506</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Samuel Bazzi, Andreas Ferrara, Martin Fiszbein, Thomas P. Pearson, Patrick A. Testa.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper provides a novel perspective on the Great Migration out of the U.S. South. Using a shift-share identification strategy, we show how millions of Southern white migrants transformed the cultural and political landscape across America. Counties with a larger Southern white share by 1940 exhibited growing support for right-wing politics throughout the 20th century and beyond. Racial animus, religious conservatism, and localist attitudes among the Southern white diaspora hastened partisan realignment as the Republican Party found fresh support for the Southern strategy outside the South. Their congressional representatives were more likely to oppose politically liberal legislation, such as the Civil Rights Act of 1964, and to object to the Electoral College count in 2021. These migrants helped shape institutions that reinforced racial inequity and exclusion, they shared ideology through religious organizations and popular media, and they transmitted an array of cultural norms to non-Southern populations. Together, our findings suggest that Southern white migrants may have forever changed the trajectory of American politics.]]></description><author>Samuel Bazzi, Andreas Ferrara, Martin Fiszbein, Thomas P. Pearson, Patrick A. Testa</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29506</guid></item><item><title>Discrimination and State Capacity: Evidence from WWII U.S. Army Enlistment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29482</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nancy Qian, Marco Tabellini.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper investigates the empirical relationship between inclusion and state capacity, as theorized by Besley and Persson (2009). We examine the impact of racial discrimination on Black U.S. military enlistment during the onset of WWII. We find that discrimination had a large and negative effect on volunteer enlistment after the Pearl Harbor attack. The result is robust to a large number of controls that account for potential confounders. The negative effect of discrimination is moderated by geographical proximity to Pearl Harbor, and is larger for educated men. We provide consistent evidence for Japanese Americans.]]></description><author>Nancy Qian, Marco Tabellini</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29482</guid></item><item><title>Cooperation in the Commons: Community-based Rangeland Management in Namibia</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29469</link><description><![CDATA[<i>D. Layne Coppock, Lucas Crowley, Susan L. Durham, Dylan Groves, Julian C. Jamison, Dean Karlan, Brien E. Norton, R. Douglas Ramsey.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Classic theories suggest that common pool resources are subject to overexploitation. Community-based resource management approaches may ameliorate “tragedy of the commons” effects. Using a randomized evaluation in Namibia’s communal rangelands, we find that a comprehensive four-year program to support community-based rangeland and cattle management led to persistent and large improvements for eight of thirteen indices of social and behavioral outcomes. Effects on rangeland health, cattle productivity and household economics, however, were either negative or nil. Positive impacts on community resource management may have been offset by communities’ inability to control grazing by non-participating herds and inhibited by an unresponsive rangeland sub-system. This juxtaposition, in which measurable improvements in community resource management did not translate into better outcomes for households or rangeland health, demonstrates the fragility of the causal pathway from program implementation to intended socioeconomic and environmental outcomes. It also points to challenges for improving climate change–adaptation strategies.]]></description><author>D. Layne Coppock, Lucas Crowley, Susan L. Durham, Dylan Groves, Julian C. Jamison, Dean Karlan, Brien E. Norton, R. Douglas Ramsey</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29469</guid></item><item><title>AI-tocracy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29466</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Beraja, Andrew Kao, David Y. Yang, Noam Yuchtman.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Can frontier innovation be sustained under autocracy? We argue that innovation and autocracy can be mutually reinforcing when: (i) the new technology bolsters the autocrat’s power; and (ii) the autocrat’s demand for the technology stimulates further innovation in applications beyond those benefiting it directly. We test for such a mutually reinforcing relationship in the context of facial recognition AI in China. To do so, we gather comprehensive data on AI firms and government procurement contracts, as well as on social unrest across China during the last decade. We first show that autocrats benefit from AI: local unrest leads to greater government procurement of facial recognition AI, and increased AI procurement suppresses subsequent unrest. We then show that AI innovation benefits from autocrats’ suppression of unrest: the contracted AI firms innovate more both for the government and commercial markets. Taken together, these results suggest the possibility of sustained AI innovation under the Chinese regime: AI innovation entrenches the regime, and the regime’s investment in AI for political control stimulates further frontier innovation.]]></description><author>Martin Beraja, Andrew Kao, David Y. Yang, Noam Yuchtman</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29466</guid></item><item><title>Does Social Media cause Polarization? Evidence from access to Twitter Echo Chambers during the 2019 Argentine Presidential Debate</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29458</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rafael Di Tella, Ramiro H. Gálvez, Ernesto Schargrodsky.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study how two groups, those inside vs those outside echo chambers, react to a political event when we vary social media status (Twitter). Our treatments mimic two strategies often suggested as a way to limit polarization on social media: they expose people to counter-attitudinal data, and they get people to switch off social media. Our main result is that subjects that started inside echo chambers became more polarized when these two strategies were implemented. The only scenario where they did not become more polarized is when they did not even experience the political event. Interestingly, subjects that were outside echo chambers before our study began experienced no change (or a reduction) in polarization. We also study a group of non-Twitter users in order to have a simple, offline benchmark of the debate’s impact on polarization.]]></description><author>Rafael Di Tella, Ramiro H. Gálvez, Ernesto Schargrodsky</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29458</guid></item><item><title>Policy Experimentation in China: the Political Economy of Policy Learning</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29402</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Shaoda Wang, David Y. Yang.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Many governments have engaged in policy experimentation in various forms to resolve uncertainty and facilitate learning. However, little is understood about the characteristics of policy experimentation, and how the structure of experimentation may affect policy learning and policy outcomes. We aim to describe and understand China’s policy experimentation since 1980, among the largest and most systematic in recent history. We collect comprehensive data on policy experimentation conducted in China over the past four decades. We find three main results. First, more than 80% of the experiments exhibit positive sample selection in terms of a locality’s economic development, and much of this can be attributed to misaligned incentives across political hierarchies. Second, local politicians allocate more resources to ensure the experiments’ success, and such effort is not replicable when policies roll out to the entire country. Third, the presence of sample selection and strategic effort is not fully accounted for by the central government, thus affecting policy learning and distorting national policies originating from the experimentation. Taken together, these results suggest that while China’s bureaucratic and institutional conditions make policy experimentation at such scale possible, the complex political environments can also limit the scope and bias the direction of policy learning.]]></description><author>Shaoda Wang, David Y. Yang</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29402</guid></item><item><title>Perceptions and Preferences for Redistribution</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29370</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefanie Stantcheva.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The relationship between the degree of inequality and the demand for redistribution has been a central question in political science and political economy. The famous median-voter model predicts that higher inequality, reflected in a growing gap between the income of the average and the median voter, should lead to increased demand for redistribution, as policymakers cater to the median voter’s preferences (Meltzer and Richard, 1981). Yet, using data from OECD countries, Kenworthy and McCall (2008) show that, despite increases in inequality in those countries, there was no corresponding increase in demand for redistribution. Part of the explanation of this puzzle lies in the realization that it is not only (or even mainly) reality, but perceptions that shape support for policy. This article will explore recent evidence using large-scale social economics surveys and experiments that sheds lights on beliefs about inequality, social mobility, diversity and immigration, social position, and understanding of how policies work.]]></description><author>Stefanie Stantcheva</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29370</guid></item></channel></rss>