<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic International Macroeconomics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic International Macroeconomics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 16:25:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Deindustrialization and Industry Polarization</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29483</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We add to recent evidence on deindustrialization and document a new pattern: increasing industry polarization over time. We assess whether these patterns can be explained by a dynamic open economy model of structural change in which the two primary driving forces are sector-biased productivity growth and sectoral trade integration. We calibrate the model to the same countries used to document our patterns. We find that sector-biased productivity growth is important for deindustrialization, and sectoral trade integration is important for industry polarization through specialization. The interaction of these two driving forces is also essential. The key transmission channel is the declining relative price of manufacturing goods to services over time.]]></description><author>Michael Sposi, Kei-Mu Yi, Jing Zhang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29483</guid></item><item><title>The Prudential Use of Capital Controls and Foreign Currency Reserves</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29476</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We provide a simple framework to study the prudential use of capital controls and currency reserves that have been explored in the recent literature. We cover the role of both pecuniary externalities and aggregate demand externalities. The model features a central policy dilemma for emerging economies facing large capital outflows: the choice between increasing the policy rate to stabilize the exchange rate and decreasing the policy rate to stabilize employment. Ex ante capital controls and reserve accumulation can help mitigate this dilemma. We use our framework to survey the recent literature and provide an overview of recent empirical findings on the use of these policies.]]></description><author>Javier Bianchi, Guido Lorenzoni</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29476</guid></item><item><title>Optimal Bank Reserve Remuneration and Capital Control Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29473</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> This paper studies optimal capital-control and bank-reserve remuneration policy in an open economy with a banking channel and a collateral constraint that limits household debt by a fraction of income. It finds that the unregulated economy borrows too little relative to what is optimal (underborrowing). This finding contrasts with the standard overborrowing result obtained in the absence of a banking channel. Under optimal policy, the central bank injects bank reserves during recessions. In this way, the monetary authority is able to uncouple household deleveraging from economy-wide deleveraging, thereby ameliorating the severity of the financial crisis. The paper documents that in emerging and developed economies the lending spread (lending rate minus deposit rate) displayed a muted response during the 2007-2009 financial crisis. This fact is consistent with a decline in the demand rather than in the supply of loans and gives credence to models in which the collateral constraint is placed at the level of the nonfinancial sector as opposed to at the level of the bank.]]></description><author>Chun-Che Chi, Stephanie Schmitt-Grohé, Martín Uribe</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29473</guid></item><item><title>Scrambling for Dollars: International Liquidity, Banks and Exchange Rates</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29457</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We develop a theory of exchange rate fluctuations arising from financial institutions’ demand for dollar liquid assets. Financial flows are unpredictable and may leave banks “scrambling for dollars.” Because of settlement frictions in interbank markets, a precautionary demand for dollar reserves emerges and gives rise to an endogenous convenience yield on the dollar. We show that an increase in the dollar funding risk leads to a rise in the convenience yield and an appreciation of the dollar, as banks scramble for dollars. We present empirical evidence on the relationship between exchange rate fluctuations for the G10 currencies and the quantity of dollar liquidity, which is consistent with the theory.]]></description><author>Javier Bianchi, Saki Bigio, Charles Engel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29457</guid></item><item><title>Macroprudential Policies and The Covid-19 Pandemic: Risks and Challenges For Emerging Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29441</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> This paper deals with COVID and macroprudential regulations in emerging markets. I document the build-up of a sturdy macroprudential structure during 2009-2019, and the relaxation of regulations in 2020-2021, as part of the effort to deal with the sanitary emergency. I show that in every country, regulatory forbearance played a key role in the response to COVID. I discuss capital controls as macroprudential instruments. I argue that rebuilding the macroprudential fabric is important to reduce the costs of future systemic shocks. I maintain that post-COVID regulations should incorporate the risks associated with digital currencies.]]></description><author>Sebastian Edwards</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29441</guid></item><item><title>The International Price of Remote Work</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29437</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We use data from a large web-based job platform to study how the price of remote work is determined in a globalized labor market. In the platform, workers from around the world compete for jobs that can be done remotely. We document that, despite the global nature of the marketplace, the location of the worker accounts for over a third of the variance in wages. The observed wage differences are strongly correlated to the GDP per-capita of the worker’s country. This correlation is not accounted for by differences in workers’ characteristics, occupations, nor for differences in the employers’ locations. We also document that remote wages in local currency move almost one-for-one with the dollar exchange rate of the worker’s country, and are highly sensitive to changes in the wages of foreign competitors. Finally, we provide a new measure on which jobs are easier to offshore that is based on the prevalence of cross-border contracts rather than on subjective job characteristics, and show that there is substantial heterogeneity in the offshorability of remote occupations.]]></description><author>Agostina Brinatti, Alberto Cavallo, Javier Cravino, Andres Drenik</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29437</guid></item><item><title>Rethinking Exchange Rate Regimes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29347</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper employs an updated algorithm and database for classifying exchange rate and anchor currency choice, to explore the evolution of the global exchange rate system, including parallel rates, capital controls and reserves. In line with a large recent literature, we find that the dollar has become ever-more central as the de facto anchor or reference currencies for much of the world. Our discussion encompasses the history of anchor currency choice, methods for classifying exchange rate regimes, a detailed discussion of the evolution of regimes, the growing substitution of reserves for capital controls as a tool for exchange rate stabilization, the modern Triffin dilemma, and the surprising recent trend decline in volatility of exchange rates at the core of the system. It concludes with issues surrounding the rise of China.]]></description><author>Ethan Ilzetzki, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29347</guid></item><item><title>International Reserve Management, Global Financial Shocks, and Firms’ Investment in Emerging Market Economies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29303</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We examine the effects of active international reserve management (IRM) conducted by central banks of emerging market economies (EMEs) on firm investment in the presence of global financial shocks. Using firm level data from 46 EMEs from 2000 to 2018, we document four findings. First, active IRM positively affects firm investment - the effect strengthens with the magnitude of adverse external financial shocks. Second, financially constrained firms, compared with unconstrained ones, are less responsive to active IRM. Third, our results suggest that the country credit spread is a plausible causal channel of the positive IRM effect on firm investment. Fourth, the policies of capital controls and exchange rate managements are complementary to the IRM – it is beneficial to form a macro policy mix including active IRM to safeguard firm investment against global financial shocks. Further, our results indicate the IRM effect on firm investment is both statistical and economical significance and is relevant to the aggregate economy.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yin-Wong Cheung, Xingwang Qian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29303</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Policy in the Age of COVID: Does it ‘Get in all of the Cracks?’</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the effects of fiscal policy in response to the COVID-19 pandemic at the firm, sector, country and global level. First, we estimate the impact of COVID-19 and policy responses on small and medium sized enterprise (SME) business failures. We combine firm-level financial data from 50 sectors in 27 countries, a detailed I-O network, real-time data on lockdown policies and mobility patterns, and a rich model of firm behavior that allows for several dimensions of heterogeneity. We find: (a) Absent government support, the failure rate of SMEs would have increased by 9 percentage points, significantly more so in emerging market economies (EMs). With policy support it only increased by 4.3 percentage points, and even decreased in advanced economies (AEs). (b) Fiscal policy was poorly targeted: most of the funds disbursed went to firms who did not need it. (c) Nevertheless, we find little evidence of the policy merely postponing mass business failures or creating many ‘zombie’ firms: failure rates rise only slightly in 2021 once policy support is removed. Next, we build a tractable global intertemporal general equilibrium I-O model with fiscal policy. We calibrate the model to 64 countries and 36 sectors. We find that: (d) a sizable share of the global economy is demand-constrained under COVID-19, especially so in EMs. (e) Globally, fiscal policy helped offset about 8% of the downturn in COVID, with a low ‘traditional’ fiscal multiplier. Yet it significantly reduced the share of demand- constrained sectors, preserving employment in these sectors. (f) Fiscal policy exerted small and negative spillovers to output in other countries but positive spillovers on employment. (g) A two-speed recovery would put significant upwards pressure on global interest rates which imposes an additional headwind on the EM recovery. (h) Corporate and sovereign spreads rise when global rates increase, suggesting that EM may face challenging external funding conditions as AEs economies normalize.]]></description><author>Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, Ṣebnem Kalemli-Özcan, Veronika Penciakova, Nick Sander</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</guid></item><item><title>The Aftermath of Debt Surges</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29266</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Debt in emerging market and developing economies (EMDEs) is at its highest level in half a century. In about nine out of 10 EMDEs, debt is higher now than it was in 2010 and, in half of the EMDEs, debt is more than 30 percentage points of gross domestic product higher. Historically, elevated debt levels increased the incidence of debt distress, particularly in EMDEs and particularly when financial market conditions turned less benign. This paper reviews an encompassing menu of options that have, in the past, helped lower debt burdens. Specifically, it examines orthodox options (enhancing growth, fiscal consolidation, privatization, and wealth taxation) and heterodox options (inflation, financial repression, debt default and restructuring). The mix of feasible options depends on country characteristics and the type of debt. However, none of these options comes without political, economic, and social costs. Some options may ultimately be ineffective unless vigorously implemented. Policy reversals in difficult times have been common. The challenges associated with debt reduction raise questions of global governance, including to what extent advanced economies can cast their net wider to cushion prospective shocks to EMDEs.]]></description><author>M. Ayhan Kose, Franziska L. Ohnsorge, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29266</guid></item><item><title>The Flight to Safety and International Risk Sharing</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29238</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study a business cycle model of the international monetary system featuring a time-varying demand for safe dollar bonds, greater risk-bearing capacity in the U.S. than the rest of the world, and nominal rigidities.  A flight to safety generates a dollar appreciation and decline in global output.  Dollar bonds thus command a negative risk premium and the U.S. holds a levered portfolio of capital financed in dollars.  We quantify the effects of safety shocks and heterogeneity in risk-bearing capacity for global macroeconomic volatility; U.S. external adjustment; and the international transmission of monetary and fiscal policies, including dollar swap lines.]]></description><author>Rohan Kekre, Moritz Lenel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29238</guid></item><item><title>Simulating Endogenous Global Automation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29220</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper develops a 17-region, 3-skill group, overlapping generations, computable general equilibrium model to evaluate the global consequences of automation. Automation, modeled as capital- and high-skill biased technological change, is endogenous with regions adopting new technologies when profitable. Our approach captures and quantifies key macro implications of a range of foundational models of automation. In our baseline scenario, automation has a moderate effect on regional outputs and a small effect on world interest rates. However, it has a major impact on inequality, both wage inequality within regions and per capita GDP inequality across regions. We examine two policy responses to technological change -- mandating use of the advanced technology and providing universal basic income to share gains from automation. The former policy can raise a region's output, but at a welfare cost. The latter policy can transform automation into a win-win for all generations in a region.]]></description><author>Seth G. Benzell, Laurence J. Kotlikoff, Guillermo LaGarda, Victor Yifan Ye</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29220</guid></item><item><title>A Theory of the Global Financial Cycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29217</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We develop a theory to account for changes in prices of risky and safe assets and gross and net capital flows over the global financial cycle (GFC). The multi-country model features global risk-aversion shocks and heterogeneity of investors both within and across countries. Within-country heterogeneity is needed to account for the drop in gross capital flows during a negative GFC shock (higher global risk-aversion). Cross-country heterogeneity is needed to account for the differential vulnerability of countries to a negative GFC shock. The key vulnerability is associated with leverage. In both the data and the theory, leveraged countries (net borrowers of safe assets) deleverage through negative net outflows of risky assets and positive net outflows of safe assets, experience a rise in the current account and a greater than average drop in risky asset prices. The opposite is the case for non-leveraged countries (net lenders of safe assets).]]></description><author>J. Scott Davis, Eric van Wincoop</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29217</guid></item><item><title>Sovereign Spreads and the Political Leaning of Nations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29197</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Using data from 56 nations over 45 years, we find that nations that are more likely to elect left wing governments face higher (and more volatile) sovereign spreads. To explain these facts, we build a sovereign default model in which two policymakers (left and right) alternate in power. The probability of an incumbent staying in power is increasing in the share of government spending. We parametrize the left policymaker as having a higher marginal political gain from increasing government spending than the right does, a feature found in our data. Model economies in which the left is more frequently in power face worse borrowing terms due to higher default risk, a greater reluctance for fiscal austerity in bad times, and a higher share of government spending on average. These features imply large welfare losses for households.]]></description><author>Ionut Cotoc, Alok Johri, César Sosa-Padilla</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29197</guid></item><item><title>Do Central Banks Rebalance Their Currency Shares?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29190</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Do central banks rebalance their currency shares? The answer matters because the dollar’s predominant role in large official reserve holdings means that widespread rebalancing requires central banks to buy (sell) a depreciating (appreciating) dollar, stabilising its value against other major currencies. We hypothesise that larger reserve holdings have led central banks to approach their investment more systematically and to make rebalancing in the face of exchange rate changes the norm. We illustrate the choice with two polar case studies: the US clearly does not rebalance its small FX reserves; Switzerland does rebalance its very large reserves, so that changes in exchange rates do not move its currency allocation. Our hypothesis finds partial support in global aggregated data. They reject both no rebalancing and full rebalancing and point to emerging market economies as the source of the aggregate result. We also test for rebalancing with panel data and find that our sample economies on average again behave in intermediate fashion, partially but not fully rebalancing. However, when observations are weighted by the size of reserves, the panel analysis finds full rebalancing. A variety of control variables and splits of the panel sample do not alter the thrust of these findings. Central banks rebalance their FX reserves extensively but not uniformly.]]></description><author>Menzie D. Chinn, Hiro Ito, Robert N. McCauley</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29190</guid></item><item><title>Procyclical Fiscal Policy and Asset Market Incompleteness</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29149</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> To explain the fact that government spending and tax policy are procyclical in emerging and developing countries, we develop a model for the joint behavior of optimal tax rates and government spending over the business cycle. Our set-up relies on financial frictions, which have been shown to be critical features of emerging markets, captured by various degrees of asset market incompleteness as well as varying levels of debt-elastic interest rate spreads. We first uncover a novel theoretical result within a simple static framework: incomplete markets can account for procyclical government spending but not necessarily procyclical tax policy. Explaining procyclical tax policy also requires that the ratio of private to public consumption comoves positively with the business cycle, which leads to larger fluctuations in the tax base. We then show that the procyclicality of tax policy holds in a more realistic DSGE model calibrated to emerging markets. Finally, we illustrate how larger financial frictions, which amplify the business cycle through more procyclical fiscal policies, have sizeable Lucas-type welfare costs.]]></description><author>Andrés Fernández, Daniel Guzman, Ruy E. Lama, Carlos A. Vegh</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29149</guid></item></channel></rss>