<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Culture</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Culture</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:20:08 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>"When Anything Can Happen”: Anticipated Adversity and Postsecondary Decision-Making</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29472</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Stefanie DeLuca, Nicholas W. Papageorge, Joseph L. Boselovic, Seth Gershenson, Andrew Gray, Kiara M. Nerenberg, Jasmine Sausedo, Allison Young.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We examine how disadvantaged students make postsecondary education decisions, focusing on why they often opt for short, ﬂexible programs that tend to have low returns in the labor market. Prior literature emphasizes information deﬁcits and ﬁnancial constraints. We draw upon qualitative data collected via open-ended interviews conducted with a sample of economically disadvantaged Black youth in Baltimore. We use these data to develop and explore a complementary narrative: students who have faced instability or hardship in the form of disruptive events, or “adverse shocks” (e.g., violence, eviction or incarceration of a family member), anticipate future shocks that could derail their educational plans. In response, they opt for shorter, more ﬂexible educational programs that they expect they can complete despite anticipated shocks. When possible, we corroborate this narrative using publicly available, large-N data sets such as the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth (NLSY). Finally, we formalize this narrative as a simple dynamic structural model calibrated using data on education choices and returns. The model clariﬁes that it is impossible to identify costs of schooling without data on beliefs about the probability of non-completion, thus providing guidance on future data collection priorities. More broadly, our approach demonstrates a novel application of mixed methods research: using qualitative data to aid in the speciﬁcation of a structural model. This approach could be applied in other contexts where behavior is poorly understood and extant data do not contain all of the information needed to generate and test plausible hypotheses.]]></description><author>Stefanie DeLuca, Nicholas W. Papageorge, Joseph L. Boselovic, Seth Gershenson, Andrew Gray, Kiara M. Nerenberg, Jasmine Sausedo, Allison Young</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29472</guid></item><item><title>The Hot Hand in the NBA 3-Point Contest: The Importance of Location, Location, Location</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29468</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Robert M. Lantis, Erik T. Nesson.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Do basketball players exhibit a hot hand? Results from controlled shooting situations suggest the answer is yes, while results from in-game shooting are mixed. Are the differing results because a hot hand is only present in similar shots or because testing for the hot hand in game situations is difficult? Combining repeated shots in a location and shots across locations, the NBA 3-Point Contests mimics game situations without many of the confounding factors. Using data on the 1986-2019 contests, we find a hot hand, but only within shot locations. Shooting streaks increase a hot hand only if a player makes his previous shot and only within locations. Even making three shots in a row has no effect on making the next shot if a player moves locations. Our results suggest that any hot hand in basketball is only present in extremely similar shooting situations and likely not in the run-of-play.]]></description><author>Robert M. Lantis, Erik T. Nesson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29468</guid></item><item><title>Does Social Media cause Polarization? Evidence from access to Twitter Echo Chambers during the 2019 Argentine Presidential Debate</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29458</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Rafael Di Tella, Ramiro H. Gálvez, Ernesto Schargrodsky.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study how two groups, those inside vs those outside echo chambers, react to a political event when we vary social media status (Twitter). Our treatments mimic two strategies often suggested as a way to limit polarization on social media: they expose people to counter-attitudinal data, and they get people to switch off social media. Our main result is that subjects that started inside echo chambers became more polarized when these two strategies were implemented. The only scenario where they did not become more polarized is when they did not even experience the political event. Interestingly, subjects that were outside echo chambers before our study began experienced no change (or a reduction) in polarization. We also study a group of non-Twitter users in order to have a simple, offline benchmark of the debate’s impact on polarization.]]></description><author>Rafael Di Tella, Ramiro H. Gálvez, Ernesto Schargrodsky</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29458</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Gap in Preferences: Evidence from 45,397 Facebook Interests</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Ángel Cuevas, Rubén Cuevas, Klaus Desmet, Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses information on the frequency of 45,397 Facebook interests to study how the difference in preferences between men and women changes with a country's degree of gender equality. For preference dimensions that are systematically biased toward the same gender across the globe, differences between men and women are larger in more gender-equal countries. In contrast, for preference dimensions with a gender bias that varies across countries, the opposite holds. This finding takes an important step toward reconciling evolutionary psychology and social role theory as they relate to gender.]]></description><author>Ángel Cuevas, Rubén Cuevas, Klaus Desmet, Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</guid></item><item><title>Licence to Dine: 007 and the Real Exchange Rate</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29415</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Lee A. Craig, Julianne Treme, Thomas J. Weiss.</b> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We constructed a time series of menu prices for the identifiable restaurants at which James Bond dined in France and the UK that yields one of the few international price series representing luxury services.  This series enabled us to calculate a real exchange rate based on prices pertinent to international travelers.  We also compiled a time series on the salary of workers in the British Civil Service at Grade 7, like Bond, from 1953 to 2019.  Our results indicate that French restaurant prices increased faster than Grade 7 salaries over the entire period and changes in the British exchange rate were not favorable for British travelers.  To dine weekly in France, during the 1950s and 1960s, Bond would have spent 18 percent of his salary; whereas over the course of the Euro era the same basket of luxury services would have required on average 26 percent of his salary.  Finally, our data indicate a likely violation of the law of one price during both the Pound-Franc and Pound-Euro eras.]]></description><author>Lee A. Craig, Julianne Treme, Thomas J. Weiss</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29415</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Fragility of For-profit Hospitals: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun.</b> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We estimate the likelihood of financial distress of U.S. hospitals in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic using AHA Annual Survey data for 2011-2019 and smartphone mobility data for 2020. We find that while the average likelihood of distress across all hospitals is 28.53 % in 2020, slightly increasing from 2019, for-profit hospitals are much more likely to be distressed. Their average likelihood of financial distress is 39.13 %---a 6.93 percentage point increase from 2019. For-profit hospitals are the main providers of specialty health care services, such as psychiatric and acute long-term care, so their increased likelihood of distress poses a risk to service provision in these specialty areas, and particularly in rural communities. Our prediction model based on mobility data performs very well in sample against actual data and can potentially help policymakers and hospital administrators to monitor financial distress in real-time when case mixes change, or other large shocks materialize.]]></description><author>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</guid></item><item><title>Herding, Warfare, and a Culture of Honor: Global Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29250</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Yiming Cao, Benjamin Enke, Armin Falk, Paola Giuliano, Nathan Nunn.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> According to the widely known ‘culture of honor’ hypothesis from social psychology, traditional herding practices are believed to have generated a value system that is conducive to revenge-taking and violence. We test this idea at a global scale using a combination of ethnographic records, historical folklore information, global data on contemporary conflict events, and large-scale surveys. The data show systematic links between traditional herding practices and a culture of honor. First, the culture of pre-industrial societies that relied on animal herding emphasizes violence, punishment, and revenge-taking. Second, contemporary ethnolinguistic groups that historically subsisted more strongly on herding have more frequent and severe conflict today. Third, the contemporary descendants of herders report being more willing to take revenge and punish unfair behavior in the globally representative Global Preferences Survey. In all, the evidence supports the idea that this form of economic subsistence generated a functional psychology that has persisted until today and plays a role in shaping conflict across the globe.]]></description><author>Yiming Cao, Benjamin Enke, Armin Falk, Paola Giuliano, Nathan Nunn</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29250</guid></item><item><title>The Dynamics of Referral Hiring and Racial Inequality: Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29246</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Conrad Miller, Ian M. Schmutte.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study how referral hiring contributes to racial inequality in firm-level labor demand over the firm's life cycle using data from Brazil. We consider a search model where referral networks are segregated, firms are more informed about the match quality of referred candidates, and some referrals are made by non-referred employees. Consistent with the model, we find that firms are more likely to hire candidates and less likely to dismiss employees of the same race as the founder, but these differences diminish as firms' cumulative hires increase. Referral hiring helps to explain racial differences in dismissals, seniority, and employer size.]]></description><author>Conrad Miller, Ian M. Schmutte</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29246</guid></item><item><title>Media and Social Capital</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29230</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Filipe R. Campante, Ruben Durante, Andrea Tesei.</b> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We survey the empirical literature in economics on the impact of media technologies on social capital. Motivated by a simple model of information and collective action, we cover a range of different outcomes related to social capital, from social and political participation to interpersonal trust, in its benign and destructive manifestations. The impact of media technologies hinges on their content ("information" vs "entertainment"), their effectiveness in fostering coordination, and the networks they create, as well as individual characteristics and media consumption choices.]]></description><author>Filipe R. Campante, Ruben Durante, Andrea Tesei</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29230</guid></item><item><title>What We Teach About Race and Gender: Representation in Images and Text of Children’s Books</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29123</link><description><![CDATA[<b>Anjali Adukia, Alex Eble, Emileigh Harrison, Hakizumwami Birali Runesha, Teodora Szasz.</b> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Books shape how children learn about society and social norms, in part through the representation of different characters. To better understand the messages children encounter in books, we introduce new artificial intelligence methods for systematically converting images into data. We apply these image tools, along with established text analysis methods, to measure the representation of race, gender, and age in children’s books commonly found in US schools and homes over the last century. We find that more characters with darker skin color appear over time, but "mainstream" award-winning books, which are twice as likely to be checked out from libraries, persistently depict more lighter-skinned characters even after conditioning on perceived race. Across all books, children are depicted with lighter skin than adults. Over time, females are increasingly present but are more represented in images than in text, suggesting greater symbolic inclusion in pictures than substantive inclusion in stories. Relative to their growing share of the US population, Black and Latinx people are underrepresented in the mainstream collection; males, particularly White males, are persistently overrepresented. Our data provide a view into the "black box" of education through children’s books in US schools and homes, highlighting what has changed and what has endured.]]></description><author>Anjali Adukia, Alex Eble, Emileigh Harrison, Hakizumwami Birali Runesha, Teodora Szasz</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29123</guid></item></channel></rss>