<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER program Children</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER program Children</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 13:42:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>School Food Policy Affects Everyone: Retail Responses to the National School Lunch Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29384</link><description>We study the private market response to the National School Lunch Program, documenting economically meaningful spillovers to non-recipients. We focus on the Community Eligibility Provision (CEP), an expansion of the lunch program under the 2010 Healthy, Hunger-Free Kids Act. Under the CEP, participating schools offer free lunch to all students. We leverage both the staggered roll-out and eligibility criterion for the CEP, which is limited to schools where at least 40% of students participate in other means-tested welfare programs. We find that local adoption of the CEP causes households with children to reduce their grocery purchases, leading to a 10% decline in grocery sales at large retail chains. Retailers respond with chain-level price adjustments: chains with the most exposure lower prices by 2.5% across all outlets in the years following adoption, so that the program's welfare benefits propagate spatially. Using a stylized model of grocery demand, we estimate that, by 2016, the indirect benefit had reduced grocery costs for the median household by approximately 4.5%.
&lt;/p&gt;


              &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    function getCookieValue(name) {
      var cookies = "; " + document.cookie,
          parts = cookies.split("; " + name + "=");
      if (parts.length == 2) {
        return parts.pop().split(";").shift();
      }
    }
    fetch("/api/v1/auth/333863", { credentials: "include" })
      .then(
        function(response) {
          if (response.status !== 200) {
            console.log('Looks like there was a problem. Status Code: ' + response.status);
            return;
          }
          response.text().then(function(data) {
            var cookieValue = getCookieValue('STYXKEY_expecting_cookie'),
                userEmailInput = document.getElementById('user_email');

            document.getElementById('authorize-banner').innerHTML = data;

            if (userEmailInput) {
              userEmailInput.value = cookieValue ? cookieValue : '';
            }

            window.dataLayer = window.dataLayer || [];
            let can_view = Boolean(response.headers.get('X-NBER-CAN-VIEW-PAPER'));
            let sub_type = response.headers.get('X-NBER-SUBSCRIBER-TYPE');

            dataLayer.push({
              "event": "can_view_paper_response",
              "can_view_paper": can_view,
              "subscriber_type": sub_type,
            });
          });
        }
      )
      .catch(function(err) {
        console.log('Fetch Error :-S', err);
      });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;div id="authorize-banner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="accordion-set"&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;div class="accordion"&gt;
          &lt;button class="accordion__title js-accordion" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="accordion-body-guid1" id="accordion-button-guid1"&gt;Acknowledgements and Disclosures&lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;div class="accordion__body" id="accordion-body-guid1" aria-labelledby="accordion-button-guid1" style="display: none;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;
We would like to thank Lin Fan, Erik James, and Megan Taylor for excellent research assistance and participants at the AREUEA, ASSA-Industrial Organization Society, National Tax Association, NBER Urban Economics Summer Institute, UC Berkeley Opportunity Lab, and Urban Economics Association conferences and the Atlanta Fed, McGill, INRAE, UBC, UC Irvine, and Yale Economics for helpful comments, especially discussants Justin Gallagher, Justine Hastings, Xavier Jaravel, and Adam Kapor. This work is supported by the Robert King Steel Faculty Fellowship at the University of Chicago Booth School of Business and the Research Sponsor's Program of the Zell/Lurie Real Estate Center. Researcher(s) own analyses calculated (or derived) based in part on data from Nielsen Consumer LLC and marketing databases provided through the NielsenIQ Datasets at the Kilts Center for Marketing Data Center at The University of Chicago Booth School of Business. Researcher(s) own analyses calculated (or derived) based in part on data from Nielsen Consumer LLC and marketing databases provided through the NielsenIQ Datasets at the Kilts Center for Marketing Data Center at The University of Chicago Booth School of Business. The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Bureau of Economic Research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
              &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/jessie_handbury"&gt;Jessie Handbury&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
No additional disclosures.</description><author>Jessie Handbury, Sarah Moshary</author></item><item><title>The Anti-Poverty, Targeting, and Labor Supply Effects of the Proposed Child Tax Credit Expansion</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29366</link><description>The proposed change under the American Families Plan (AFP) to the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act (TCJA) Child Tax Credit (CTC) would increase maximum benefit amounts to $3,000 or $3,600 per child (up from $2,000 per child) and make the full credit available to all low and middle-income families regardless of earnings or income. We estimate the anti-poverty, targeting, and labor supply effects of the expansion by linking survey data with administrative tax and government program data which form part of the Comprehensive Income Dataset (CID). Initially ignoring any behavioral responses, we estimate that the expansion of the CTC would reduce child poverty by 34% and deep child poverty by 39%. The expansion of the CTC would have a larger anti-poverty effect on children than any existing government program, though at a higher cost per child raised above the poverty line than any other means-tested program. Relatedly, the CTC expansion would allocate a smaller share of its total dollars to families at the bottom of the income distribution—as well as families with the lowest levels of long-term income, education, or health—than any existing means-tested program with the exception of housing assistance. We then simulate anti-poverty effects accounting for labor supply responses. By replacing the TCJA CTC (which contained substantial work incentives akin to the Earned Income Tax Credit) with a universal basic income-type benefit, the CTC expansion reduces the return to working at all by at least $2,000 per child for most workers with children. Relying on elasticity estimates consistent with mainstream simulation models and the academic literature, we estimate that this change in policy would lead 1.5 million workers (constituting 2.6% of all working parents) to exit the labor force. The decline in employment and the consequent earnings loss would mean that child poverty would only fall by 22% and deep child poverty would not fall at all with the CTC expansion.</description><author>Kevin Corinth, Bruce D. Meyer, Matthew Stadnicki, Derek Wu</author></item><item><title>Early Childhood Development, Human Capital and Poverty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29362</link><description>Children's experiences during early childhood are critical for their cognitive and socio-emotional development, two key dimensions of human capital. However, children from low income backgrounds often grow up lacking stimulation and basic investments, leading to developmental deficits that are difficult, if not impossible, to reverse later in life without intervention. The existence of these deficits are a key driver of inequality and contribute to the intergenerational transmission of poverty. In this paper, we discuss the framework used in economics to model parental investments and early childhood development and use it as an organizing tool to review some of the empirical evidence on early childhood research. We then present results from various important early childhoods interventions with emphasis on developing countries. Bringing these elements together we draw conclusions on what we have learned and provide some directions for future research.</description><author>Orazio Attanasio, Sarah Cattan, Costas Meghir</author></item><item><title>A Taste of Their Own Medicine: Guideline Adherence and Access to Expertise</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29356</link><description>We use population administrative data from Sweden to study adherence to 63 medication-related guidelines. We compare the adherence of patients without personal access to medical expertise to the adherence of those with access, namely doctors and their close relatives. We estimate that, among observably similar patients, access to expertise is associated with 3.8 percentage points lower adherence, relative to a baseline adherence rate of 54.4 percent among those without access. This association is larger for recommendations with a weaker clinical motivation. Our findings suggest an important role in non-adherence for factors other than those, such as ignorance, complexity, or failures of patient-provider communication, that would be expected to diminish with access to expertise.
&lt;/p&gt;


              &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    function getCookieValue(name) {
      var cookies = "; " + document.cookie,
          parts = cookies.split("; " + name + "=");
      if (parts.length == 2) {
        return parts.pop().split(";").shift();
      }
    }
    fetch("/api/v1/auth/329147", { credentials: "include" })
      .then(
        function(response) {
          if (response.status !== 200) {
            console.log('Looks like there was a problem. Status Code: ' + response.status);
            return;
          }
          response.text().then(function(data) {
            var cookieValue = getCookieValue('STYXKEY_expecting_cookie'),
                userEmailInput = document.getElementById('user_email');

            document.getElementById('authorize-banner').innerHTML = data;

            if (userEmailInput) {
              userEmailInput.value = cookieValue ? cookieValue : '';
            }

            window.dataLayer = window.dataLayer || [];
            let can_view = Boolean(response.headers.get('X-NBER-CAN-VIEW-PAPER'));
            let sub_type = response.headers.get('X-NBER-SUBSCRIBER-TYPE');

            dataLayer.push({
              "event": "can_view_paper_response",
              "can_view_paper": can_view,
              "subscriber_type": sub_type,
            });
          });
        }
      )
      .catch(function(err) {
        console.log('Fetch Error :-S', err);
      });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;div id="authorize-banner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="accordion-set"&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;div class="accordion"&gt;
          &lt;button class="accordion__title js-accordion" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="accordion-body-guid1" id="accordion-button-guid1"&gt;Acknowledgements and Disclosures&lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;div class="accordion__body" id="accordion-body-guid1" aria-labelledby="accordion-button-guid1" style="display: none;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;
We acknowledge funding from the Population Studies and Training Center and the Eastman Professorship at Brown University (Shapiro), and the National Institute on Aging under grant K01AG05984301 (Polyakova). We appreciate comments from Jon Gruber, Eric Patashnik, and seminar participants at the Research Institute of Industrial Economics and the Wharton School. We are grateful to Aron Malatinszky, Gabriel Swagel, and Yuci Zhou, as well as to Sarah Bögl and Katja Hofmann at the Research Institute of Industrial Economics, for excellent research assistance. The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Bureau of Economic Research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
              &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/jesse_shapiro"&gt;Jesse M. Shapiro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
Shapiro has, in the past, been a paid visitor at Microsoft Research New England and a paid consultant for FutureOfCapitalism, LLC. Shapiro has been paid for writing by the New York Times.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Shapiro's spouse has a disclosure statement posted at https://emilyoster.net/about/.</description><author>Amy Finkelstein, Petra Persson, Maria Polyakova, Jesse M. Shapiro</author></item><item><title>Estimating the Net Fiscal Cost of a Child Tax Credit Expansion</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29342</link><description>Recent proposals to expand the Child Tax Credit (CTC) are at the center of current policy discussions in the United States. We study the fiscal cost of three such proposals that would expand refundability of the credit to low-income children, increase the maximum credit amount, and/or eliminate the income phase-out to make the credit universal. For each proposal, we use the Current Population Survey to estimate three components of the net fiscal cost: the direct cost (additional tax refunds or lower tax liability), revenue changes due to taxpayers’ labor supply responses, and long-term changes in tax revenue due to changes in children’s future earnings. We find that direct costs are by far the most important component but that long-term earning changes also play an important role, offsetting one-third or more of the direct costs, depending on the proposal and modeling assumptions. In contrast, labor supply responses only modestly contribute to the fiscal cost of CTC expansions.</description><author>Jacob Goldin, Elaine Maag, Katherine Michelmore</author></item><item><title>The Psychosocial Effects of the Flint Water Crisis on School-Age Children</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29341</link><description>Lead poisoning has well-known impacts for the developing brain of young children, with a large literature documenting the negative effects of elevated blood lead levels on academic and behavioral outcomes. In April of 2014, the municipal water source in Flint, Michigan was changed, causing lead from aging pipes to leach into the city’s drinking water. In this study, we use Michigan’s universe of longitudinal, student-level education records, combined with home water service line inspection data containing the location of lead pipes, to empirically examine the effect of the Flint Water Crisis on educational outcomes of Flint public school children. We leverage parallel causal identification strategies, a between-district synthetic control analysis and a within-Flint difference-in-differences analysis, to separate out the direct health effects of lead exposure from the broad effects of living in a community experiencing a crisis. Our results highlight a less well-appreciated consequence of the Flint Water Crisis – namely, the psychosocial effects of the crisis on the educational outcomes of school-age children. These findings suggest that cost estimates which rely only on the negative impact of direct lead exposure substantially underestimate the overall societal cost of the crisis.</description><author>Sam Trejo, Gloria Yeomans-Maldonado, Brian Jacob</author></item><item><title>Exposure to Cigarette Taxes as a Teenager and the Persistence of Smoking into Adulthood</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29325</link><description>Are teenage and adult smoking causally related?  Recent anti-tobacco policy is predicated on the assumption that preventing teenagers from smoking will ensure that fewer adults smoke, but direct evidence in support of this assumption is scant.  Using data from three nationally representative sources and cigarette taxes experienced as a teenager as an instrument, we document a strong, positive relationship between teenage and adult smoking: specifically, deterring 10 teenagers from smoking through raising cigarette taxes roughly translates into 5 or 6 fewer eventual adult smokers.  We conclude that efforts to reduce teenage smoking can have important, long-lasting consequences on smoking participation and, presumably, health.</description><author>Andrew I. Friedson, Moyan Li, Katherine Meckel, Daniel I. Rees, Daniel W. Sacks</author></item><item><title>Why Don’t Elite Colleges Expand Supply?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29309</link><description>While college enrollment has more-than doubled since 1970, elite colleges have barely increased supply, instead reducing admit rates. We show that straightforward reasons cannot explain this behavior. We propose a model where colleges compete on prestige, measured using relative selectivity or relative admit rates. A key comparative static of the model is that higher demand decreases [increases] the admit rate when the weight on prestige is above [below] a critical value, consistent with experience in elite [non-elite] colleges. A calibrated version of the model closely replicates the pattern in the data of declining admit rates at elite colleges while counter-factual simulations without prestige fail. Prestige competition is inefficient. Allowing elite colleges to collude on admissions strategy internalizes the non-pecuniary prestige externality and is Pareto improving.</description><author>Peter Q. Blair, Kent Smetters</author></item><item><title>Why Does Education Increase Voting? Evidence from Boston’s Charter Schools</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29308</link><description>In the United States, people with more education vote more. But, we know little about why education increases political participation or whether higher-quality education increases civic participation. We study applicants to Boston charter schools, using school lotteries to estimate charter attendance impacts for academic and voting outcomes. First, we confirm large academic gains for students in the sample of charter schools and cohorts investigated here. Second, we find that charter attendance boosts voter participation. Voting in the first presidential election after a student turns 18 increased substantially, by six percentage points from a base of 35 percent. The voting effect is driven entirely by girls and there is no increase in voter registration. Rich data and the differential effects by gender enable exploration of multiple potential channels for the voting impact. We find evidence consistent with two mechanisms: charter schools increase voting by increasing students’ noncognitive skills and by politicizing families who participate in charter school education.
&lt;/p&gt;


              &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    function getCookieValue(name) {
      var cookies = "; " + document.cookie,
          parts = cookies.split("; " + name + "=");
      if (parts.length == 2) {
        return parts.pop().split(";").shift();
      }
    }
    fetch("/api/v1/auth/321654", { credentials: "include" })
      .then(
        function(response) {
          if (response.status !== 200) {
            console.log('Looks like there was a problem. Status Code: ' + response.status);
            return;
          }
          response.text().then(function(data) {
            var cookieValue = getCookieValue('STYXKEY_expecting_cookie'),
                userEmailInput = document.getElementById('user_email');

            document.getElementById('authorize-banner').innerHTML = data;

            if (userEmailInput) {
              userEmailInput.value = cookieValue ? cookieValue : '';
            }

            window.dataLayer = window.dataLayer || [];
            let can_view = Boolean(response.headers.get('X-NBER-CAN-VIEW-PAPER'));
            let sub_type = response.headers.get('X-NBER-SUBSCRIBER-TYPE');

            dataLayer.push({
              "event": "can_view_paper_response",
              "can_view_paper": can_view,
              "subscriber_type": sub_type,
            });
          });
        }
      )
      .catch(function(err) {
        console.log('Fetch Error :-S', err);
      });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;div id="authorize-banner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="accordion-set"&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;div class="accordion"&gt;
          &lt;button class="accordion__title js-accordion" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="accordion-body-guid1" id="accordion-button-guid1"&gt;Acknowledgements and Disclosures&lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;div class="accordion__body" id="accordion-body-guid1" aria-labelledby="accordion-button-guid1" style="display: none;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;
We are grateful to Carrie Conaway, Matthew Deninger, Pierre Lucien, Elana McDermott and the staff of the Massachusetts Department of Elementary and Secondary Education and the Boston area charter schools for facilitating the data access which made this project possible. We thank Alex Eble, Jeff Henig, Celia Paris, Corey Savage, Kirsten Slungaard Mumma, and conference and seminar participants at the Association for Education Finance and Policy conference, the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management conference, the Columbia Women’s Microeconomics Lunch, and the Centre for Economic Policy Research Education Economics Workshop for very helpful comments. Special thanks also go to Jacob Brown, Ryan Enos, Matt Kraft, Todd Rodgers, and to the Harvard Multidisciplinary Program in Inequality and Social Policy. Cameron Arnzen, Selena Cardona, Elizabeth Huffaker, Erin Huffer, and Katharine Parham provided excellent research assistance. This study was deemed exempt from human subjects review by the Teachers College Institutional Review Board. The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Bureau of Economic Research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
              &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/sarah_cohodes"&gt;Sarah Cohodes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
I declare that I have no relevant or material financial interests related to the research described in this paper entitled “Why Does Education Increase Voting? Evidence from Boston's Charter Schools.” I declare that I do not hold any positions as officer, director, or board member of relevant non-profit organizations or profit-making entities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Massachusetts Department of Elementary and Secondary Education had the right to review this paper prior to circulation in order to determine no individual’s data was disclosed.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/james_feigenbaum"&gt;James J. Feigenbaum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
I declare that I have no relevant or material financial interests related to the research described in this paper entitled “Why Does Education Increase Voting? Evidence from Boston's Charter Schools.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I declare that I do not hold any positions as officer, director, or board member of relevant non-profit organizations or profit-making entities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Massachusetts Department of Elementary and Secondary Education had the right to review this paper prior to circulation in order to determine no individual’s data was disclosed.</description><author>Sarah Cohodes, James J. Feigenbaum</author></item><item><title>Effect of the Jamaica Early Childhood Stimulation Intervention on Labor Market Outcomes at Age 31</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29292</link><description>We report the labor market effects of the Jamaica Early Childhood Stimulation intervention at age 31. The study is a small-sample randomized early childhood education stimulation intervention targeting stunted children living in the poor neighborhoods of Kingston, Jamaica. Implemented in 1987-1989, treatment consisted of a two-year home-based intervention designed to improve nutrition and the quality of mother-child interactions to foster cognitive, language and psycho-social skills. The original sample is 127 stunted children between 9 and 24 months old. Our study is able to track and interview 75% of the original sample 30 years after the intervention, both still living in Jamaica and migrated abroad. We find large and statistically significant effects on income and schooling; the treatment group had 43% higher hourly wages and 37% higher earnings than the control group. This is a substantial increase over the treatment effect estimated for age 22 where we observed a 25% increase in earnings. The Jamaican Study is a rare case of a long-term follow up for an early childhood development (ECD) intervention implemented in a less-developed country. Our results confirm large economic returns to an early childhood intervention that targeted disadvantaged families living in poverty in the poor neighborhoods of Jamaica. The Jamaican intervention is being replicated around the world. Our analysis provides justification for expanding ECD interventions targeting disadvantaged children living in poor countries around the world.</description><author>Paul Gertler, James J. Heckman, Rodrigo Pinto, Susan M. Chang, Sally Grantham-McGregor, Christel Vermeersch, Susan Walker, Amika Wright</author></item><item><title>Mobility for All: Representative Intergenerational Mobility Estimates over the 20th Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29289</link><description>We present the first estimates of long-run trends in intergenerational relative mobility for samples that are representative of the full U.S.-born population.  Harmonizing all surveys that ask about father's occupation and own family income, we develop a mobility measure that allows for the inclusion of non-whites and women for the 1910s–1970s birth cohorts.  We show a robust increase in mobility between the 1910s and 1940s cohorts, about half of which is driven by absolute convergence in racial income gaps. We also find that excluding Black Americans, particularly Black women, considerably overstates mobility throughout the 20th century.
&lt;/p&gt;


              &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    function getCookieValue(name) {
      var cookies = "; " + document.cookie,
          parts = cookies.split("; " + name + "=");
      if (parts.length == 2) {
        return parts.pop().split(";").shift();
      }
    }
    fetch("/api/v1/auth/321642", { credentials: "include" })
      .then(
        function(response) {
          if (response.status !== 200) {
            console.log('Looks like there was a problem. Status Code: ' + response.status);
            return;
          }
          response.text().then(function(data) {
            var cookieValue = getCookieValue('STYXKEY_expecting_cookie'),
                userEmailInput = document.getElementById('user_email');

            document.getElementById('authorize-banner').innerHTML = data;

            if (userEmailInput) {
              userEmailInput.value = cookieValue ? cookieValue : '';
            }

            window.dataLayer = window.dataLayer || [];
            let can_view = Boolean(response.headers.get('X-NBER-CAN-VIEW-PAPER'));
            let sub_type = response.headers.get('X-NBER-SUBSCRIBER-TYPE');

            dataLayer.push({
              "event": "can_view_paper_response",
              "can_view_paper": can_view,
              "subscriber_type": sub_type,
            });
          });
        }
      )
      .catch(function(err) {
        console.log('Fetch Error :-S', err);
      });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;div id="authorize-banner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="accordion-set"&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;div class="accordion"&gt;
          &lt;button class="accordion__title js-accordion" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="accordion-body-guid1" id="accordion-button-guid1"&gt;Acknowledgements and Disclosures&lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;div class="accordion__body" id="accordion-body-guid1" aria-labelledby="accordion-button-guid1" style="display: none;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;
We thank Ahna Pearson and Paola Villa-Paro for excellent research assistance.  Sandy Black, Leah Boustan, Ellora Derenoncourt, James Feigenbaum, Nathan Hendren, Tom Hertz, Chi Hyun Kim, Trevon Logan, Chris Muller, and Zachary Ward have provided invaluable data and feedback at various stages of this project.  We thank seminar participants at ASSA, Berkeley, Cologne, Georgetown, NBER, Northwestern, NYU Wagner, Princeton, Toronto, UCL, USC, Warwick, and Wharton. The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Bureau of Economic Research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
              &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/ilyana_kuziemko"&gt;Ilyana Kuziemko&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
Outside of my university salary my only source of income is as a co-editor at AEJ Applied Economics.</description><author>Elisa Jácome, Ilyana Kuziemko, Suresh Naidu</author></item><item><title>The Puzzle of Falling US Birth Rates Since the Great Recession</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29286</link><description>This paper documents a set of facts about the dramatic decline in birth rates in the United States between 2007 and 2020 and explores possible explanations. The overall reduction in the birth rate reflects declines across many groups of women, including women who differ by race and ethnicity, age, and level of education. The Great Recession contributed to the decline in the early part of this period, but we are unable to identify any other economic, policy, or social factor that has changed since 2007 that is responsible for much of the decline beyond that. Mechanically, the falling birth rate can be attributed to changes in birth patterns across recent cohorts of women moving through childbearing age. We conjecture that the “shifting priorities” of more recent cohorts, reflecting changes in preferences for having children, aspirations for life, and parenting norms, may be responsible. We conclude with a brief discussion about the societal consequences for a declining birth rate and what the United States might do about it.</description><author>Melissa Schettini Kearney, Phillip B. Levine, Luke W. Pardue</author></item><item><title>The Initial Effects of the Expanded Child Tax Credit on Material Hardship</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285</link><description>The transformation of the Child Tax Credit (CTC) into a more generous, inclusive monthly payment marks a historic (temporary) shift in U.S. treatment of low-income families. To investigate the initial impact of these payments, we apply a series of difference-in-difference estimates using Census Household Pulse Survey microdata collected from April 14 through August 16, 2021. Our findings offer three primary conclusions regarding the initial effects of the monthly CTC. First, payments strongly reduced food insufficiency: the initial payments led to a 7.5 percentage point (25 percent) decline in food insufficiency among low-income households with children. Second, the effects on food insufficiency are concentrated among families with 2019 pre-tax incomes below $35,000, and the CTC strongly reduces food insufficiency among low-income Black, Latino, and White families alike. Third, increasing the CTC coverage rate would be required in order for material hardship to be reduced further. Self-reports suggest the lowest-income households were less likely than higher-income families to receive the first CTC payments. As more children receive the benefit in future months, material hardship may decline further. Even with imperfect coverage, however, our findings suggest that the first CTC payments were largely effective at reducing food insufficiency among low-income families with children.</description><author>Zachary Parolin, Elizabeth Ananat, Sophie M. Collyer, Megan Curran, Christopher Wimer</author></item><item><title>The Consequences of Chronic Pain in Mid-Life: Evidence from the National Child Development Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29278</link><description>Using data from all those born in a single week in 1958 in Britain we track the consequences of short pain and chronic pain in mid-life (age 44) on health, wellbeing and labor market outcomes in later life.  We examine data taken at age 50 in 2008, when the Great Recession hit and then five years later at age 55 in 2013.  We find those suffering both short-term and chronic pain at age 44 continue to report pain and poor general health in their 50s.  However, the associations are much stronger for those with chronic pain.  Furthermore, chronic pain at age 44 is associated with a range of poor mental health outcomes, pessimism about the future and joblessness at age 55 whereas short-duration pain at age 44 is not.  Uniquely, we also show that pain experienced in childhood, at ages 11 and 16, reported by a parent and a teacher respectively, collected decades earlier, predicts pain in mid-life, indicating just how persistent pain can be over the life-course.
&lt;/p&gt;


              &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    function getCookieValue(name) {
      var cookies = "; " + document.cookie,
          parts = cookies.split("; " + name + "=");
      if (parts.length == 2) {
        return parts.pop().split(";").shift();
      }
    }
    fetch("/api/v1/auth/317410", { credentials: "include" })
      .then(
        function(response) {
          if (response.status !== 200) {
            console.log('Looks like there was a problem. Status Code: ' + response.status);
            return;
          }
          response.text().then(function(data) {
            var cookieValue = getCookieValue('STYXKEY_expecting_cookie'),
                userEmailInput = document.getElementById('user_email');

            document.getElementById('authorize-banner').innerHTML = data;

            if (userEmailInput) {
              userEmailInput.value = cookieValue ? cookieValue : '';
            }

            window.dataLayer = window.dataLayer || [];
            let can_view = Boolean(response.headers.get('X-NBER-CAN-VIEW-PAPER'));
            let sub_type = response.headers.get('X-NBER-SUBSCRIBER-TYPE');

            dataLayer.push({
              "event": "can_view_paper_response",
              "can_view_paper": can_view,
              "subscriber_type": sub_type,
            });
          });
        }
      )
      .catch(function(err) {
        console.log('Fetch Error :-S', err);
      });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;div id="authorize-banner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="accordion-set"&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;div class="accordion"&gt;
          &lt;button class="accordion__title js-accordion" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="accordion-body-guid1" id="accordion-button-guid1"&gt;Acknowledgements and Disclosures&lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;div class="accordion__body" id="accordion-body-guid1" aria-labelledby="accordion-button-guid1" style="display: none;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Alex Bryson thanks the Health Foundation for funding (grant number 789112). We thank the ESRC Data Archive for access to the National Child Development Survey data. The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Bureau of Economic Research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
              &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/david_blanchflower"&gt;David G. Blanchflower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
None</description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson</author></item><item><title>The Returns to College(s): Relative Value-Added and Match Effects in Higher Education</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29276</link><description>Students who attend different colleges in the U.S. end up with vastly different economic outcomes. We study the role of relative value-added across colleges within student choice sets in producing these outcome disparities. Linking high school, college, and earnings registries spanning the state of Texas, we identify relative college value-added by comparing the outcomes of students who apply to and are admitted by the same set of institutions, as this approach strikingly balances observable student potential across college treatments and renders our extensive set of covariates irrelevant as controls. Methodologically, we develop a framework for identifying and interpreting value-added under varying assumptions about match effects and sorting gains. Empirically, we estimate a relatively tight, though non-degenerate, distribution of relative value-added across the wide diversity of Texas public universities. Selectivity poorly predicts value-added within student choice sets, with only a fleeting selectivity earnings premium fading to zero after a few years in the labor market. Non-peer college inputs like instructional spending more strongly predict value-added, especially conditional on selectivity. Colleges that boost BA completion, especially in STEM majors, also tend to boost earnings. Finally, we probe the potential for (mis)match effects by allowing value-added schedules to vary by student characteristics.</description><author>Jack Mountjoy, Brent R. Hickman</author></item><item><title>Life Course Effects Of The Lanham Preschools: What The First Government Preschool Effort Can Tell Us About Universal Early Care And Education Today</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29271</link><description>We examine the effects WWII Lanham Act Nursery Schools (LNS) on high school and young adult educational and labor outcomes of participants in the landmark Project Talent (PT) study. All PT places that received funding for LNS schools and all PT places that did not were identified by examining program records and contemporaneous newspaper accounts. Focusing on students who in 1960 attended high school in the same city or town where they were born, we estimate intent to treat effects of access to LNS preschool on high school academic and social emotional outcomes and on educational attainment and labor outcomes at five and eleven years following high school graduation. Preschool boosts high school academic outcomes for men and (in at least one specification) income 11 years after high school graduation. For women, preschool exposure had a negative effect on some social emotional outcomes in high school. We found no or inconsistent effects for other outcomes. The Lanham experience demonstrates that even with the less sophisticated understanding of child development of the early 1940s, the first universal, government-funded preschool program had positive impacts on boys’ outcomes at least through high school. Given today’s expanded understanding of child development and focus on the quality of early care and education programming, these findings provide some optimism as communities, states, and the federal government contemplate expanding funding for today’s early learning environments.</description><author>Taletha M. Derrington, Alison Huang, Joseph P. Ferrie</author></item><item><title>The Pandemic’s Effect on Demand for Public Schools, Homeschooling, and Private Schools</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29262</link><description>The Covid-19 pandemic drastically disrupted the functioning of U.S. public schools, potentially changing the relative appeal of alternatives such as homeschooling and private schools. Using longitudinal student-level administrative data from Michigan and nationally representative data from the Census Household Pulse Survey, we show how the pandemic affected families’ choices of school sector. We document four central facts. First, public school enrollment declined noticeably in fall 2020, with about 3 percent of Michigan students and 10 percent of kindergartners using other options. Second, most of this was driven by homeschooling rates jumping substantially, driven largely by families with children in elementary school. Third, homeschooling increased more where schools provided in-person instruction while private schooling increased more where instruction was remote, suggesting heterogeneity in parental concerns about children’s physical health and instructional quality. Fourth, kindergarten declines were highest among low income and Black families while declines in other grades were highest among higher income and White families, highlighting important heterogeneity by students’ existing attachment to public schools. Our results shed light on how families make schooling decisions and imply potential longer-run disruptions to public schools in the form of decreased enrollment and funding, changed composition of the student body, and increased size of the next kindergarten cohort.</description><author>Tareena Musaddiq, Kevin M. Stange, Andrew Bacher-Hicks, Joshua Goodman</author></item><item><title>The Effect of Safety Net Generosity on Maternal Mental Health and Risky Health Behaviors</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29258</link><description>A generous safety net may improve mental health outcomes and stress-related health behaviors for single mothers by promoting financial security, but stigma and hassle associated with welfare use could offset some of these gains. We use a simulated safety net eligibility approach that accounts for interactions across safety net programs and relies on changing policies across states and time to identify causal effects of safety net generosity on psychological distress and risky behaviors of single mothers. Our results suggest that a more generous safety net is protective of maternal mental health: we estimate that a $1000 increase to the combined cash and food benefit package reduces severe psychological distress by 5.5 percent. Breaking out effects by individual programs while still controlling for potential benefits from other programs, we find that this reduction is entirely due to simulated tax credit eligibility and appears to occur in the first half of the year, when such benefits are typically received. We find no significant effect of the overall safety net on risky behaviors like smoking and heavy drinking, but this masks offsetting effects of cash and food benefits, suggesting that the impact of improved financial resources depends on details of transfer program design.</description><author>Lucie Schmidt, Lara Shore-Sheppard, Tara Watson</author></item><item><title>Community Colleges and Upward Mobility</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29254</link><description>Two-year community colleges enroll nearly half of all first-time undergraduates in the United States, but to ambiguous effect: low persistence rates and the potential for diverting students from 4-year institutions cast ambiguity over 2-year colleges' contributions to upward mobility. This paper develops a new instrumental variables approach to identifying causal effects along multiple treatment margins, and applies it to linked education and earnings registries to disentangle the net impacts of 2-year college access into two competing causal margins: significant value-added for 2-year entrants who otherwise would not have attended college, but negative impacts on students diverted from immediate 4-year entry.</description><author>Jack Mountjoy</author></item><item><title>Inequality in Early Care Experienced by U.S. Children</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29249</link><description>Using every major nationally-representative dataset on parental and non-parental care provided to children up to age 6, we quantify differences in American children’s care experiences by socioeconomic status (SES), proxied primarily with maternal education. Increasingly, higher-SES children spend less time with their parents and more time in the care of others. Non-parental care for high-SES children is more likely to be in childcare centers, where average quality is higher, and less likely to be provided by relatives where average quality is lower. Even within types of childcare, higher-SES children tend to receive care of higher measured quality and higher cost. Inequality is evident at home as well: measures of parental enrichment at home, from both self-reports and outside observers, are on average higher for higher-SES children. We also find that parental and non-parental quality is reinforcing: children who receive higher quality non-parental care also tend to receive higher quality parental care. Head Start, one of the largest government care subsidy programs for low-income households, reduces inequality in care provided, but it is mainly limited to older children and to the lowest income households. Our evidence is from the pre-COVID-19 period, and the latest year we examine is 2019.</description><author>Sarah Flood, Joel F.S. McMurry, Aaron Sojourner, Matthew J. Wiswall</author></item><item><title>Why is Workplace Sexual Harassment Underreported? The Value of Outside Options Amid the Threat of Retaliation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29248</link><description>Why is workplace sexual harassment chronically underreported? We hypothesize that employers coerce victims into silence through the threat of a retaliatory firing, and test this theory by estimating whether external shocks that reduce the value of a worker's outside options exacerbate underreporting. Under mild assumptions, a rise in the severity of formal complaints is indicative of increased underreporting. Combining this insight with an objective measure of the quality of charges filed with the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC), we perform two analyses. First, we assess whether workers report sexual harassment more selectively during recessions, when outside labor market options are limited. We estimate the fraction of sexual harassment charges deemed to have merit by the EEOC increases by 0.5-0.7% for each one percentage point increase in a state-industry's monthly unemployment rate. The effect is amplified in industries employing a larger fraction of men and in establishments with a higher share of male managers. Second, we test whether less generous UI benefits create economic incentives for victims of workplace sexual harassment to remain silent. We find the selectivity of sexual harassment charges increases by more than 30% in response to a 50% cut to North Carolina's Unemployment Insurance (UI) program following the Great Recession.</description><author>Gordon B. Dahl, Matthew M. Knepper</author></item><item><title>Does Education Prevent Job Loss During Downturns? Evidence from Exogenous School Assignments and COVID-19 in Barbados</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29231</link><description>Canonical human capital theories posit that education, by enhancing worker skills, reduces the likelihood that a worker will be laid-off during times of economic change. Yet, this has not been demonstrated causally. We link administrative education records from 1987 through 2002 to nationally representative surveys conducted before and after COVID-19 onset in Barbados to explore the causal impact of improved education on job loss during this period. Using a regression discontinuity (RD) design, Beuermann and Jackson (2020) show that females (but not males) who score just above the admission threshold for more selective schools in Barbados attain more years of education than those that scored just below (essentially holding initial ability fixed). Here, in follow-up data, we show that these same females (but not males) are much less likely to have lost a job after the onset of COVID-19. We show that these effects are not driven by sectoral changes, or changes in labor supply. Because employers observe incumbent worker productivity, these patterns are inconsistent with pure education signalling, and suggest that education enhances worker skill.</description><author>Diether W. Beuermann, Nicolas L. Bottan, Bridget Hoffmann, C. Kirabo Jackson, Diego A. Vera Cossio</author></item><item><title>Intended and Unintended Effects of E-cigarette Taxes on Youth Tobacco Use</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29216</link><description>Over the past decade, rising youth use of e-cigarettes and other electronic nicotine delivery systems (ENDS) has prompted aggressive regulation by state and local governments. Between 2010 and 2019, ten states and two large counties adopted ENDS taxes. Applying a continuous treatment difference-in-differences approach to data from two large national datasets (Monitoring the Future and the Youth Risk Behavior Surveillance System), this study explores the impact of ENDS taxes on youth tobacco use. We find that ENDS taxes reduce youth e-cigarette consumption, with estimated e-cigarette tax elasticities of -0.06 to -0.21. However, we estimate sizable positive cigarette cross-tax elasticities, suggesting economic substitution between cigarettes and e-cigarettes for youth. These substitution effects are particularly large for frequent cigarette smoking. We conclude that the unintended effects of ENDS taxation may more than fully offset any public health gains.</description><author>Rahi Abouk, Charles J. Courtemanche, Dhaval M. Dave, Bo Feng, Abigail S. Friedman, Johanna Catherine Maclean, Michael F. Pesko, Joseph J. Sabia, Samuel Safford</author></item><item><title>Opportunity Unraveled: Private Information and the Missing Markets for Financing Human Capital</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29214</link><description>Investing in college carries high returns, but comes with considerable risk. Financial products like equity contracts can mitigate this risk, yet college is typically financed through non­dischargeable, government-backed student loans. This paper argues that adverse selection has unraveled private markets for college-financing contracts that mitigate risk. We use survey data on students' expected post-college outcomes to estimate their knowledge about future outcomes, and we translate these estimates into their implication for adverse selection of equity contracts and several state-contingent debt contracts. We find students hold significant private knowledge of their future earnings, academic persistence, employment, and loan repayment likelihood, beyond what is captured by observable characteristics. For example, our empirical results imply that a typical college-goer must expect to pay back $1.64 in present value for every $1 of equity financing to cover the financier's costs of covering those who would adversely select their contract. We estimate that college-goers are not willing to accept these terms so that private markets unravel. Nonetheless, our framework quantifies significant welfare gains from government subsidies that would open up these missing markets and partially insure college-going risks.</description><author>Daniel Herbst, Nathaniel Hendren</author></item><item><title>Inequality in Mortality between Black and White Americans by Age, Place, and Cause, and in Comparison to Europe, 1990-2018</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29203</link><description>Although there is a large gap between Black and White American life expectancies, the gap fell 48.9% between 1990-2018, mainly due to mortality declines among Black Americans. We examine age-specific mortality trends and racial gaps in life expectancy in rich and poor U.S. areas and with reference to six European countries.&lt;br /&gt;
Inequalities in life expectancy are starker in the U.S. than in Europe. In 1990 White Americans and Europeans in rich areas had similar overall life expectancy, while life expectancy for White Americans in poor areas was lower.  But since then even rich White Americans have lost ground relative to Europeans. Meanwhile, the gap in life expectancy between Black Americans and Europeans decreased by 8.3%.&lt;br /&gt;
Black life expectancy increased more than White life expectancy in all U.S. areas, but improvements in poorer areas had the greatest impact on the racial life expectancy gap. The causes that contributed the most to Black mortality reductions included: Cancer, homicide, HIV, and causes originating in the fetal or infant period.&lt;br /&gt;
Life expectancy for both Black and White Americans plateaued or slightly declined after 2012, but this stalling was most evident among Black Americans even prior to the COVID-19 pandemic. If improvements had continued at the 1990-2012 rate, the racial gap in life expectancy would have closed by 2036. European life expectancy also stalled after 2014. Still, the comparison with Europe suggests that mortality rates of both Black and White Americans could fall much further across all ages and in both rich and poor areas.
&lt;/p&gt;


              &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    function getCookieValue(name) {
      var cookies = "; " + document.cookie,
          parts = cookies.split("; " + name + "=");
      if (parts.length == 2) {
        return parts.pop().split(";").shift();
      }
    }
    fetch("/api/v1/auth/308088", { credentials: "include" })
      .then(
        function(response) {
          if (response.status !== 200) {
            console.log('Looks like there was a problem. Status Code: ' + response.status);
            return;
          }
          response.text().then(function(data) {
            var cookieValue = getCookieValue('STYXKEY_expecting_cookie'),
                userEmailInput = document.getElementById('user_email');

            document.getElementById('authorize-banner').innerHTML = data;

            if (userEmailInput) {
              userEmailInput.value = cookieValue ? cookieValue : '';
            }

            window.dataLayer = window.dataLayer || [];
            let can_view = Boolean(response.headers.get('X-NBER-CAN-VIEW-PAPER'));
            let sub_type = response.headers.get('X-NBER-SUBSCRIBER-TYPE');

            dataLayer.push({
              "event": "can_view_paper_response",
              "can_view_paper": can_view,
              "subscriber_type": sub_type,
            });
          });
        }
      )
      .catch(function(err) {
        console.log('Fetch Error :-S', err);
      });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;div id="authorize-banner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="accordion-set"&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;div class="accordion"&gt;
          &lt;button class="accordion__title js-accordion" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="accordion-body-guid1" id="accordion-button-guid1"&gt;Acknowledgements and Disclosures&lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;div class="accordion__body" id="accordion-body-guid1" aria-labelledby="accordion-button-guid1" style="display: none;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;
We would like to thank James Banks, Sonya Krutikova, and Kjell Salvanes for organizing the IFS working group on geographical approaches to measuring inequality in mortality, with financial support from the ESRC Centre for the Microeconomic Analysis of Public Policy at IFS (ES/T014334/1). Claudia Costa received support from the Science and Technology Foundation (FCT), the European Social Fund, and the Centro Operational Programme (SFRH/BD/132218/2017). Paula Santana received support from the Centre of Studies in Geography and Spatial Planning (UIDB/04084/2020), through an FCT fund. Aline Bütikofer, René Karadakic, and Kjell Salvanes received support from the Research Council of Norway through project No. 275800 and through its Centres of Excellence Scheme, FAIR project No. 262675 and by the NORFACE DIAL grant 462-16-050. Peter Redler received support from the Elite Network of Bavaria within the Evidence-Based&lt;br /&gt;
Economics programme. The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Bureau of Economic Research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
              &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/marlies_bar"&gt;Marlies Bär&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
Marlies Bar acknowledges support from the Initiative for Smarter Choices for Better Health funded by Erasmus University.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/rene_karadakic"&gt;René Karadakic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
This project was partially supported by the Research Council of Norway through project No. 275800 and through its Centres of Excellence Scheme, FAIR project No. 262675 and by NORFACE DIAL grant No. 462-16-050.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/riumalloherl"&gt;Carlos Riumallo-Herl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
Carlos Riumallo Herl received funding from the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under the Marie Sklodowska-Curie grant agreement No 840591.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/kjell_salvanes"&gt;Kjell Salvanes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
see the note from Aline Butikofer
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/vanourtieseeurnl"&gt;Tom Van Ourti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
Tom Van Ourti got support from the Initiative for Smarter Choices for Better Health funded by Erasmus University.</description><author>Hannes Schwandt, Janet Currie, Marlies Bär, James Banks, Paola Bertoli, Aline Bütikofer, Sarah Cattan, Beatrice Zong-Ying Chao, Claudia Costa, Libertad Gonzalez, Veronica Grembi, Kristiina Huttunen, René Karadakic, Lucy Kraftman, Sonya Krutikova, Stefano Lombardi, Peter Redler, Carlos Riumallo-Herl, Ana Rodríguez-González, Kjell Salvanes, Paula Santana, Josselin Thuilliez, Eddy van Doorslaer, Tom Van Ourti, Joachim Winter, Bram Wouterse, Amelie Wuppermann</author></item><item><title>The Consumption, Income, and Well-Being of Single Mother Headed Families 25 Years After Welfare Reform</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29188</link><description>We investigate how material well-being has changed over time for single mother headed families—the primary group affected by welfare reform and other policy changes of the 1990s. We focus on consumption as well as other indicators including components of consumption, measures of housing quality, and health insurance coverage. The results provide strong evidence that the material circumstances of single mothers improved in the decades following welfare reform. The consumption of the most disadvantaged single mother headed families—those with low consumption or low education—rose noticeably over time and at a faster rate than for those in comparison groups.</description><author>Jeehoon Han, Bruce D. Meyer, James X. Sullivan</author></item></channel></rss>