<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Portfolio Selection and Asset Pricing</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Portfolio Selection and Asset Pricing</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 14:04:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Does Political Partisanship Cross Borders? Evidence from International Capital Flows</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29280</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>Does partisan perception shape the flow of international capital? We provide evidence from two settings, syndicated corporate loans and equity mutual funds, to show that ideological alignment with foreign governments affects the cross-border capital allocation by U.S. institutional investors. Moreover, we find that ideological alignment with foreign countries also affects investments of non-U.S. investors and can explain patterns in bilateral FDI flows. Our empirical strategy ensures that direct economic effects of foreign elections or bilateral ties between countries are not driving the result. Combined, our findings imply that partisan perception is a global phenomenon and its economic effects transcend national borders.]]></description><author>Elisabeth Kempf, Mancy Luo, Larissa Schäfer, Margarita Tsoutsoura</author></item><item><title>Corporate Actions and the Manipulation of Retail Investors in China: An Analysis of Stock Splits</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29212</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>We identify a group of “suspicious” firms that use stock splits—perhaps, along with other activities—to artificially inflate their share prices. Following the initiation of suspicious splits, share prices temporarily increase, and subsequently decline below their pre-split levels. Using account level data from the Shanghai Stock Exchange, we find that small retail investors acquire shares in firms initiating suspicious splits, while more sophisticated investors accumulate positions before suspicious split announcements and sell in the post-split period. We also find that insiders sell large blocks of shares and obtain loans using company stock as collateral around the initiation of suspicious splits.]]></description><author>Sheridan Titman, Chishen Wei. Wei, Bin Zhao</author></item><item><title>Why Did Small Business Fintech Lending Dry Up During March 2020?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29205</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>With the onset of the COVID-19 crisis in March 2020, small business lending through fintech lenders collapsed. We explore the reasons for the market shutdown using detailed data about loan applications, offers, and take-up from a major small business fintech credit platform. We document that while the number of loan applications increased sharply early in March 2020, the supply of credit collapsed as online lenders dropped from the platform and the likelihood of applicants receiving loan offers fell precipitously. Our analysis shows that the drying up of the loan supply is most consistent with fintech lenders becoming financially constrained and losing their ability to fund new loans.]]></description><author>Itzhak Ben-David, Mark J. Johnson, René M. Stulz</author></item><item><title>When Uncertainty and Volatility Are Disconnected: Implications for Asset Pricing and Portfolio Performance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29195</link><description><![CDATA[August 2021<p>We analyze an environment where the uncertainty in the equity market return and its volatility are both stochastic, and may be potentially disconnected. We solve a representative investor's optimal asset allocation and derive the resulting conditional equity premium and risk-free rate in equilibrium. Our empirical analysis shows that the equity premium appears to be earned for facing uncertainty, especially high uncertainty that is disconnected from lower volatility, rather than for facing volatility as traditionally assumed. Incorporating the possibility of a disconnect between volatility and uncertainty significantly improves portfolio performance, over and above the performance obtained by conditioning on volatility only.]]></description><author>Yacine Aït-Sahalia, Felix Matthys, Emilio Osambela, Ronnie Sircar</author></item></channel></rss>