<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: COVID-19</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: COVID-19</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 15:51:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Did Pandemic Unemployment Benefits Reduce Employment? Evidence from Early State-Level Expirations in June 2021</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29575</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Harry  J. Holzer, R. Glenn Hubbard, Michael R. Strain.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The generosity of Unemployment Insurance (UI) benefits was expanded during the pandemic (FPUC), along with the groups of workers eligible for benefits (PUA). These two programs were set to expire in September 2021, but 18 states opted out of both in June 2021. Using Current Population Survey data, we present difference-in-difference and event study estimates that the flow of unemployed workers into employment increased by around two-thirds following early termination. We construct a counterfactual scenario that implies the national unemployment rate in each of July and August would have been around 0.3 percentage point lower than they were, and the employment-population ratio would have been around 0.1-0.2 percentage point higher than it was, had all states ended FPUC and PUA in June. Expanded eligibility and generosity of UI may have both slowed transitions from unemployment to employment. We also present some suggestive evidence that households with relatively high confidence in their ability to meet expenses may have been less sensitive to the termination of expanded benefits. Finally, we present evidence that early termination reduced the share of households that had no difficulty meeting expenses by five percent. The welfare implications of the early termination of FPUC and PUA are therefore ambiguous.]]></description><author>Harry  J. Holzer, R. Glenn Hubbard, Michael R. Strain</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29575</guid></item><item><title>Peltzman Revisited: Quantifying 21st Century Opportunity Costs of FDA Regulation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29574</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Casey B. Mulligan.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> This paper revisits Peltzman (1973) in light of two recent opportunities to quantitatively assess tradeoffs in drug regulation.  First, reduced regulatory barriers to drug manufacturing associated with the 2017 reauthorization of Generic Drug User Fee Amendments were followed by significantly more entry and lower consumer prices for prescription drugs.  Using a simple and versatile industry model and historical data on entry, I find that easing generic restrictions discourages innovation, but this welfare cost is more than offset by consumer benefits from enhanced competition, especially after 2016.  Second, accelerated vaccine approval in 2020 had unprecedented net benefits as it not only improved health but substantially changed the trajectory of the wider economy.  The evidence suggests that cost-benefit analysis of FDA regulation is incomplete without accounting for substitution toward potentially unsafe and ineffective treatments that are both outside FDA jurisdiction and heavily utilized prior to FDA approval.  Moreover, the policy processes initiating these 21st century regulatory changes show a clear influence of Peltzman’s 1973 findings.]]></description><author>Casey B. Mulligan</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29574</guid></item><item><title>STEM Employment Resiliency During Recessions: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29568</link><description><![CDATA[<i>James C. Davis, Holden A. Diethorn, Gerald R. Marschke, Andrew J. Wang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Employment in STEM occupations suffered smaller peak-to-trough percentage declines than non-STEM occupations during the Great Recession and COVID-19 recession, suggesting a relative resiliency of STEM employment.  We exploit the sudden peak-to-trough declines in STEM and non-STEM employment during the COVID-19 recession to measure STEM recession-resiliency, decomposing our difference-in-differences estimate into parts explained by various sources.  We find that STEM knowledge importance on the job explains the greatest share of STEM employment resiliency, and that workers in non-STEM occupations who nonetheless use STEM knowledge experienced better employment outcomes. STEM employment resiliency may explain the mild effects of COVID-19 on innovative activity.]]></description><author>James C. Davis, Holden A. Diethorn, Gerald R. Marschke, Andrew J. Wang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29568</guid></item><item><title>Job Training Through Turmoil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29565</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Adriana D. Kugler, Mikko I. Silliman.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We follow the labor market outcomes of applicants who were randomized into job training a year and a half before the pandemic through the subsequent economic turmoil that resulted from COVID-19. Despite persistently improved labor market outcomes of training participants prior to March 2020, we show that job losses resulting from the pandemic washed away all the benefits of the program. A year and a half after the initial scars of the pandemic, there are no visible signs of recovery of trainees’ labor market outcomes.]]></description><author>Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Adriana D. Kugler, Mikko I. Silliman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29565</guid></item><item><title>COVID-19 Vaccination Mandates and Vaccine Uptake</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29563</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexander Karaivanov, Dongwoo Kim, Shih En Lu, Hitoshi Shigeoka.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We evaluate the impact of government mandated proof of vaccination requirements for access to public venues and non-essential businesses on COVID-19 vaccine uptake. We find that the announcement of a mandate is associated with a rapid and significant surge in new vaccinations (more than 60\% increase in weekly first doses) using the variation in the timing of these measures across Canadian provinces in a difference-in-differences approach. Time-series analysis for each province and for France, Italy and Germany corroborates this finding, and we estimate cumulative gains of up to 5 percentage points in provincial vaccination rates and 790,000 or more first doses for Canada as a whole as of October 31, 2021 (5 to 13 weeks after the provincial mandate announcements). We also find large vaccination gains in France (3 to 5 mln first doses), Italy (around 6 mln) and Germany (around 3.5 mln) 11 to 16 weeks after the proof of vaccination mandate announcements.]]></description><author>Alexander Karaivanov, Dongwoo Kim, Shih En Lu, Hitoshi Shigeoka</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29563</guid></item><item><title>Has Global Agricultural Trade Been Resilient Under Covid-19? Findings from an Econometric Assessment of 2020</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29551</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Shawn Arita, Jason Grant, Sharon S. Sydow, Jayson Beckman.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Global agricultural trade, which increased at the end of 2020, has been described as “resilient” to the impacts of the COVID-19 coronavirus pandemic; however, the size and channels of its quantitative impacts are not clear. Using a reduced-form, gravity-based econometric model for monthly trade, we estimate the effects of COVID-19 incidence rates, policy restrictions imposed by governments to curb the outbreak, and the de facto reduction in human mobility/lockdown effect on global agricultural trade through the end of 2020. We find that while agricultural trade remained quite stable through the pandemic, the sector as a whole did not go unscathed. First, we estimate that COVID-19 reduced agricultural trade by the approximate range of 5 to 10 percent at the aggregate sector level; a quantified impact two to three times smaller in magnitude than our estimated impact on trade occurring in the non-agricultural sector. Second, we find sharp differences across individual commodities. In particular, we find that non-food items (hides and skins, ethanol, cotton, and other commodities), meat products including seafood, and higher value agri-food products were most severely impacted by the pandemic; however, the COVID- 19 trade effect for the majority of food and bulk agricultural commodity sectors were found to be insignificant, or in a few cases, positive. Finally, we also examine the effects across low vs high income countries, the changing dynamics of the pandemic’s effect on trade flows, and the effects along the extensive product margins of trade.]]></description><author>Shawn Arita, Jason Grant, Sharon S. Sydow, Jayson Beckman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29551</guid></item><item><title>Researchers' Degrees-of-Flexibility and the Credibility of Difference-in-Differences Estimates: Evidence From the Pandemic Policy Evaluations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29550</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joakim A. Weill, Matthieu Stigler, Olivier Deschenes, Michael R. Springborn.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic brought unprecedented policy responses and a large literature evaluating their impacts. This paper re-examines this literature and investigates the role of researchers' degrees-of-flexibility on the estimated effects of mobility-reducing policies on social-distancing behavior. We find that two-way fixed effects estimates are not robust to minor changes in usually-unexplored dimensions of the degree-of-flexibility space. While standard robustness tests based on the sequential addition of covariates are very stable, small changes in the outcome variable and its transformation lead to large and sometimes contradictory changes in the estimates, where the same policy can be found to significantly increase or decrease mobility. Yet, due to the large number of degrees-of-flexibility, one can focus on a set of results that appears stable, while ignoring problematic ones. We show that recently developed heterogeneity-robust difference-in-differences estimators only partially mitigate these issues, and discuss how a strategy of identifying the point at which a sequence of ever more-stringent robustness tests eventually fail could increase the credibility of policy evaluations.]]></description><author>Joakim A. Weill, Matthieu Stigler, Olivier Deschenes, Michael R. Springborn</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29550</guid></item><item><title>Selection in Surveys</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29549</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Deniz Dutz, Ingrid Huitfeldt, Santiago Lacouture, Magne Mogstad, Alexander Torgovitsky, Winnie van Dijk.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We evaluate how nonresponse affects conclusions drawn from survey data and consider how researchers can reliably test and correct for nonresponse bias. To do so, we examine a survey on labor market conditions during the COVID-19 pandemic that used randomly assigned financial incentives to encourage participation. We link the survey data to administrative data sources, allowing us to observe a ground truth for participants and nonparticipants. We find evidence of large nonresponse bias, even after correcting for observable differences between participants and nonparticipants. We apply a range of existing methods that account for nonresponse bias due to unobserved differences, including worst-case bounds, bounds that incorporate monotonicity assumptions, and approaches based on parametric and nonparametric selection models. These methods produce bounds (or point estimates) that are either too wide to be useful or far from the ground truth. We show how these shortcomings can be addressed by modeling how nonparticipation can be both active (declining to participate) and passive (not seeing the survey invitation). The model makes use of variation from the randomly assigned financial incentives, as well as the timing of reminder emails. Applying the model to our data produces bounds (or point estimates) that are narrower and closer to the ground truth than the other methods.]]></description><author>Deniz Dutz, Ingrid Huitfeldt, Santiago Lacouture, Magne Mogstad, Alexander Torgovitsky, Winnie van Dijk</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29549</guid></item><item><title>Race and Economic Well-Being in the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29539</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jean-Felix Brouillette, Charles I. Jones, Peter J. Klenow.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We construct a measure of consumption-equivalent welfare for Black and White Americans. Our statistic incorporates life expectancy, consumption, leisure, and inequality, with mortality rates playing a key role quantitatively. According to our estimates, welfare for Black Americans was 43% of that for White Americans in 1984 and rose to 60% by 2019. Going back further in time (albeit with more limited data), the gap was even larger, with Black welfare equal to just 28% of White welfare in 1940. On the one hand, there has been remarkable progress for Black Americans: the level of their consumption-equivalent welfare increased by a factor of 28 between 1940 and 2019, when aggregate consumption per person rose a more modest 5-fold. On the other hand, despite this remarkable progress, the welfare gap in 2019 remains disconcertingly large. Mortality from COVID-19 has temporarily reversed a decade of progress, lowering Black welfare by 17% while reducing White welfare by 10%.]]></description><author>Jean-Felix Brouillette, Charles I. Jones, Peter J. Klenow</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29539</guid></item><item><title>Real-Time Forecasting with a (Standard) Mixed-Frequency VAR During a Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29535</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Frank Schorfheide, Dongho Song.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We resuscitated the mixed-frequency vector autoregression (MF-VAR) developed in Schorfheide and Song (2015, JBES) to generate macroeconomic forecasts for the U.S. during the COVID-19 pandemic in real time. The model combines eleven time series observed at two frequencies: quarterly and monthly. We deliberately did not modify the model specification in view of the COVID-19 outbreak, except for the exclusion of crisis observations from the estimation sample. We compare the MF-VAR forecasts to the median forecast from the Survey of Professional Forecasters (SPF). While the MF-VAR performed poorly during 2020:Q2, subsequent forecasts were at par with the SPF forecasts. We show that excluding a few months of extreme observations is a promising way of handling VAR estimation going forward, as an alternative of a sophisticated modeling of outliers.]]></description><author>Frank Schorfheide, Dongho Song</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29535</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Multipliers in the COVID19 Recession</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29531</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alan J. Auerbach, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Peter McCrory, Daniel Murphy.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> In response to the record-breaking COVID19 recession, many governments have adopted unprecedented fiscal stimuli. While countercyclical fiscal policy is effective in fighting conventional recessions, little is known about the effectiveness of fiscal policy in the current environment with widespread shelter-in-place (“lockdown”) policies and the associated considerable limits on economic activity. Using detailed regional variation in economic conditions, lockdown policies, and U.S. government spending, we document that the effects of government spending were stronger during the peak of the pandemic recession, but only in cities that were not subject to strong stay-at-home orders. We examine mechanisms that can account for our evidence and place our findings in the context of other recent evidence from microdata.]]></description><author>Alan J. Auerbach, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Peter McCrory, Daniel Murphy</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29531</guid></item><item><title>COVID-19, Government Performance, and Democracy: Survey Experimental Evidence from 12 Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29514</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Becher, Nicolas Longuet Marx, Vincent Pons, Sylvain Brouard, Martial Foucault, Vincenzo Galasso, Eric Kerrouche, Sandra León Alfonso, Daniel Stegmueller.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Beyond its immediate impact on public health and the economy, the COVID-19 pandemic has put democracy under stress. While a common view is that people should blame the government rather than the political system for bad crisis management, an opposing view is that dissatisfaction with government performance may cause deeper dissatisfaction with democracy even in consolidated democratic regimes. We use a pre-registered survey and experiment covering 12 countries and 22,500 respondents to examine the impact of the pandemic on public attitudes about incumbent governments, the functioning of democracy and support for different types of regimes. To estimate causal effects, we leverage experimental treatments using an instrumental variable design. We find that dissatisfaction with the government, which is equally driven by economic and health considerations, decreases satisfaction with how democracy works. However, it does not translate into an embrace of non-democratic regime types.]]></description><author>Michael Becher, Nicolas Longuet Marx, Vincent Pons, Sylvain Brouard, Martial Foucault, Vincenzo Galasso, Eric Kerrouche, Sandra León Alfonso, Daniel Stegmueller</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29514</guid></item><item><title>Is Hard and Soft Information Substitutable? Evidence from Lockdown</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29513</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jennie Bai, Massimo Massa.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study information substitutability in the financial market through a quasi-natural experiment: the pandemic-triggered lockdown that has hampered people's physical interactions hence the ability to collect, process, and transmit soft information. Exploiting the cross- sectional and time-series variations of lockdown, we investigate how the difficulty to use soft information has prompted a switch to hard information and its implication on fund investment, performance, and risk management. We show that lockdown reduces fund investment in proximate stocks and generates a portfolio rebalancing toward distant stocks. The re- balancing negatively impacts fund performance by reducing fund raw (excess) return of an additional 0.76% (0.29%) per month during lockdown, suggesting that soft and hard information is not easily substitutable. Lastly, we show that soft information originates mainly from physical human interactions, primarily in cafés, restaurants, bars, and fitness centers; and the virtual world based on Zoom/Skype/Team fails to substitute physical interactions fully, thus cannot provide sufficient soft information.]]></description><author>Jennie Bai, Massimo Massa</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29513</guid></item><item><title>Excess Deaths in the United States During the First Year of COVID-19</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29503</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher J. Ruhm.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Accurately determining the number of excess deaths caused by the COVID-19 pandemic is hard. The most important challenge is accurately estimating the counterfactual count of baseline deaths that would have occurred in its absence. This analysis used new methods to: estimate this baseline metric; calculate excess deaths during the first year of the U.S. COVID-19 pandemic; and examine plausibility of the excess death estimates obtained in this and prior analyses. Total, group-specific and cause-specific excess deaths in the U.S. from March 2020 through February 2021 were calculated using publicly available data covering all deaths from March 2009 through December 2019 and provisional data from January 2020 through February 2021. The estimates indicate that there were 646,514 (95% CI: 597,514 to 695,520) excess deaths in the U.S. during this period, with 83.4% (95% CI: 77.5% - 90.2%) of these attributed directly to COVID-19. There were substantial differences across population groups and causes in the ratio of actual-to-baseline deaths, and in the contribution of COVID-19 to excess mortality. Prior research has frequently underestimated baseline deaths and so has overstated excess mortality and the percentage of it attributed to non-COVID-19 causes.]]></description><author>Christopher J. Ruhm</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29503</guid></item><item><title>International Evidence on Vaccines and the Mortality to Infections Ratio</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29498</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Aizenman, Alex Cukierman, Yothin Jinjarak, Weining Xin.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Recent observations on countries like the UK that have accumulated a large fraction of inoculated individuals suggest that, although initially, vaccines have little effect on new infections they strongly reduce the share of mortality out of a given pool of infections. This paper examines the extent to which this phenomenon is more general by testing the hypothesis that the ratio of current mortality to lagged infections is decreasing in the total number of vaccines per one hundred individuals. This is done in a pooled time-series, cross-section sample with weekly observations for up to 208 countries. The main conclusion from the statistical analysis is that, passed a certain threshold, vaccines moderate the share of mortality from a given pool of lagged infections. This is essentially a favorable shift in the tradeoff between life preservation and economic performance. Controlling for income per capita, stringency of containment measures, and the fraction of recovered and old individuals, estimation is carried out by linear least squares, with standard errors clustered by country and region. The main result is robust to sensitivity analysis with a logarithmic specification. The practical lesson is that, in the presence of a sufficiently high share of inoculated individuals, governments can shade down containment measures, even as infections are still rampant, without significant adverse effects on mortality.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Alex Cukierman, Yothin Jinjarak, Weining Xin</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29498</guid></item><item><title>Pandemic Schooling Mode and Student Test Scores: Evidence from US States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29497</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clare Halloran, Rebecca Jack, James C. Okun, Emily Oster.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We estimate the impact of district-level schooling mode (in-person versus hybrid or distance learning) on test scores. We combine Spring 2021 state standardized test score data with comprehensive data on schooling in the 2020-21 school year across 12 states. We find that pass rates declined compared to prior years and that these declines were larger in districts with less in-person instruction. Passing rates in math declined by 14.2 percentage points on average; we estimate this decline was 10.1 percentage points smaller for districts fully in-person. Changes in English language arts scores were smaller, but were significantly larger in districts with larger populations of students who are Black, Hispanic or eligible for free and reduced price lunch.]]></description><author>Clare Halloran, Rebecca Jack, James C. Okun, Emily Oster</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29497</guid></item><item><title>Support for Paid Family Leave among Small Employers Increases during the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29486</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ann P. Bartel, Maya Rossin-Slater, Christopher J. Ruhm, Meredith Slopen, Jane Waldfogel.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The United States is one of the few countries that does not guarantee paid family leave (PFL) to workers. Proposals for PFL legislation are often met with opposition from employer organizations, who fear disruptions to business, especially among small employers. But there has been limited data on employers’ views. We surveyed firms with 10-99 employees in New York and New Jersey on their attitudes towards PFL programs before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. We found high support for state PFL programs in 2019 that rose substantially over the course of the pandemic: by the fall of 2020, almost 70% of firms were supportive. Increases in support were larger among firms that had an employee use PFL, suggesting that experience with PFL led to employers becoming more supportive. Thus, concerns about negative impacts on small employers should not impede efforts to expand PFL at the state or federal levels.]]></description><author>Ann P. Bartel, Maya Rossin-Slater, Christopher J. Ruhm, Meredith Slopen, Jane Waldfogel</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29486</guid></item><item><title>Modeling to Inform Economy-Wide Pandemic Policy: Bringing Epidemiologists and Economists Together</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29475</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael E. Darden, David Dowdy, Lauren Gardner, Barton Hamilton, Karen Kopecky, Melissa Marx, Nicholas W. Papageorge, Daniel Polsky, Kimberly Powers, Elizabeth Stuart, Matthew Zahn.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Facing unprecedented uncertainty and drastic trade-offs between public health and other forms of human well-being, policy makers during the Covid-19 pandemic have sought the guidance of epidemiologists and economists. Unfortunately, while both groups of scientists use many of the same basic mathematical tools, the models they develop to inform policy tend to rely on different sets of assumptions and, thus, often lead to different policy conclusions. This divergence in policy recommendations can lead to uncertainty and confusion, opening the door to disinformation, distrust of institutions, and politicization of scientific facts. Unfortunately, to date, there have not been widespread efforts to build bridges and find consensus or even to clarify sources of differences across these fields, members of whom often continue to work within their traditional academic silos. In response to this “crisis of communication,” we convened a group of scholars from epidemiology, economics, and related fields (e.g., statistics, engineering, and health policy) to discuss approaches to modeling economy-wide pandemics. We summarize these conversations by providing a consensus view of disciplinary differences (including critiques) and working through a specific policy example. Thereafter, we chart a path forward for more effective synergy between disciplines, which we hope will lead to better policies as the current pandemic evolves and future pandemics emerge.]]></description><author>Michael E. Darden, David Dowdy, Lauren Gardner, Barton Hamilton, Karen Kopecky, Melissa Marx, Nicholas W. Papageorge, Daniel Polsky, Kimberly Powers, Elizabeth Stuart, Matthew Zahn</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29475</guid></item><item><title>Were Federal COVID Relief Funds for Schools Enough?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29470</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nora E. Gordon, Sarah J. Reber.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Congress responded to the COVID pandemic’s disruptions to instruction with unprecedented federal aid for school districts. While this relief has been widely characterized as a major windfall for K-12 education, per-pupil amounts vary considerably across districts, as will the costs districts face for COVID mitigation and recovery. In this paper, we conduct simulations to understand the potential distribution of net effects of the pandemic and federal aid on the finances of local school districts in the next several years. In our baseline scenario, we assume one-time adjustment costs of $500 per pupil plus additional costs of $1,000 per student in poverty and $500 per student not in poverty per year for four years. Federal aid was distributed proportional to the longstanding Title I program, which sends more money per pupil to higher poverty districts. Low-poverty districts are therefore projected to face some budgetary shortfalls, while many higher poverty districts are projected to have excess funds, which they could direct towards long-standing challenges. While our findings depend on key assumptions about the COVID-related costs, we find significant district-level variation in simulated net fiscal impacts, in part but not completely due to poverty rates, across all the scenarios we consider.]]></description><author>Nora E. Gordon, Sarah J. Reber</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29470</guid></item><item><title>A Simple Model of Social Distancing and Vaccination</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29463</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher Avery.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper analyzes a simple model of infectious disease where the incentives for individuals to reduce risks through endogenous social distancing take straightforward cost-benefit form. Since disease is transmitted through social interactions, the threat of spread of infection poses a collective action problem. Policy interventions such as lockdowns, testing, and mask-wearing serve, in part, as substitutes for social distancing. Provision of a vaccination is the only intervention that unambiguously reduces both the peak infection level and the herd immunity level of infection. Adoption of vaccination remains limited in a decentralized equilibrium, with resulting reproductive rate of disease Rt &gt; 1 at the conclusion of vaccination. Vaccine mandates yield increases in vaccination rates and corresponding reductions in future infection rates but do not increase expected payoffs to individuals.]]></description><author>Christopher Avery</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29463</guid></item><item><title>Which Beliefs? Behavior-Predictive Beliefs are Inconsistent with Information-Based Beliefs: Evidence from COVID-19</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29452</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ori Heffetz, Guy Ishai.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the relationship between (a) official information on COVID-19 infection and death case counts; (b) beliefs about such case counts, at present and in the future; (c) beliefs about average infection chance—in principle, directly calculable from (b); and (d) self-reported health-protective behavior. We elicit (b), (c), and (d) with a daily online survey in the US from March to August 2020 (N ≈ 13,900).<br />
We have three main findings: (1) beliefs elicited as infection case counts are closely related to present and future official case-count information; however (2) beliefs elicited as risk perceptions—i.e., the chance to get infected—are inconsistent with those case-count beliefs, even when mathematically, they should be identical; notably, (3) it is the latter—the risk perceptions—that are significantly better predictors of reported behavior than the former.<br />
Together, these findings suggest that researchers and policymakers, who increasingly engage in direct elicitation and communication of numeric measures of uncertainty, may get very different outcomes, depending on which measures they use. We discuss potential implications for public communication of health-risk information.]]></description><author>Ori Heffetz, Guy Ishai</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29452</guid></item><item><title>Risks and global supply chains: What we know and what we need to know</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29444</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Richard Baldwin, Rebecca Freeman.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Recent supply disruptions catapulted the issue of risk in global supply chains (GSCs) to the top of policy agendas and created the impression that shortages would have been less severe if GSCs were either shorter and more domestic, or more diversified. But is this right? We start our answer by reviewing studies that look at risks to and from GSCs, and how GSCs have recovered from past shocks. We then look at whether GSCs are too risky—starting with business research on how firms approach the cost-resiliency trade-off. We propose the risk-versus-reward framework from portfolio theory as a good way to evaluate whether anti-risk policy is justified. We then discuss how exposures to foreign shocks are measured and argue that exposure is higher than direct indicators imply. Finally, we consider the future of GSCs in the light of current policy proposals and advancing technology before pointing to the rich menu of topics for future research on the risk-GSC nexus.]]></description><author>Richard Baldwin, Rebecca Freeman</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29444</guid></item><item><title>Macroprudential Policies and The Covid-19 Pandemic: Risks and Challenges For Emerging Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29441</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sebastian Edwards.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper deals with COVID and macroprudential regulations in emerging markets. I document the build-up of a sturdy macroprudential structure during 2009-2019, and the relaxation of regulations in 2020-2021, as part of the effort to deal with the sanitary emergency. I show that in every country, regulatory forbearance played a key role in the response to COVID. I discuss capital controls as macroprudential instruments. I argue that rebuilding the macroprudential fabric is important to reduce the costs of future systemic shocks. I maintain that post-COVID regulations should incorporate the risks associated with digital currencies.]]></description><author>Sebastian Edwards</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29441</guid></item><item><title>"Potential Capital”, Working From Home, and Economic Resilience</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29431</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Janice C. Eberly, Jonathan Haskel, Paul Mizen.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The impact of an economic shock depends both on its severity and the resilience of the economic response. Resilience can include the ability to relocate factors, for example, even when new technologies or skills are not yet at the ready. This resilience per se buffers production and has an economic value, which we estimate. The COVID-19 pandemic caused a widespread decline in recorded GDP. Yet, as catastrophic as the collapse was, it was buffered by an unprecedented and spontaneous deployment of what we call “Potential Capital,” the dwelling/residential capital and connective technologies used alongside working from home. Together potential capital and labor working from home provided additional output margins and capacity. We estimate the contribution of this capital, and the remote work that it facilitated, to have roughly halved the decline in GDP in the US reducing the fall in GDP to 9.4 log points in 2020Q2 at the trough of the recession. Similar effects are seen in the 6 OECD countries for which data are available, output fell by 14 log points, but would have fallen by 26 log points had only workplace inputs been available. Accounting for the contribution of “Potential Capital” also revises downwards estimated total productivity gains in the business sector during the pandemic from 8 log points to 5 log points in 2020Q2. We also find an output elasticity of domestic non-dwellings capital to be similar to that of workplace ICT capital, reflecting its role as productive capital. Turning to the future, changes in working from home depend upon relative costs, relative technologies and, crucially, the elasticity of substitution between home and work tasks. We estimate that that elasticity to be more than unity, meaning that the growth of ICT will raise the share of work done remotely.]]></description><author>Janice C. Eberly, Jonathan Haskel, Paul Mizen</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29431</guid></item><item><title>Effects of COVID-19 Shutdowns on Domestic Violence in US Cities</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29429</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Amalia R. Miller, Carmit Segal, Melissa K. Spencer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We empirically investigate the impact of COVID-19 shutdowns on domestic violence using incident-level data on both domestic-related calls for service and crime reports of domestic violence assaults from the 18 major US police departments for which both types of records are available. Although we confirm prior reports of an increase in domestic calls for service at the start of the pandemic, we find that the increase preceded mandatory shutdowns, and there was an incremental decline following the government imposition of restrictions. We find no evidence that domestic violence crimes increased. Rather, domestic violence assaults declined significantly during the initial shutdown period and there was no significant change in intimate partner homicides in these months. Nationwide intimate partner violence rates in the National Crime Victimization Survey, including crimes not reported to police, were also lower during shutdown months. Our results fail to support claims that shutdowns increased domestic violence and suggest caution before drawing inference or basing policy on calls data alone.]]></description><author>Amalia R. Miller, Carmit Segal, Melissa K. Spencer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29429</guid></item><item><title>The Evolving Impacts of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Gender Inequality in the U.S. Labor Market: The COVID Motherhood Penalty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29426</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Robert W. Fairlie, Kenneth Couch, Huanan Xu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We explore whether COVID-19 disproportionately affected women in the labor market using CPS data through the end of 2020. We find that male-female gaps in the employment-to-population ratio and hours worked for women with school-age children have widened but not for those with younger children. Triple-difference estimates are consistent with most of the reductions observed for women with school-age children being attributable to additional child care responsibilities (the “COVID motherhood penalty”). Conducting decompositions, we find women had a greater likelihood to telework, higher education levels and a less-impacted occupational distribution, which all contributed to lessening negative impacts relative to men.]]></description><author>Robert W. Fairlie, Kenneth Couch, Huanan Xu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29426</guid></item><item><title>FinTech Lending</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29421</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tobias Berg, Andreas Fuster, Manju Puri.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we review the growing literature on FinTech lending – the provision of credit facilitated by technology that improves the customer-lender interaction or lenders’ screening and monitoring of borrowers. FinTech lending has grown rapidly, though in developed economies like the U.S. it still only accounts for a small share of total credit. An increase in convenience and speed appears to have been more central to FinTech lending’s growth than improved screening or monitoring, though there is certainly potential for the latter, as is the case for increased financial inclusion. The COVID-19 pandemic has shown potential vulnerabilities of FinTech lenders, although in certain segments they have displayed rapid growth.]]></description><author>Tobias Berg, Andreas Fuster, Manju Puri</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29421</guid></item><item><title>A Social Insurance Perspective on Pandemic Fiscal Policy: Implications for Unemployment Insurance and Hazard Pay</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper considers fiscal policy during the pandemic through the lens of optimal social insurance. We develop a simple framework to analyze how government taxes and transfers could mimic the insurance against pandemic income losses that people would like to have had. Permutations of the framework provide insight into how unemployment insurance should be structured, when and how much hazard pay is called for, and whether fiscal policy should aim just to redistribute income or also to stimulate aggregate demand during a pandemic. When we use the insights from the model to evaluate unemployment insurance measures taken during the pandemic, we find that some, but far from all, of the implications of the social insurance framework were followed. In the case of hazard pay, we find that the proposal for a national program (the never-implemented HEROES Act) was both broader and more generous than a social insurance perspective would call for. We suggest that the social insurance perspective on fiscal policy is likely to become increasingly relevant as pandemics and climate-related natural disasters become more common causes of unemployment and recessions.]]></description><author>Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</guid></item><item><title>Financial Incentives and Other Nudges Do Not Increase COVID-19 Vaccinations among the Vaccine Hesitant</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29403</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tom Chang, Mireille Jacobson, Manisha Shah, Rajiv Pramanik, Samir B. Shah.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Can financial incentives, public health messages and other behavioral nudges –approaches deployed by state and local governments, employers, and health systems – increase SARS-CoV-2 vaccination rates among the vaccine hesitant in the US? In mid-2021, we randomly assigned unvaccinated members of a Medicaid managed care health plan to $10 or $50 financial incentives, different public health messages, a simple appointment scheduler, or control to assess impacts on SARS-CoV-2 vaccination intentions and vaccine uptake within 30 days of intervention. While messages increased vaccination intentions, none of the treatments increased overall vaccination rates. Consistent with backlash concerns, financial incentives and negative messages decreased vaccination rates for some subgroups. Financial incentives and other behavioral nudges do not meaningfully increase SARS-CoV-2 vaccination rates amongst the vaccine hesitant.]]></description><author>Tom Chang, Mireille Jacobson, Manisha Shah, Rajiv Pramanik, Samir B. Shah</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29403</guid></item><item><title>The Fiscal and Welfare Effects of Policy Responses to the Covid-19 School Closures</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29398</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicola Fuchs-Schündeln, Dirk Krueger, André Kurmann, Etienne Lalé, Alexander Ludwig, Irina Popova.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Using a structural life-cycle model and data on school visits from Safegraph and school closures from Burbio, we quantify the heterogeneous impact of school closures during the Corona crisis on children affected at different ages and coming from households with different parental characteristics. Our data suggests that secondary schools were closed for in-person learning for longer periods than elementary schools (implying that younger children experienced less school closures than older children), and that private schools experienced shorter closures than public schools, and schools in poorer U.S. counties experienced shorter school closures. We then extend the structural life cycle model of private and public schooling investments studied in Fuchs-Schuendeln, Krueger, Ludwig and Popova (2021) to include the choice of parents whether to send their children to private schools, empirically discipline it with data on parental investments from the PSID, and then feed into the model the school closure measures from our empirical analysis to quantify the long-run consequences of the Covid-19 school closures on the cohorts of children currently in school. Future earnings- and welfare losses are largest for children that started public secondary schools at the onset of the Covid-19 crisis. Comparing children from the top- to children from the bottom quartile of the income distribution, welfare losses are ca. 0.8 percentage points larger for the poorer children if school closures were unrelated to income. Accounting for the longer school closures in richer counties reduces this gap by about 1/3. A policy intervention that extends schools by 3 months (6 weeks in the next two summers) generates significant welfare gains for the children and raises future tax approximately sufficient to pay for the cost of this schooling expansion.]]></description><author>Nicola Fuchs-Schündeln, Dirk Krueger, André Kurmann, Etienne Lalé, Alexander Ludwig, Irina Popova</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29398</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Fragility of For-profit Hospitals: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We estimate the likelihood of financial distress of U.S. hospitals in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic using AHA Annual Survey data for 2011-2019 and smartphone mobility data for 2020. We find that while the average likelihood of distress across all hospitals is 28.53 % in 2020, slightly increasing from 2019, for-profit hospitals are much more likely to be distressed. Their average likelihood of financial distress is 39.13 %---a 6.93 percentage point increase from 2019. For-profit hospitals are the main providers of specialty health care services, such as psychiatric and acute long-term care, so their increased likelihood of distress poses a risk to service provision in these specialty areas, and particularly in rural communities. Our prediction model based on mobility data performs very well in sample against actual data and can potentially help policymakers and hospital administrators to monitor financial distress in real-time when case mixes change, or other large shocks materialize.]]></description><author>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</guid></item><item><title>Telemigration and Development: On the Offshorability of Teleworkable Jobs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29387</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Richard Baldwin, Jonathan I. Dingel.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The Covid-19 pandemic has introduced huge numbers of employers and employees to remote work. How many of these newly remote jobs will go overseas? We offer a rough quantification based on two observations: 1) offshore work is trade in services, and 2) the number of telemigrants is the volume of this trade divided by the average wage. Combining these with gravity-model estimates, we can roughly predict the number of new telemigrants that would arise from lower barriers to trade in services. Telemigration seems unlikely to be transformative when it comes to the development paths of most emerging economies. The baseline service trade flows are modest, and the standard gravity model restricts modest changes to have modest impacts. There are no tipping points in structural gravity models. Finally, we propose a simple model of telemigration in which small changes can have large consequences. The key is to assume that latent comparative advantage takes a different shape than typically assumed in quantitative trade models. Given this, small changes in trade costs can generate large and asymmetric increases in the exports of service tasks from low-wage nations.]]></description><author>Richard Baldwin, Jonathan I. Dingel</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29387</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Access to Small Business Credit: Evidence from the Paycheck Protection Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sabrina T. Howell, Theresa Kuchler, David Snitkof, Johannes Stroebel, Jun Wong.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We explore the sources of racial disparities in small business lending by studying the $806 billion Paycheck Protection Program (PPP), which was designed to support small business jobs during the COVID-19 pandemic. PPP loans were administered by private lenders but federally guaranteed, largely eliminating unobservable credit risk as a factor in explaining differential lending by race. We document that even after controlling for a firm’s zip code, industry, loan size, PPP approval date, and other characteristics, Black-owned businesses were 12.1 percentage points (70% of the mean) more likely to obtain their PPP loan from a fintech lender than a traditional bank. Among conventional lenders, smaller banks were much less likely to lend to Black-owned firms, while the Top-4 banks exhibited little to no disparity after including controls. We use novel data to show that the disparity is not primarily explained by differences in pre-existing bank or credit relationships, firm financial positions, fintech affinity, borrower application behavior, or racial differences in rates of fraudulent PPP applications. In contrast, we document that Black-owned businesses’ higher rate of borrowing from fintechs compared to smaller banks is particularly large in places with high anti-Black racial animus, pointing to a potential role for discrimination in explaining some of the racial disparities in small business lending. We find evidence that when small banks automate their lending processes, and thus reduce human involvement in the loan origination process, their rate of PPP lending to Black-owned businesses increases, with larger effects in places with more racial animus.]]></description><author>Sabrina T. Howell, Theresa Kuchler, David Snitkof, Johannes Stroebel, Jun Wong</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</guid></item><item><title>The Political Economy of the COVID-19 Fiscal Stimulus Packages of 2020</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29360</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Ilan Noy.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Almost all countries announced fiscal support programs once COVID-19 hit. However, there was significant diversity in the magnitude and composition of these fiscal stimulus programs. These differences were determined by myriad political, financial, social, and economic factors - these factors are our focus. We ask what were the factors that are associated with the structure of the fiscal programs that governments chose to adopt in the early stage of the pandemic in 2020. We answer this question using details about the fiscal programs that were announced by 98 governments in the first six months of the pandemic, together with a large set of explanatory variables. Maybe not surprisingly, we find that politics played a very significant part in determining the size and composition of these fiscal programs. Governments and societies that are less polarized and more capable were able to mobilise more fiscal resources. We also find that it was governments with bigger debt loads that announced bigger programs, but that sovereign spreads were not so clearly associated with the size of these program plans. There is a limit, however, to what we can glean from these cross-country comparisons. Ultimately, the understanding of the politics and political-economy considerations that led to the specific content of each fiscal program will have to rely on information about the actual deliberations in each government’s halls of power, should these ever become public.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Ilan Noy</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29360</guid></item><item><title>Macroprudential Policy during COVID-19: The Role of Policy Space</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Katharina Bergant, Kristin Forbes.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses the initial phase of the COVID-19 pandemic to examine how macroprudential frameworks developed over the past decade performed during a period of heightened financial and economic stress. It discusses a new measure of the macroprudential stance that better captures the intensity of different policies across countries and time. Then it shows that macroprudential policy has been used countercyclically—with stances tightened during the 2010’s and eased in response to COVID-19 by more than previous risk-off periods. Countries that tightened macroprudential policy more aggressively before COVID, as well as those that eased more during the pandemic, experienced less financial and economic stress. Countries’ ability to use macroprudential policy, however, was significantly constrained by the extent of existing “policy space”, i.e., by how aggressively policy was tightened before COVID-19. The use of macroprudential tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use other policy tools (such as fiscal policy, monetary policy, FX intervention, and capital flow management measures), and the use of other tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use macroprudential policy. This suggests that although macroprudential tools are being used countercyclically and should therefore help stabilize economies and financial markets, there appears to be an opportunity to better integrate the use of macroprudential tools with other policies in the future.]]></description><author>Katharina Bergant, Kristin Forbes</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</guid></item><item><title>From Just in Time, to Just in Case, to Just in Worst-Case: Simple models of a Global Supply Chain under Uncertain Aggregate Shocks.</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29345</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Bomin Jiang, Daniel E. Rigobon, Roberto Rigobon.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Covid-19 highlighted the weaknesses in the supply chain. Many have argued that a more resilient or robust supply chain is needed. But what does a robust supply chain mean? And how do firms’ decisions change when taken that approach? This paper studies a very stylized model of a supply chain, where we study how the decision of a multinational corporation changes in the presence of uncertainty. The two standard theories of supply chain are Just-in-time and Just-in-case. Just-in-time argues in favor of pursuing efficiency, while Just-in-case studies how such decision changes when the firm faces idiosyncratic risk. We find that a robust supply chain is very different specially in the presence of systemic shocks. In this case, firms need to concentrate on the worst-case. This strategy implies a supply chain where the allocation of resources and capabilities does not correspond to the standard theories studied in economics, but follow a heuristic behavioral rule called “probability matching”. It has been found in nature and in experimental research that subjects appeal to probability matching when seeking survival. We find that a robust supply chain will reproduce this behavioral outcome. In fact, a multinational optimizing under uncertainty, follows a probability matching which leads to an allocation that is suboptimal from the individual producer point of view, but rules out the possibility of supply disruptions.]]></description><author>Bomin Jiang, Daniel E. Rigobon, Roberto Rigobon</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29345</guid></item><item><title>The Economics of the COVID-19 Pandemic in Poor Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29339</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Edward Miguel, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic has upended health and living standards around the world. This article provides an interim overview of these effects, with a particular focus on low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). Economists have explained how the pandemic is likely to have differential consequences for LMICs, and demand distinct policy responses, compared to rich countries. We survey the rapidly expanding body of empirical research that documents its many adverse economic and non-economic effects in terms of living standards, education, health, and gender equality, which appear to be unprecedented in depth and scale. We also review research on successful and failed policy responses, including the failure to ensure widespread vaccine coverage in LMICs, which is needed to end the pandemic. We close with a discussion of implications for public policy in LMICs, and for the institutions of international governance, given the likelihood of future pandemics and other major shocks (e.g., climate).]]></description><author>Edward Miguel, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29339</guid></item><item><title>Mortality Rates by College Degree Before and During COVID-19</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29328</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anne Case, Angus Deaton.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> It is now established that mortality and excess mortality from COVID-19 differed across racial and ethnic groups in 2020. Less is known about educational differences in mortality during the pandemic. We examine mortality rates by BA status within sex, age, and race/ethnic groups comparing 2020 with 2019. Mortality rates have increasingly differed by BA status in the US in recent years and there are good reasons to expect the gap to have widened further during the pandemic. Using publicly available provisional data from the National Center for Health Statistics we find that mortality rates increased in 2020 over 2019 for those with and without a BA, irrespective of age, sex, or race/ethnicity. Although mortality rates increased by more for those without a BA, the ratio of mortality rates for those with and without a BA changed surprisingly little from 2019 to 2020. The BA was protective against mortality prior to the pandemic, and it was equally protective during the pandemic. Among 60 groups (sex by race/ethnicity by age) that are available in the data, the ratio of mortality rates of those without a BA to those with a BA fell for more than half of the groups. Our results suggest that differences in the risk of infection were less important in structuring mortality by education than differences in the risk of death conditional on infection.]]></description><author>Anne Case, Angus Deaton</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29328</guid></item><item><title>Recovery from the COVID-19 Recession: Uneven Effects among Young Workers?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29307</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pinka Chatterji, Yue Li.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We test for heterogeneity in the effects of the COVID-19 recession on young workers by estimating month-by-month effects of the pandemic on labor market outcomes among workers aged 15-19 and aged 20-24. We use CPS data from January 2016 to June 2021, limiting the sample to childless individuals who lack a college degree. In the younger group (aged 15-19), we observe the expected sharp reduction in outcomes at the start of the pandemic, followed by a return to pre-pandemic levels of work hours, employment, and labor force participation starting in September 2020, with outcomes even surpassing pre-pandemic levels in April and May 2021. In the older age group (20-24-year-olds), however, work hours, employment, and labor force participation were still lagging below pre-pandemic levels as of June 2021. As of June 2021, weekly earnings and hourly wages were higher than typical pre-pandemic levels for that month for both age groups. Although we cannot test directly whether enhanced UI programs have played a role in these differences by age group, our findings show that within the 15-24-year-old age group, there is significant heterogeneity in labor market recovery from the COVID-19 recession.]]></description><author>Pinka Chatterji, Yue Li</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29307</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Policy in the Age of COVID: Does it ‘Get in all of the Cracks?’</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, Ṣebnem Kalemli-Özcan, Veronika Penciakova, Nick Sander.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study the effects of fiscal policy in response to the COVID-19 pandemic at the firm, sector, country and global level. First, we estimate the impact of COVID-19 and policy responses on small and medium sized enterprise (SME) business failures. We combine firm-level financial data from 50 sectors in 27 countries, a detailed I-O network, real-time data on lockdown policies and mobility patterns, and a rich model of firm behavior that allows for several dimensions of heterogeneity. We find: (a) Absent government support, the failure rate of SMEs would have increased by 9 percentage points, significantly more so in emerging market economies (EMs). With policy support it only increased by 4.3 percentage points, and even decreased in advanced economies (AEs). (b) Fiscal policy was poorly targeted: most of the funds disbursed went to firms who did not need it. (c) Nevertheless, we find little evidence of the policy merely postponing mass business failures or creating many ‘zombie’ firms: failure rates rise only slightly in 2021 once policy support is removed. Next, we build a tractable global intertemporal general equilibrium I-O model with fiscal policy. We calibrate the model to 64 countries and 36 sectors. We find that: (d) a sizable share of the global economy is demand-constrained under COVID-19, especially so in EMs. (e) Globally, fiscal policy helped offset about 8% of the downturn in COVID, with a low ‘traditional’ fiscal multiplier. Yet it significantly reduced the share of demand- constrained sectors, preserving employment in these sectors. (f) Fiscal policy exerted small and negative spillovers to output in other countries but positive spillovers on employment. (g) A two-speed recovery would put significant upwards pressure on global interest rates which imposes an additional headwind on the EM recovery. (h) Corporate and sovereign spreads rise when global rates increase, suggesting that EM may face challenging external funding conditions as AEs economies normalize.]]></description><author>Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, Ṣebnem Kalemli-Özcan, Veronika Penciakova, Nick Sander</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</guid></item><item><title>Is Healthcare Employment Resilient and “Recession Proof”?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29287</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marcus Dillender, Andrew I. Friedson, Cong T. Gian, Kosali I. Simon.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Conventional wisdom often holds that the healthcare sector fares better than other sectors during economic downturns. However, little research has examined the relationship between local economic conditions and healthcare employment. Understanding how the healthcare sector responds to economic conditions is important for policy makers seeking to ensure an adequate supply of healthcare workers, as well as for those directing displaced workers into new jobs. We examine the impact of macroeconomic conditions on both the healthcare labor market and the pipeline of healthcare workers receiving healthcare degrees during a pre-COVID time period, 2005-2017. Our results indicate that the healthcare sector is stable across past business cycles. If anything, when areas experience more severe local economic downturns, healthcare employment increases. Much remains unknown about the adjustments and lasting impacts for the healthcare sector associated with the COVID era. Our study represents an important backdrop as policy makers consider ways to sustain the healthcare sector during economic and public health turbulence.]]></description><author>Marcus Dillender, Andrew I. Friedson, Cong T. Gian, Kosali I. Simon</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29287</guid></item><item><title>External Balance Sheets and the COVID-19 Crisis</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29277</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Galina Hale, Luciana Juvenal.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> At the onset of the COVID-19 economic crisis, as in other crisis episodes, the flight to safety was accompanied by a rapid appreciation of “safe haven” currencies. We quantify currency-induced balance sheet effects for total external positions as well as for individual asset classes using new data on the currency composition of cross-border stocks for 48 countries for the first quarter as well as for the full year 2020. We also conduct the stock-flow reconciliation of net international investment positions to measure overall valuation effects. We show that for many countries currency-induced valuation gains mitigated losses that resulted from declining asset prices in the first quarter of 2020. Moreover, for countries with excess capital out flows during this period, the impact on external balance sheet positions was mitigated by valuation gains. This is because, in contrast with past financial crises, many emerging markets did not experience negative external balance sheet effects from their currency depreciation, partly due to currency-induced valuation gains on equity positions offsetting losses on debt positions, partly due to reduced currency mismatch on their external debt positions.]]></description><author>Galina Hale, Luciana Juvenal</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29277</guid></item></channel></rss>