<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER working group Innovation Policy</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER working group Innovation Policy</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 14:04:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Fragile Algorithms and Fallible Decision-Makers: Lessons from the Justice System</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29267</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>Algorithms (in some form) are already widely used in the criminal justice system.  We draw lessons from this experience for what is to come for the rest of society as machine learning diffuses. We find economists and other social scientists have a key role to play in shaping the impact of algorithms, in part through improving the tools used to build them.]]></description><author>Jens Ludwig, Sendhil Mullainathan</author></item><item><title>The Rise of Scientific Research in Corporate America</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29260</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>Corporate science in America emerged in the interwar period, as some companies set up state-of-the-art corporate laboratories, hired trained scientists, and embarked upon basic research of the kind we would associate today with academic institutions. Using a newly assembled dataset on U.S. companies between 1926 and 1940 combining information on corporate ownership, organization, research and innovation, we attempt to explain the rise of corporate research. We argue that it was driven by companies trying to take advantage of opportunities for innovation made possible by scientific advances and an underdeveloped academic research system in the United States. Measuring  field-specific scientific backwardness in several different ways, we find that large firms, business group affiliated firms, and firms close to the technological frontier were more likely to initiate scientific  research. We also find that companies in monopolistic or concentrated industries were more likely to  engage in basic research. Corporate research was positively correlated with novel and valuable patents, and with market-to-book ratios. For companies choosing to do so, investment in corporate research seems to have paid off. The results shed light on the link between corporate organization, market structure and corporate science.]]></description><author>Ashish Arora, Sharon Belenzon, Konstantin Kosenko, Jungkyu Suh, Yishay Yafeh</author></item></channel></rss>