<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Growth and Productivity</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Growth and Productivity</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 15:16:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Misallocation in Indian Agriculture</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29363</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We exploit substantial variation in land-market institutions across Indian states and detailed micro household-level panel data to assess the effect of distortions in land rental markets on agricultural productivity. We provide empirical evidence that states with more rental-market activity feature less misallocation and reallocate land more efficiently over time. We develop a model of heterogeneous farms and land rentals to estimate land-market distortions in each state. Land rentals have substantial positive effects on agricultural productivity: an efficient reallocation of land increases agricultural productivity by 38 percent on average and by more than 50 percent in states with highly distorted rental markets. Both farm and state-level land market distortions are quantitatively important, with state-level wedges accounting for a significant fraction of rental market participation differences across states. Land market distortions contribute about one-third to the large differences in agricultural total factor productivity across Indian states.]]></description><author>Marijn A. Bolhuis, Swapnika R. Rachapalli, Diego Restuccia</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29363</guid></item><item><title>The Effects of Taxes on Innovation: Theory and Empirical Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29359</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Income taxes are typically set to raise revenues and redistribute income at the lowest possible efficiency costs, which result from the distortions in individual behaviors that taxes entail. Individuals can respond along many margins, such as labor supply, tax avoidance and evasion, and geographic mobility. But one margin that taxes may affect — innovation — is less frequently considered. Conceptually, taxes reduce the expected net returns to innovation inputs and can reduce innovation. Much like other margins of responses to taxes, this efficiency cost must be taken into account. Innovation is done by a relatively small number of people, but it is nevertheless likely to have widespread benefits. While inventors may have divergent motivations, such as social recognition or the love of discovery, they also face an economic reality. How strongly innovation responds to taxes is an empirical question that has been the subject of a growing body of recent work. In this paper, I study how to account for innovation when setting personal income and capital taxation. I distinguish between two cases: one in which the government can set a differentiated tax on inventors and one in which the government is constrained to set the same tax on all agents. I provide a model that flexibly accounts for the spillovers generated by innovation and the non-pecuniary benefits inventors receive from innovation and derive tax formulas expressed in terms of estimable sufficient statistics. The second part of the paper discusses the empirical evidence on the effects of taxes on the quantity, quality, and location of innovation, as well as tax avoidance and income shifting done through innovation.]]></description><author>Stefanie Stantcheva</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29359</guid></item><item><title>Economic Production and Biodiversity in the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29357</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Species extinctions and ecological degradation are accelerating to a degree unprecedented in human history. We present causal evidence on the economic drivers of biodiversity loss using a novel panel dataset on the types and quantities of wildlife at thousands of locations across the U.S. from 1960-2015. Exploiting fiscal and regulatory shocks to local economic output, we document large, negative impacts of GDP on abundance and diversity of species spanning multiple taxa. The adverse effects of production are mitigated by conservation and air emission abatement efforts, which points toward habitat losses and pollution as underlying contributors to contemporaneous biodiversity declines.]]></description><author>Yuanning Liang, Ivan J. Rudik, Eric Zou</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29357</guid></item><item><title>Outsourcing, Inequality and Aggregate Output</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Outsourced workers experience large wage declines, yet domestic outsourcing may raise aggregate productivity. To study this equity-efficiency trade-off, we contribute a framework in which firms either hire many imperfectly substitutable worker types in-house by posting wages along a job ladder, or rent labor services from contractors who hire in the same frictional labor markets. Three implications arise. First, more productive firms are more likely to outsource to save on higher wage premia. Second, outsourcing raises output at the firm level. Third, contractors endogenously locate at the bottom of the job ladder, implying that outsourced workers receive lower wages. Using firm-level instruments for outsourcing and revenue productivity, we find empirical support for all three predictions in French administrative data. After structurally estimating the model, we find that the rise in outsourcing in France between 1996 and 2007 raised aggregate output by 3% and reduced the labor share by 0.7 percentage points. A 9% minimum wage increase stabilizes the labor share and maintains two thirds of the output gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</guid></item><item><title>Creative Destruction, Distance to Frontier, and Economic Development</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29333</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We construct a model of creative destruction with endogenous firm dynamics. We integrate the theory into a general equilibrium multi-country model of technological convergence where countries interact via international spillovers. We derive implications for both firm dynamics and aggregate productivity dynamics. In richer economies, firms are on average larger and the best firms grow larger over time. In poorer economies, there is little creative destruction, low selection, and firms remain small. We estimate the parameters of the model using firm-level data for India and the United States. We study the effect of counterfactual policy reforms. Industrial policy that selectively targets the more productive firms can be beneficial in poor countries while being harmful in countries close to the economic frontier. The findings echo Acemoglu et al. (2006).]]></description><author>Michael Peters, Fabrizio Zilibotti</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29333</guid></item><item><title>Market Size and Spatial Growth - Evidence from Germany’s Post-War Population Expulsions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29329</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Virtually all theories of economic growth predict a positive relationship between population size and productivity. In this paper I study a particular historical episode to provide direct evidence for the empirical relevance of such scale effects. In the aftermath of the Second World War about 8m ethnic Germans were expelled from their domiciles in Eastern Europe and transferred to West Germany. This inflow increased the German population by almost 20%. Using variation across counties I show that the settlement of refugees had a large and persistent effect on the size of the local population, manufacturing employment and income per capita. I show that these findings are quantitatively consistent with an idea-based model of spatial growth if population mobility is subject to frictions and productivity spillovers occur locally. The model implies that the refugee settlement increased aggregate income per capita by about 12% after 25 years and that the historical settlement rule triggered persistent industrialization of rural areas.]]></description><author>Michael Peters</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29329</guid></item><item><title>Economic Growth and Bank Innovation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29326</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Based on archival and survey data we show that the maturity of U.S. business loans has been continuously increasing since the mid-1930s when banks invented the term loan. Concurrently, bank innovation first involved the invention of credit analysis and covenant design. Later, bank innovation included the advent of loan sales, increased loan syndications, the opening of the leveraged loan market, and the securitization of loans in collateralized loan obligations. We estimate and calibrate a model of bank innovation to determine the quantitative contribution of bank innovation to economic growth.]]></description><author>Gary B. Gorton, Ping He</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29326</guid></item><item><title>Can Today's and Tomorrow's World Uniformly Gain from Carbon Taxation?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29224</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Climate change will impact current and future generations in different regions very differently. This paper develops a large-scale, annually calibrated, multi-region, overlapping generations model of climate change to study its heterogeneous effects across space and time. We model the relationship between carbon emissions and the global average temperature based on the latest climate science. Predicated average global temperature is used to determine, via pattern-scaling, region-specific temperatures and damages. Our main focus is determining the carbon policy that delivers present and future mankind the highest uniform percentage welfare gains – arguably the policy with the highest chance of global adoption. Damages from climate change are positive for all regions apart from Russia and Canada, with India and South Asia Pacific suffering the most. The optimal policy is implemented via a time-varying global carbon tax plus region- and generation-specific net transfers. Uniform welfare improving carbon policy can materially limit global emissions, dramatically shorten the use of fossil fuels, and raise the welfare of all current and future agents by over four percent. Unfortunately, the pursuit of carbon policy by individual regions, even large ones, makes only a limited difference. However, coalitions of regions, particularly ones including China, can materially limit carbon emissions.]]></description><author>Laurence J. Kotlikoff, Felix Kubler, Andrey Polbin, Simon Scheidegger</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29224</guid></item><item><title>Simulating Endogenous Global Automation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29220</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper develops a 17-region, 3-skill group, overlapping generations, computable general equilibrium model to evaluate the global consequences of automation. Automation, modeled as capital- and high-skill biased technological change, is endogenous with regions adopting new technologies when profitable. Our approach captures and quantifies key macro implications of a range of foundational models of automation. In our baseline scenario, automation has a moderate effect on regional outputs and a small effect on world interest rates. However, it has a major impact on inequality, both wage inequality within regions and per capita GDP inequality across regions. We examine two policy responses to technological change -- mandating use of the advanced technology and providing universal basic income to share gains from automation. The former policy can raise a region's output, but at a welfare cost. The latter policy can transform automation into a win-win for all generations in a region.]]></description><author>Seth G. Benzell, Laurence J. Kotlikoff, Guillermo LaGarda, Victor Yifan Ye</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29220</guid></item></channel></rss>