<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Other History</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Other History</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 15:27:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Technology Transfer and Early Industrial Development: Evidence from the Sino-Soviet Alliance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29455</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the causal effect of technology and knowledge transfers on early industrial development. Between 1950 and 1957, the Soviet Union supported the “156 Projects” in China for the construction of technologically advanced, large-scale, capital-intensive industrial facilities. We exploit idiosyncratic delays in project completion and the unexpected end of the Sino-Soviet Alliance, due to which some projects received Soviet technology embedded in capital goods and know-how, while others were eventually realized by China alone using domestic technology. We find that receiving both Soviet technology and know-how had large, persistent effects on plant performance, while the effects of receiving only Soviet capital goods were short-lived. The intervention generated horizontal and vertical spillovers, as well as production reallocation from state-owned to privately owned companies since the late 1990s.]]></description><author>Michela Giorcelli, Bo Li</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29455</guid></item><item><title>Environmental Drivers of Agricultural Productivity Growth: CO2 Fertilization of US Field Crops</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29320</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We assess the CO2 fertilization effect on US agriculture using spatially-varying CO2 data from NASA's Orbiting Carbon Observatory-2 (OCO-2) satellite covering the majority of US cropland under actual growing conditions. This study complements the many CO2 enrichment experiments that have found important interactions between CO2 and local environmental conditions in controlled settings.  We use three empirical strategies: (i) a panel of CO2 anomalies and county yields, (ii) a panel of spatial first-differences between neighboring counties, and (iii) a cross-sectional spatial first-difference. We find consistently high fertilization effects: a 1 ppm increase in CO2 equates to a 0.5%, 0.6%, and 0.8% yield increase for corn, soybeans, and wheat, respectively. Viewed retrospectively, 10%, 30%, and 40% of each crop's yield improvements since 1940 are attributable to rising CO2.]]></description><author>Charles A. Taylor, Wolfram Schlenker</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29320</guid></item><item><title>Learning to Use Trade Agreements</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29319</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Free trade or preferential trade areas (PTAs) allow importers who belong to the area to export to each other while paying zero or preferential tariffs as long as Rules of Origin (ROOs) are met. Meeting them is costly not only in terms of production costs but also in terms of documentation costs. We ask if these fixed costs of documentation change over time with the experience of the firm in obtaining preferential tariffs. We explore this using a unique importer-exporter matched transaction-level customs data set on a group of Latin American countries. Our estimating equation is model-based and shows that these fixed costs depend on the history of preference utilization. Most of the effect comes from experience in the same product and same partner, with some spillover to other partners buying the same product. There is little learning from experience in other products and other partners. When considering products that have been under preferences for a while, some learning might have occurred prior to the start of our data. Using a natural experiment in Argentina, where some products were newly brought under preferences, we show that learning is indeed larger for such products. As facilitating preference use today also makes it easier to use preferences in the future, interventions early on in the life of the FTA to reduce such costs would be more effective.]]></description><author>Kala Krishna, Carlos Salamanca, Yuta Suzuki, Christian Volpe Martincus</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29319</guid></item><item><title>From Hermit Kingdom to Miracle on the Han: Policy Decisions that Transformed South Korea into an Export Powerhouse</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29299</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> In 1960, South Korea’s exports were about 1 percent of GDP, and the country’s ability to import depended almost entirely on US aid. After changing its foreign exchange and trade policies in the mid-1960s, Korea saw a surge in exports to more than 10 percent of GDP by the end of the decade. What factors account for the shift in policy that enabled this dramatic export growth to occur? The United States helped initiate the process by withholding financial assistance, pressuring Korea to devalue its currency and reform its foreign exchange regime. Initially, the Korean government resisted taking these steps, but in 1964 it became firmly committed to an export promotion strategy to boost foreign exchange earnings and end its dependence on American aid.]]></description><author>Douglas A. Irwin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29299</guid></item><item><title>How Economic Ideas Led to Taiwan’s Shift to Export Promotion in the 1950s</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29298</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Taiwan was perhaps the first developing country to adopt an export-oriented trade strategy after World War II. The factors usually associated with big shifts in policy—a macroeconomic crisis, a change in political power or institutions, lobbying by export interests, pressure from international financial institutions—were not present; it was ideas that were key. In 1954, economist S. C. Tsiang proposed that Taiwan boost export earnings rather than squeeze import spending to deal with its chronic shortage of foreign exchange. He recommended a currency devaluation to establish a realistic exchange rate and a market-based system of foreign exchange allocation to end the inefficient rationing by the government. Four years later, a leading policymaker, K. Y. Yin, fought for the adoption of Tsiang’s proposal, helping clear the way for Taiwan’s phenomenal growth in trade.]]></description><author>Douglas A. Irwin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29298</guid></item><item><title>The Rise of Scientific Research in Corporate America</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29260</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Corporate science in America emerged in the interwar period, as some companies set up state-of-the-art corporate laboratories, hired trained scientists, and embarked upon basic research of the kind we would associate today with academic institutions. Using a newly assembled dataset on U.S. companies between 1926 and 1940 combining information on corporate ownership, organization, research and innovation, we attempt to explain the rise of corporate research. We argue that it was driven by companies trying to take advantage of opportunities for innovation made possible by scientific advances and an underdeveloped academic research system in the United States. Measuring  field-specific scientific backwardness in several different ways, we find that large firms, business group affiliated firms, and firms close to the technological frontier were more likely to initiate scientific  research. We also find that companies in monopolistic or concentrated industries were more likely to  engage in basic research. Corporate research was positively correlated with novel and valuable patents, and with market-to-book ratios. For companies choosing to do so, investment in corporate research seems to have paid off. The results shed light on the link between corporate organization, market structure and corporate science.]]></description><author>Ashish Arora, Sharon Belenzon, Konstantin Kosenko, Jungkyu Suh, Yishay Yafeh</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29260</guid></item><item><title>New Evidence on Redlining by Federal Housing Programs in the 1930s</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29244</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We show that the Federal Housing Administration (FHA), from its inception in the 1930s, did not insure mortgages in low income urban neighborhoods where the vast majority of urban Black Americans lived.  The agency evaluated neighborhoods using block-level information collected by New Deal relief programs and the Census in many cities.  The FHA’s exclusionary pattern predates the advent of the infamous maps later made by the Home Owners’ Loan Corporation (HOLC) and shows little change after the drafting of those maps.  In contrast, the HOLC itself broadly loaned to such neighborhoods and to Black homeowners.  We conclude that the HOLC’s redlining maps had little effect on the geographic distribution of either program’s mortgage market activity, and that the FHA crafted and implemented its own redlining methodology prior to the HOLC.]]></description><author>Price V. Fishback, Jonathan Rose, Kenneth A. Snowden, Thomas Storrs</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29244</guid></item></channel></rss>