<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Public Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Public Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 18:08:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Let the Worst One Fail: A Credible Solution to the Too-Big-To-Fail Conundrum</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29560</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Thomas Philippon, Olivier Wang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study time-consistent bank resolution mechanisms. When interventions are ex post efficient, a government cannot commit not to inject capital into the banking system. Contrary to common wisdom, we show that the government may still avoid moral hazard and implement the first best allocation by using the distribution of bailouts across banks to provide ex ante incentives. In particular, we analyze properties of credible tournament mechanisms that provide support to the best performing banks and resolve the worst performing ones, including through mergers. Our mechanism continues to perform well if banks are partially substitutable, and if they are heterogeneous in their size, interconnections, and thus systemic risk, as long as bailout funds can be targeted to particular banks.]]></description><author>Thomas Philippon, Olivier Wang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29560</guid></item><item><title>Selection in Surveys</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29549</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Deniz Dutz, Ingrid Huitfeldt, Santiago Lacouture, Magne Mogstad, Alexander Torgovitsky, Winnie van Dijk.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We evaluate how nonresponse affects conclusions drawn from survey data and consider how researchers can reliably test and correct for nonresponse bias. To do so, we examine a survey on labor market conditions during the COVID-19 pandemic that used randomly assigned financial incentives to encourage participation. We link the survey data to administrative data sources, allowing us to observe a ground truth for participants and nonparticipants. We find evidence of large nonresponse bias, even after correcting for observable differences between participants and nonparticipants. We apply a range of existing methods that account for nonresponse bias due to unobserved differences, including worst-case bounds, bounds that incorporate monotonicity assumptions, and approaches based on parametric and nonparametric selection models. These methods produce bounds (or point estimates) that are either too wide to be useful or far from the ground truth. We show how these shortcomings can be addressed by modeling how nonparticipation can be both active (declining to participate) and passive (not seeing the survey invitation). The model makes use of variation from the randomly assigned financial incentives, as well as the timing of reminder emails. Applying the model to our data produces bounds (or point estimates) that are narrower and closer to the ground truth than the other methods.]]></description><author>Deniz Dutz, Ingrid Huitfeldt, Santiago Lacouture, Magne Mogstad, Alexander Torgovitsky, Winnie van Dijk</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29549</guid></item><item><title>The Incidence of the Corporate Income Tax is Irrelevant for its (Benefit-Based) Justification</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29547</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Simon M. Naitram, Matthew C. Weinzierl.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Robust support for corporate income taxation is a puzzle for standard tax theory because the tax’s incidence is uncertain and unreliable. We propose a resolution: if the corporate tax is seen as a benefit-based tax, its normative appeal depends on the correspondence between its incidence and that of the benefit which corporations derive from the state’s activities. We show that a simple mechanism makes this correspondence exact—and the net incidence of the tax zero—when the tax base matches what we call the benefit base. As a result, the appeal of the corporate income tax is independent of incidence as conventionally understood.]]></description><author>Simon M. Naitram, Matthew C. Weinzierl</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29547</guid></item><item><title>Reconstruction Aid, Public Infrastructure, and Economic Development: The Case of the Marshall Plan in Italy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29537</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michela Giorcelli, Nicola Bianchi.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The Marshall Plan (1948–1952) was the largest aid transfer in history. This paper estimates its effects on Italy’s postwar economic development. It exploits differences between Italian provinces in the value of reconstruction grants they received. Provinces that could modernize more their infrastructure experienced higher increases in agricultural production, especially for perishable crops. In the same provinces, we observe larger investments in labor-saving machines, the entry of more firms into the industrial sector, and a larger expansion of the industrial and service workforce.]]></description><author>Michela Giorcelli, Nicola Bianchi</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29537</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Multipliers in the COVID19 Recession</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29531</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alan J. Auerbach, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Peter McCrory, Daniel Murphy.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> In response to the record-breaking COVID19 recession, many governments have adopted unprecedented fiscal stimuli. While countercyclical fiscal policy is effective in fighting conventional recessions, little is known about the effectiveness of fiscal policy in the current environment with widespread shelter-in-place (“lockdown”) policies and the associated considerable limits on economic activity. Using detailed regional variation in economic conditions, lockdown policies, and U.S. government spending, we document that the effects of government spending were stronger during the peak of the pandemic recession, but only in cities that were not subject to strong stay-at-home orders. We examine mechanisms that can account for our evidence and place our findings in the context of other recent evidence from microdata.]]></description><author>Alan J. Auerbach, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Peter McCrory, Daniel Murphy</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29531</guid></item><item><title>Local Economic and Political Effects of Trade Deals: Evidence from NAFTA</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29525</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jiwon Choi, Ilyana Kuziemko, Ebonya L. Washington, Gavin Wright.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Why have white, less educated voters left the Democratic Party over the past few decades? Scholars have proposed ethnocentrism, social issues and deindustrialization as potential answers. We highlight the role played by the 1994 North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA).  In event-study analysis, we demonstrate that counties whose 1990 employment depended on industries vulnerable to NAFTA suffered large and persistent employment losses relative to other counties. These losses begin in the mid-1990s and are only modestly offset by transfer programs.  While exposed counties historically voted Democratic, in the mid-1990s they turn away from the party of the president (Bill Clinton) who ushered in the agreement and by 2000 vote majority Republican in House elections. Employing a variety of micro-data sources, including 1992-1994 respondent-level panel data, we show that protectionist views predict movement toward the GOP in the years that NAFTA is debated and implemented. This shift among protectionist respondents is larger for whites (especially men and those without a college degree) and those with conservative social views, suggesting an interactive effect whereby racial identity and social-issue positions mediate reactions to economic policies.]]></description><author>Jiwon Choi, Ilyana Kuziemko, Ebonya L. Washington, Gavin Wright</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29525</guid></item><item><title>The Responsiveness of Medicaid Spending to the Federal Subsidy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29492</link><description><![CDATA[<i>M. Kate Bundorf, Daniel P. Kessler.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Although economic theory suggests that the federal government can influence spending by states through subsidies to programs that states operate, no recent work has quantified the magnitude of this effect for Medicaid, the largest program of this type in the U.S. We find that Medicaid spending per enrollee responds to the magnitude of the federal subsidy. The Affordable Care Act (ACA) and its subsequent interpretation by the Supreme Court gave states the option to expand eligibility for their Medicaid programs in exchange for increases in the generosity of the federal subsidy. States that exercised this option increased Medicaid spending per enrollee on enrollees who were eligible even before the ACA by approximately 15 percent. Depending on the specification, this translates into an elasticity of Medicaid spending per enrollee with respect to the after-subsidy price of Medicaid to a state of -0.494 to -0.579.]]></description><author>M. Kate Bundorf, Daniel P. Kessler</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29492</guid></item><item><title>Ambulance Taxis: The Impact of Regulation and Litigation on Health Care Fraud</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29491</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Paul J. Eliason, Riley J. League, Jetson Leder-Luis, Ryan C. McDevitt, James W. Roberts.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the relative effectiveness of administrative regulations, criminal enforcement, and civil lawsuits for combatting health care fraud. Between 2003 and 2017, Medicare spent $7.7 billion on 37.5 million regularly scheduled, non-emergency ambulance rides for patients traveling to and from dialysis facilities, with dozens of lawsuits alleging that Medicare reimbursed rides for patients who did not meet the requirements for receiving one. Using a novel data set and an identification strategy based on the staggered timing of regulations and lawsuits across the United States, we find that a regulation requiring prior authorization for ambulance reimbursements reduced spending much more than criminal and civil lawsuits did. Despite the sharp drop in both ambulance transports and the companies that provide them following prior authorization, patients’ health outcomes did not change, indicating that most rides were not medically necessary. Our results suggest that administrative actions have a much larger impact than targeted criminal enforcement, providing novel evidence that regulations may be more cost-effective than ex post ligation for preventing health care fraud.]]></description><author>Paul J. Eliason, Riley J. League, Jetson Leder-Luis, Ryan C. McDevitt, James W. Roberts</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29491</guid></item><item><title>Support for Paid Family Leave among Small Employers Increases during the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29486</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ann P. Bartel, Maya Rossin-Slater, Christopher J. Ruhm, Meredith Slopen, Jane Waldfogel.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The United States is one of the few countries that does not guarantee paid family leave (PFL) to workers. Proposals for PFL legislation are often met with opposition from employer organizations, who fear disruptions to business, especially among small employers. But there has been limited data on employers’ views. We surveyed firms with 10-99 employees in New York and New Jersey on their attitudes towards PFL programs before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. We found high support for state PFL programs in 2019 that rose substantially over the course of the pandemic: by the fall of 2020, almost 70% of firms were supportive. Increases in support were larger among firms that had an employee use PFL, suggesting that experience with PFL led to employers becoming more supportive. Thus, concerns about negative impacts on small employers should not impede efforts to expand PFL at the state or federal levels.]]></description><author>Ann P. Bartel, Maya Rossin-Slater, Christopher J. Ruhm, Meredith Slopen, Jane Waldfogel</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29486</guid></item><item><title>Capital Investment and Labor Demand</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29485</link><description><![CDATA[<i>E. Mark Curtis, Daniel G. Garrett, Eric C. Ohrn, Kevin A. Roberts, Juan Carlos Suárez Serrato.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study how tax policies that lower the cost of capital impact investment and labor demand. Diﬀerence-in-diﬀerences estimates using conﬁdential US Census Data on manufacturing establishments show that tax policies increased both investment and employment, but did not lead to wage or productivity gains. Using a structural model, we show that the primary eﬀect of the policy was to increase the use of all inputs by lowering overall costs of production. The policy further stimulated production employment due to the complementarity of production labor and capital. Supporting this conclusion, we ﬁnd that investment is greater in plants with lower labor costs. Our results show that recent tax policies that incentivize capital investment do not lead manufacturing plants to replace workers with machines.]]></description><author>E. Mark Curtis, Daniel G. Garrett, Eric C. Ohrn, Kevin A. Roberts, Juan Carlos Suárez Serrato</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29485</guid></item><item><title>Pollution Trends and US Environmental Policy: Lessons from the Last Half Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29478</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joseph S. Shapiro.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This article proposes and evaluates four hypotheses about US pollution and environmental policy over the last half century. First, air and water pollution have declined substantially, although greenhouse gas emissions have not. Second, environmental policy explains a large share of these trends. Third, much of the regulation of air and drinking water pollution has benefits that exceed costs, although the evidence for surface water pollution regulation is less clear. Fourth, while the distribution of pollution across social groups is unequal, market-based environmental policies and command-and-control policies do not appear to produce systematically different distributions of environmental outcomes. I also discuss recent innovations in methods and data that can be used to evaluate pollution trends and policies, including the increased use of environmental administrative data, statistical cost-benefit comparisons, analysis of previously understudied policies, more sophisticated analyses of pollution transport, micro-macro frameworks, and a focus on the distribution of environmental outcomes.]]></description><author>Joseph S. Shapiro</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29478</guid></item><item><title>Modeling to Inform Economy-Wide Pandemic Policy: Bringing Epidemiologists and Economists Together</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29475</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael E. Darden, David Dowdy, Lauren Gardner, Barton Hamilton, Karen Kopecky, Melissa Marx, Nicholas W. Papageorge, Daniel Polsky, Kimberly Powers, Elizabeth Stuart, Matthew Zahn.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Facing unprecedented uncertainty and drastic trade-offs between public health and other forms of human well-being, policy makers during the Covid-19 pandemic have sought the guidance of epidemiologists and economists. Unfortunately, while both groups of scientists use many of the same basic mathematical tools, the models they develop to inform policy tend to rely on different sets of assumptions and, thus, often lead to different policy conclusions. This divergence in policy recommendations can lead to uncertainty and confusion, opening the door to disinformation, distrust of institutions, and politicization of scientific facts. Unfortunately, to date, there have not been widespread efforts to build bridges and find consensus or even to clarify sources of differences across these fields, members of whom often continue to work within their traditional academic silos. In response to this “crisis of communication,” we convened a group of scholars from epidemiology, economics, and related fields (e.g., statistics, engineering, and health policy) to discuss approaches to modeling economy-wide pandemics. We summarize these conversations by providing a consensus view of disciplinary differences (including critiques) and working through a specific policy example. Thereafter, we chart a path forward for more effective synergy between disciplines, which we hope will lead to better policies as the current pandemic evolves and future pandemics emerge.]]></description><author>Michael E. Darden, David Dowdy, Lauren Gardner, Barton Hamilton, Karen Kopecky, Melissa Marx, Nicholas W. Papageorge, Daniel Polsky, Kimberly Powers, Elizabeth Stuart, Matthew Zahn</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29475</guid></item><item><title>Were Federal COVID Relief Funds for Schools Enough?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29470</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nora E. Gordon, Sarah J. Reber.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Congress responded to the COVID pandemic’s disruptions to instruction with unprecedented federal aid for school districts. While this relief has been widely characterized as a major windfall for K-12 education, per-pupil amounts vary considerably across districts, as will the costs districts face for COVID mitigation and recovery. In this paper, we conduct simulations to understand the potential distribution of net effects of the pandemic and federal aid on the finances of local school districts in the next several years. In our baseline scenario, we assume one-time adjustment costs of $500 per pupil plus additional costs of $1,000 per student in poverty and $500 per student not in poverty per year for four years. Federal aid was distributed proportional to the longstanding Title I program, which sends more money per pupil to higher poverty districts. Low-poverty districts are therefore projected to face some budgetary shortfalls, while many higher poverty districts are projected to have excess funds, which they could direct towards long-standing challenges. While our findings depend on key assumptions about the COVID-related costs, we find significant district-level variation in simulated net fiscal impacts, in part but not completely due to poverty rates, across all the scenarios we consider.]]></description><author>Nora E. Gordon, Sarah J. Reber</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29470</guid></item><item><title>A Temporary VAT Cut as Unconventional Fiscal Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We exploit the unexpected announcement of an immediate, temporary VAT cut in Germany in the second half of 2020 as a natural experiment to study the spending response to unconventional fiscal policy. We use survey and scanner data on households’ consumption expenditures and their perceived pass-through of the tax change into prices to quantify its effects. The temporary VAT cut led to a substantial relative increase in durable spending of 36% for individuals with a high perceived pass-through. Semi- and non-durable spending also increased. According to our preferred estimates, the VAT policy increased aggregate consumption spending by 34 billion Euros.]]></description><author>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</guid></item><item><title>Estimating the Economic Value of Zoning Reform</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29440</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Santosh Anagol, Fernando V. Ferreira, Jonah M. Rexer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We develop a framework to estimate the economic value of a recent zoning reform in the city of Sao Paulo, which altered maximum permitted construction at the city-block level. Using a spatial regression discontinuity design, we find that developers file for more multi-family construction permits in blocks with higher allowable densities. We incorporate these micro-estimates into an equilibrium model of housing supply and demand to estimate the long term impact of zoning changes. Supply responses from the reform produce a 2.2 percent increase in the total housing stock, leading to a 0.5% reduction in prices on average, with substantial heterogeneity across neighborhoods. Consumer welfare gains due to price reductions are small, but increase 4-fold once we account for changes in the built environment, with more gains accruing to college-educated and higher income households. However, nominal house price losses faced by existing homeowners and landlords overshadow all consumer welfare gains.]]></description><author>Santosh Anagol, Fernando V. Ferreira, Jonah M. Rexer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29440</guid></item><item><title>The Debt Capacity of a Government</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Bernard Dumas, Paul Ehling, Chunyu Yang.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In a deterministic overlapping-generations economy with production and physical capital, the price of debt can be positive without any budget surpluses being in the offing, because debt incorporates a rational bubble. Yet the dynamics of debt remain a function of the dynamics of the primary budget deficit. As a way to study their joint behavior, we endogenize a structural deficit in the form of an underfunded social-security scheme. We define debt capacity as the level of debt that can be just sustained without a change of policy all the way to an unstable steady state. When it starts below the capacity, the debt converges to a stable steady state, in which the bubble is sustained. Above capacity the bubble unravels and the deficit cannot be financed. In several realistic scenarios occurring in economies, we calculate the needed policy response, which is the true "fiscal cost" of exceeding debt capacity.]]></description><author>Bernard Dumas, Paul Ehling, Chunyu Yang</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</guid></item><item><title>A Social Insurance Perspective on Pandemic Fiscal Policy: Implications for Unemployment Insurance and Hazard Pay</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper considers fiscal policy during the pandemic through the lens of optimal social insurance. We develop a simple framework to analyze how government taxes and transfers could mimic the insurance against pandemic income losses that people would like to have had. Permutations of the framework provide insight into how unemployment insurance should be structured, when and how much hazard pay is called for, and whether fiscal policy should aim just to redistribute income or also to stimulate aggregate demand during a pandemic. When we use the insights from the model to evaluate unemployment insurance measures taken during the pandemic, we find that some, but far from all, of the implications of the social insurance framework were followed. In the case of hazard pay, we find that the proposal for a national program (the never-implemented HEROES Act) was both broader and more generous than a social insurance perspective would call for. We suggest that the social insurance perspective on fiscal policy is likely to become increasingly relevant as pandemics and climate-related natural disasters become more common causes of unemployment and recessions.]]></description><author>Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</guid></item><item><title>Mental Health Therapy as a Core Strategy for Increasing Human Capital: Evidence from Ghana</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the impact of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) for individuals selected from the general population of poor households in rural Ghana. Results from 2-3 months after a randomized intervention show strong impacts on mental and physical health, cognitive and socioemotional skills, and downstream economic outcomes. We find no evidence of heterogeneity by baseline mental distress; we argue that this is because CBT can improve human capital for a general population of poor individuals through two pathways. First, CBT reduces vulnerability to deteriorating mental health; and second, CBT directly improves bandwidth, increasing cognitive and socioemotional skills and hence economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Burden of Pension Shortfalls: Evidence from House Prices</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> U.S. state pensions are underfunded by trillions of dollars, but their economic burden is unclear. In a model of inefficient taxation, real estate fully reflects the cost of pension shortfalls when it is the only form of immobile capital. We study the effect of pension shortfalls on real estate values at state borders, where labor and physical capital could more easily relocate to a state with a smaller shortfall. Using plausibly exogenous variation driven by pension asset returns, we find that one dollar of pension underfunding reduces house prices near state borders by approximately two dollars. Our estimates imply a deadweight loss associated with addressing pension shortfalls that is consistent with prior research in settings with high returns to public spending and costs of taxation.]]></description><author>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</guid></item><item><title>The Rise of Pass-Throughs and the Decline of the Labor Share</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29400</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Matthew Smith, Danny Yagan, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the coevolution of the fall in the US corporate sector labor share and the rise of business activity in tax-preferred, pass-through form. Reallocating activity to the form it would have taken prior to the Tax Reform Act of 1986 accounts for one third of the decline in the corporate sector labor share between 1978 and 2017. Our adjustments are concentrated among mid-market firms in services, leaving a larger role for the manufacturing sector and superstar firms in driving the remaining decline in the labor share. Our findings highlight the importance of tax policy when measuring factor shares.]]></description><author>Matthew Smith, Danny Yagan, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29400</guid></item><item><title>The Effect of Free School Meals on Household Food Purchases: Evidence from the Community Eligibility Provision</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29395</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michelle M. Marcus, Katherine G. Yewell.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We find evidence that exposure to universal free school meals through the Community Eligibility Provision (CEP) had a meaningful impact on grocery spending for households with children, with monthly food purchases declining by about $11, or 5 percent. For households in zip codes with higher exposure, the decline is as high as $39 per month, or 19 percent. We also show evidence that the composition of food purchases changes, with low income households experiencing an increase in the dietary quality of their food purchases by about 3 percent after CEP. Finally, we show CEP exposure is associated with an 11 percent decline in the percent of households that ran short of money or tried to make their food money go further, and an almost 5 percent decline in households classified as food insecure. Our results on the heterogeneous effects of CEP exposure by prior free/reduced price lunch eligibility reveal large benefits in terms of both spending, dietary composition, and food insecurity for previously eligible low-income families, suggesting that the stigma of free school meals may be declining after universal access.]]></description><author>Michelle M. Marcus, Katherine G. Yewell</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29395</guid></item><item><title>Who Pays Sin Taxes? Understanding the Overlapping Burdens of Corrective Taxes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29393</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher Conlon, Nirupama L. Rao, Yinan Wang.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We find that sin good purchases are highly concentrated with 10% of households paying more than 80% of taxes on alcohol and cigarettes. Total sin tax burdens are poorly explained by demographics (including income), but are well explained by eight household clusters defined by purchasing patterns. The two most taxed clusters comprise 8% of households, pay 68% of sin taxes, are older, less educated, and lower income. Taxes on sugary beverages broaden the tax base but add to the burdens of heavily taxed households. Efforts to increase sin taxes should consider the heavy burdens borne by few households.]]></description><author>Christopher Conlon, Nirupama L. Rao, Yinan Wang</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29393</guid></item><item><title>Inflation, Interest, and the Secular Rise in Wealth Inequality in the U.S.: Is the Fed Responsible?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29392</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Edward N. Wolff.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Two hallmarks of U.S. monetary policy since the 1981-1982 recession have been declining interest rates and moderation in inflation. Coincident with these trends has been a surge in U.S. wealth inequality, with the Gini coefficient up by 0.070 between 1983 and 2019. This paper analyzes the connection between these two developments on the basis of the Survey of Consumer Finances. Contrary to expectations, the paper finds that these two monetary effects have reduced wealth inequality rather than increasing it. The effect is sizeable, with the Gini coefficient declining by 0.045 over these years. Asset price changes and debt devaluation accounted for 72.6 percent of the advance of mean wealth over 1983-2019. They also would have led to a 204.9 percent gain in median wealth, compared to the actual rise of 23.4 percent. Moreover, they have helped lower the racial wealth gap rather than enlarging it. These results are at odds with previous literature in which estimates range from a weak negative effect on inequality to neutral, small positive, and strong positive. In terms of methodology, this paper differs from previous work by focusing on only the direct effects of interest rate changes and inflation on the household balance sheet.]]></description><author>Edward N. Wolff</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29392</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Fragility of For-profit Hospitals: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We estimate the likelihood of financial distress of U.S. hospitals in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic using AHA Annual Survey data for 2011-2019 and smartphone mobility data for 2020. We find that while the average likelihood of distress across all hospitals is 28.53 % in 2020, slightly increasing from 2019, for-profit hospitals are much more likely to be distressed. Their average likelihood of financial distress is 39.13 %---a 6.93 percentage point increase from 2019. For-profit hospitals are the main providers of specialty health care services, such as psychiatric and acute long-term care, so their increased likelihood of distress poses a risk to service provision in these specialty areas, and particularly in rural communities. Our prediction model based on mobility data performs very well in sample against actual data and can potentially help policymakers and hospital administrators to monitor financial distress in real-time when case mixes change, or other large shocks materialize.]]></description><author>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</guid></item><item><title>School Food Policy Affects Everyone: Retail Responses to the National School Lunch Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29384</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jessie Handbury, Sarah Moshary.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the private market response to the National School Lunch Program, documenting economically meaningful spillovers to non-recipients. We focus on the Community Eligibility Provision (CEP), an expansion of the lunch program under the 2010 Healthy, Hunger-Free Kids Act. Under the CEP, participating schools offer free lunch to all students. We leverage both the staggered roll-out and eligibility criterion for the CEP, which is limited to schools where at least 40% of students participate in other means-tested welfare programs. We find that local adoption of the CEP causes households with children to reduce their grocery purchases, leading to a 10% decline in grocery sales at large retail chains. Retailers respond with chain-level price adjustments: chains with the most exposure lower prices by 2.5% across all outlets in the years following adoption, so that the program's welfare benefits propagate spatially. Using a stylized model of grocery demand, we estimate that, by 2016, the indirect benefit had reduced grocery costs for the median household by approximately 4.5%.]]></description><author>Jessie Handbury, Sarah Moshary</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29384</guid></item><item><title>Top Wealth in America: New Estimates and Implications for Taxing the Rich</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29374</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Matthew Smith, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses administrative tax data to estimate top wealth in the United States. We assemble new data that links people to their sources of capital income and develop new methods to estimate the degree of return heterogeneity within asset classes. Disaggregated fixed income data reveal that rich individuals earn much more of their interest income in higher-yielding forms, and have much greater exposure to credit risk. Consequently, in recent years, the interest rate on fixed income at the top is approximately three times higher than the average. Using firm-level characteristics to value firms, we find that twenty percent of total pass-through business wealth accrues to those with losses. We combine this new data on fixed income and pass-through business returns with refined estimates of C-corporation equity, housing, and pension wealth to deliver new capitalized wealth estimates. Our approach---which builds on Saez and Zucman (2016) and Bricker, Henriques, and Hansen (2018)---reduces bias because wealth and rates of return are correlated. From 1989 to 2016, the top 1%, 0.1%, and 0.01% wealth shares increased by 7.6, 5.1, and 3.0 percentage points, respectively, to 31.5%, 15.0%, and 7.0%. While these changes are less dramatic than some prior estimates, wealth is very concentrated: the top 1% holds nearly as much wealth as either the bottom 90% or the "P90-99" class. We discuss implications for income inequality measures, capital tax policy, and savings behavior.]]></description><author>Matthew Smith, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29374</guid></item><item><title>Perceptions and Preferences for Redistribution</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29370</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefanie Stantcheva.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The relationship between the degree of inequality and the demand for redistribution has been a central question in political science and political economy. The famous median-voter model predicts that higher inequality, reflected in a growing gap between the income of the average and the median voter, should lead to increased demand for redistribution, as policymakers cater to the median voter’s preferences (Meltzer and Richard, 1981). Yet, using data from OECD countries, Kenworthy and McCall (2008) show that, despite increases in inequality in those countries, there was no corresponding increase in demand for redistribution. Part of the explanation of this puzzle lies in the realization that it is not only (or even mainly) reality, but perceptions that shape support for policy. This article will explore recent evidence using large-scale social economics surveys and experiments that sheds lights on beliefs about inequality, social mobility, diversity and immigration, social position, and understanding of how policies work.]]></description><author>Stefanie Stantcheva</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29370</guid></item><item><title>The Anti-Poverty, Targeting, and Labor Supply Effects of the Proposed Child Tax Credit Expansion</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29366</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kevin Corinth, Bruce D. Meyer, Matthew Stadnicki, Derek Wu.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The proposed change under the American Families Plan (AFP) to the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act (TCJA) Child Tax Credit (CTC) would increase maximum benefit amounts to $3,000 or $3,600 per child (up from $2,000 per child) and make the full credit available to all low and middle-income families regardless of earnings or income. We estimate the anti-poverty, targeting, and labor supply effects of the expansion by linking survey data with administrative tax and government program data which form part of the Comprehensive Income Dataset (CID). Initially ignoring any behavioral responses, we estimate that the expansion of the CTC would reduce child poverty by 34% and deep child poverty by 39%. The expansion of the CTC would have a larger anti-poverty effect on children than any existing government program, though at a higher cost per child raised above the poverty line than any other means-tested program. Relatedly, the CTC expansion would allocate a smaller share of its total dollars to families at the bottom of the income distribution—as well as families with the lowest levels of long-term income, education, or health—than any existing means-tested program with the exception of housing assistance. We then simulate anti-poverty effects accounting for labor supply responses. By replacing the TCJA CTC (which contained substantial work incentives akin to the Earned Income Tax Credit) with a universal basic income-type benefit, the CTC expansion reduces the return to working at all by at least $2,000 per child for most workers with children. Relying on elasticity estimates consistent with mainstream simulation models and the academic literature, we estimate that this change in policy would lead 1.5 million workers (constituting 2.6% of all working parents) to exit the labor force. The decline in employment and the consequent earnings loss would mean that child poverty would only fall by 22% and deep child poverty would not fall at all with the CTC expansion.]]></description><author>Kevin Corinth, Bruce D. Meyer, Matthew Stadnicki, Derek Wu</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29366</guid></item><item><title>The Political Economy of the COVID-19 Fiscal Stimulus Packages of 2020</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29360</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Ilan Noy.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Almost all countries announced fiscal support programs once COVID-19 hit. However, there was significant diversity in the magnitude and composition of these fiscal stimulus programs. These differences were determined by myriad political, financial, social, and economic factors - these factors are our focus. We ask what were the factors that are associated with the structure of the fiscal programs that governments chose to adopt in the early stage of the pandemic in 2020. We answer this question using details about the fiscal programs that were announced by 98 governments in the first six months of the pandemic, together with a large set of explanatory variables. Maybe not surprisingly, we find that politics played a very significant part in determining the size and composition of these fiscal programs. Governments and societies that are less polarized and more capable were able to mobilise more fiscal resources. We also find that it was governments with bigger debt loads that announced bigger programs, but that sovereign spreads were not so clearly associated with the size of these program plans. There is a limit, however, to what we can glean from these cross-country comparisons. Ultimately, the understanding of the politics and political-economy considerations that led to the specific content of each fiscal program will have to rely on information about the actual deliberations in each government’s halls of power, should these ever become public.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Ilan Noy</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29360</guid></item><item><title>The Effects of Taxes on Innovation: Theory and Empirical Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29359</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefanie Stantcheva.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Income taxes are typically set to raise revenues and redistribute income at the lowest possible efficiency costs, which result from the distortions in individual behaviors that taxes entail. Individuals can respond along many margins, such as labor supply, tax avoidance and evasion, and geographic mobility. But one margin that taxes may affect — innovation — is less frequently considered. Conceptually, taxes reduce the expected net returns to innovation inputs and can reduce innovation. Much like other margins of responses to taxes, this efficiency cost must be taken into account. Innovation is done by a relatively small number of people, but it is nevertheless likely to have widespread benefits. While inventors may have divergent motivations, such as social recognition or the love of discovery, they also face an economic reality. How strongly innovation responds to taxes is an empirical question that has been the subject of a growing body of recent work. In this paper, I study how to account for innovation when setting personal income and capital taxation. I distinguish between two cases: one in which the government can set a differentiated tax on inventors and one in which the government is constrained to set the same tax on all agents. I provide a model that flexibly accounts for the spillovers generated by innovation and the non-pecuniary benefits inventors receive from innovation and derive tax formulas expressed in terms of estimable sufficient statistics. The second part of the paper discusses the empirical evidence on the effects of taxes on the quantity, quality, and location of innovation, as well as tax avoidance and income shifting done through innovation.]]></description><author>Stefanie Stantcheva</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29359</guid></item><item><title>College Choice, Private Options, and The Incidence of Public Investment in Higher Education</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29353</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John Bound, Andrew Simon.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Previous measures of the incidence of public investment in higher education focus on the transfer to public college students. This implies that the net benefits to students who do not attend public colleges is negative. However, they miss potential general equilibrium effects on the private college and labor markets. Changes in the public college market affect who private colleges admit, what prices they charge, and the number of students who enroll in any college. We show that capturing these spillovers is important for characterizing incidence using a model of higher education that we validate with quasi-experimental variation in state spending. Unlike previous measures, we find that high-income-modest-ability students especially benefit since they are only admitted to high-quality private colleges when state spending is high, and the public colleges create sufficient competitive pressure. Decreased investment also reduces educational attainment, raising the college wage premium. This exacerbates private college market power.]]></description><author>John Bound, Andrew Simon</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29353</guid></item><item><title>Tax Policy Design with Low Interest Rates</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29352</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alan J. Auerbach, William Gale.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Interest rates on government debt have fallen in many countries over the last several decades, with markets indicating that rates may stay low well into the future.  It is by now well understood that sustained low interest rates can change the nature of long-run fiscal policy choices.  In this paper, we examine a related issue: the implications of sustained low interest rates for the structure of tax policy.  We show that low interest rates (a) reduce the differences between consumption and income taxes; (b) make wealth taxes less efficient relative to capital income taxes, at given rates of tax; (c) reduce the value of firm-level investment incentives, and (d) substantially raise the valuation of benefits of carbon abatement policies relative to their costs.]]></description><author>Alan J. Auerbach, William Gale</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29352</guid></item><item><title>Estimating the Net Fiscal Cost of a Child Tax Credit Expansion</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29342</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jacob Goldin, Elaine Maag, Katherine Michelmore.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Recent proposals to expand the Child Tax Credit (CTC) are at the center of current policy discussions in the United States. We study the fiscal cost of three such proposals that would expand refundability of the credit to low-income children, increase the maximum credit amount, and/or eliminate the income phase-out to make the credit universal. For each proposal, we use the Current Population Survey to estimate three components of the net fiscal cost: the direct cost (additional tax refunds or lower tax liability), revenue changes due to taxpayers’ labor supply responses, and long-term changes in tax revenue due to changes in children’s future earnings. We find that direct costs are by far the most important component but that long-term earning changes also play an important role, offsetting 20% of the direct costs of making the credit fully refundable. In contrast, labor supply responses modestly contribute to the fiscal cost of the CTC expansions we model.]]></description><author>Jacob Goldin, Elaine Maag, Katherine Michelmore</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29342</guid></item><item><title>Charitable Giving Responses to Education Budgets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29331</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan Meer, Hedieh Tajali.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Do changes in government spending affect voluntary contributions to those recipients? We examine how changes in K-12 education budgets impact donations to teachers using data from DonorsChoose.org, an online crowdfunding platform for public school teachers to raise money for their classrooms. Using a district-year panel and instruments to address the endogeneity of budgets, we find evidence for crowd-out of private giving, though the magnitudes are fairly small in this setting and do not offset a large proportion of a budget change. These results are driven by entirely teachers' posting of requests, illustrating the importance of considering the demand side of the charitable giving market.]]></description><author>Jonathan Meer, Hedieh Tajali</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29331</guid></item><item><title>Exposure to Cigarette Taxes as a Teenager and the Persistence of Smoking into Adulthood</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29325</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andrew I. Friedson, Moyan Li, Katherine Meckel, Daniel I. Rees, Daniel W. Sacks.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Are teenage and adult smoking causally related?  Recent anti-tobacco policy is predicated on the assumption that preventing teenagers from smoking will ensure that fewer adults smoke, but direct evidence in support of this assumption is scant.  Using data from three nationally representative sources and cigarette taxes experienced as a teenager as an instrument, we document a strong, positive relationship between teenage and adult smoking: specifically, deterring 10 teenagers from smoking through raising cigarette taxes roughly translates into 5 or 6 fewer eventual adult smokers.  We conclude that efforts to reduce teenage smoking can have important, long-lasting consequences on smoking participation and, presumably, health.]]></description><author>Andrew I. Friedson, Moyan Li, Katherine Meckel, Daniel I. Rees, Daniel W. Sacks</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29325</guid></item><item><title>Why Don’t Elite Colleges Expand Supply?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29309</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Peter Q. Blair, Kent Smetters.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> While college enrollment has more-than doubled since 1970, elite colleges have barely increased supply, instead reducing admit rates. We show that straightforward reasons cannot explain this behavior. We propose a model where colleges compete on prestige, measured using relative selectivity or relative admit rates. A key comparative static of the model is that higher demand decreases [increases] the admit rate when the weight on prestige is above [below] a critical value, consistent with experience in elite [non-elite] colleges. A calibrated version of the model closely replicates the pattern in the data of declining admit rates at elite colleges while counter-factual simulations without prestige fail. Prestige competition is inefficient. Allowing elite colleges to collude on admissions strategy internalizes the non-pecuniary prestige externality and is Pareto improving.]]></description><author>Peter Q. Blair, Kent Smetters</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29309</guid></item><item><title>Mobility for All: Representative Intergenerational Mobility Estimates over the 20th Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29289</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Elisa Jácome, Ilyana Kuziemko, Suresh Naidu.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We present the first estimates of long-run trends in intergenerational relative mobility for samples that are representative of the full U.S.-born population.  Harmonizing all surveys that ask about father's occupation and own family income, we develop a mobility measure that allows for the inclusion of non-whites and women for the 1910s–1970s birth cohorts.  We show a robust increase in mobility between the 1910s and 1940s cohorts, about half of which is driven by absolute convergence in racial income gaps. We also find that excluding Black Americans, particularly Black women, considerably overstates mobility throughout the 20th century.]]></description><author>Elisa Jácome, Ilyana Kuziemko, Suresh Naidu</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29289</guid></item><item><title>The Initial Effects of the Expanded Child Tax Credit on Material Hardship</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zachary Parolin, Elizabeth Ananat, Sophie M. Collyer, Megan Curran, Christopher Wimer.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> The transformation of the Child Tax Credit (CTC) into a more generous, inclusive monthly payment marks a historic (temporary) shift in U.S. treatment of low-income families. To investigate the initial impact of these payments, we apply a series of difference-in-difference estimates using Census Household Pulse Survey microdata collected from April 14 through August 16, 2021. Our findings offer three primary conclusions regarding the initial effects of the monthly CTC. First, payments strongly reduced food insufficiency: the initial payments led to a 7.5 percentage point (25 percent) decline in food insufficiency among low-income households with children. Second, the effects on food insufficiency are concentrated among families with 2019 pre-tax incomes below $35,000, and the CTC strongly reduces food insufficiency among low-income Black, Latino, and White families alike. Third, increasing the CTC coverage rate would be required in order for material hardship to be reduced further. Self-reports suggest the lowest-income households were less likely than higher-income families to receive the first CTC payments. As more children receive the benefit in future months, material hardship may decline further. Even with imperfect coverage, however, our findings suggest that the first CTC payments were largely effective at reducing food insufficiency among low-income families with children.]]></description><author>Zachary Parolin, Elizabeth Ananat, Sophie M. Collyer, Megan Curran, Christopher Wimer</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285</guid></item><item><title>The Geography of Unemployment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Unemployment rates differ widely across local labor markets. I offer new empirical evidence that high local unemployment emerges because of elevated local job losing rates. Local employers, rather than local workers, account for most of spatial gaps in job stability. I then propose a theory in which spatial differences in job loss arise endogenously, due to the spatial sorting of heterogeneous employers across local labor markets.  Labor market frictions induce productive employers to over-value locating close to each other. The optimal policy incentivizes them to relocate to areas with high job losing rates, providing a rationale for commonly used place-based policies. I estimate the model using French administrative data. The estimated model accounts for over three fourths of the cross-sectional dispersion in unemployment rates, as well as for the respective contributions of job losing and job finding rates. Employers' inefficient location choices amplify spatial unemployment differentials five-fold. Both real-world and optimal place-based policies can yield sizable local and aggregate welfare gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</guid></item></channel></rss>