<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Game Theory</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Game Theory</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 14:13:40 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Market Design</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29367</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This Handbook chapter seeks to introduce students and researchers of industrial organization (IO) to the field of market design. We emphasize two important points of connection between the IO and market design fields: a focus on market failures—both understanding sources of market failure and analyzing how to fix them—and an appreciation of institutional detail.<br />
Section II reviews theory, focusing on introducing the theory of matching and assignment mechanisms to a broad audience. It introduces a novel “taxonomy” of market design problems, covers the key mechanisms and their properties, and emphasizes several points of connection to traditional economic theory involving prices and competitive equilibrium.<br />
Section III reviews structural empirical methods that build on this theory. We describe how to estimate a workhorse random utility model under various data environments, ranging from data on reported preference data such as rank-order lists to data only on observed matches. These methods enable a quantification of trade-offs in designing markets and the effects of new market designs.<br />
Section IV discusses a wide variety of applications. We organize this discussion into three broad aims of market design research: (i) diagnosing market failures; (ii) evaluating and comparing various market designs; (iii) proposing new, improved designs. A point of emphasis is that theoretical and empirical analysis have been highly complementary in this research.]]></description><author>Nikhil Agarwal, Eric Budish</author></item><item><title>Task Allocation and On-the-job Training</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29312</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study dynamic task allocation when providers' expertise evolves endogenously through training. We characterize optimal assignment protocols and compare them to discretionary procedures, where it is the clients who select their service providers. Our results indicate that welfare gains from centralization are greater when tasks arrive more rapidly, and when training technologies improve. Monitoring seniors' backlog of clients always increases welfare but may decrease training. Methodologically, we explore a matching setting with endogenous types, and illustrate useful adaptations of queueing theory techniques for such environments.]]></description><author>Mariagiovanna Baccara, SangMok Lee, Leeat Yariv</author></item><item><title>Experimental Evidence on Semi-structured Bargaining with Private Information</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29265</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We conduct a laboratory experiment to study a decentralized market where goods are differentiated and evaluations are private. We implement different semi-structured bargaining protocols based on deferred acceptance, and we compare their performance to the benchmark scenario of a sealed-bid auction. We show that bargaining dramatically improves efficiency, mainly to the benefit of players rather than the silent auctioneer. A protocol of unconstrained simultaneous bargaining performs best, doubling the proportion of deals relative to the benchmark. This is because participants seek to reveal information through a gradual bidding-up strategy that favors bargaining environments. Aggregate efficiency nonetheless suffers from the fact that buyers bargain harder than sellers, and that some players over-bargain to appropriate a larger share of the unknown surplus.]]></description><author>Margherita Comola, Marcel Fafchamps</author></item><item><title>Who Cares More? Allocation with Diverse Preference Intensities</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29208</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Goods and services---public housing, medical appointments, schools---are often allocated to individuals who rank them similarly but differ in their preference intensities. We characterize optimal allocation rules when individual preferences are known and when they are not. Several insights emerge. First-best allocations may involve assigning some agents "lotteries" between high- and low-ranked goods. When preference intensities are private information, second-best allocations always involve such lotteries and, crucially, may coincide with first-best allocations. Furthermore, second-best allocations may entail disposal of services. We discuss a market-based alternative and show how it differs.]]></description><author>Pietro Ortoleva, Evgenii Safonov, Leeat Yariv</author></item><item><title>How Well Does Bargaining Work in Consumer Markets? A Robust Bounds Approach</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29202</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This study provides a structural analysis of detailed, alternating-offer bargaining data from eBay, deriving bounds on buyers and sellers private value distributions using a range of assumptions on behavior. These assumptions range from very weak (assuming only that acceptance and rejection decisions are rational) to less weak (e.g., assuming that bargaining offers are weakly increasing in players' private values). We estimate the bounds and show what they imply for consumer negotiation behavior in theory and practice. For the median product, bargaining ends in impasses in 43% of negotiations even when the buyer values the good more than the seller.]]></description><author>Joachim Freyberger, Bradley Larsen</author></item></channel></rss>