<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Households and Firms</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Households and Firms</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 14:04:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Human Frictions in the Transmission of Economic Policies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>Many consumers below the top of the distribution of a representative population by cognitive abilities barely react to  monetary and fiscal policies that aim to stimulate consumption and borrowing, even when they are financially unconstrained and despite substantial debt capacity. Differences in income, formal education levels, economic expectations, and a large set of registry-based demographics do not explain these facts. Heterogeneous cognitive abilities thus act as human frictions in the transmission of economic policies that operate through the household sector and might imply  redistribution from low- to high-cognitive-ability agents. We conclude by discussing how our findings inform the microfoundation of behavioral macroeconomic theory.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber</author></item><item><title>Measuring the Welfare Cost of Asymmetric Information in Consumer Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>Information asymmetries are known in theory to lead to inefficiently low credit provision, yet empirical estimates of the resulting welfare losses are scarce. This paper leverages a randomized experiment conducted by a large fintech lender to estimate welfare losses arising from asymmetric information in the market for online consumer credit. Building on methods from the insurance literature, we show how exogenous variation in interest rates can be used to estimate borrower demand and lender cost curves and recover implied welfare losses. While asymmetric information generates large equilibrium price distortions, we find only small overall welfare losses, particularly for high-credit-score borrowers.]]></description><author>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis</author></item><item><title>Empirical Models of Demand and Supply in Differentiated Products Industries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29257</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>This is an invited chapter for the forthcoming Volume 4 of the Handbook of Industrial Organization. We present empirical models of demand and supply in differentiated products industries with an emphasis on the key ideas arising from the recent applied literature. We start with a discussion of the challenges in modeling and estimation of demand for  differentiated products, and focus on discrete choice characteristics-based demand models that address these challenges while allowing enough flexibility to capture realistic substitution patterns. Our discussion emphasizes how empirical strategies can leverage different features of data depending on the sources of variation that are commonly found in applied work. Moving to the supply-side, we show how demand estimates combined with a pricing model, can be used to recover markups and marginal costs. We also show how the model of pricing can be tested. We discuss a baseline Bertrand-Nash model of competitive pricing, and expand it to cover a) coordinated pricing, b) wholesale relationships, and c) bargaining. We end the chapter with extensions of the demand model, including dynamic and continuous demand.]]></description><author>Amit Gandhi, Aviv Nevo</author></item><item><title>An Industrial Organization Perspective on Productivity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29229</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>This chapter overviews productivity research from an industrial organization perspective. We focus on what is known and what still needs to be learned about the productivity levels and dynamics of individual producers, but also how these interact through markets and industries to influence productivity aggregates. We overview productivity concepts, facts, data, measurement, analysis, and open questions.]]></description><author>Jan De Loecker, Chad Syverson</author></item><item><title>What Can Stockouts Tell Us About Inflation? Evidence from Online Micro Data</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29209</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>We use a detailed micro dataset on product availability to construct a direct high-frequency measure of consumer product shortages during the 2020–2021 pandemic. We document a widespread multi-fold rise in shortages in nearly all sectors early in the pandemic. Over time, the composition of shortages evolved from many temporary stockouts to mostly discontinued products, concentrated in fewer sectors. We show that product shortages have significant but transitory inflationary effects, and that these effects can be associated with elevated cost of replenishing inventories.]]></description><author>Alberto Cavallo, Oleksiy Kryvtsov</author></item><item><title>Hedging and Competition</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29207</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>We study how risk management through hedging impacts firms and competition among firms in the life insurance industry - an industry with over 7 Trillion in assets and over 1,000 private and public firms. We show that firms that are likely to face costly external finance increase hedging after staggered state-level financial reform that reduces the costs of hedging. Post reform impacted firms have lower risk and fewer negative income shocks. Product market competition is also impacted. Firms that previously are more likely to face costly external finance, lower price, increase policy sales and increase their market share post reform. The results are consistent with hedging allowing firms that face potential costly financial distress to decrease risk and become more competitive.]]></description><author>Erasmo Giambona, Anil Kumar, Gordon M. Phillips</author></item><item><title>Income-Contingent Loans As an Unemployment Benefit</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29198</link><description><![CDATA[August 2021<p>Imperfections in risk and capital markets imply that individuals who lose jobs suffer from imperfect smoothing of consumption across states and times. Compared to the first best, there will be too little search. Optimal unemployment programs, which balance the marginal benefit of consumption smoothing vs. the marginal cost of the insurance externality, increase welfare and may even increase GDP. Our analytical results suggest that welfare is higher if the unemployment benefits program includes income-contingent unemployment loans (ICL), where the amount repaid depends on the individual’s future income. Such loans can be financed by a risk premium imposed on the unemployed who avail themselves of the loans, and partially substitute for unemployment insurance (UI) benefits. Optimal unemployment benefits programs (UB) with ICL do a better job of smoothing consumption across states and time, and in particular total benefits when unemployed increase. We analyze how changes in key parameters, such as the degree of risk aversion and the nature of post-employment work, affect the design of the optimal UB program and the magnitude of the incremental benefits from including income-contingent loans.]]></description><author>Haaris Mateen ⓡ, Joseph E. Stiglitz ⓡ, Jungyoll Yun</author></item><item><title>The Consumption, Income, and Well-Being of Single Mother Headed Families 25 Years After Welfare Reform</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29188</link><description><![CDATA[August 2021<p>We investigate how material well-being has changed over time for single mother headed families—the primary group affected by welfare reform and other policy changes of the 1990s. We focus on consumption as well as other indicators including components of consumption, measures of housing quality, and health insurance coverage. The results provide strong evidence that the material circumstances of single mothers improved in the decades following welfare reform. The consumption of the most disadvantaged single mother headed families—those with low consumption or low education—rose noticeably over time and at a faster rate than for those in comparison groups.]]></description><author>Jeehoon Han, Bruce D. Meyer, James X. Sullivan</author></item></channel></rss>