<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Labor Market Structures</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Labor Market Structures</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 14:09:27 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Worker Beliefs About Outside Options</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29623</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Simon Jäger, Christopher Roth, Nina Roussille, Benjamin Schoefer.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Workers wrongly anchor their beliefs about outside options on their current wage. In particular, low-paid workers underestimate wages elsewhere. We document this anchoring bias by eliciting workers’ beliefs in a representative survey in Germany and comparing them to measures of actual outside options in linked administrative labor market data. In an equilibrium model, such anchoring can give rise to monopsony and labor market segmentation. In line with the model, misperceptions are particularly pronounced among workers in low-wage firms. If workers had correct beliefs, at least 10% of jobs, concentrated in low-wage firms, would not be viable at current wages.]]></description><author>Simon Jäger, Christopher Roth, Nina Roussille, Benjamin Schoefer</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29623</guid></item><item><title>The Effects of Letters of Recommendation in the Youth Labor Market</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29579</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sara B. Heller, Judd B. Kessler.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Youth employment has been near historic lows in recent years, and racial gaps persist. This paper tests whether information frictions limit young people's labor market success with a field experiment involving over 43,000 youth in New York City. We build software that allows employers to quickly and easily produce letters of recommendation for randomly selected youth who worked under their supervision during a summer youth employment program. We then send these letters to nearly 9,000 youth over two years. Being sent a letter generates a 3 percentage point (4.5 percent) increase in employment the following year, with both employment and earnings increases persisting over the two-year follow-up period. By posting our own job advertisement, we document that while treatment youth do use the letters in applications, there is no evidence of other supply-side responses (i.e., no increased job search, motivation, or confidence); effects appear to be driven by the demand side. Labor market benefits accrue primarily to racial and ethnic minorities, suggesting frictions may contribute to racial employment gaps. But improved employment may also hamper on-time high school graduation. Additional evidence indicates that letters help improve job match quality. Results suggest that expanding the availability credible signals about young workers—particularly for those not on the margin of graduating high school—could improve the efficiency of the youth labor market.]]></description><author>Sara B. Heller, Judd B. Kessler</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29579</guid></item><item><title>Making Teaching Last: Long-Run Value-Added</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29555</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Gilraine, Nolan G. Pope.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Teacher value-added (VA) measures how teachers improve their students' contemporaneous test scores. Many teachers, however, argue that contemporaneous test scores are a poor proxy for their permanent influence on students.  This paper considers a new VA measure -- 'long-run VA' -- that captures teachers' contributions that persist by replacing contemporaneous test scores with subsequent test scores in VA estimation.  We find that students assigned to high long-run VA teachers fare substantially better in terms of long-term outcomes.  Policy simulations indicate that the use of long-run VA improves policy effectiveness by a factor of two compared to traditional VA measures.]]></description><author>Michael Gilraine, Nolan G. Pope</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29555</guid></item><item><title>Trade Competition and the Decline in Union Organizing: Evidence from Certification Elections</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29464</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kerwin Kofi Charles, Matthew S. Johnson, Nagisa Tadjfar.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We assess whether and why trade competition partly explains the sharp decline in U.S. workers’ attempts to organize labor unions in recent decades. We find that between 1990-2007, import competition due to the “China Shock” lowered union certification elections by 4.5% among workers in manufacturing industries directly exposed to it, and by 8.8% among workers indirectly exposed through its effect on their local labor market. Consistent with a simple model of workers’ decision to seek union representa- tion, we show that direct exposure lowered the expected wage gain from unionization, whereas indirect exposure increased the cost of job loss, both of which discourage worker organizing.]]></description><author>Kerwin Kofi Charles, Matthew S. Johnson, Nagisa Tadjfar</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29464</guid></item><item><title>Spillover Effects from Voluntary Employer Minimum Wages</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29425</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ellora Derenoncourt, Clemens Noelke, David Weil, Bledi Taska.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Low unionization rates, a falling real federal minimum wage, and outsourcing have hampered wage growth in the low-wage sector in the US. In recent years, a number of private employers have opted to institute or raise company-wide minimum wages for their employees, sometimes in response to public pressure. To what extent do wage-setting changes at major employers spill over to other employers, and what are the broader labor market effects of these policies? In this paper, we study recent minimum wages by Amazon, Walmart, Target, CVS, and Costco using data from millions of online job ads and employee surveys. We document that these policies induced wage increases at low-wage jobs at other employers, where the modal response was to match the wage announced by the large retailer. In the case of Amazon’s $15 minimum wage in October 2018, our estimates imply that a 10% increase in Amazon’s advertised hourly wages led to an average increase of 2.3% among other employers in the same commuting zone. Using the CPS, we estimate wage increases in exposed jobs in line with our magnitudes from employee surveys and find that large employer minimum wage policies led to small but precisely estimated declines in employment, with employment elasticities ranging from -0.04 to -0.13. Large employer minimum wage announcements influenced wages more broadly. The magnitude of these wage spillovers cannot easily be explained by standard competitive pressures, suggesting a role for both market power and norms in wage determination.]]></description><author>Ellora Derenoncourt, Clemens Noelke, David Weil, Bledi Taska</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29425</guid></item><item><title>The Human Side of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We document that nearly half of the global decline in agricultural employment during the 20th-century was driven by new cohorts entering the labor market. A newly compiled dataset of policy reforms supports an interpretation of these cohort effects as human capital. Through the lens of a model of frictional labor reallocation, we conclude that human capital growth, both as a mediating factor and as an independent driver, led to a sharp decline in the agricultural labor supply. This decline accounts, at fixed prices, for 40% of the decrease in agricultural employment. This aggregate effect is roughly halved in general equilibrium.]]></description><author>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</guid></item><item><title>“Beauty Too Rich for Use”*: Billionaires’ Assets and Attractiveness</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29361</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel S. Hamermesh, Andrew Leigh.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We examine how the net worth of billionaires relates to their looks, as rated by 16 people of different gender and ethnicity. Surprisingly, their financial assets are unrelated to their beauty; nor are they related to their educational attainment. As a group, however, billionaires are both more educated and better-looking than average for their age. Men, people who reside in Western countries, and those who inherited substantial wealth, are wealthier than other billionaires. The results do not arise from measurement error or nonrandom sample selectivity. They are consistent with econometric theory about the impact of truncating a sample to include observations only from the extreme tail of the dependent variable. The point is underscored by comparing estimates of earnings equations using all employees in the 2018 American Community Survey to those using a sample of the top 0.1 percent. The findings suggest the powerful role of luck within the extremes of the distributions of economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Daniel S. Hamermesh, Andrew Leigh</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29361</guid></item><item><title>Outsourcing, Inequality and Aggregate Output</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Outsourced workers experience large wage declines, yet domestic outsourcing may raise aggregate productivity. To study this equity-efficiency trade-off, we contribute a framework in which firms either hire many imperfectly substitutable worker types in-house by posting wages along a job ladder, or rent labor services from contractors who hire in the same frictional labor markets. Three implications arise. First, more productive firms are more likely to outsource to save on higher wage premia. Second, outsourcing raises output at the firm level. Third, contractors endogenously locate at the bottom of the job ladder, implying that outsourced workers receive lower wages. Using firm-level instruments for outsourcing and revenue productivity, we find empirical support for all three predictions in French administrative data. After structurally estimating the model, we find that the rise in outsourcing in France between 1996 and 2007 raised aggregate output by 3% and reduced the labor share by 0.7 percentage points. A 9% minimum wage increase stabilizes the labor share and maintains two thirds of the output gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</guid></item><item><title>The Geography of Unemployment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Unemployment rates differ widely across local labor markets. I offer new empirical evidence that high local unemployment emerges because of elevated local job losing rates. Local employers, rather than local workers, account for most of spatial gaps in job stability. I then propose a theory in which spatial differences in job loss arise endogenously, due to the spatial sorting of heterogeneous employers across local labor markets.  Labor market frictions induce productive employers to over-value locating close to each other. The optimal policy incentivizes them to relocate to areas with high job losing rates, providing a rationale for commonly used place-based policies. I estimate the model using French administrative data. The estimated model accounts for over three fourths of the cross-sectional dispersion in unemployment rates, as well as for the respective contributions of job losing and job finding rates. Employers' inefficient location choices amplify spatial unemployment differentials five-fold. Both real-world and optimal place-based policies can yield sizable local and aggregate welfare gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</guid></item></channel></rss>