<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Subnational Fiscal Issues</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Subnational Fiscal Issues</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 14:01:51 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Economic Burden of Pension Shortfalls: Evidence from House Prices</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> U.S. state pensions are underfunded by trillions of dollars, but their economic burden is unclear. In a model of inefficient taxation, real estate fully reflects the cost of pension shortfalls when it is the only form of immobile capital. We study the effect of pension shortfalls on real estate values at state borders, where labor and physical capital could more easily relocate to a state with a smaller shortfall. Using plausibly exogenous variation driven by pension asset returns, we find that one dollar of pension underfunding reduces house prices near state borders by approximately two dollars. Our estimates imply a deadweight loss associated with addressing pension shortfalls that is consistent with prior research in settings with high returns to public spending and costs of taxation.]]></description><author>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</guid></item><item><title>College Choice, Private Options, and The Incidence of Public Investment in Higher Education</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29353</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Previous measures of the incidence of public investment in higher education focus on the transfer to public college students. This implies that the net benefits to students who do not attend public colleges is negative. However, they miss potential general equilibrium effects on the private college and labor markets. Changes in the public college market affect who private colleges admit, what prices they charge, and the number of students who enroll in any college. We show that capturing these spillovers is important for characterizing incidence using a model of higher education that we validate with quasi-experimental variation in state spending. Unlike previous measures, we find that high-income-modest-ability students especially benefit since they are only admitted to high-quality private colleges when state spending is high, and the public colleges create sufficient competitive pressure. Decreased investment also reduces educational attainment, raising the college wage premium. This exacerbates private college market power.]]></description><author>John Bound, Andrew Simon</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29353</guid></item><item><title>The Causal Effects of Place on Health and Longevity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29321</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Life expectancy varies substantially across local regions within a country, raising conjectures that place of residence affects health. However, population sorting and other confounders make it difficult to disentangle the effects of place on health from other geographic differences in life expectancy. Recent studies have overcome such challenges to demonstrate that place of residence substantially influences health and mortality. Whether policies that encourage people to move to places that are better for their health or that improve areas that are detrimental to health are desirable depends on the mechanisms behind place effects, yet these mechanisms remain poorly understood.]]></description><author>Tatyana Deryugina, David Molitor</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29321</guid></item><item><title>Why Does Education Increase Voting? Evidence from Boston’s Charter Schools</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29308</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> In the United States, people with more education vote more. But, we know little about why education increases political participation or whether higher-quality education increases civic participation. We study applicants to Boston charter schools, using school lotteries to estimate charter attendance impacts for academic and voting outcomes. First, we confirm large academic gains for students in the sample of charter schools and cohorts investigated here. Second, we find that charter attendance boosts voter participation. Voting in the first presidential election after a student turns 18 increased substantially, by six percentage points from a base of 35 percent. The voting effect is driven entirely by girls and there is no increase in voter registration. Rich data and the differential effects by gender enable exploration of multiple potential channels for the voting impact. We find evidence consistent with two mechanisms: charter schools increase voting by increasing students’ noncognitive skills and by politicizing families who participate in charter school education.]]></description><author>Sarah Cohodes, James J. Feigenbaum</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29308</guid></item><item><title>The Returns to College(s): Relative Value-Added and Match Effects in Higher Education</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29276</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Students who attend different colleges in the U.S. end up with vastly different economic outcomes. We study the role of relative value-added across colleges within student choice sets in producing these outcome disparities. Linking high school, college, and earnings registries spanning the state of Texas, we identify relative college value-added by comparing the outcomes of students who apply to and are admitted by the same set of institutions, as this approach strikingly balances observable student potential across college treatments and renders our extensive set of covariates irrelevant as controls. Methodologically, we develop a framework for identifying and interpreting value-added under varying assumptions about match effects and sorting gains. Empirically, we estimate a relatively tight, though non-degenerate, distribution of relative value-added across the wide diversity of Texas public universities. Selectivity poorly predicts value-added within student choice sets, with only a fleeting selectivity earnings premium fading to zero after a few years in the labor market. Non-peer college inputs like instructional spending more strongly predict value-added, especially conditional on selectivity. Colleges that boost BA completion, especially in STEM majors, also tend to boost earnings. Finally, we probe the potential for (mis)match effects by allowing value-added schedules to vary by student characteristics.]]></description><author>Jack Mountjoy, Brent R. Hickman</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29276</guid></item><item><title>Police Officer Assignment and Neighborhood Crime</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29243</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We develop an empirical model of the mechanism used to assign police officers to Chicago districts and examine the efficiency and equity of alternative allocations. We document that the current bidding process, which grants priority based on seniority, results in the assignment of more experienced officers to less violent and high-income neighborhoods. Our empirical model combines estimates of heterogeneous officer preferences underlying the bidding process with causal estimates of the effects of officer experience on neighborhood crime. Equalizing officer seniority across districts would reduce violent crime rate by 4.6 percent and significantly decrease inequality in crime, discretionary arrests, and officer use of force across neighborhoods. Moreover, this assignment can be achieved in a revenue-neutral way while resulting in small welfare gains for police officers, implying that it is more equitable and efficient.]]></description><author>Bocar Ba, Patrick Bayer, Nayoung Rim, Roman Rivera, Modibo Sidibé</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29243</guid></item></channel></rss>