<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by groups: Household Finance</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by groups: Household Finance</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 21:30:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Machine-Learning the Skill of Mutual Fund Managers</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29723</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ron Kaniel, Zihan Lin, Markus Pelger, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We show, using machine learning, that fund characteristics can consistently differentiate high from low-performing mutual funds, as well as identify funds with net-of-fees abnormal returns. Fund momentum and fund flow are the most important predictors of future risk-adjusted fund performance, while characteristics of the stocks that funds hold are not predictive. Returns of predictive long-short portfolios are higher following a period of high sentiment or a good state of the macro-economy. Our estimation with neural networks enables us to uncover novel and substantial interaction effects between sentiment and both fund flow and fund momentum.]]></description><author>Ron Kaniel, Zihan Lin, Markus Pelger, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29723</guid></item><item><title>Two-Way Fixed Effects and Differences-in-Differences with Heterogeneous Treatment Effects: A Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29691</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&#039;Haultfoeuille.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Linear regressions with period and group fixed effects are widely used to estimate policies' effects: 26 of the 100 most cited papers published by the American Economic Review from 2015 to 2019 estimate such regressions. It has recently been show that those regressions may produce misleading estimates, if the policy's effect is heterogeneous between groups or over time, as is often the case. This survey reviews a fast-growing literature that documents this issue, and that proposes alternative estimators robust to heterogeneous effects.]]></description><author>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&amp;#039;Haultfoeuille</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29691</guid></item><item><title>Long-Term Care Insurance Financing Using Home Equity Release: Evidence from an Online Experimental Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29689</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Katja Hanewald, Hazel Bateman, Hanming Fang, Tin Long Ho.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper explores new mechanisms to fund long-term care using housing wealth. Using data from an online experimental survey fielded to a sample of 1,200 Chinese homeowners aged 45-64, we assess the potential demand for new financial products that allow individuals to access their housing wealth to buy long-term care insurance. We find that access to housing wealth increases the stated demand for long-term care insurance. When they could only use savings, participants used on average 5% of their total (hypothetical) wealth to purchase long-term care insurance. When they could use savings and a reverse mortgage, participants used 15% of their total wealth to buy long-term care insurance. With savings and home reversion, they used 12%. Reverse mortgages do not require regular payments until the home is sold, while home reversion involves a partial sale and leaseback. Our results inform the design of new public or private sector programs that allow individuals to access their housing wealth while still living in their homes.]]></description><author>Katja Hanewald, Hazel Bateman, Hanming Fang, Tin Long Ho</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29689</guid></item><item><title>A Simple Mapping from MPCs to MPXs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29664</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Laibson, Peter Maxted, Benjamin Moll.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Standard consumption models assume a notional consumption flow that does not distinguish between nondurable and durable consumption. Such notional-consumption models generate notional marginal propensities to consume (MPC). By contrast, empirical work and policy discussions often highlight marginal propensities for expenditure (MPX), which incorporate spending on a durable stock. We compare the notional-consumption model to an isomorphic model with a durable stock, and map notional MPCs into MPXs. The mapping is especially simple for a one-period horizon: MPX =  (1 - s + s/(r+d)) x MPC, with durable share s, real interest rate r, and durable depreciation rate d.]]></description><author>David Laibson, Peter Maxted, Benjamin Moll</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29664</guid></item><item><title>A Cross-Country Comparison of Old Age Financial Readiness in Asian Countries vs. the United States: The Case of Japan and the Republic of Korea</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29649</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Isaac Ehrlich, Yong Yin.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We pursue a cross-country comparison of relative financial readiness of older households in Japan and the Republic of Korea relative to the US.  Our comparative analysis, using macro-level and harmonized longitudinal household financial data, covers the principal financial channels of old age support: public and private pension plans, family support, and self-management of private financial portfolios. We find that while all three countries have similar public pension systems, older Americans benefit from more developed and better-funded public and private pension systems, as well as individual management of risky financial portfolios. We find that educational and health attainments of household heads and household wealth lead to a greater tendency to hold and manage risky assets. Our decomposition analysis also shows that the gap in stock ownership in Asian countries relative to the US is attributable to lower development levels of financial and pension markets. However, these gaps are shrinking more recently.]]></description><author>Isaac Ehrlich, Yong Yin</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29649</guid></item><item><title>Household Spending Responses to the Economic Impact Payments of 2020: Evidence from the Consumer Expenditure Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29648</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan A. Parker, Jake Schild, Laura Erhard, David Johnson.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Using the Consumer Expenditure Survey and variation in amount, receipt, and timing of receipt of Economic Impact Payments (EIPs) authorized by the CARES Act, this paper estimates that people spent less of their EIPs in the few months following arrival than in similar previous policy episodes and than estimated by existing studies using other types of data. Accounting for volatility during the pandemic and comparing the consumer spending behavior of broadly similar households, people spent roughly 10 percent (standard error 3.4) of their EIPs on non-durable goods and services in the three months of arrival, with little evidence of additional spending in the subsequent three months or on  durable goods. People who report mostly spending their EIPs spent 14.3\% (3.7) of their EIPs compared to 5.9\% (8.3) and -1.6\% (5.0) for those who report mostly paying off debt and saving respectively. People with low liquid wealth and people receiving their EIPs on debit cards spent at higher rates: 21.7\% (6.4) and 36.8\% (24.6) respectively, with economically larger estimates for total spending.]]></description><author>Jonathan A. Parker, Jake Schild, Laura Erhard, David Johnson</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29648</guid></item><item><title>The Moral Preferences of Investors: Experimental Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29647</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jean-François Bonnefon, Augustin Landier, Parinitha R. Sastry, David Thesmar.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We characterize investors’ moral preferences in a parsimonious experimental setting, where we auction stocks with various ethical features. We find strong evidence that investors seek to align their investments with their social values (“value alignment”), and find no evidence of behavior driven by the social impact of investment decisions (“impact-seeking preferences”). First, the willingness to pay for a stock is a linear function of corporate externalities, and is symmetric for positive or negative externalities. Second, whether charity transfers are contingent or independent on investors buying the auctioned stock does not affect their WTP. Our results are thus compatible with a utility model where non-pecuniary benefits of firms’ externalities only accrue through stock ownership, not through the actual impact of investment decisions. Finally, non-pecuniary preferences are linear and additive: willingness to pay for social externalities is proportional to the expected sum of charity transfers made by firms (even if some of these donations are negative).]]></description><author>Jean-François Bonnefon, Augustin Landier, Parinitha R. Sastry, David Thesmar</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29647</guid></item><item><title>Cognitive Decline, Limited Awareness, Imperfect Agency, and Financial Well-being</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29634</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John Ameriks, Andrew Caplin, Minjoon Lee, Matthew D. Shapiro, Christopher Tonetti.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Cognitive decline may lead older Americans to make poor financial decisions. Preventing poor decisions may require timely transfer of financial control to a reliable agent. Cognitive decline, however, can develop unnoticed, creating the possibility of suboptimal timing of the transfer of control. This paper presents survey-based evidence that wealthholders regard suboptimal timing of the transfer of control, in particular delay due to unnoticed cognitive decline, as a substantial risk to financial well-being. This paper provides a theoretical framework to model such a lack of awareness and the resulting welfare loss.]]></description><author>John Ameriks, Andrew Caplin, Minjoon Lee, Matthew D. Shapiro, Christopher Tonetti</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29634</guid></item><item><title>What Drives Variation in Investor Portfolios? Evidence from Retirement Plans</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29604</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Mark L. Egan, Alexander MacKay, Hanbin Yang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study empirical patterns in investment behavior using a comprehensive data set of defined contribution plans. Using plan-level portfolio allocation data for the near universe of 401(k) plans over the period 2009-2019, we document substantial differences in investment behavior across plans. Plans with wealthier and more educated participants tend to have higher equity exposure while plans with more retirees and minorities tend to have lower equity exposure. These patterns cannot be explained by differences in 401(k) menus or participation costs. To help interpret these facts, we use a revealed preference approach to estimate investors' expectations of stock market returns and risk aversion, where we allow investors to have heterogeneous risk aversion and subjective and potentially biased beliefs. We find that there is substantial variation in both beliefs and risk aversion across investors and over time, and that both sources of variation help explain investors' portfolio decisions. We also provide new evidence to understand how investors form beliefs. We find that investors extrapolate beliefs from past fund returns even when they initially allocate portfolios in new plans. We also find that investors extrapolate beliefs about the market from the past performance of their employer, which suggests that investor experience helps shape beliefs.]]></description><author>Mark L. Egan, Alexander MacKay, Hanbin Yang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29604</guid></item><item><title>Cognitive Uncertainty in Intertemporal Choice</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29577</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin Enke, Thomas Graeber.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the relevance of cognitive uncertainty – subjective uncertainty over one's utility-maximizing action – for understanding and predicting intertemporal choice. The main idea is that when people are cognitively noisy, such as when a decision is complex, they implicitly treat different time delays to some degree alike. By experimentally measuring and manipulating cognitive uncertainty, we document  three economic implications of this idea. First,  cognitive uncertainty explains various core empirical regularities, such as why people often appear very impatient, why per-period impatience is smaller over long than over short horizons, why discounting is often hyperbolic even when the present is not involved, and why choices frequently violate transitivity. Second, impatience is context-dependent: discounting is substantially more hyperbolic when the decision environment is more complex. Third, cognitive uncertainty matters for choice architecture: people who are nervous about making mistakes are twice as likely to follow expert advice to be more patient.]]></description><author>Benjamin Enke, Thomas Graeber</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29577</guid></item><item><title>Is Digital Credit Filling a Hole or Digging a Hole? Evidence from Malawi</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29573</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Valentina Brailovskaya, Pascaline Dupas, Jonathan Robinson.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Digital credit has expanded rapidly in Africa, mostly in the form of short-term, high-interest loans offered via mobile money. Loan terms are often opaque and consumer financial literacy is low, providing opportunities for predatory lending. A regression discontinuity analysis shows no negative effect of access to digital loans on financial well-being, but the majority of borrowers fail to repay on time and incur high late fees. We randomize exposure to a short phone-based financial literacy intervention. The intervention improved knowledge and marginally improved loan repayment but increased loan demand, increasing overall default risk.]]></description><author>Valentina Brailovskaya, Pascaline Dupas, Jonathan Robinson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29573</guid></item><item><title>Randomization for Causality, Ethnography for Mechanisms: Illiquid Savings for Liquor in an Autarkic Society</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29566</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ricardo Godoy, Dean Karlan, Jonathan Zinman.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> What should researchers do when confronted with surprising results? Financial access innovations usually leave “temptation” spending unaffected or reduced. However, we found that promotion of savings lockboxes in a largely autarkic society increased alcohol consumption and blood pressure, despite no one reporting intentions to save for alcohol. To probe mechanisms that could explain this pattern, we then used ethnographic methods, including direct observations of drinking (“scans”) and debriefing interviews to discuss the earlier trial results. We learn that sponsoring drinks confers prestige, but the stigma attached to drinking by outsiders likely discouraged reporting intentions to save for it.]]></description><author>Ricardo Godoy, Dean Karlan, Jonathan Zinman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29566</guid></item><item><title>Simple Allocation Rules and Optimal Portfolio Choice Over the Lifecycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29559</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Victor Duarte, Julia Fonseca, Aaron S. Goodman, Jonathan A. Parker.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We develop a machine-learning solution algorithm to solve for optimal portfolio choice in a detailed and quantitatively-accurate lifecycle model that includes many features of reality modelled only separately in previous work.  We use the quantitative model to evaluate the consumption-equivalent welfare losses from using simple rules for portfolio allocation across stocks, bonds, and liquid accounts instead of the optimal portfolio choices. We find that the consumption-equivalent losses from using an age-dependent rule as embedded in current target-date/lifecycle funds (TDFs) are substantial, around 2 to 3 percent of consumption, despite the fact that TDF rules mimic average optimal behavior by age closely until shortly before retirement. Our model recommends higher average equity shares in the second half of life than the portfolio of the typical TDF, so that the typical TDF portfolio does not improve on investing an age-independent 2/3 share in equity. Finally, optimal equity shares have substantial heterogeneity, particularly by wealth level, state of the business cycle, and dividend-price ratio, implying substantial gains to further customization of advice or TDFs in these dimensions.]]></description><author>Victor Duarte, Julia Fonseca, Aaron S. Goodman, Jonathan A. Parker</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29559</guid></item><item><title>Unlocking the Benefits of Credit through Saving</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29542</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sanghamitra W. Mukherjee, Lauren F. Bergquist, Marshall Burke, Edward Miguel.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Access to microcredit has been shown to generate only modest average benefits for recipient households. We study whether other financial market frictions—in particular, lack of access to a safe place to save—might limit credit's benefits. Working with Kenyan farmers, we cross-randomize access to a simple savings product with a harvest-time loan. Among farmers offered a loan, the additional offer of a savings lockbox increased farm investment by 11% and household consumption by 7%. Results suggest that financial market frictions can interact in important ways and that multifaceted financial access programs might unlock dynamic household gains.]]></description><author>Sanghamitra W. Mukherjee, Lauren F. Bergquist, Marshall Burke, Edward Miguel</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29542</guid></item><item><title>The Cost of Consumer Collateral: Evidence from Bunching</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29527</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin L. Collier, Cameron Ellis, Benjamin J. Keys.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We show that borrowers are highly sensitive to the requirement of posting their homes as collateral. Using administrative loan application and performance data from the U.S. Federal Disaster Loan Program, we exploit a loan amount threshold above which households must post their residence as collateral. One-third of all borrowers select the maximum uncollateralized loan amount, and our bunching estimates suggest that the median borrower is willing to give up 40% of their loan amount to avoid collateral. Exploiting time variation in the loan amount threshold, we find that collateral causally reduces default rates by 35%. Our results help to explain high perceived default costs in the mortgage market, and uniquely quantify the extent to which collateral reduces moral hazard in consumer credit markets.]]></description><author>Benjamin L. Collier, Cameron Ellis, Benjamin J. Keys</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29527</guid></item><item><title>FinTech as a Financial Liberator</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Greg Buchak, Jiayin Hu, Shang-Jin Wei.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> A binding interest rate cap on household savings is a common form of financial repression in developing economies and typically benefits banks. Using proprietary data from a leading Chinese FinTech company, we study Fintech's role in ending financial repression in China through the introduction of a money market fund with deposit-like features available through an already widely-adopted household payment platform.  Cities and banks whose depositor base is more exposed to FinTech see greater deposit outflows. Importantly, exposed banks respond to FinTech competition by offering competing products with market interest rates. FinTech thus facilitates a bottom-up interest rate liberalization.]]></description><author>Greg Buchak, Jiayin Hu, Shang-Jin Wei</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</guid></item><item><title>A Temporary VAT Cut as Unconventional Fiscal Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We exploit the unexpected announcement of an immediate, temporary VAT cut in Germany in the second half of 2020 as a natural experiment to study the spending response to unconventional fiscal policy. We use survey and scanner data on households’ consumption expenditures and their perceived pass-through of the tax change into prices to quantify its effects. The temporary VAT cut led to a substantial relative increase in durable spending of 36% for individuals with a high perceived pass-through. Semi- and non-durable spending also increased. According to our preferred estimates, the VAT policy increased aggregate consumption spending by 34 billion Euros.]]></description><author>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</guid></item><item><title>A Child Support Framework Accounting for Parenting Time and Half-Siblings</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29411</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Kulldorff, Jay Bhattacharya.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In the United States, child support guidelines sometimes generate surprising and presumably unintentional child support amounts, especially in situations with extended visitation, shared parenting, and half-siblings. These are consequences of the ad-hoc mathematical formulas that are in common use to account for such situations. This paper provides ten such surprising examples from ten randomly selected states.<br />
A child support calculation framework is constructed that takes as inputs the subjective/normative decisions that the public and legislators must make regarding children's expenditures, the progressivity of the contributions between parents, and other matters. Our goal is to derive mathematical formulas for child support amounts that achieve those normative goals while satisfying basic desiderata such as supporting children in both of their families, equity between siblings, neutral medical decisions, and not requiring higher contributions from parents with a lower salary.]]></description><author>Martin Kulldorff, Jay Bhattacharya</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29411</guid></item><item><title>Mental Health Therapy as a Core Strategy for Increasing Human Capital: Evidence from Ghana</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the impact of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) for individuals selected from the general population of poor households in rural Ghana. Results from 2-3 months after a randomized intervention show strong impacts on mental and physical health, cognitive and socioemotional skills, and downstream economic outcomes. We find no evidence of heterogeneity by baseline mental distress; we argue that this is because CBT can improve human capital for a general population of poor individuals through two pathways. First, CBT reduces vulnerability to deteriorating mental health; and second, CBT directly improves bandwidth, increasing cognitive and socioemotional skills and hence economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Burden of Pension Shortfalls: Evidence from House Prices</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> U.S. state pensions are underfunded by trillions of dollars, but their economic burden is unclear. In a model of inefficient taxation, real estate fully reflects the cost of pension shortfalls when it is the only form of immobile capital. We study the effect of pension shortfalls on real estate values at state borders, where labor and physical capital could more easily relocate to a state with a smaller shortfall. Using plausibly exogenous variation driven by pension asset returns, we find that one dollar of pension underfunding reduces house prices near state borders by approximately two dollars. Our estimates imply a deadweight loss associated with addressing pension shortfalls that is consistent with prior research in settings with high returns to public spending and costs of taxation.]]></description><author>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</guid></item><item><title>Inflation, Interest, and the Secular Rise in Wealth Inequality in the U.S.: Is the Fed Responsible?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29392</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Edward N. Wolff.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Two hallmarks of U.S. monetary policy since the 1981-1982 recession have been declining interest rates and moderation in inflation. Coincident with these trends has been a surge in U.S. wealth inequality, with the Gini coefficient up by 0.070 between 1983 and 2019. This paper analyzes the connection between these two developments on the basis of the Survey of Consumer Finances. Contrary to expectations, the paper finds that these two monetary effects have reduced wealth inequality rather than increasing it. The effect is sizeable, with the Gini coefficient declining by 0.045 over these years. Asset price changes and debt devaluation accounted for 72.6 percent of the advance of mean wealth over 1983-2019. They also would have led to a 204.9 percent gain in median wealth, compared to the actual rise of 23.4 percent. Moreover, they have helped lower the racial wealth gap rather than enlarging it. These results are at odds with previous literature in which estimates range from a weak negative effect on inequality to neutral, small positive, and strong positive. In terms of methodology, this paper differs from previous work by focusing on only the direct effects of interest rate changes and inflation on the household balance sheet.]]></description><author>Edward N. Wolff</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29392</guid></item><item><title>Household Credit as Stimulus? Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> From 2011 to 2014, the Brazilian government conducted a heavily advertised major credit expansion program through government banks as part of its effort to stimulate the economy. Using administrative data on individual-level borrowing and spending, we find that the program led to a substantial rise in borrowing by government employees, especially those with low financial literacy. We trace the impact of credit stimulus on borrowers' consumption through the 2011-16 business cycle, and find that the credit stimulus resulted in higher consumption volatility and lower average consumption over the cycle. Our results suggest a potential downside of using household credit as stimulus in emerging markets.]]></description><author>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</guid></item><item><title>Top Wealth in America: New Estimates and Implications for Taxing the Rich</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29374</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Matthew Smith, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses administrative tax data to estimate top wealth in the United States. We assemble new data that links people to their sources of capital income and develop new methods to estimate the degree of return heterogeneity within asset classes. Disaggregated fixed income data reveal that rich individuals earn much more of their interest income in higher-yielding forms, and have much greater exposure to credit risk. Consequently, in recent years, the interest rate on fixed income at the top is approximately three times higher than the average. Using firm-level characteristics to value firms, we find that twenty percent of total pass-through business wealth accrues to those with losses. We combine this new data on fixed income and pass-through business returns with refined estimates of C-corporation equity, housing, and pension wealth to deliver new capitalized wealth estimates. Our approach---which builds on Saez and Zucman (2016) and Bricker, Henriques, and Hansen (2018)---reduces bias because wealth and rates of return are correlated. From 1989 to 2016, the top 1%, 0.1%, and 0.01% wealth shares increased by 7.6, 5.1, and 3.0 percentage points, respectively, to 31.5%, 15.0%, and 7.0%. While these changes are less dramatic than some prior estimates, wealth is very concentrated: the top 1% holds nearly as much wealth as either the bottom 90% or the "P90-99" class. We discuss implications for income inequality measures, capital tax policy, and savings behavior.]]></description><author>Matthew Smith, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29374</guid></item><item><title>Exposure, Experience, and Expertise: Why Personal Histories Matter in Economics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ulrike Malmendier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Personal experiences of economic outcomes, from global financial crises to individual-level job losses, can shape individual beliefs, risk attitudes, and choices for years to come. A growing literature on experience effects shows that individuals act as if past outcomes that they experienced were overly likely to occur again, even if they are fully informed about the actual likelihood. This reaction to past experiences is long-lasting though it decays over time as individuals accumulate new experiences. Modern brain science helps understand these processes. Evidence on neuroplasticity reveals that personal experiences and learning alter the strength of neural connections and fine-tune the brain structure to those past experiences ("use-dependent brain"). I show that experience effects help understand belief formation and decision-making in a wide area of economic applications, including inflation, home purchases, mortgage choices, and consumption expenditures. I argue that experience-based learning is broadly applicable to economic decision-making and discuss topics for future research in education, health, race, and gender economics.]]></description><author>Ulrike Malmendier</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</guid></item><item><title>Big Loans to Small Businesses: Predicting Winners and Losers in an Entrepreneurial Lending Experiment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We experimentally study the impact of substantially larger enterprise loans, in collaboration with an Egyptian lender. Larger loans generate small average impacts, but machine learning using psychometric data reveals dramatic heterogeneity. Top-performers (i.e., those with the highest predicted treatment effects) substantially increase profits, whereas profits for poor-performers drop. The magnitude of this difference implies that an individual lender’s credit allocation choices matter for aggregate income. Evidence on two fronts suggests large loans would be misallocated: top-performers are predicted by loan officers to have higher default rates; and, top-performers grow less than others when given small loans, implying that allocating larger loans based on prior performance is not efficient. Our results have important implications for credit expansion policy and our understanding of entrepreneurial talent: on the former, the use of psychometric data to identify top-performers suggests a pathway towards better allocation that revolves around entrepreneurial type more than firm type; on the latter, the reversal of fortune for poor-performers, who do well with small loans but not large, indicates a type of entrepreneur that we call a “go-getter” who performs well when constrained but poorly when not.]]></description><author>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Housing Returns</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29306</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Amir Kermani, Francis Wong.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We document the existence of a racial gap in realized housing returns that is an order of magnitude larger than disparities arising from housing costs alone, and is driven almost entirely by differences in distressed home sales (i.e. foreclosures and short sales). Black and Hispanic homeowners are both more likely to experience a distressed sale and to live in neighborhoods where distressed sales erase more house value. Importantly, absent financial distress, houses owned by minorities do not appreciate at slower rates than houses owned by non-minorities. Racial differences in income stability and liquid wealth explain a large share of the differences in distress. We use quasi-experimental variation in loan modifications to show that policies that restructure mortgages for distressed minorities can increase housing returns and reduce the racial wealth gap.]]></description><author>Amir Kermani, Francis Wong</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29306</guid></item><item><title>Human Frictions in the Transmission of Economic Policies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Many consumers below the top of the distribution of a representative population by cognitive abilities barely react to  monetary and fiscal policies that aim to stimulate consumption and borrowing, even when they are financially unconstrained and despite substantial debt capacity. Differences in income, formal education levels, economic expectations, and a large set of registry-based demographics do not explain these facts. Heterogeneous cognitive abilities thus act as human frictions in the transmission of economic policies that operate through the household sector and might imply  redistribution from low- to high-cognitive-ability agents. We conclude by discussing how our findings inform the microfoundation of behavioral macroeconomic theory.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</guid></item><item><title>Diverse Policy Committees Can Reach Underrepresented Groups</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Francesco D’Acunto, Andreas Fuster, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Increasing the diversity of policy committees has taken center stage worldwide, but whether and why diverse committees are more effective is still unclear. In a randomized control trial that varies the salience of female and minority representation on the Federal Reserve’s monetary policy committee, the FOMC, we test whether diversity affects how Fed information influences consumers’ subjective beliefs. Women and Black respondents form unemployment expectations more in line with FOMC forecasts and trust the Fed more after this intervention. Women are also more likely to acquire Fed-related information when associated with a female official. White men, who are overrepresented on the FOMC, do not react negatively. Heterogeneous taste for diversity can explain these patterns better than homophily. Our results suggest more diverse policy committees are better able to reach underrepresented groups without inducing negative reactions by others, thereby enhancing the effectiveness of policy communication and public trust in the institution.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Andreas Fuster, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</guid></item><item><title>Measuring the Welfare Cost of Asymmetric Information in Consumer Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Information asymmetries are known in theory to lead to inefficiently low credit provision, yet empirical estimates of the resulting welfare losses are scarce. This paper leverages a randomized experiment conducted by a large fintech lender to estimate welfare losses arising from asymmetric information in the market for online consumer credit. Building on methods from the insurance literature, we show how exogenous variation in interest rates can be used to estimate borrower demand and lender cost curves and recover implied welfare losses. While asymmetric information generates large equilibrium price distortions, we find only small overall welfare losses, particularly for high-credit-score borrowers.]]></description><author>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</guid></item><item><title>Signaling in Online Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29268</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kei Kawai, Ken Onishi, Kosuke Uetake.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study how signaling affects equilibrium outcomes and welfare in an online credit market using detailed data on loan characteristics and borrower repayment. We build and estimate an equilibrium model in which a borrower may signal her default risk through the reserve interest rate. Comparing a market with and without signaling relative to the benchmark with no asymmetric information, we find that adverse selection destroys as much as 34% of total surplus, up to 78% of which can be restored with signaling. We also estimate backward-bending supply curves for some markets, consistent with the prediction of Stiglitz &amp; Weiss (1981).]]></description><author>Kei Kawai, Ken Onishi, Kosuke Uetake</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29268</guid></item></channel></rss>