<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: International Factor Mobility</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: International Factor Mobility</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 18:10:34 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Sources and Transmission of Country Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29526</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tarek Alexander Hassan, Jesse Schreger, Markus Schwedeler, Ahmed Tahoun.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We use textual analysis of earnings conference calls held by listed firms around the world to measure the amount of risk managers and investors at each firm associate with each country at each point in time. Flexibly aggregating this firm-country-quarter-level data allows us to systematically identify spikes in perceived country risk (“crises”) and document their source and pattern of transmission to foreign firms. While this pattern usually follows a gravity structure, it often changes dramatically during crises. For example, while crises originating in developed countries propagate disproportionately to foreign financial firms, emerging market crises transmit less financially and more to traditionally exposed countries. We apply our measures to show that (i) elevated perceptions of a country's riskiness, particularly those of foreign and financial firms, are associated with significant falls in local asset prices, capital outflows, and reductions in firm-level investment and employment. (ii) Risk transmitted from foreign countries affects the investment decisions of domestic firms.  (iii) Heterogeneous currency loadings on perceived global risk can help explain the cross-country pattern of interest rates and currency risk premia.]]></description><author>Tarek Alexander Hassan, Jesse Schreger, Markus Schwedeler, Ahmed Tahoun</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29526</guid></item><item><title>Does Employing Skilled Immigrants Enhance Competitive Performance? Evidence from European Football Clubs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29446</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Britta Glennon, Francisco Morales, Seth Carnahan, Exequiel Hernandez.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the effect of hiring skilled immigrant employees on the performance of organizations. This relationship has been difficult to establish in prior work due to theoretical ambiguity, limited data, and inherent endogeneity. We overcome these difficulties by studying European football (soccer) clubs during 1990-2020. Detailed microdata from this setting offers unusual transparency on the migration and hiring of talent and their contribution to collective performance. Further, the industry is characterized by country-level rule changes that govern the number of immigrant players clubs can hire. Using these rule changes as the basis for instrumental variables, we find a positive local average treatment effect of the number of immigrant players on the club’s in-game performance. To examine the theoretical mechanisms, we explore whether immigrants cause superior performance because they are more talented than natives or because they enhance the national diversity of their clubs. We find strong evidence for the talent mechanism. We find contingent evidence for the national diversity mechanism: national diversity has a positive relationship with club performance only when the club employs an immigrant manager (coach). The presence of an immigrant manager also strengthens the positive relationship between the number of immigrant players and club performance.]]></description><author>Britta Glennon, Francisco Morales, Seth Carnahan, Exequiel Hernandez</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29446</guid></item><item><title>Risks and global supply chains: What we know and what we need to know</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29444</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Richard Baldwin, Rebecca Freeman.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Recent supply disruptions catapulted the issue of risk in global supply chains (GSCs) to the top of policy agendas and created the impression that shortages would have been less severe if GSCs were either shorter and more domestic, or more diversified. But is this right? We start our answer by reviewing studies that look at risks to and from GSCs, and how GSCs have recovered from past shocks. We then look at whether GSCs are too risky—starting with business research on how firms approach the cost-resiliency trade-off. We propose the risk-versus-reward framework from portfolio theory as a good way to evaluate whether anti-risk policy is justified. We then discuss how exposures to foreign shocks are measured and argue that exposure is higher than direct indicators imply. Finally, we consider the future of GSCs in the light of current policy proposals and advancing technology before pointing to the rich menu of topics for future research on the risk-GSC nexus.]]></description><author>Richard Baldwin, Rebecca Freeman</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29444</guid></item><item><title>The International Price of Remote Work</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29437</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Agostina Brinatti, Alberto Cavallo, Javier Cravino, Andres Drenik.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We use data from a large web-based job platform to study how the price of remote work is determined in a globalized labor market. In the platform, workers from around the world compete for jobs that can be done remotely. We document that, despite the global nature of the marketplace, the location of the worker accounts for over a third of the variance in wages. The observed wage differences are strongly correlated to the GDP per capita of the worker’s country. This correlation is not accounted for by differences in workers’ characteristics, occupations, nor for differences in the employers’ locations. We also document that remote wages in local currency move almost one-for-one with the dollar exchange rate of the worker’s country, and are highly sensitive to changes in the wages of foreign competitors. Finally, we provide a new measure on which jobs are easier to offshore that is based on the prevalence of cross-border contracts rather than on subjective job characteristics, and show that there is substantial heterogeneity in the offshorability of remote occupations.]]></description><author>Agostina Brinatti, Alberto Cavallo, Javier Cravino, Andres Drenik</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29437</guid></item><item><title>Nonlinearities and a Pecking Order in Cross-border Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29432</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sara B. Holland, Sergei Sarkissian, Michael Schill, Francis E. Warnock.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Nonlinearities arise in international investment because of a pecking order in barriers. Some severe barriers render all others meaningless, and only when they are alleviated do other barriers become important. We show, using quantile regressions designed to model relations at more points than just the conditional mean, how various investment theories hold at different points in the distribution of bilateral cross-border equity holdings. Our results reconcile a number of findings in the literature by highlighting that datasets that focus on different points of the barriers (investment) distribution can naturally lead to different results.]]></description><author>Sara B. Holland, Sergei Sarkissian, Michael Schill, Francis E. Warnock</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29432</guid></item><item><title>Immigration and Occupational Comparative Advantage</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29418</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gordon H. Hanson, Chen Liu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Job choice by high-skilled foreign-born workers in the US correlates strongly with country of origin. We apply a Fréchet-Roy model of occupational choice to evaluate the causes of immigrant sorting. In a gravity specification, we find that revealed comparative advantage in the US is stronger for workers from countries with higher education quality in occupations that are more intensive in cognitive reasoning, and for workers from countries that are more linguistically similar to the US in occupations that are more intensive in communication. Our findings hold for immigrants who arrived in the US at age 18 or older (who received their K-12 education abroad) but not for immigrants who arrived in the US as children (who received their K-12 education domestically). We obtain similar results for immigrant sorting in Canada, which supports our interpretation that origin-country education quality, rather than US immigration policy, is what drives sorting patterns. In counterfactual analysis, we evaluate the consequences of reallocating visas for college-educated immigrants according to origin-country education quality.]]></description><author>Gordon H. Hanson, Chen Liu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29418</guid></item><item><title>Licence to Dine: 007 and the Real Exchange Rate</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29415</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Lee A. Craig, Julianne Treme, Thomas J. Weiss.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We constructed a time series of menu prices for the identifiable restaurants at which James Bond dined in France and the UK that yields one of the few international price series representing luxury services. This series enabled us to calculate a real exchange rate based on prices pertinent to international travelers. We also compiled a time series on the salary of workers in the British Civil Service at Grade 7, like Bond, from 1953 to 2019. Our results indicate that French restaurant prices increased faster than Grade 7 salaries over the entire period and changes in the British exchange rate were not favorable for British travelers. To dine weekly in France, during the 1950s and 1960s, Bond would have spent 18 percent of his salary; whereas over the course of the Euro era the same basket of luxury services would have required on average 26 percent of his salary. Finally, our data indicate a likely violation of the law of one price during both the Pound-Franc and Pound-Euro eras.]]></description><author>Lee A. Craig, Julianne Treme, Thomas J. Weiss</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29415</guid></item><item><title>Decrypting New Age International Capital Flows</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29337</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clemens Graf von Luckner, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper employs high frequency transactions data on the world’s oldest and most extensive centralized peer-to-peer Bitcoin market, which enables trade in the currencies of more than 135 countries.  We develop an algorithm that allows, with high probability, the detection of “crypto vehicle transactions” in which crypto currency is used to move capital across borders or facilitate domestic transactions. In contrast to previous work which has used “on-chain” data, our approach enables one to investigate parts of the vastly larger pool of “off-chain” transactions. We find that, as a conservative lower bound, over 7 percent of the 45 million trades on the exchange we explore represent crypto vehicle transactions in which Bitcoin is used to make payment in fiat currency.  Roughly 20 percent of these represent international capital flight/flows/remittances.  Although our work cannot be used to put a price on cryptocurrencies, it provides the first systematic quantitative evidence that the transactional use of cryptocurrencies constitutes a fundamental component of their value, at least under the current regulatory regime.]]></description><author>Clemens Graf von Luckner, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29337</guid></item><item><title>Dynamics of Large Multinationals</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29317</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Elhanan Helpman, Benjamin C. Niswonger.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We develop a model of large multinational enterprises, each one producing a continuum of products. These outsized firms compete as oligopolists in a domestic and foreign market, facing competitive pressure from single-product firms that engage in monopolistic competition. The multinational enterprises invest in R&amp;D in order to expand the span of their products and in foreign direct investment (FDI) in order to expand the range of products manufactured by their foreign affiliates. We study the dynamic evolution of these markets and characterize transition dynamics and steady states. In addition to the evolution of product spans, we characterize the evolution of prices, markups, market shares, and exports relative to subsidiary sales. Furthermore, we study comparative dynamics that result from changes in trade costs, R&amp;D costs, the cost of FDI and productivity changes of the multinational firms.]]></description><author>Elhanan Helpman, Benjamin C. Niswonger</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29317</guid></item></channel></rss>