<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by programs: Corporate Finance</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by programs: Corporate Finance</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 20:54:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Share Pledging in China: Funding Listed Firms or Funding Entrepreneurship?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29731</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhiguo He, Bibo Liu, Feifei Zhu.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> This paper studies the connection between share pledging and entrepreneurial activities in China, challenging the common wisdom that share pledging funds circle back to the listed firms. Share pledging funds are at the discretion of the shareholders who pledge their publicly traded shares, and survey evidence shows that a majority of the largest shareholders (67.3%) used pledging funds outside the listed firms. By linking firm registration data with share pledging data, we show a positive relation between shareholders’ pledging transactions and entrepreneurial activities. Utilizing the launch of the exchange market in 2013 as a quasi-natural experiment that favors share pledging by natural person shareholders against that by legal entity shareholders, our difference-in-differences (DiD) analysis shows natural person shareholders increased their entrepreneurial activities significantly in response to the policy shock, relative to legal entity shareholders. In addition to various robustness checks, we also show that shareholders with better access to share pledging invest more heavily in industries with above-median growth potential.]]></description><author>Zhiguo He, Bibo Liu, Feifei Zhu</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29731</guid></item><item><title>Decentralization Through Tokenization</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29720</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Sockin, Wei Xiong.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We examine decentralization of digital platforms through tokenization as an innovation to resolve the conflict between platforms and users. By delegating control to users, tokenization through utility tokens acts as a commitment device that prevents a platform from exploiting users. This commitment comes at the cost of not having an owner with an equity stake who, in conventional platforms, would subsidize participation to maximize the platform's network effect. This trade-off makes utility tokens a more appealing funding scheme than equity for platforms with weak fundamentals. The conflict reappears when non-users, such as token investors and validators, participate on the platform.]]></description><author>Michael Sockin, Wei Xiong</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29720</guid></item><item><title>Waiting for Capital: Dynamic Intermediation in Illiquid Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29712</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Barney Hartman-Glaser, Simon Mayer, Konstantin Milbradt.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We consider a firm with infrequent access to capital markets, continuous access to financing by a risk-averse intermediary, and a cost of holding cash. The intermediary absorbs a fraction of cash-flow risk that decreases with the firm’s liquidity reserves and acquires a stake in the firm under distress. Implementing the optimal contract suggests an overlapping pecking order. The firm simultaneously finances shortfalls with cash reserves and a credit line and sells equity to the intermediary when it runs out of cash. The model helps explain empirical facts and trends in financial intermediation, such as the rise of private equity.]]></description><author>Barney Hartman-Glaser, Simon Mayer, Konstantin Milbradt</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29712</guid></item><item><title>Making Money</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29710</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gary B. Gorton, Chase P. Ross, Sharon Y. Ross.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> It is difficult for private agents to produce money that circulates at par with no questions asked. We study two cases of privately-produced money: pre-Civil War U.S. private banknotes and modern stablecoins. Private monies are introduced when there are no better alternatives, but they initially carry an inconvenience yield. Over time, these monies may become more money-like, but they do not always achieve a positive convenience yield. Technology advances and reputation formation pushed private banknotes toward a positive convenience yield. We show that the same forces are at work for stablecoins.]]></description><author>Gary B. Gorton, Chase P. Ross, Sharon Y. Ross</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29710</guid></item><item><title>Why Are Returns to Private Business Wealth So Dispersed?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29705</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Corina Boar, Denis Gorea, Virgiliu Midrigan.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We  use micro data from Orbis on firm level balance sheets and income statements to document that accounting returns for privately held businesses are dispersed, persistent, and negatively correlated with firm equity. We also show that firms experience large, fat-tailed, and partly transitory changes in output that are not fully accompanied by changes in their capital stock and wage bill. This implies that capital and labor choices are risky, as fluctuations in output are accompanied by large changes in firm profits. We interpret this evidence using a model of entrepreneurial dynamics in which return heterogeneity can arise from both limited span of control, as well as from financial frictions which generate differences in financial returns to saving. The model matches the evidence on accounting returns  and predicts that financial returns to saving are half as large and dispersed as accounting returns. Financial returns mostly reflect risk, as opposed to collateral constraints which play a negligible role due to  firms' unwillingness to expand and take on more risk.]]></description><author>Corina Boar, Denis Gorea, Virgiliu Midrigan</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29705</guid></item><item><title>Two-Way Fixed Effects and Differences-in-Differences with Heterogeneous Treatment Effects: A Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29691</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&#039;Haultfoeuille.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Linear regressions with period and group fixed effects are widely used to estimate policies' effects: 26 of the 100 most cited papers published by the American Economic Review from 2015 to 2019 estimate such regressions. It has recently been show that those regressions may produce misleading estimates, if the policy's effect is heterogeneous between groups or over time, as is often the case. This survey reviews a fast-growing literature that documents this issue, and that proposes alternative estimators robust to heterogeneous effects.]]></description><author>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&amp;#039;Haultfoeuille</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29691</guid></item><item><title>Liquidity, Liquidity Everywhere, Not a Drop to Use - Why Flooding Banks with Central Bank Reserves May Not Expand Liquidity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29680</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Viral V. Acharya, Raghuram Rajan.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Central bank balance sheet expansion is financed by commercial banks. It involves not just a substitution of liquid central bank reserves for other assets held by commercial banks, but also a counterpart alteration in commercial bank liabilities, such as in short-term deposits issued to finance reserves and in off-balance-sheet encumbrances pledged against reserves, which are also claims on liquidity. In ordinary times, when these claims are not called on, central bank balance sheet expansion will typically enhance the net availability of liquidity to the system. However, in times of stress when these offsetting claims on liquidity are exercised, the demand for liquidity can be significantly more. Furthermore, liquid commercial banks, desiring to maintain unimpeachable balance sheets, may provide only limited re-intermediation of liquidity and contribute significantly to liquidity shortages. Commercial banks do not fully internalize prospective stress ex ante or take sufficient steps to avoid it. Consequently, central bank balance sheet expansion need not eliminate episodes of stress; it may even exacerbate them. This may also attenuate any positive effects of central bank balance sheet expansion on economic activity.]]></description><author>Viral V. Acharya, Raghuram Rajan</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29680</guid></item><item><title>Understanding the Ownership Structure of Corporate Bonds</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29679</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ralph S. J. Koijen, Motohiro Yogo.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Insurers are the largest institutional investors of corporate bonds. However, a standard theory of insurance markets, in which insurers maximize firm value subject to regulatory or risk constraints, predicts no allocation to corporate bonds. We resolve this puzzle in an equilibrium asset pricing model with leverage-constrained households and institutional investors. Insurers have relatively cheap access to leverage through their underwriting activity. They hold a leveraged portfolio of low-beta assets in equilibrium, relaxing other investors' leverage constraints. The model explains recent empirical findings on insurers' portfolio choice and its impact on asset prices.]]></description><author>Ralph S. J. Koijen, Motohiro Yogo</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29679</guid></item><item><title>Robots and Firm Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29676</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Efraim Benmelech, Michal Zator.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Automation technologies, and robots in particular, are thought to be massively displacing workers and transforming the future of work. We study firm investment in automation using cross-country data on robotization as well as administrative data from Germany with information on firm-level automation decisions. Our findings suggest that the impact of robots on firms has been limited. First, investment in robots is small and highly concentrated in a few industries, accounting for less than 0.30% of aggregate expenditures on equipment. Second, recent increases in robotization do not resemble the explosive growth observed for IT technologies in the past, and are driven mostly by catching-up of developing countries. Third, robot adoption by firms endogenously responds to labor scarcity, alleviating potential displacement of existing workers. Fourth, firms that invest in robots increase employment, while total employment effect in exposed industries and regions is negative, but modest in magnitude. We contrast robots with other digital technologies that are more widespread. Their importance in firms’ investment is significantly higher, and their link with labor markets, while sharing some similarities with robots, appears markedly different.]]></description><author>Efraim Benmelech, Michal Zator</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29676</guid></item><item><title>A New Era of Midnight Mergers: Antitrust Risk and Investor Disclosures</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29655</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John M. Barrios, Thomas G. Wollmann.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Antitrust authorities search public documents to discover anticompetitive mergers. Thus, investor disclosures may alert them to deals that would otherwise escape scrutiny, creating disincentives for managers to divulge transactions. We study this behavior in publicly traded US companies. First, we estimate a regression discontinuity that exploits mandatory disclosure thresholds stipulated by securities law. We find that releasing information to investors poses antitrust risk. Second, we present a method for measuring undisclosed merger activity that relies on financial accounting reporting requirements. We find that undisclosed mergers total $2.3 trillion between 2002 and 2016.]]></description><author>John M. Barrios, Thomas G. Wollmann</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29655</guid></item><item><title>Inclusive Monetary Policy: How Tight Labor Markets Facilitate Broad-Based Employment Growth</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29651</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nittai Bergman, David A. Matsa, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper analyzes the heterogeneous effects of monetary policy on workers with differing levels of labor force attachment. Exploiting variation in labor market tightness across metropolitan areas, we show that the employment of populations with lower labor force attachment—Blacks, high school dropouts, and women—is more responsive to expansionary monetary policy in tighter labor markets. The effect builds up over time and is long lasting. We develop a New Keynesian model with heterogeneous workers that rationalizes these results. The model shows that expansionary monetary shocks lead to larger increases in the employment of less attached workers when the central bank follows an average inflation targeting rule and when the Phillips curve is flatter. These findings suggest that, by tightening labor markets, the Federal Reserve's recent move from a strict to an average inflation targeting framework especially benefits workers with lower labor force attachment.]]></description><author>Nittai Bergman, David A. Matsa, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29651</guid></item><item><title>Household Spending Responses to the Economic Impact Payments of 2020: Evidence from the Consumer Expenditure Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29648</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan A. Parker, Jake Schild, Laura Erhard, David Johnson.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Using the Consumer Expenditure Survey and variation in amount, receipt, and timing of receipt of Economic Impact Payments (EIPs) authorized by the CARES Act, this paper estimates that people spent less of their EIPs in the few months following arrival than in similar previous policy episodes and than estimated by existing studies using other types of data. Accounting for volatility during the pandemic and comparing the consumer spending behavior of broadly similar households, people spent roughly 10 percent (standard error 3.4) of their EIPs on non-durable goods and services in the three months of arrival, with little evidence of additional spending in the subsequent three months or on  durable goods. People who report mostly spending their EIPs spent 14.3\% (3.7) of their EIPs compared to 5.9\% (8.3) and -1.6\% (5.0) for those who report mostly paying off debt and saving respectively. People with low liquid wealth and people receiving their EIPs on debit cards spent at higher rates: 21.7\% (6.4) and 36.8\% (24.6) respectively, with economically larger estimates for total spending.]]></description><author>Jonathan A. Parker, Jake Schild, Laura Erhard, David Johnson</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29648</guid></item><item><title>The Moral Preferences of Investors: Experimental Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29647</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jean-François Bonnefon, Augustin Landier, Parinitha R. Sastry, David Thesmar.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We characterize investors’ moral preferences in a parsimonious experimental setting, where we auction stocks with various ethical features. We find strong evidence that investors seek to align their investments with their social values (“value alignment”), and find no evidence of behavior driven by the social impact of investment decisions (“impact-seeking preferences”). First, the willingness to pay for a stock is a linear function of corporate externalities, and is symmetric for positive or negative externalities. Second, whether charity transfers are contingent or independent on investors buying the auctioned stock does not affect their WTP. Our results are thus compatible with a utility model where non-pecuniary benefits of firms’ externalities only accrue through stock ownership, not through the actual impact of investment decisions. Finally, non-pecuniary preferences are linear and additive: willingness to pay for social externalities is proportional to the expected sum of charity transfers made by firms (even if some of these donations are negative).]]></description><author>Jean-François Bonnefon, Augustin Landier, Parinitha R. Sastry, David Thesmar</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29647</guid></item><item><title>Financial Intermediaries and the Macroeconomy: Evidence from a High-Frequency Identification</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29638</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pablo Ottonello, Wenting Song.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We provide empirical evidence of the causal effects of changes in financial intermediaries' net worth in the aggregate economy. Our strategy identifies financial shocks as high-frequency changes in the market value of intermediaries' net worth in a narrow window around their earnings announcements, based on U.S. tick-by-tick data. Using these shocks, we estimate that news of a 1-percent decline in intermediaries' net worth leads to a 0.2-0.4 percent decrease in the market value of nonfinancial firms.  These effects are more pronounced for firms with high default risk and low liquidity and when the aggregate net worth of intermediaries is low.]]></description><author>Pablo Ottonello, Wenting Song</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29638</guid></item><item><title>Information versus Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29636</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stephen J. Terry, Toni M. Whited, Anastasia A. Zakolyukina.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We quantify the real implications of trade-offs between firm information disclosure and long-term investment efficiency. We estimate a dynamic equilibrium model in which firm managers confront realistic incentives to misreport earnings and distort their real investment choices. The model implies a socially optimal level of disclosure regulation that exceeds the estimated value. Counterfactual analysis reveals that eliminating earnings misreporting completely through disclosure regulation incentivizes managers to distort real investment. Lower earnings informativeness raises the cost of capital, which results in a 5.7% drop in average firm value, but more modest effects on social welfare and aggregate growth.]]></description><author>Stephen J. Terry, Toni M. Whited, Anastasia A. Zakolyukina</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29636</guid></item><item><title>Intermediation via Credit Chains</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29632</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhiguo He, Jian Li.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The modern financial system features complicated financial intermediation chains, with each layer performing a certain degree of credit/maturity transformation. We develop a dynamic model in which an entrepreneur borrows from overlapping-generation households via layers of funds, forming a credit chain. Each intermediary fund in the chain faces rollover risks from its lenders, and the optimal debt contracts among layers are time invariant and layer independent. The model delivers new insights regarding the benefits of intermediation via layers: the chain structure insulates interim negative fundamental shocks and protects the underlying cash flows from being discounted heavily during bad times, resulting in a greater borrowing capacity. We show that the equilibrium chain length minimizes the run risk for any given contract and find that restricting credit chain length can improve total welfare once the available funding from households has been endogenized.]]></description><author>Zhiguo He, Jian Li</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29632</guid></item><item><title>Revealing Corruption: Firm and Worker Level Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29627</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Emanuele Colonnelli, Spyridon Lagaras, Jacopo Ponticelli, Mounu Prem, Margarita Tsoutsoura.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We study how the disclosure of corrupt practices affects the growth of firms involved in illegal interactions with the government using randomized audits of public procurement in Brazil. On average, firms exposed by the anti-corruption program grow larger after the audits, despite experiencing a decrease in procurement contracts. We manually collect new data on the details of thousands of corruption cases, through which we uncover a large heterogeneity in our firm-level effects depending on the degree of involvement in corruption cases. Using investment-, loan-, and worker- level data, we show that the average exposed firms adapt to the loss of government contracts by changing their investment strategy. They increase capital investment and borrow more to finance such investment, while there is no change in their internal organization.  We provide qualitative support to our results by conducting new face-to-face surveys with business owners of government-dependent firms.]]></description><author>Emanuele Colonnelli, Spyridon Lagaras, Jacopo Ponticelli, Mounu Prem, Margarita Tsoutsoura</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29627</guid></item><item><title>The Political Economy of Anti-Bribery Enforcement</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29624</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Lauren Cohen, Bo Li.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper documents novel evidence on the influence of political incentives in the regulatory enforcement of foreign bribery. Using exogenous variation in the timing and geographic location of U.S. Congressional elections, we find that the probability of a Foreign Corrupt Practices Act (FCPA) enforcement action against foreign firms located in the Senator’s jurisdiction increases significantly pre-election, spiking 23%, with zero equivalent move for equivalently global (but domestic-headquartered) firms in the Senator’s jurisdiction. Using hand-collected case-level data from the U.S. SEC and DOJ, we also observe larger discretion in regions where foreign firms are larger global competitors of in-state firms, operate in locally important industries, and when Senators serve as the Chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee (which oversees the DOJ). Anti-bribery enforcement has electoral implications, leading to spikes in media coverage of the FCPA enforcement coupled with greater vote shares for the Senator. Moreover, the cases pushed through against these foreign firms just prior to elections appear to be weaker cases. The enforcements result in real effects, as in response to strategic timing in enforcement, firms reallocate business segments and sales.]]></description><author>Lauren Cohen, Bo Li</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29624</guid></item><item><title>Interest Received by Banks during the Financial Crisis: LIBOR vs Hypothetical SOFR Loans</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29614</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Urban Jermann.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The credit sensitivity of LIBOR helped lenders during the financial crisis. SOFR is not credit-sensitive and would not have provided that support. The cumulative additional interest from LIBOR during the crisis is estimated to be between 1% to 2% of the notional amount of outstanding loans, depending on the tenor and type of SOFR rate used. The amount of LIBOR business loans owned by banks could have been as high as about 2trn, and the overall additional interest income banks received thanks to LIBOR could have been as high as 30bn dollars. The analysis also shows that a compounded SOFR reduces insurance relative to a term SOFR.]]></description><author>Urban Jermann</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29614</guid></item><item><title>Innovation Networks and Innovation Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29607</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ernest Liu, Song Ma.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study the optimal allocation of R&amp;D resources in an endogenous growth model with an innovation network, through which one sector’s past innovations may benefit other sectors’ future innovations. First, we provide closed-form sufficient statistics for the optimal path of R&amp;D resource allocation, and we show that planners valuing long-term growth should allocate more R&amp;D toward key sectors that are upstream in the innovation network. Second, we extend to an open-economy setting and illustrate an incentive for countries to free-ride on fundamental technologies: an economy more reliant on foreign knowledge spillovers has less incentive to direct resources toward innovation-upstream sectors, leading to cross-country differences in unilaterally optimal R&amp;D allocations across sectors. Third, we build the global innovation network based on over 30 million global patents and establish its empirical importance for knowledge spillovers. Fourth, we apply the model to evaluate R&amp;D allocations across countries and time. Adopting optimal R&amp;D allocations can generate substantial welfare improvements across the globe. For the United States, R&amp;D misallocation accounts for about 0.68 percentage points of missing annual growth since the 2000s.]]></description><author>Ernest Liu, Song Ma</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29607</guid></item><item><title>Zombie Lending and Policy Traps</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29606</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Viral V. Acharya, Simone Lenzu, Olivier Wang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We build a model with heterogeneous firms and banks to analyze how policy affects credit allocation and long-term economic outcomes. When firms are hit by small negative shocks, conventional monetary policy can restore efficient bank lending and production by lowering interest rates. Large shocks, however, necessitate unconventional policy such as regulatory forbearance towards banks to stabilize the economy. Aggressive accommodation runs the risk of introducing zombie lending and a “diabolical sorting”, whereby low-capitalization banks extend new credit or evergreen existing loans to low-productivity firms. If shocks reduce the profitability gap between healthy and zombie firms, the optimal forbearance policy is non-monotone in the size of the shock. In a dynamic setting, policy aimed at avoiding short-term recessions can be trapped into protracted low rates and excessive forbearance, due to congestion externalities imposed by zombie lending on healthier firms. The resulting economic sclerosis delays the recovery from transitory shocks, and can even lead to permanent output losses.]]></description><author>Viral V. Acharya, Simone Lenzu, Olivier Wang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29606</guid></item><item><title>What Drives Variation in Investor Portfolios? Evidence from Retirement Plans</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29604</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Mark L. Egan, Alexander MacKay, Hanbin Yang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study empirical patterns in investment behavior using a comprehensive data set of defined contribution plans. Using plan-level portfolio allocation data for the near universe of 401(k) plans over the period 2009-2019, we document substantial differences in investment behavior across plans. Plans with wealthier and more educated participants tend to have higher equity exposure while plans with more retirees and minorities tend to have lower equity exposure. These patterns cannot be explained by differences in 401(k) menus or participation costs. To help interpret these facts, we use a revealed preference approach to estimate investors' expectations of stock market returns and risk aversion, where we allow investors to have heterogeneous risk aversion and subjective and potentially biased beliefs. We find that there is substantial variation in both beliefs and risk aversion across investors and over time, and that both sources of variation help explain investors' portfolio decisions. We also provide new evidence to understand how investors form beliefs. We find that investors extrapolate beliefs from past fund returns even when they initially allocate portfolios in new plans. We also find that investors extrapolate beliefs about the market from the past performance of their employer, which suggests that investor experience helps shape beliefs.]]></description><author>Mark L. Egan, Alexander MacKay, Hanbin Yang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29604</guid></item><item><title>Let the Worst One Fail: A Credible Solution to the Too-Big-To-Fail Conundrum</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29560</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Thomas Philippon, Olivier Wang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study time-consistent bank resolution mechanisms. When interventions are ex post efficient, a government cannot commit not to inject capital into the banking system. Contrary to common wisdom, we show that the government may still avoid moral hazard and implement the first best allocation by using the distribution of bailouts across banks to provide ex ante incentives. In particular, we analyze properties of credible tournament mechanisms that provide support to the best performing banks and resolve the worst performing ones, including through mergers. Our mechanism continues to perform well if banks are partially substitutable, and if they are heterogeneous in their size, interconnections, and thus systemic risk, as long as bailout funds can be targeted to particular banks.]]></description><author>Thomas Philippon, Olivier Wang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29560</guid></item><item><title>Technology-Skill Complementarity and Labor Displacement: Evidence from Linking Two Centuries of Patents with Occupations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29552</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leonid Kogan, Dimitris Papanikolaou, Lawrence D. W. Schmidt, Bryan Seegmiller.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We construct new technology indicators using textual analysis of patent documents and occupation task descriptions that span almost two centuries (1850–2010). At the industry level, improvements in technology are associated with higher labor productivity but a decline in the labor share. Exploiting variation in the extent certain technologies are related to specific occupations, we show that technological innovation has been largely associated with worse labor market outcomes—wages and employment—for incumbent workers in related occupations using a combination of public-use and confidential administrative data. Panel data on individual worker earnings reveal that less educated, older, and more highly-paid workers experience significantly greater declines in average earnings and earnings risk following related technological advances. We reconcile these facts with the standard view of technology-skill complementarity using a model that allows for skill displacement.]]></description><author>Leonid Kogan, Dimitris Papanikolaou, Lawrence D. W. Schmidt, Bryan Seegmiller</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29552</guid></item><item><title>Private or Public Equity? The Evolving Entrepreneurial Finance Landscape</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29532</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Ewens, Joan Farre-Mensa.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The U.S. entrepreneurial finance market has changed dramatically over the last two decades. Entrepreneurs raising their first round of venture capital retain 30% more equity in their firm and are more likely to control their board of directors. Late-stage startups are raising larger amounts of capital in the private markets from a growing pool of traditional and new investors. These private market changes have coincided with a sharp decline in the number of firms going public—and when firms do go public, they are older and have raised more private capital. To understand these facts, we provide a systematic description of the differences between private and public firms. Next, we review several regulatory, technological, and competitive changes affecting both startups and investors that help explain how the trade-offs between going public and staying private have changed. We conclude by listing several open research questions.]]></description><author>Michael Ewens, Joan Farre-Mensa</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29532</guid></item><item><title>The Cost of Consumer Collateral: Evidence from Bunching</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29527</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin L. Collier, Cameron Ellis, Benjamin J. Keys.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We show that borrowers are highly sensitive to the requirement of posting their homes as collateral. Using administrative loan application and performance data from the U.S. Federal Disaster Loan Program, we exploit a loan amount threshold above which households must post their residence as collateral. One-third of all borrowers select the maximum uncollateralized loan amount, and our bunching estimates suggest that the median borrower is willing to give up 40% of their loan amount to avoid collateral. Exploiting time variation in the loan amount threshold, we find that collateral causally reduces default rates by 35%. Our results help to explain high perceived default costs in the mortgage market, and uniquely quantify the extent to which collateral reduces moral hazard in consumer credit markets.]]></description><author>Benjamin L. Collier, Cameron Ellis, Benjamin J. Keys</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29527</guid></item><item><title>Sources and Transmission of Country Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29526</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tarek Alexander Hassan, Jesse Schreger, Markus Schwedeler, Ahmed Tahoun.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We use textual analysis of earnings conference calls held by listed firms around the world to measure the amount of risk managers and investors at each firm associate with each country at each point in time. Flexibly aggregating this firm-country-quarter-level data allows us to systematically identify spikes in perceived country risk (“crises”) and document their source and pattern of transmission to foreign firms. While this pattern usually follows a gravity structure, it often changes dramatically during crises. For example, while crises originating in developed countries propagate disproportionately to foreign financial firms, emerging market crises transmit less financially and more to traditionally exposed countries. We apply our measures to show that (i) elevated perceptions of a country's riskiness, particularly those of foreign and financial firms, are associated with significant falls in local asset prices, capital outflows, and reductions in firm-level investment and employment. (ii) Risk transmitted from foreign countries affects the investment decisions of domestic firms.  (iii) Heterogeneous currency loadings on perceived global risk can help explain the cross-country pattern of interest rates and currency risk premia.]]></description><author>Tarek Alexander Hassan, Jesse Schreger, Markus Schwedeler, Ahmed Tahoun</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29526</guid></item><item><title>An Economic Model of Consensus on Distributed Ledgers</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29515</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hanna Halaburda, Zhiguo He, Jiasun Li.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In recent years, the designs of many new blockchain applications have been inspired by the Byzantine fault tolerance (BFT) problem. While traditional BFT protocols assume that most system nodes are honest (in that they follow the protocol), we recognize that blockchains are deployed in environments where nodes are subject to strategic incentives. This paper develops an economic framework for analyzing such cases. Specifically, we assume that 1) non-Byzantine nodes are rational, so we explicitly study their incentives when participating in a BFT consensus process; 2) non-Byzantine nodes are ambiguity averse, and specifically, Knightian uncertain about Byzantine actions; and 3) decisions/inferences are all based on local information. We thus obtain a consensus game with preplay communications. We characterize all equilibria, some of which feature rational leaders withholding messages from some nodes in order to achieve consensus. These findings enrich those from traditional BFT algorithms, where an honest leader always sends messages to all nodes. We also study how the progress of communication technology (i.e., potential message losses) affects the equilibrium consensus outcome.]]></description><author>Hanna Halaburda, Zhiguo He, Jiasun Li</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29515</guid></item><item><title>Technological Obsolescence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29504</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Song Ma.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper proposes a new measure of technological obsolescence using detailed patent data. Using this measure, we present two sets of results. First, firms' technological obsolescence foreshadows substantially lower growth, productivity, and reallocation of capital. This finding applies mainly for obsolescence of core innovation and embodied innovation, and it is stronger in competitive product markets. Second, in stock markets, high-obsolescence firms under-perform low-obsolescence firms by 7 percent annually. Using analyst forecast data, we show this is due to a systematic overestimation of future profits of obsolescent firms. The measure contains incremental information about firm innovation relative to measures focusing on new innovation.]]></description><author>Song Ma</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29504</guid></item><item><title>Buyouts: A Primer</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29502</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tim Jenkinson, Hyeik Kim, Michael S. Weisbach.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper provides an introduction to buyouts and the academic literature about them. Buyouts are initiated by “buyout funds”, which are limited partnerships raised from mostly institutional investors. The funds earn returns for their investors by improving the operations of the firms they acquire and exiting them for a profit. Buyout funds have grown substantially and currently raise more than $400 billion annually in capital commitments. We first discuss the institutional environment that developed to foster such buyouts and to provide incentives for general partners and firm managers to earn returns for the fund’s investors. We then describe various strategies that funds use to increase the values of their portfolio companies. The paper provides up to date statistics on all aspects of the buyout industry. Finally, we present a summary of the academic literature on buyouts. This literature has paid particular attention to the extent to which buyouts earn risk-adjusted abnormal returns for their investors, as well as the sources of those returns.]]></description><author>Tim Jenkinson, Hyeik Kim, Michael S. Weisbach</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29502</guid></item><item><title>Capital Investment and Labor Demand</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29485</link><description><![CDATA[<i>E. Mark Curtis, Daniel G. Garrett, Eric C. Ohrn, Kevin A. Roberts, Juan Carlos Suárez Serrato.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study how tax policies that lower the cost of capital impact investment and labor demand. Diﬀerence-in-diﬀerences estimates using conﬁdential US Census Data on manufacturing establishments show that tax policies increased both investment and employment, but did not lead to wage or productivity gains. Using a structural model, we show that the primary eﬀect of the policy was to increase the use of all inputs by lowering overall costs of production. The policy further stimulated production employment due to the complementarity of production labor and capital. Supporting this conclusion, we ﬁnd that investment is greater in plants with lower labor costs. Our results show that recent tax policies that incentivize capital investment do not lead manufacturing plants to replace workers with machines.]]></description><author>E. Mark Curtis, Daniel G. Garrett, Eric C. Ohrn, Kevin A. Roberts, Juan Carlos Suárez Serrato</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29485</guid></item><item><title>Intermediation and Voluntary Exposure to Counterparty Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29467</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Maryam Farboodi.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> I study a model of the financial sector in which intermediation among debt financed banks gives rise to an endogenous core-periphery network – few highly interconnected and many sparsely connected banks. Endogenous intermediation generates excessive systemic risk in the financial network. Financial institutions have incentives to capture intermediation spreads through strategic borrowing and lending decisions. By doing so, they tilt the division of surplus along an intermediation chain in their favor, while at the same time reducing aggregate surplus. The network is inefficient relative to a constrained efficient benchmark since banks who make risky investments “overconnect”, exposing themselves to excessive counterparty risk, while banks who mainly provide funding end up with too few connections.]]></description><author>Maryam Farboodi</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29467</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Firm Environmental Performance to Inform Asset Management and Standardized Disclosure</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicholas Z. Muller.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Investing according to environmental, social, and governance (ESG) criteria is gaining momentum. Most environmental performance indices focus only on the tonnage of carbon dioxide (CO₂) emissions. This paper proposes an index covering eight pollutants expressed in monetary damage. Inclusion of multiple pollutants reflects a broader range of reputational and regulatory risks. Monetization appropriately weights emissions. CO₂ dominates the mass of other pollutants, yet the marginal damages from other pollutants are larger than CO₂. In the U.S. utility sector from 2014 to 2017, indices which only track CO₂ mischaracterize firms’ environmental performance and underestimate its effect on financial outcomes relative to the multipollutant index. Dirtier firms exhibit lower share prices and higher forward returns. The effect is twice as large for the multipollutant index compared to CO₂. Analysts’ earnings forecasts for dirtier firms systematically undershoot actuals. Earnings errors are between three and five times more sensitive to the multipollutant index than to CO₂. The multipollutant index may suggest new management strategies to financial market participants relative to those based on carbon intensity. ESG disclosure standards based on the new index are more likely to affect financial outcomes, capital allocation decisions, and firm behavior than disclosure of carbon intensity.]]></description><author>Nicholas Z. Muller</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</guid></item><item><title>A Temporary VAT Cut as Unconventional Fiscal Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We exploit the unexpected announcement of an immediate, temporary VAT cut in Germany in the second half of 2020 as a natural experiment to study the spending response to unconventional fiscal policy. We use survey and scanner data on households’ consumption expenditures and their perceived pass-through of the tax change into prices to quantify its effects. The temporary VAT cut led to a substantial relative increase in durable spending of 36% for individuals with a high perceived pass-through. Semi- and non-durable spending also increased. According to our preferred estimates, the VAT policy increased aggregate consumption spending by 34 billion Euros.]]></description><author>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</guid></item><item><title>FinTech Lending</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29421</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tobias Berg, Andreas Fuster, Manju Puri.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we review the growing literature on FinTech lending – the provision of credit facilitated by technology that improves the customer-lender interaction or lenders’ screening and monitoring of borrowers. FinTech lending has grown rapidly, though in developed economies like the U.S. it still only accounts for a small share of total credit. An increase in convenience and speed appears to have been more central to FinTech lending’s growth than improved screening or monitoring, though there is certainly potential for the latter, as is the case for increased financial inclusion. The COVID-19 pandemic has shown potential vulnerabilities of FinTech lenders, although in certain segments they have displayed rapid growth.]]></description><author>Tobias Berg, Andreas Fuster, Manju Puri</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29421</guid></item><item><title>CLO Performance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29410</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Larry Cordell, Michael R. Roberts, Michael Schwert.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the performance of collateralized loan obligations (CLOs) to understand the market imperfections giving rise to these vehicles and their corresponding economic costs. CLO equity tranches earn positive abnormal returns from the risk-adjusted price differential between leveraged loans and CLO debt tranches. Debt tranches offer higher returns than similarly rated corporate bonds, making them attractive to banks and insurers that face risk-based capital requirements. Temporal variation in equity performance highlights the resilience of CLOs to market volatility due to their closed-end structure, long-term funding, and embedded options to reinvest principal proceeds.]]></description><author>Larry Cordell, Michael R. Roberts, Michael Schwert</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29410</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Burden of Pension Shortfalls: Evidence from House Prices</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> U.S. state pensions are underfunded by trillions of dollars, but their economic burden is unclear. In a model of inefficient taxation, real estate fully reflects the cost of pension shortfalls when it is the only form of immobile capital. We study the effect of pension shortfalls on real estate values at state borders, where labor and physical capital could more easily relocate to a state with a smaller shortfall. Using plausibly exogenous variation driven by pension asset returns, we find that one dollar of pension underfunding reduces house prices near state borders by approximately two dollars. Our estimates imply a deadweight loss associated with addressing pension shortfalls that is consistent with prior research in settings with high returns to public spending and costs of taxation.]]></description><author>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</guid></item><item><title>The Rise of Pass-Throughs and the Decline of the Labor Share</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29400</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Matthew Smith, Danny Yagan, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the coevolution of the fall in the US corporate sector labor share and the rise of business activity in tax-preferred, pass-through form. Reallocating activity to the form it would have taken prior to the Tax Reform Act of 1986 accounts for one third of the decline in the corporate sector labor share between 1978 and 2017. Our adjustments are concentrated among mid-market firms in services, leaving a larger role for the manufacturing sector and superstar firms in driving the remaining decline in the labor share. Our findings highlight the importance of tax policy when measuring factor shares.]]></description><author>Matthew Smith, Danny Yagan, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29400</guid></item><item><title>Do Credit Conditions Move House Prices?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29391</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel L. Greenwald, Adam Guren.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> To what extent did an expansion and contraction of credit drive the 2000s housing boom and bust? The existing literature lacks consensus, with findings ranging from credit having no effect to credit driving most of the house price cycle. We show that the key difference behind these disparate results is the extent to which credit insensitive agents such as landlords and unconstrained savers absorb credit-driven demand, which depends on the degree of segmentation in housing markets. We develop a model with frictional rental markets that allows us to consider cases in between the extremes of no segmentation and perfect segmentation typically assumed in the literature. We argue that the relative elasticities of the price-rent ratio and homeownership with respect to an identified credit shock is a sufficient statistic to measure the degree of segmentation. We estimate this moment using three different credit supply instruments and use it to calibrate our model. Our results reveal that rental markets are highly frictional and closer to fully segmented, which implies large effects of credit on house prices. In particular, changes to credit standards can explain between 34% and 55% of the rise in price-rent ratios over the boom.]]></description><author>Daniel L. Greenwald, Adam Guren</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29391</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Fragility of For-profit Hospitals: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We estimate the likelihood of financial distress of U.S. hospitals in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic using AHA Annual Survey data for 2011-2019 and smartphone mobility data for 2020. We find that while the average likelihood of distress across all hospitals is 28.53 % in 2020, slightly increasing from 2019, for-profit hospitals are much more likely to be distressed. Their average likelihood of financial distress is 39.13 %---a 6.93 percentage point increase from 2019. For-profit hospitals are the main providers of specialty health care services, such as psychiatric and acute long-term care, so their increased likelihood of distress poses a risk to service provision in these specialty areas, and particularly in rural communities. Our prediction model based on mobility data performs very well in sample against actual data and can potentially help policymakers and hospital administrators to monitor financial distress in real-time when case mixes change, or other large shocks materialize.]]></description><author>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</guid></item><item><title>Household Credit as Stimulus? Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> From 2011 to 2014, the Brazilian government conducted a heavily advertised major credit expansion program through government banks as part of its effort to stimulate the economy. Using administrative data on individual-level borrowing and spending, we find that the program led to a substantial rise in borrowing by government employees, especially those with low financial literacy. We trace the impact of credit stimulus on borrowers' consumption through the 2011-16 business cycle, and find that the credit stimulus resulted in higher consumption volatility and lower average consumption over the cycle. Our results suggest a potential downside of using household credit as stimulus in emerging markets.]]></description><author>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</guid></item><item><title>Pay, Productivity and Management</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29377</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicholas Bloom, Scott W. Ohlmacher, Cristina J. Tello-Trillo, Melanie Wallskog.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Using confidential Census matched employer-employee earnings data we find that employees at more productive firms, and firms with more structured management practices, have substantially higher pay, both on average and across every percentile of the pay distribution. This pay-performance relationship is particularly strong amongst higher paid employees, with a doubling of firm productivity associated with 11% more pay for the highest-paid employee (likely the CEO) compared to 4.7% for the median worker. This pay-performance link holds in public and private firms, although it is almost twice as strong in public firms for the highest-paid employees. Top pay volatility is also strongly related to productivity and structured management, suggesting this performance-pay relationship arises from more aggressive monitoring and incentive practices for top earners.]]></description><author>Nicholas Bloom, Scott W. Ohlmacher, Cristina J. Tello-Trillo, Melanie Wallskog</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29377</guid></item><item><title>Top Wealth in America: New Estimates and Implications for Taxing the Rich</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29374</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Matthew Smith, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses administrative tax data to estimate top wealth in the United States. We assemble new data that links people to their sources of capital income and develop new methods to estimate the degree of return heterogeneity within asset classes. Disaggregated fixed income data reveal that rich individuals earn much more of their interest income in higher-yielding forms, and have much greater exposure to credit risk. Consequently, in recent years, the interest rate on fixed income at the top is approximately three times higher than the average. Using firm-level characteristics to value firms, we find that twenty percent of total pass-through business wealth accrues to those with losses. We combine this new data on fixed income and pass-through business returns with refined estimates of C-corporation equity, housing, and pension wealth to deliver new capitalized wealth estimates. Our approach---which builds on Saez and Zucman (2016) and Bricker, Henriques, and Hansen (2018)---reduces bias because wealth and rates of return are correlated. From 1989 to 2016, the top 1%, 0.1%, and 0.01% wealth shares increased by 7.6, 5.1, and 3.0 percentage points, respectively, to 31.5%, 15.0%, and 7.0%. While these changes are less dramatic than some prior estimates, wealth is very concentrated: the top 1% holds nearly as much wealth as either the bottom 90% or the "P90-99" class. We discuss implications for income inequality measures, capital tax policy, and savings behavior.]]></description><author>Matthew Smith, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29374</guid></item><item><title>Falling Rates and Rising Superstars</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29368</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Thomas Kroen, Ernest Liu, Atif R. Mian, Amir Sufi.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Do low interest rates contribute to the rise in market concentration? Using data on firm financials and high frequency monetary policy shocks, we find that falling interest rates disproportionately benefit industry leaders, especially when the initial interest rate is already low. Falling rates raise the valuation of industry leaders relative to industry followers and this effect snowballs as the interest rate approaches zero. There are multiple channels through which falling rates disproportionately benefit industry leaders: (i) the cost of borrowing falls more for industry leaders, (ii) industry leaders are able to raise more debt, increase leverage, and buyback more shares, and (iii) capital investment and acquisitions increase more for industry leaders. All three of these effects also snowball as the interest rate approaches zero. The findings provide empirical support to the idea that extremely low interest rates and the rise of superstar firms are connected.]]></description><author>Thomas Kroen, Ernest Liu, Atif R. Mian, Amir Sufi</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29368</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Access to Small Business Credit: Evidence from the Paycheck Protection Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sabrina T. Howell, Theresa Kuchler, David Snitkof, Johannes Stroebel, Jun Wong.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We explore the sources of racial disparities in small business lending by studying the $806 billion Paycheck Protection Program (PPP), which was designed to support small business jobs during the COVID-19 pandemic. PPP loans were administered by private lenders but federally guaranteed, largely eliminating unobservable credit risk as a factor in explaining differential lending by race. We document that even after controlling for a firm’s zip code, industry, loan size, PPP approval date, and other characteristics, Black-owned businesses were 12.1 percentage points (70% of the mean) more likely to obtain their PPP loan from a fintech lender than a traditional bank. Among conventional lenders, smaller banks were much less likely to lend to Black-owned firms, while the Top-4 banks exhibited little to no disparity after including controls. We use novel data to show that the disparity is not primarily explained by differences in pre-existing bank or credit relationships, firm financial positions, fintech affinity, borrower application behavior, or racial differences in rates of fraudulent PPP applications. In contrast, we document that Black-owned businesses’ higher rate of borrowing from fintechs compared to smaller banks is particularly large in places with high anti-Black racial animus, pointing to a potential role for discrimination in explaining some of the racial disparities in small business lending. We find evidence that when small banks automate their lending processes, and thus reduce human involvement in the loan origination process, their rate of PPP lending to Black-owned businesses increases, with larger effects in places with more racial animus.]]></description><author>Sabrina T. Howell, Theresa Kuchler, David Snitkof, Johannes Stroebel, Jun Wong</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</guid></item><item><title>Exposure, Experience, and Expertise: Why Personal Histories Matter in Economics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ulrike Malmendier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Personal experiences of economic outcomes, from global financial crises to individual-level job losses, can shape individual beliefs, risk attitudes, and choices for years to come. A growing literature on experience effects shows that individuals act as if past outcomes that they experienced were overly likely to occur again, even if they are fully informed about the actual likelihood. This reaction to past experiences is long-lasting though it decays over time as individuals accumulate new experiences. Modern brain science helps understand these processes. Evidence on neuroplasticity reveals that personal experiences and learning alter the strength of neural connections and fine-tune the brain structure to those past experiences ("use-dependent brain"). I show that experience effects help understand belief formation and decision-making in a wide area of economic applications, including inflation, home purchases, mortgage choices, and consumption expenditures. I argue that experience-based learning is broadly applicable to economic decision-making and discuss topics for future research in education, health, race, and gender economics.]]></description><author>Ulrike Malmendier</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</guid></item><item><title>Economic Growth and Bank Innovation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29326</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gary B. Gorton, Ping He.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Based on archival and survey data we show that the maturity of U.S. business loans has been continuously increasing since the mid-1930s when banks invented the term loan. Concurrently, bank innovation first involved the invention of credit analysis and covenant design. Later, bank innovation included the advent of loan sales, increased loan syndications, the opening of the leveraged loan market, and the securitization of loans in collateralized loan obligations. We estimate and calibrate a model of bank innovation to determine the quantitative contribution of bank innovation to economic growth.]]></description><author>Gary B. Gorton, Ping He</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29326</guid></item><item><title>Corporate Culture</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29322</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gary B. Gorton, Jill Grennan, Alexander K. Zentefis.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Corporate culture is an omnibus term that includes many elements like norms, values, knowledge, and customs that are relevant to a firm. Economists have made great progress recently in devising methods of measuring different aspects of corporate culture. These empirical measures of culture have explained mergers and acquisitions, corporate risk-taking, and unethical behaviors observed in corporations, among other topics. We argue that unpacking corporate culture into its components is the right way to research it empirically. Theories of corporate culture are still in development, and we discuss the major contributions thus far. We argue that a theory of the firm and of corporate decision-making that is based on corporate culture is more germane to the practical realities of firms’ inner workings than prevailing theories based on agency costs. Corporate culture has the potential to set the theoretical paradigm for all corporate finance research.]]></description><author>Gary B. Gorton, Jill Grennan, Alexander K. Zentefis</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29322</guid></item><item><title>Occupational Licensing and Accountant Quality: Evidence from the 150-Hour Rule</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29318</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John M. Barrios.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> I examine the effects of occupational licensing on the quality of Certified Public Accountants (CPAs). I exploit the staggered adoption of the 150-hour rule, which increases the educational requirements for a CPA license. The analysis shows that the rule decreases the number of entrants into the profession, reducing both low- and high-quality candidates. Labor market proxies for quality find no difference between 150-hour rule CPAs and the rest. Moreover, rule CPAs exit public accounting at similar rates and have comparable writing quality to their non-rule counterparts. Overall, these findings are consistent with the theoretical argument that increases in licensing requirements restrict the supply of entrants and do little to improve quality in the labor market.]]></description><author>John M. Barrios</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29318</guid></item><item><title>Big Loans to Small Businesses: Predicting Winners and Losers in an Entrepreneurial Lending Experiment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We experimentally study the impact of substantially larger enterprise loans, in collaboration with an Egyptian lender. Larger loans generate small average impacts, but machine learning using psychometric data reveals dramatic heterogeneity. Top-performers (i.e., those with the highest predicted treatment effects) substantially increase profits, whereas profits for poor-performers drop. The magnitude of this difference implies that an individual lender’s credit allocation choices matter for aggregate income. Evidence on two fronts suggests large loans would be misallocated: top-performers are predicted by loan officers to have higher default rates; and, top-performers grow less than others when given small loans, implying that allocating larger loans based on prior performance is not efficient. Our results have important implications for credit expansion policy and our understanding of entrepreneurial talent: on the former, the use of psychometric data to identify top-performers suggests a pathway towards better allocation that revolves around entrepreneurial type more than firm type; on the latter, the reversal of fortune for poor-performers, who do well with small loans but not large, indicates a type of entrepreneur that we call a “go-getter” who performs well when constrained but poorly when not.]]></description><author>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic Strategic Corporate Finance: A Tug of War with Financial Frictions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29310</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ulrich Doraszelski, João F. Gomes, Felix Nockher.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Access to capital markets plays a key role for the evolution of an industry over time. We develop a benchmark theoretical setting that integrates core corporate finance insights about the impact of financial frictions on investment with those from industrial organization on dynamic competition and industry evolution under perfect capital markets. Using state of the art computational tools to systematically detect and evaluate multiple equilibria and to thoroughly explore the parameter space of our model, we show how, depending on key industry characteristics such as market size, financial frictions impact firms' pricing and investment strategies and the degree of industry concentration.]]></description><author>Ulrich Doraszelski, João F. Gomes, Felix Nockher</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29310</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Housing Returns</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29306</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Amir Kermani, Francis Wong.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We document the existence of a racial gap in realized housing returns that is an order of magnitude larger than disparities arising from housing costs alone, and is driven almost entirely by differences in distressed home sales (i.e. foreclosures and short sales). Black and Hispanic homeowners are both more likely to experience a distressed sale and to live in neighborhoods where distressed sales erase more house value. Importantly, absent financial distress, houses owned by minorities do not appreciate at slower rates than houses owned by non-minorities. Racial differences in income stability and liquid wealth explain a large share of the differences in distress. We use quasi-experimental variation in loan modifications to show that policies that restructure mortgages for distressed minorities can increase housing returns and reduce the racial wealth gap.]]></description><author>Amir Kermani, Francis Wong</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29306</guid></item><item><title>Bank Mergers, Acquirer Choice and Small Business Lending: Implications for Community Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29284</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Bernadette A. Minton, Alvaro G. Taboada, Rohan Williamson.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We examine the effects of bank merger and local market characteristics on local small business lending.  Mergers involving small, in-state acquirers are positively associated with small business loan (SBL) originations in counties where target banks are located.  Conversely, mergers involving large, out-of-state acquirers are associated with fewer SBL originations.  The analysis suggests that the results are driven by acquirer’s choice of target.  Small and in-state acquirers target banks that focus more on SBL and targets with strong relationships while large, out-of-state acquirers pursue better performing banks with stronger balance sheets and less focus on SBL.  Results are particularly strong in counties with a large number of small firms.  Post-merger activity supports banks expanding on their acquisition strategy decisions.  The findings suggest that acquirer strategy is important for evaluating the impact of acquisitions on local community development and that one-size-fits-all policy solutions for bank mergers may not produce common local outcomes.]]></description><author>Bernadette A. Minton, Alvaro G. Taboada, Rohan Williamson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29284</guid></item><item><title>Banking-Crisis Interventions, 1257-2019</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29281</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andrew Metrick, Paul Schmelzing.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We present a new database of banking-crisis interventions since the 13th century.  The database includes 1886 interventions in 20 categories across 138 countries, covering interventions during all of the crises identified in the main banking-crisis  chronologies, while also cataloguing a large number of interventions outside of  those crises. The data show a gradual shift over the past centuries from the  traditional interventions of a lender-of-last-resort, suspensions of convertibility, and bank holidays, towards a much more prominent role for capital injections and  sweeping guarantees of bank liabilities. Furthermore, intervention frequencies and  sizes suggest that the crisis problem in the financial sector has indeed reached an  apex during the post-Bretton Woods era – but that such trends are part of a more  deeply entrenched development that saw global intervention frequencies and sizes  gradually rise since at least the late 17th century.]]></description><author>Andrew Metrick, Paul Schmelzing</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29281</guid></item><item><title>Does Political Partisanship Cross Borders? Evidence from International Capital Flows</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29280</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Elisabeth Kempf, Mancy Luo, Larissa Schäfer, Margarita Tsoutsoura.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Does partisan perception shape the flow of international capital? We provide evidence from two settings, syndicated corporate loans and equity mutual funds, to show that ideological alignment with foreign governments affects the cross-border capital allocation by U.S. institutional investors. Moreover, we find that ideological alignment with foreign countries also affects investments of non-U.S. investors and can explain patterns in bilateral FDI flows. Our empirical strategy ensures that direct economic effects of foreign elections or bilateral ties between countries are not driving the result. Combined, our findings imply that partisan perception is a global phenomenon and its economic effects transcend national borders.]]></description><author>Elisabeth Kempf, Mancy Luo, Larissa Schäfer, Margarita Tsoutsoura</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29280</guid></item><item><title>Measuring the Welfare Cost of Asymmetric Information in Consumer Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Information asymmetries are known in theory to lead to inefficiently low credit provision, yet empirical estimates of the resulting welfare losses are scarce. This paper leverages a randomized experiment conducted by a large fintech lender to estimate welfare losses arising from asymmetric information in the market for online consumer credit. Building on methods from the insurance literature, we show how exogenous variation in interest rates can be used to estimate borrower demand and lender cost curves and recover implied welfare losses. While asymmetric information generates large equilibrium price distortions, we find only small overall welfare losses, particularly for high-credit-score borrowers.]]></description><author>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</guid></item></channel></rss>