<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic National Fiscal Issues</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic National Fiscal Issues</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 22:06:51 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Local Economic and Political Effects of Trade Deals: Evidence from NAFTA</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29525</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Why have white, less educated voters left the Democratic Party over the past few decades? Scholars have proposed ethnocentrism, social issues and deindustrialization as potential answers. We highlight the role played by the 1994 North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA).  In event-study analysis, we demonstrate that counties whose 1990 employment depended on industries vulnerable to NAFTA suffered large and persistent employment losses relative to other counties. These losses begin in the mid-1990s and are only modestly offset by transfer programs.  While exposed counties historically voted Democratic, in the mid-1990s they turn away from the party of the president (Bill Clinton) who ushered in the agreement and by 2000 vote majority Republican in House elections. Employing a variety of micro-data sources, including 1992-1994 respondent-level panel data, we show that protectionist views predict movement toward the GOP in the years that NAFTA is debated and implemented. This shift among protectionist respondents is larger for whites (especially men and those without a college degree) and those with conservative social views, suggesting an interactive effect whereby racial identity and social-issue positions mediate reactions to economic policies.]]></description><author>Jiwon Choi, Ilyana Kuziemko, Ebonya L. Washington, Gavin Wright</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29525</guid></item><item><title>Support for Paid Family Leave among Small Employers Increases during the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29486</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> The United States is one of the few countries that does not guarantee paid family leave (PFL) to workers. Proposals for PFL legislation are often met with opposition from employer organizations, who fear disruptions to business, especially among small employers. But there has been limited data on employers' views. We surveyed firms with 10-99 employees in New York and New Jersey on their attitudes towards PFL programs before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. We found high support for state PFL programs in 2019 that rose substantially over the course of the pandemic: by the fall of 2020, almost 70% of firms were supportive. Increases in support were larger among firms that had an employee use PFL, suggesting that experience with PFL led to employers becoming more supportive. Thus, concerns about negative impacts on small employers should not impede efforts to expand PFL at the state or federal levels.]]></description><author>Ann P. Bartel, Maya Rossin-Slater, Christopher J. Ruhm, Meredith Slopen, Jane Waldfogel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29486</guid></item><item><title>Were Federal COVID Relief Funds for Schools Enough?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29470</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Congress responded to the COVID pandemic’s disruptions to instruction with unprecedented federal aid for school districts. While this relief has been widely characterized as a major windfall for K-12 education, per-pupil amounts vary considerably across districts, as will the costs districts face for COVID mitigation and recovery. In this paper, we conduct simulations to understand the potential distribution of net effects of the pandemic and federal aid on the finances of local school districts in the next several years. In our baseline scenario, we assume one-time adjustment costs of $500 per pupil plus additional costs of $1,000 per student in poverty and $500 per student not in poverty per year for four years. Federal aid was distributed proportional to the longstanding Title I program, which sends more money per pupil to higher poverty districts. Low-poverty districts are therefore projected to face some budgetary shortfalls, while many higher poverty districts are projected to have excess funds, which they could direct towards long-standing challenges. While our findings depend on key assumptions about the COVID-related costs, we find significant district-level variation in simulated net fiscal impacts, in part but not completely due to poverty rates, across all the scenarios we consider.]]></description><author>Nora E. Gordon, Sarah J. Reber</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29470</guid></item><item><title>The Debt Capacity of a Government</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> In a deterministic overlapping-generations economy with production and physical capital, the price of debt can be positive without any budget surpluses being in the offing, because debt incorporates a rational bubble. Yet the dynamics of debt remain a function of the dynamics of the primary budget deficit. As a way to study their joint behavior, we endogenize a structural deficit in the form of an underfunded social-security scheme. We define debt capacity as the level of debt that can be just sustained without a change of policy all the way to an unstable steady state. When it starts below the capacity, the debt converges to a stable steady state, in which the bubble is sustained. Above capacity the bubble unravels and the deficit cannot be financed. In several realistic scenarios occurring in economies, we calculate the needed policy response, which is the true "fiscal cost" of exceeding debt capacity.]]></description><author>Bernard Dumas, Paul Ehling, Chunyu Yang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Burden of Pension Shortfalls: Evidence from House Prices</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> U.S. state pensions are underfunded by trillions of dollars, but their economic burden is unclear. In a model of inefficient taxation, real estate fully reflects the cost of pension shortfalls when it is the only form of immobile capital. We study the effect of pension shortfalls on real estate values at state borders, where labor and physical capital could more easily relocate to a state with a smaller shortfall. Using plausibly exogenous variation driven by pension asset returns, we find that one dollar of pension underfunding reduces house prices near state borders by approximately two dollars. Our estimates imply a deadweight loss associated with addressing pension shortfalls that is consistent with prior research in settings with high returns to public spending and costs of taxation.]]></description><author>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</guid></item><item><title>The Effect of Free School Meals on Household Food Purchases: Evidence from the Community Eligibility Provision</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29395</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We find evidence that exposure to universal free school meals through the Community Eligibility Provision (CEP) had a meaningful impact on grocery spending for households with children, with monthly food purchases declining by about $11, or 5 percent. For households in zip codes with higher exposure, the decline is as high as $39 per month, or 19 percent. We also show evidence that the composition of food purchases changes, with low income households experiencing an increase in the dietary quality of their food purchases by about 3 percent after CEP. Finally, we show CEP exposure is associated with an 11 percent decline in the percent of households that ran short of money or tried to make their food money go further, and an almost 5 percent decline in households classified as food insecure. Our results on the heterogeneous effects of CEP exposure by prior free/reduced price lunch eligibility reveal large benefits in terms of both spending, dietary composition, and food insecurity for previously eligible low-income families, suggesting that the stigma of free school meals may be declining after universal access.]]></description><author>Michelle M. Marcus, Katherine G. Yewell</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29395</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Fragility of For-profit Hospitals: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We estimate the likelihood of financial distress of U.S. hospitals in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic using AHA Annual Survey data for 2011-2019 and smartphone mobility data for 2020. We find that while the average likelihood of distress across all hospitals is 28.53 % in 2020, slightly increasing from 2019, for-profit hospitals are much more likely to be distressed. Their average likelihood of financial distress is 39.13 %---a 6.93 percentage point increase from 2019. For-profit hospitals are the main providers of specialty health care services, such as psychiatric and acute long-term care, so their increased likelihood of distress poses a risk to service provision in these specialty areas, and particularly in rural communities. Our prediction model based on mobility data performs very well in sample against actual data and can potentially help policymakers and hospital administrators to monitor financial distress in real-time when case mixes change, or other large shocks materialize.]]></description><author>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</guid></item><item><title>The Political Economy of the COVID-19 Fiscal Stimulus Packages of 2020</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29360</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Almost all countries announced fiscal support programs once COVID-19 hit. However, there was significant diversity in the magnitude and composition of these fiscal stimulus programs. These differences were determined by myriad political, financial, social, and economic factors - these factors are our focus. We ask what were the factors that are associated with the structure of the fiscal programs that governments chose to adopt in the early stage of the pandemic in 2020. We answer this question using details about the fiscal programs that were announced by 98 governments in the first six months of the pandemic, together with a large set of explanatory variables. Maybe not surprisingly, we find that politics played a very significant part in determining the size and composition of these fiscal programs. Governments and societies that are less polarized and more capable were able to mobilise more fiscal resources. We also find that it was governments with bigger debt loads that announced bigger programs, but that sovereign spreads were not so clearly associated with the size of these program plans. There is a limit, however, to what we can glean from these cross-country comparisons. Ultimately, the understanding of the politics and political-economy considerations that led to the specific content of each fiscal program will have to rely on information about the actual deliberations in each government’s halls of power, should these ever become public.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Ilan Noy</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29360</guid></item><item><title>The Initial Effects of the Expanded Child Tax Credit on Material Hardship</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The transformation of the Child Tax Credit (CTC) into a more generous, inclusive monthly payment marks a historic (temporary) shift in U.S. treatment of low-income families. To investigate the initial impact of these payments, we apply a series of difference-in-difference estimates using Census Household Pulse Survey microdata collected from April 14 through August 16, 2021. Our findings offer three primary conclusions regarding the initial effects of the monthly CTC. First, payments strongly reduced food insufficiency: the initial payments led to a 7.5 percentage point (25 percent) decline in food insufficiency among low-income households with children. Second, the effects on food insufficiency are concentrated among families with 2019 pre-tax incomes below $35,000, and the CTC strongly reduces food insufficiency among low-income Black, Latino, and White families alike. Third, increasing the CTC coverage rate would be required in order for material hardship to be reduced further. Self-reports suggest the lowest-income households were less likely than higher-income families to receive the first CTC payments. As more children receive the benefit in future months, material hardship may decline further. Even with imperfect coverage, however, our findings suggest that the first CTC payments were largely effective at reducing food insufficiency among low-income families with children.]]></description><author>Zachary Parolin, Elizabeth Ananat, Sophie M. Collyer, Megan Curran, Christopher Wimer</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285</guid></item><item><title>The Aftermath of Debt Surges</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29266</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Debt in emerging market and developing economies (EMDEs) is at its highest level in half a century. In about nine out of 10 EMDEs, debt is higher now than it was in 2010 and, in half of the EMDEs, debt is more than 30 percentage points of gross domestic product higher. Historically, elevated debt levels increased the incidence of debt distress, particularly in EMDEs and particularly when financial market conditions turned less benign. This paper reviews an encompassing menu of options that have, in the past, helped lower debt burdens. Specifically, it examines orthodox options (enhancing growth, fiscal consolidation, privatization, and wealth taxation) and heterodox options (inflation, financial repression, debt default and restructuring). The mix of feasible options depends on country characteristics and the type of debt. However, none of these options comes without political, economic, and social costs. Some options may ultimately be ineffective unless vigorously implemented. Policy reversals in difficult times have been common. The challenges associated with debt reduction raise questions of global governance, including to what extent advanced economies can cast their net wider to cushion prospective shocks to EMDEs.]]></description><author>M. Ayhan Kose, Franziska L. Ohnsorge, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29266</guid></item><item><title>The Affordable Care Act After a Decade: Its Impact on the Labor Market and the Macro Economy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29240</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The Affordable Care Act (ACA) is one of the most important reforms of the US health insurance system since the introduction of Medicare. Since employment is a main source of health insurance for the working age population in the United States, this sweeping health insurance reform also has important implications for the labor market and the macro economy. In this paper, we survey the prototype models that are used in the macro and labor literature, extended to integrate health and health insurance, to study the short- and long-run consequences of the ACA. We also suggest open areas for future research.]]></description><author>Hanming Fang, Dirk Krueger</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29240</guid></item><item><title>Income-Contingent Loans As an Unemployment Benefit</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29198</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Imperfections in risk and capital markets imply that individuals who lose jobs suffer from imperfect smoothing of consumption across states and times. Compared to the first best, there will be too little search. Optimal unemployment programs, which balance the marginal benefit of consumption smoothing vs. the marginal cost of the insurance externality, increase welfare and may even increase GDP. Our analytical results suggest that welfare is higher if the unemployment benefits program includes income-contingent unemployment loans (ICL), where the amount repaid depends on the individual’s future income. Such loans can be financed by a risk premium imposed on the unemployed who avail themselves of the loans, and partially substitute for unemployment insurance (UI) benefits. Optimal unemployment benefits programs (UB) with ICL do a better job of smoothing consumption across states and time, and in particular total benefits when unemployed increase. We analyze how changes in key parameters, such as the degree of risk aversion and the nature of post-employment work, affect the design of the optimal UB program and the magnitude of the incremental benefits from including income-contingent loans.]]></description><author>Haaris Mateen ⓡ, Joseph E. Stiglitz ⓡ, Jungyoll Yun</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29198</guid></item><item><title>A Watershed Moment: The Clean Water Act and Infant Health</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29152</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The Clean Water Act (CWA) significantly improved surface water quality, but at a cost exceeding the estimated benefits. We quantify the effect of the CWA on a direct measure of health and incorporate health benefits into a cost-benefit analysis. Using a difference-in-differences framework, we compare health upstream and downstream from wastewater treatment facilities before and after CWA grant receipt. Pollution only decreased downstream from facilities required to upgrade their treatment technology, and we leverage this additional variation with a triple difference. CWA grants increased average birth weight by 8 grams. A back-of-the-envelope calculation bounds infant health benefits below $29 billion.]]></description><author>Patrick Flynn, Michelle M. Marcus</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29152</guid></item><item><title>Public Debt Bubbles in Heterogeneous Agent Models with Tail Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29138</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the public debt implications of a class of Aiyagari (1994)-Bewley (1977)-Huggett (1993) (ABH) models of incomplete insurance in which agents face a near-zero probability of a highly adverse outcome. In generic models of this kind, there exists a public debt bubble, so that the government is able to borrow at a real interest rate that is perpetually below the economic growth rate. Given an equilibrium with a public debt bubble, the primary deficit and the level of debt are both strictly increasing in the real interest rate and in the fraction of government expenditures used for lumpsum transfers. There is no upper bound on the deficit level or long-run debt level that is sustainable in equilibrium. In a public debt bubble, regardless of its size, agents are better off in the long run if the government chooses policies that give rise to a larger debt and primary deficit.]]></description><author>Narayana R. Kocherlakota</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29138</guid></item><item><title>Return on Student Loans in Canada</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29130</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper uses new administrative data with detailed borrower information and lengthy repayment histories from the Canada Student Loans Program (CSLP) to measure rates of return on undergraduate student loans. We document substantial heterogeneity in returns based on information available at the time loans were disbursed, including province of residence, field of study, and institution of attendance. Field of study is a particularly important determinant of rates of return, explaining 22% of the variation in predicted returns across borrowers.  We explore the implications of this variation for CSLP cross-subsidization across borrowers and potential risk-based loan limits. Given the variation in ex ante predicted returns across borrowers, using all available information at the time of loan disbursement, we study the implications of potential cream-skimming of high-return borrowers by private lenders.]]></description><author>Lance Lochner, Qian Liu, Martin Gervais</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29130</guid></item><item><title>Economic Consequences of Hospital Closures</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29110</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Hospitals anchor much of US health care and receive a third of all medical spending, including various subsidies. Nevertheless, some become insolvent and exit the market. Research has documented subsequent access problems; however, less is understood about broader implications. We examine over 100 rural hospital closures spanning 2005-2017 to quantify the effects on the local economy. We find sharp and persistent reductions in employment, but these localize to health care occupations and are largely driven by areas experiencing complete closures. Aggregate consumer financial health is only modestly affected, and housing markets were already depressed prior to hospital closures.]]></description><author>Diane E. Alexander, Michael R. Richards</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29110</guid></item></channel></rss>