<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Financial History</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Financial History</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 21:53:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Environmental Liabilities, Creditors, and Corporate Pollution: Evidence from the Apex Oil Ruling</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29740</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jianqiang Chen, Pei-Fang Hsieh, Po-Hsuan Hsu, Ross Levine.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We evaluate the impact of the 2008 Apex Oil court decision that made the creditors of some corporations financially liable for the environmental damages caused by specific pollutants. Apex reduced the circumstances under which environmental liabilities were dischargeable in Chapter 11, which generated financial incentives for the creditors of firms near bankruptcy to pressure their firms to reduce emissions of those pollutants. We discover that Apex lowered bond prices, widened loan spreads, and reduced corporate pollution among firms that (a) release the specific chemicals covered by Apex and (b) are close to Chapter 11 and hence likely to be affected by changes to the dischargeability of environmental liabilities. Further tests suggest that creditors rapidly responded to Apex and successfully induced firms to reduce pollution.]]></description><author>Jianqiang Chen, Pei-Fang Hsieh, Po-Hsuan Hsu, Ross Levine</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29740</guid></item><item><title>O.M.W. Sprague (the Man Who “Wrote the Book” on Financial Crises) meets the Great Depression</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29416</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hugh Rockoff.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> When the Great Depression struck the United States, Oliver M.W. Sprague was America’s foremost expert on financial crises. His History of Crises under the National Banking System is a frequently cited classic. Had he diagnosed a banking panic and called for an aggressive response by the Federal Reserve, it might have made a difference; but he did not. Sprague’s misdiagnosis had, I argue, two causes. First, the crisis lacked the symptoms of a panic, such as high short-term interest rates in the New York money market, which Sprague had identified from his studies of previous crises. Second, Sprague’s macro-economic ideas led him to conclude that an expansionary monetary policy would be of little help once a depression was underway. Sprague’s main concern was that abandoning the gold standard would intensify the crisis, a concern that led him to resign his position as advisor to the U.S. Treasury to protest Roosevelt’s gold policy.]]></description><author>Hugh Rockoff</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29416</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Consequences of the Opium War</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29404</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Wolfgang Keller, Carol H. Shiue.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the economic consequences of the West’s foray into China after the Opium War (1839-42), when Western colonial influence was introduced in dozens of so-called treaty ports. We document a turnaround during the 19th century in the nature of China’s capital markets. Whereas before the Opium War, coastal cities were of relatively minor importance, the treaty port system of the West transformed China into an economy focused on coastal areas and on international trade that aligned with the trading interests of the West. We show, first, that the West had a positive impact on China’s economy during the 19th century. It brought down local interest rates, and regions under Western influence exhibited both higher rates of industry growth and technology adoption. Second, the geographic scope of influence went far beyond the ports, impacting most of China. Interest rates fell by more than a quarter in the immediate vicinity of the ports and still by almost ten percent at distances of 450 kilometers from treaty ports. The development of China was not simply propelled by its own pre-1800 history, or by post-1978 reforms. The nearly 100 years of semi-colonization have shaped China’s economy today as one focused on the coastal areas.]]></description><author>Wolfgang Keller, Carol H. Shiue</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29404</guid></item><item><title>Rethinking Exchange Rate Regimes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29347</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ethan Ilzetzki, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper employs an updated algorithm and database for classifying exchange rate and anchor currency choice, to explore the evolution of the global exchange rate system, including parallel rates, capital controls and reserves. In line with a large recent literature, we find that the dollar has become ever-more central as the de facto anchor or reference currencies for much of the world. Our discussion encompasses the history of anchor currency choice, methods for classifying exchange rate regimes, a detailed discussion of the evolution of regimes, the growing substitution of reserves for capital controls as a tool for exchange rate stabilization, the modern Triffin dilemma, and the surprising recent trend decline in volatility of exchange rates at the core of the system. It concludes with issues surrounding the rise of China.]]></description><author>Ethan Ilzetzki, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29347</guid></item></channel></rss>