<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Fiscal Policy</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Fiscal Policy</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 22:46:59 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>State-Level Economic Policy Uncertainty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29714</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Scott R. Baker, Steven J. Davis, Jeffrey A. Levy.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We quantify and study state-level economic policy uncertainty. Tapping digital archives for nearly 3,500 local newspapers, we construct three monthly indexes for each state: one that captures state and local sources of policy uncertainty (EPU-S), one that captures national and international sources (EPU-N), and a composite index that captures both. EPU-S rises around gubernatorial elections and own-state episodes like the California electricity crisis of 2000-01 and the Kansas tax experiment of 2012. EPU-N rises around presidential elections and in response to 9-11, Gulf Wars I and II, the 2011 debt-ceiling crisis, the 2012 fiscal cliff episode, and federal government shutdowns. Close elections elevate policy uncertainty much more than the average election. The COVID-19 pandemic drove huge increases in policy uncertainty and unemployment, more so in states with stricter government-mandated lockdowns. VAR models fit to pre-COVID data imply that upward shocks to own-state EPU foreshadow weaker economic activity in the state.]]></description><author>Scott R. Baker, Steven J. Davis, Jeffrey A. Levy</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29714</guid></item><item><title>A Goldilocks Theory of Fiscal Deficits</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29707</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Atif R. Mian, Ludwig Straub, Amir Sufi.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper proposes a tractable framework to analyze fiscal space and the dynamics of government debt, with a possibly binding zero lower bound (ZLB) constraint. Without the ZLB, a greater primary deficit unambiguously raises debt. However, debt need not explode: When R &lt; G – φ, where φ is the sensitivity of R – G to debt, a modest permanent increase in the deficit can be sustained forever, a policy we call “free lunch”. With the ZLB, the relationship between deficit and debt can become non-monotone. Both high and low deficits can increase debt, as the latter weaken demand and reduce nominal growth at the ZLB. A rise in income inequality expands fiscal space outside the ZLB, but contracts it at the ZLB. Calibrating the model, we find little space for “free lunch” policies for the United States in 2019, but ample space for Japan.]]></description><author>Atif R. Mian, Ludwig Straub, Amir Sufi</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29707</guid></item><item><title>Should We Have Automatic Triggers for Unemployment Benefit Duration And How Costly Would They Be?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29703</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gabriel Chodorow-Reich, Peter Ganong, Jonathan Gruber.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We model automatic trigger policies for unemployment insurance by simulating a weekly panel of individual labor market histories, grouped by state. We reach three conclusions: (i) policies designed to trigger immediately at the onset of a recession result in benefit extensions that occur in less sick labor markets than the historical average for benefit extensions; (ii) the ad hoc extensions in the 2001 and 2007-09 recessions in total cover a similar number of additional weeks as common proposals for automatic triggers, but concentrate coverage more in weaker labor markets; (iii) compared to ex post policy, the cost of common proposals for automatic triggers is close to zero.]]></description><author>Gabriel Chodorow-Reich, Peter Ganong, Jonathan Gruber</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29703</guid></item><item><title>The $800 Billion Paycheck Protection Program: Where Did the Money Go and Why Did it Go There?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29669</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Autor, David Cho, Leland D. Crane, Mita Goldar, Byron Lutz, Joshua K. Montes, William B. Peterman, David D. Ratner, Daniel Villar Vallenas, Ahu Yildirmaz.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The Paycheck Protection Program (PPP) provided small businesses with roughly $800 billion dollars in uncollateralized, low-interest loans during the pandemic, almost all of which will be forgiven. With 93 percent of small businesses ultimately receiving one or more loans, the PPP nearly saturated its market in just two months. We estimate that the program cumulatively preserved between 2 and 3 million job-years of employment over 14 months at a cost of $170K to $257K per job-year retained. These estimates imply that only 23 to 34 percent of PPP dollars went directly to workers who would otherwise have lost jobs; the balance flowed to business owners and shareholders, including creditors and suppliers of PPP-receiving firms. Program incidence was highly regressive, with about three-quarters of PPP funds accruing to the top quintile of households. This compares unfavorably to the other two major pandemic aid programs, enhanced UI benefits and Economic Impact Payments (i.e. stimulus checks). PPP’s breakneck scale-up, its high cost per job saved, and its regressive incidence have a common origin: PPP was essentially untargeted because the United States lacked the administrative infrastructure to do otherwise. The more targeted pandemic business aid programs deployed by other high-income countries exemplify what is feasible with better administrative systems. Building similar capacity in the U.S. would enable greatly improved targeting of either employment subsidies or business liquidity when the next pandemic or other large-scale economic emergency occurs, as it surely will.]]></description><author>David Autor, David Cho, Leland D. Crane, Mita Goldar, Byron Lutz, Joshua K. Montes, William B. Peterman, David D. Ratner, Daniel Villar Vallenas, Ahu Yildirmaz</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29669</guid></item><item><title>Political Constraints and Sovereign Default</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29667</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marina Azzimonti, Nirvana Mitra.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We study how political constraints, characterized by the degree of flexibility to choose fiscal policy, affect the probability of sovereign default. To that end, we relax the assumption that policymakers always repay their debt in the dynamic model of fiscal policy developed by Battaglini and Coate (2008). In our setup, legislators bargain over taxes, general spending, debt repayment, and a local public good that can be targeted to the region they represent. Under tighter political constraints, more legislators have veto power, implying that local public goods need to be provided to a larger number of regions. The resources that are freed after a default have to be shared with a higher number of individuals, which reduces the benefits from defaulting in per-capita terms. This lowers the incentive to default compared to the case with lax political constraints. The model is calibrated to Argentina and the results conform to robust empirical evidence. An event study for the 2001/2002 sovereign debt crisis shows that political constraints had an important role in the buildup that led to the crisis.]]></description><author>Marina Azzimonti, Nirvana Mitra</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29667</guid></item><item><title>A Simple Mapping from MPCs to MPXs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29664</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Laibson, Peter Maxted, Benjamin Moll.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Standard consumption models assume a notional consumption flow that does not distinguish between nondurable and durable consumption. Such notional-consumption models generate notional marginal propensities to consume (MPC). By contrast, empirical work and policy discussions often highlight marginal propensities for expenditure (MPX), which incorporate spending on a durable stock. We compare the notional-consumption model to an isomorphic model with a durable stock, and map notional MPCs into MPXs. The mapping is especially simple for a one-period horizon: MPX =  (1 - s + s/(r+d)) x MPC, with durable share s, real interest rate r, and durable depreciation rate d.]]></description><author>David Laibson, Peter Maxted, Benjamin Moll</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29664</guid></item><item><title>Household Spending Responses to the Economic Impact Payments of 2020: Evidence from the Consumer Expenditure Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29648</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan A. Parker, Jake Schild, Laura Erhard, David Johnson.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Using the Consumer Expenditure Survey and variation in amount, receipt, and timing of receipt of Economic Impact Payments (EIPs) authorized by the CARES Act, this paper estimates that people spent less of their EIPs in the few months following arrival than in similar previous policy episodes and than estimated by existing studies using other types of data. Accounting for volatility during the pandemic and comparing the consumer spending behavior of broadly similar households, people spent roughly 10 percent (standard error 3.4) of their EIPs on non-durable goods and services in the three months of arrival, with little evidence of additional spending in the subsequent three months or on  durable goods. People who report mostly spending their EIPs spent 14.3\% (3.7) of their EIPs compared to 5.9\% (8.3) and -1.6\% (5.0) for those who report mostly paying off debt and saving respectively. People with low liquid wealth and people receiving their EIPs on debit cards spent at higher rates: 21.7\% (6.4) and 36.8\% (24.6) respectively, with economically larger estimates for total spending.]]></description><author>Jonathan A. Parker, Jake Schild, Laura Erhard, David Johnson</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29648</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Policy in a Networked Economy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29619</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joel P. Flynn, Christina Patterson, John Sturm.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Advanced economies feature complicated networks that connect households, ﬁrms, and regions. How do these structures aﬀect the impact of ﬁscal policy and its optimal targeting? We study these questions in a model with input-output linkages, regional structure, and household heterogeneity in MPCs, consumption baskets, and shock exposures. Theoretically, we derive estimable formulae for the eﬀects of ﬁscal policies on aggregate GDP, or ﬁscal multipliers, and show how network structures determine their size. Empirically, we ﬁnd that multipliers vary substantially across policies, so targeting is important. Beneath these aggregate eﬀects are large spatial and sectoral spillovers from policies directed to any one ﬁrm or household. However, virtually all variation in multipliers stems from diﬀerences in policies’ direct incidence onto households’ MPCs. Thus, while the distributional eﬀects of ﬁscal policy depend on the detailed structure of the economy, maximally expansionary ﬁscal policy simply targets households’ MPCs.]]></description><author>Joel P. Flynn, Christina Patterson, John Sturm</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29619</guid></item><item><title>International Evidence of Strengthening Taxes and Spending For Sustainable Development</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29594</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Donghyun Park.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We trace the linkages between the episodes of fiscal expansion and consolidation in 72 advanced and emerging and developing economies. The findings suggest that fiscal expansions are positively associated with economic growth, which in turn is positively linked with better sustainable development outcomes. The association between fiscal consolidation and growth as well as the sustainable development indicators, however, is not clear-cut. Jointly, more tax revenues and expenditures, together with better governance help explain the association between economic growth and inclusive development. High-income, high-tax-revenue, and manufacture-exporting economies have made significant progress on reducing disease-linked mortality and improving environment protection along with economic growth. Meanwhile, emerging and developing, low-tax-revenue, and commodity-exporting economies have gained notable improvement in poverty reduction, pre-primary enrolment and access to basic sanitation services and clean cooking fuels and technologies, and lowering bribery incidence. On average, the sampled economies have persistently achieved better primary goals such as sanitation, clean fuels and technologies. Achievements in mortality reduction, and environmental protection goals are shown more recently.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Donghyun Park</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29594</guid></item><item><title>The Missing Intercept: A Demand Equivalence Approach</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29558</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christian K. Wolf.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> I give conditions under which changes in private spending are accommodated in general equilibrium exactly like changes in aggregate fiscal expenditure. Under such demand equivalence, researchers can use time series evidence on fiscal multipliers to recover the general equilibrium "missing intercept" of shocks to private spending identified in the cross section. I apply this method to deficit-financed stimulus checks, and find a) a large direct consumption spending response, and  b) a fiscal multiplier of one and so a missing intercept close to zero. I also discuss the robustness of this aggregation approach to empirically plausible violations of demand equivalence.]]></description><author>Christian K. Wolf</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29558</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Multipliers in the COVID19 Recession</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29531</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alan J. Auerbach, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Peter McCrory, Daniel Murphy.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> In response to the record-breaking COVID19 recession, many governments have adopted unprecedented fiscal stimuli. While countercyclical fiscal policy is effective in fighting conventional recessions, little is known about the effectiveness of fiscal policy in the current environment with widespread shelter-in-place (“lockdown”) policies and the associated considerable limits on economic activity. Using detailed regional variation in economic conditions, lockdown policies, and U.S. government spending, we document that the effects of government spending were stronger during the peak of the pandemic recession, but only in cities that were not subject to strong stay-at-home orders. We examine mechanisms that can account for our evidence and place our findings in the context of other recent evidence from microdata.]]></description><author>Alan J. Auerbach, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Peter McCrory, Daniel Murphy</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29531</guid></item><item><title>Unemployment Insurance in Macroeconomic Stabilization</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29505</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rohan Kekre.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> I study unemployment insurance (UI) in general equilibrium with incomplete markets, search frictions, and nominal rigidities.  An increase in generosity raises the aggregate demand for consumption if the unemployed have a higher marginal propensity to consume (MPC) than the employed or if agents precautionary save in light of future income risk.  This raises output and employment unless monetary policy raises the nominal interest rate.  In an analysis of the U.S. economy over 2008-2014, UI benefit extensions had a contemporaneous output multiplier around 1 or higher.  The unemployment rate would have been as much as 0.4pp higher absent these extensions.]]></description><author>Rohan Kekre</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29505</guid></item><item><title>A Temporary VAT Cut as Unconventional Fiscal Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We exploit the unexpected announcement of an immediate, temporary VAT cut in Germany in the second half of 2020 as a natural experiment to study the spending response to unconventional fiscal policy. We use survey and scanner data on households’ consumption expenditures and their perceived pass-through of the tax change into prices to quantify its effects. The temporary VAT cut led to a substantial relative increase in durable spending of 36% for individuals with a high perceived pass-through. Semi- and non-durable spending also increased. According to our preferred estimates, the VAT policy increased aggregate consumption spending by 34 billion Euros.]]></description><author>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</guid></item><item><title>The Debt Capacity of a Government</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Bernard Dumas, Paul Ehling, Chunyu Yang.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In a deterministic overlapping-generations economy with production and physical capital, the price of debt can be positive without any budget surpluses being in the offing, because debt incorporates a rational bubble. Yet the dynamics of debt remain a function of the dynamics of the primary budget deficit. As a way to study their joint behavior, we endogenize a structural deficit in the form of an underfunded social-security scheme. We define debt capacity as the level of debt that can be just sustained without a change of policy all the way to an unstable steady state. When it starts below the capacity, the debt converges to a stable steady state, in which the bubble is sustained. Above capacity the bubble unravels and the deficit cannot be financed. In several realistic scenarios occurring in economies, we calculate the needed policy response, which is the true "fiscal cost" of exceeding debt capacity.]]></description><author>Bernard Dumas, Paul Ehling, Chunyu Yang</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</guid></item><item><title>A Social Insurance Perspective on Pandemic Fiscal Policy: Implications for Unemployment Insurance and Hazard Pay</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper considers fiscal policy during the pandemic through the lens of optimal social insurance. We develop a simple framework to analyze how government taxes and transfers could mimic the insurance against pandemic income losses that people would like to have had. Permutations of the framework provide insight into how unemployment insurance should be structured, when and how much hazard pay is called for, and whether fiscal policy should aim just to redistribute income or also to stimulate aggregate demand during a pandemic. When we use the insights from the model to evaluate unemployment insurance measures taken during the pandemic, we find that some, but far from all, of the implications of the social insurance framework were followed. In the case of hazard pay, we find that the proposal for a national program (the never-implemented HEROES Act) was both broader and more generous than a social insurance perspective would call for. We suggest that the social insurance perspective on fiscal policy is likely to become increasingly relevant as pandemics and climate-related natural disasters become more common causes of unemployment and recessions.]]></description><author>Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</guid></item><item><title>The Fiscal and Welfare Effects of Policy Responses to the Covid-19 School Closures</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29398</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicola Fuchs-Schündeln, Dirk Krueger, André Kurmann, Etienne Lalé, Alexander Ludwig, Irina Popova.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Using a structural life-cycle model and data on school visits from Safegraph and school closures from Burbio, we quantify the heterogeneous impact of school closures during the Corona crisis on children affected at different ages and coming from households with different parental characteristics. Our data suggests that secondary schools were closed for in-person learning for longer periods than elementary schools (implying that younger children experienced less school closures than older children), and that private schools experienced shorter closures than public schools, and schools in poorer U.S. counties experienced shorter school closures. We then extend the structural life cycle model of private and public schooling investments studied in Fuchs-Schuendeln, Krueger, Ludwig and Popova (2021) to include the choice of parents whether to send their children to private schools, empirically discipline it with data on parental investments from the PSID, and then feed into the model the school closure measures from our empirical analysis to quantify the long-run consequences of the Covid-19 school closures on the cohorts of children currently in school. Future earnings- and welfare losses are largest for children that started public secondary schools at the onset of the Covid-19 crisis. Comparing children from the top- to children from the bottom quartile of the income distribution, welfare losses are ca. 0.8 percentage points larger for the poorer children if school closures were unrelated to income. Accounting for the longer school closures in richer counties reduces this gap by about 1/3. A policy intervention that extends schools by 3 months (6 weeks in the next two summers) generates significant welfare gains for the children and raises future tax approximately sufficient to pay for the cost of this schooling expansion.]]></description><author>Nicola Fuchs-Schündeln, Dirk Krueger, André Kurmann, Etienne Lalé, Alexander Ludwig, Irina Popova</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29398</guid></item><item><title>What Drives Variation in the U.S. Debt/Output Ratio? The Dogs that Didn't Bark</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29351</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhengyang Jiang, Hanno Lustig, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh, Mindy Z. Xiaolan.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> If the U.S. is on a fiscally sustainable path, then higher U.S. government debt/output ratios should reliably predict higher future surpluses or lower real returns on Treasurys. In the post-war sample, we find no evidence for this. Neither future cash flows nor discount rates account for the variation in the current debt/output ratio. Instead, the future debt/output ratio accounts for most of the variation. Systematic surplus forecast errors can account for part of these findings. Since the start of the GFC, surplus projections have anticipated a large fiscal correction that failed to materialize.]]></description><author>Zhengyang Jiang, Hanno Lustig, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh, Mindy Z. Xiaolan</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29351</guid></item><item><title>Outsourcing, Inequality and Aggregate Output</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Outsourced workers experience large wage declines, yet domestic outsourcing may raise aggregate productivity. To study this equity-efficiency trade-off, we contribute a framework in which firms either hire many imperfectly substitutable worker types in-house by posting wages along a job ladder, or rent labor services from contractors who hire in the same frictional labor markets. Three implications arise. First, more productive firms are more likely to outsource to save on higher wage premia. Second, outsourcing raises output at the firm level. Third, contractors endogenously locate at the bottom of the job ladder, implying that outsourced workers receive lower wages. Using firm-level instruments for outsourcing and revenue productivity, we find empirical support for all three predictions in French administrative data. After structurally estimating the model, we find that the rise in outsourcing in France between 1996 and 2007 raised aggregate output by 3% and reduced the labor share by 0.7 percentage points. A 9% minimum wage increase stabilizes the labor share and maintains two thirds of the output gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</guid></item><item><title>Macroprudential Policy during COVID-19: The Role of Policy Space</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Katharina Bergant, Kristin Forbes.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses the initial phase of the COVID-19 pandemic to examine how macroprudential frameworks developed over the past decade performed during a period of heightened financial and economic stress. It discusses a new measure of the macroprudential stance that better captures the intensity of different policies across countries and time. Then it shows that macroprudential policy has been used countercyclically—with stances tightened during the 2010’s and eased in response to COVID-19 by more than previous risk-off periods. Countries that tightened macroprudential policy more aggressively before COVID, as well as those that eased more during the pandemic, experienced less financial and economic stress. Countries’ ability to use macroprudential policy, however, was significantly constrained by the extent of existing “policy space”, i.e., by how aggressively policy was tightened before COVID-19. The use of macroprudential tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use other policy tools (such as fiscal policy, monetary policy, FX intervention, and capital flow management measures), and the use of other tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use macroprudential policy. This suggests that although macroprudential tools are being used countercyclically and should therefore help stabilize economies and financial markets, there appears to be an opportunity to better integrate the use of macroprudential tools with other policies in the future.]]></description><author>Katharina Bergant, Kristin Forbes</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Policy in the Age of COVID: Does it ‘Get in all of the Cracks?’</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, Ṣebnem Kalemli-Özcan, Veronika Penciakova, Nick Sander.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study the effects of fiscal policy in response to the COVID-19 pandemic at the firm, sector, country and global level. First, we estimate the impact of COVID-19 and policy responses on small and medium sized enterprise (SME) business failures. We combine firm-level financial data from 50 sectors in 27 countries, a detailed I-O network, real-time data on lockdown policies and mobility patterns, and a rich model of firm behavior that allows for several dimensions of heterogeneity. We find: (a) Absent government support, the failure rate of SMEs would have increased by 9 percentage points, significantly more so in emerging market economies (EMs). With policy support it only increased by 4.3 percentage points, and even decreased in advanced economies (AEs). (b) Fiscal policy was poorly targeted: most of the funds disbursed went to firms who did not need it. (c) Nevertheless, we find little evidence of the policy merely postponing mass business failures or creating many ‘zombie’ firms: failure rates rise only slightly in 2021 once policy support is removed. Next, we build a tractable global intertemporal general equilibrium I-O model with fiscal policy. We calibrate the model to 64 countries and 36 sectors. We find that: (d) a sizable share of the global economy is demand-constrained under COVID-19, especially so in EMs. (e) Globally, fiscal policy helped offset about 8% of the downturn in COVID, with a low ‘traditional’ fiscal multiplier. Yet it significantly reduced the share of demand- constrained sectors, preserving employment in these sectors. (f) Fiscal policy exerted small and negative spillovers to output in other countries but positive spillovers on employment. (g) A two-speed recovery would put significant upwards pressure on global interest rates which imposes an additional headwind on the EM recovery. (h) Corporate and sovereign spreads rise when global rates increase, suggesting that EM may face challenging external funding conditions as AEs economies normalize.]]></description><author>Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, Ṣebnem Kalemli-Özcan, Veronika Penciakova, Nick Sander</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</guid></item><item><title>Human Frictions in the Transmission of Economic Policies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Many consumers below the top of the distribution of a representative population by cognitive abilities barely react to  monetary and fiscal policies that aim to stimulate consumption and borrowing, even when they are financially unconstrained and despite substantial debt capacity. Differences in income, formal education levels, economic expectations, and a large set of registry-based demographics do not explain these facts. Heterogeneous cognitive abilities thus act as human frictions in the transmission of economic policies that operate through the household sector and might imply  redistribution from low- to high-cognitive-ability agents. We conclude by discussing how our findings inform the microfoundation of behavioral macroeconomic theory.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</guid></item><item><title>The Geography of Unemployment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Unemployment rates differ widely across local labor markets. I offer new empirical evidence that high local unemployment emerges because of elevated local job losing rates. Local employers, rather than local workers, account for most of spatial gaps in job stability. I then propose a theory in which spatial differences in job loss arise endogenously, due to the spatial sorting of heterogeneous employers across local labor markets.  Labor market frictions induce productive employers to over-value locating close to each other. The optimal policy incentivizes them to relocate to areas with high job losing rates, providing a rationale for commonly used place-based policies. I estimate the model using French administrative data. The estimated model accounts for over three fourths of the cross-sectional dispersion in unemployment rates, as well as for the respective contributions of job losing and job finding rates. Employers' inefficient location choices amplify spatial unemployment differentials five-fold. Both real-world and optimal place-based policies can yield sizable local and aggregate welfare gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</guid></item></channel></rss>