<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Monetary Policy</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Monetary Policy</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 13:50:33 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Firms' Inflation Expectations: New Evidence from France</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29376</link><description>Using a new survey of firms’ inflation expectations in France, we provide novel evidence about the measurement and formation of inflation expectations on the part of firms. First, French firms report inflation expectations with a smaller, but still positive, bias than households and display less disagreement. Second, we characterize the extent and manner in which the wording of questions matters for the measurement of firms’ inflation expectations. Third, we document whether and how the position of the respondent within the firm affects the provided responses. Fourth, because our survey measures firms’ expectations about aggregate and firm-level wage growth along with their inflation expectations, we are able to show that expectations about wages are even more condensed than firms’ inflation expectations and almost completely uncorrelated with them, indicating that firms perceive little link between price and wage inflation. Finally, an experimental treatment indicates that an exogenous change in firms’ inflation expectations has no effect on their aggregate wage expectations.</description><author>Frédérique Savignac, Erwan Gautier, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Olivier Coibion</author></item><item><title>Rethinking Exchange Rate Regimes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29347</link><description>This paper employs an updated algorithm and database for classifying exchange rate and anchor currency choice, to explore the evolution of the global exchange rate system, including parallel rates, capital controls and reserves. In line with a large recent literature, we find that the dollar has become ever-more central as the de facto anchor or reference currencies for much of the world. Our discussion encompasses the history of anchor currency choice, methods for classifying exchange rate regimes, a detailed discussion of the evolution of regimes, the growing substitution of reserves for capital controls as a tool for exchange rate stabilization, the modern Triffin dilemma, and the surprising recent trend decline in volatility of exchange rates at the core of the system. It concludes with issues surrounding the rise of China.</description><author>Ethan Ilzetzki, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author></item><item><title>Macroprudential Policy during COVID-19: The Role of Policy Space</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</link><description>This paper uses the initial phase of the COVID-19 pandemic to examine how macroprudential frameworks developed over the past decade performed during a period of heightened financial and economic stress. It discusses a new measure of the macroprudential stance that better captures the intensity of different policies across countries and time. Then it shows that macroprudential policy has been used countercyclically—with stances tightened during the 2010’s and eased in response to COVID-19 by more than previous risk-off periods. Countries that tightened macroprudential policy more aggressively before COVID, as well as those that eased more during the pandemic, experienced less financial and economic stress. Countries’ ability to use macroprudential policy, however, was significantly constrained by the extent of existing “policy space”, i.e., by how aggressively policy was tightened before COVID-19. The use of macroprudential tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use other policy tools (such as fiscal policy, monetary policy, FX intervention, and capital flow management measures), and the use of other tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use macroprudential policy. This suggests that although macroprudential tools are being used countercyclically and should therefore help stabilize economies and financial markets, there appears to be an opportunity to better integrate the use of macroprudential tools with other policies in the future.</description><author>Katharina Bergant, Kristin Forbes</author></item><item><title>Decrypting New Age International Capital Flows</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29337</link><description>This paper employs high frequency transactions data on the world’s oldest and most extensive centralized peer-to-peer Bitcoin market, which enables trade in the currencies of more than 135 countries.  We develop an algorithm that allows, with high probability, the detection of “crypto vehicle transactions” in which crypto currency is used to move capital across borders or facilitate domestic transactions. In contrast to previous work which has used “on-chain” data, our approach enables one to investigate parts of the vastly larger pool of “off-chain” transactions. We find that, as a conservative lower bound, over 7 percent of the 45 million trades on the exchange we explore represent crypto vehicle transactions in which Bitcoin is used to make payment in fiat currency.  Roughly 20 percent of these represent international capital flight/flows/remittances.  Although our work cannot be used to put a price on cryptocurrencies, it provides the first systematic quantitative evidence that the transactional use of cryptocurrencies constitutes a fundamental component of their value, at least under the current regulatory regime.</description><author>Clemens Graf von Luckner, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author></item><item><title>The Global Financial Cycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29327</link><description>We review the literature on the empirical characteristics of the global financial cycle and associated stylized facts on international capital flows, asset prices, risk aversion and liquidity in the financial system. We analyse the co-movements of global factors in asset prices and capital flows with commodity prices, international trade and world output as well as the sensitivity of different parts of the world to the Global Financial Cycle.  We present evidence of the causal effects of the monetary policies of the US Federal Reserve, the European Central Bank and of the People's Bank of China on the Global Financial Cycle.  We then assess whether the 2008 financial crisis has altered the transmission channels of monetary policies on the Global Financial Cycle. Finally, we discuss the theoretical modelling of the Global Financial Cycle and avenues for future research.
&lt;/p&gt;


              &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    function getCookieValue(name) {
      var cookies = "; " + document.cookie,
          parts = cookies.split("; " + name + "=");
      if (parts.length == 2) {
        return parts.pop().split(";").shift();
      }
    }
    fetch("/api/v1/auth/325305", { credentials: "include" })
      .then(
        function(response) {
          if (response.status !== 200) {
            console.log('Looks like there was a problem. Status Code: ' + response.status);
            return;
          }
          response.text().then(function(data) {
            var cookieValue = getCookieValue('STYXKEY_expecting_cookie'),
                userEmailInput = document.getElementById('user_email');

            document.getElementById('authorize-banner').innerHTML = data;

            if (userEmailInput) {
              userEmailInput.value = cookieValue ? cookieValue : '';
            }

            window.dataLayer = window.dataLayer || [];
            let can_view = Boolean(response.headers.get('X-NBER-CAN-VIEW-PAPER'));
            let sub_type = response.headers.get('X-NBER-SUBSCRIBER-TYPE');

            dataLayer.push({
              "event": "can_view_paper_response",
              "can_view_paper": can_view,
              "subscriber_type": sub_type,
            });
          });
        }
      )
      .catch(function(err) {
        console.log('Fetch Error :-S', err);
      });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;div id="authorize-banner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="accordion-set"&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;div class="accordion"&gt;
          &lt;button class="accordion__title js-accordion" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="accordion-body-guid1" id="accordion-button-guid1"&gt;Acknowledgements and Disclosures&lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;div class="accordion__body" id="accordion-body-guid1" aria-labelledby="accordion-button-guid1" style="display: none;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This paper has been prepared for the Handbook of International Economics, Volume V, edited by Gita Gopinath, Elhanan Helpman and Kenneth Rogoff. We are grateful to the editors, to Sebnem Kalemli-Ozcan and Livio Stracca (discussants) and to other participants at the International Macroeconomic Handbook Conference for helpful comments and discussions. Rey is grateful to the ERC for funding (Advanced Grant 695722). The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the Bank of England or any of its Committees, or of the National Bureau of Economic Research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
              &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/silvia_mirandaagrippino"&gt;Silvia Miranda-Agrippino&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
I declare that I have not benefited from any additional sources of funding for this research, and have no material outside financial relationships that may relate to this research.</description><author>Silvia Miranda-Agrippino, Hélène Rey</author></item><item><title>Low Inflation Bends the Phillips Curve around the World</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29323</link><description>This paper finds strong support for a Phillips curve that becomes nonlinear when inflation is “low”—which our baseline model defines as less than 3 percent. The nonlinear curve is steep when output is above potential (slack is negative), but flat when output is below potential (slack is positive), so that further increases in economic slack have little effect on inflation. This finding is consistent with evidence of downward nominal wage and price rigidity. When inflation is high, the Phillips curve is linear and relatively steep. These results are robust to placing the threshold between the high and low inflation regimes at 2, 3, or 4 percent inflation or for a threshold based on country-specific medians of inflation. In this nonlinear model, international factors play a large role in explaining headline inflation (albeit less so for core inflation), a role that has been increasing since the global financial crisis.</description><author>Kristin Forbes, Joseph Gagnon, Christopher G. Collins</author></item><item><title>Demand Composition and the Strength of Recoveries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29304</link><description>We argue that recoveries from demand-driven recessions with expenditure cuts concentrated in services or non-durables will tend to be weaker than recoveries from recessions more biased towards durables. Intuitively, the smaller the bias towards more durable goods, the less the recovery is buffeted by pent-up demand. We show that, in a standard multi-sector business-cycle model, this prediction holds if and only if, following an aggregate demand shock to all categories of spending (e.g., a monetary shock), expenditure on more durable goods reverts back faster. This testable condition receives ample support in U.S. data. We then use (i) a semi-structural shift-share and (ii) a structural model to quantify this effect of varying demand composition on recovery dynamics, and find it to be large. We also discuss implications for optimal stabilization policy.</description><author>Martin Beraja, Christian K. Wolf</author></item><item><title>Human Frictions in the Transmission of Economic Policies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</link><description>Many consumers below the top of the distribution of a representative population by cognitive abilities barely react to  monetary and fiscal policies that aim to stimulate consumption and borrowing, even when they are financially unconstrained and despite substantial debt capacity. Differences in income, formal education levels, economic expectations, and a large set of registry-based demographics do not explain these facts. Heterogeneous cognitive abilities thus act as human frictions in the transmission of economic policies that operate through the household sector and might imply  redistribution from low- to high-cognitive-ability agents. We conclude by discussing how our findings inform the microfoundation of behavioral macroeconomic theory.</description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber</author></item><item><title>Diverse Policy Committees Can Reach Underrepresented Groups</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</link><description>Increasing the diversity of policy committees has taken center stage worldwide, but whether and why diverse committees are more effective is still unclear. In a randomized control trial that varies the salience of female and minority representation on the Federal Reserve’s monetary policy committee, the FOMC, we test whether diversity affects how Fed information influences consumers’ subjective beliefs. Women and Black respondents form unemployment expectations more in line with FOMC forecasts and trust the Fed more after this intervention. Women are also more likely to acquire Fed-related information when associated with a female official. White men, who are overrepresented on the FOMC, do not react negatively. Heterogeneous taste for diversity can explain these patterns better than homophily. Our results suggest more diverse policy committees are better able to reach underrepresented groups without inducing negative reactions by others, thereby enhancing the effectiveness of policy communication and public trust in the institution.</description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Andreas Fuster, Michael Weber</author></item><item><title>Measuring Market Expectations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29232</link><description>Asset prices are a valuable source of information about financial market participants' expectations about key macroeconomic variables. However, the presence of time-varying risk premia requires an adjustment of market prices to obtain the market's rational assessment of future price and policy developments. This paper reviews empirical approaches for recovering market-based expectations. It starts by laying out the two canonical modeling frameworks that form the backbone for estimating risk premia and highlights the proliferation of risk pricing factors that result in a wide range of different asset-price-based expectation measures. It then describes a key methodological innovation to evaluate the empirical plausibility of risk premium estimates and to identify the most accurate market-based expectation measure. The usefulness of this general approach is illustrated for price expectations in the global oil market. Then, the paper provides an overview of the body of empirical evidence for monetary policy and inflation expectations with a special emphasis on market-specific characteristics that complicate the quest for the best possible market-based expectation measure. Finally, it discusses a number of economic applications where market expectations play a key role for evaluating economic models, guiding policy analysis, and deriving shock measures.</description><author>Christiane Baumeister</author></item><item><title>Stabilization with Fiscal Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29226</link><description>I reconsider the long-standing consensus view that macroeconomic stabilization should rely on monetary policy, not fiscal policy. I use an analytically tractable heterogeneous agent New Keynesian (HANK) model that is parameterized so as to admit a bubble in public debt. In this context, I show that it is possible to stabilize either inflation or output in response to aggregate shocks by varying only fiscal policy (that is, lump-sum uniform transfers). In contrast, when the public debt bubble is large, it is impossible to stabilize either inflation or output by varying only interest rates (monetary policy). The theoretical analysis implies that, in the presence of a large public debt bubble, fiscal policy is a more reliable stabilization tool than monetary policy.</description><author>Narayana R. Kocherlakota</author></item><item><title>Market Freezes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29210</link><description>During the financial crisis apparently centralized markets continued to function while trade in OTC markets froze. We use search-and-bargaining theory to ascertain conditions that allow trade to temporarily freeze in decentralized markets, focusing on the roles of liquidity and self-fulfilling prophecies. We show standard models can have recurrent, belief-driven hot and cold spells, but not freezes and thaws. A simple specification that has freezes assumes negative returns. A more realistic one incorporates information frictions (costly asset-quality verification). Another uses different frictions to get credit freezes. We also discuss policy implications, and go into detail on the nature of OTC markets.</description><author>Chao Gu, Guido Menzio, Randall Wright, Yu Zhu</author></item></channel></rss>