<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Antitrust</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Antitrust</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 16:25:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Privatization of Public Goods: Evidence from the Sanitation Sector in Senegal</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29295</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Privatization of a public good (the management of sewage treatment centers in Dakar, Senegal) leads to an increase in the productivity of downstream sewage dumping companies and a decrease in downstream prices of the services they provide to households. We use the universe of legal dumps of sanitation waste from May 2009 to November 2018 to show that legal dumping increased substantially following privatization–on average an increase of 61.7%, or an increase of about 14,000 cubic meters each month. This is due to increased productivity of all trucks, not just those associated with the company managing the treatment centers. Household-level survey data shows that prices of legal sanitary dumping decreased by ten percent following privatization, and DHS data show that diarrhea rates among children under five decreased in Dakar relative to secondary cities in Senegal following privatization with no similar effect on respiratory illness as a placebo.]]></description><author>Joshua W. Deutschmann, Jared E. Gars, Jean-François Houde, Molly Lipscomb, Laura A. Schechter</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29295</guid></item><item><title>Hub and Spoke Cartels: Theory and Evidence from the Grocery Industry</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29253</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Numerous recently uncovered cartels operated along the supply chain, with firms at one end facilitating collusion at the other – hub-and-spoke arrangements. These cartels are hard to rationalize because they induce double marginalization and higher costs. We examine Canada’s alleged bread cartel and provide the first comprehensive analysis of hub-and-spoke collusion. We make three contributions: i) Using court documents and pricing data we provide evidence that collusion existed at both ends of the supply chain, ii) we show that collusion was effective, increasing inflation by about 40% and iii) we provide a model explaining why this form of collusion arose.]]></description><author>Robert Clark, Ignatius Horstmann, Jean-François Houde</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29253</guid></item><item><title>Harms of AI</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29247</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This essay discusses several potential economic, political and social costs of the current path of AI technologies. I argue that if AI continues to be deployed along its current trajectory and remains unregulated, it may produce various social, economic and political harms. These include: damaging competition, consumer privacy and consumer choice; excessively automating work, fueling inequality, inefficiently pushing down wages, and failing to improve worker productivity; and damaging political discourse, democracy's most fundamental lifeblood. Although there is no conclusive evidence suggesting that these costs are imminent or substantial, it may be useful to understand them before they are fully realized and become harder or even impossible to reverse, precisely because of AI's promising and wide-reaching potential. I also suggest that these costs are not inherent to the nature of AI technologies, but are related to how they are being used and developed at the moment - to empower corporations and governments against workers and citizens. As a result, efforts to limit and reverse these costs may need to rely on regulation and policies to redirect AI research. Attempts to contain them just by promoting competition may be insufficient.]]></description><author>Daron Acemoglu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29247</guid></item><item><title>Markups and Fixed Costs in Generic and Off-Patent Pharmaceutical Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29206</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> There is wide dispersion in pharmaceutical prices across countries with comparable quality standards. Under monopoly, off-patent and generic drug prices are at least four times higher in the United States than in comparable English-speaking high income countries. With five or more competitors, off-patent drug prices are similar or lower. Our analysis shows that differential US markups are largely driven by the market power of drug suppliers and not due to wholesale intermediaries or pharmacies. Furthermore, we show that the traditional mechanism of reducing market power – free entry – is limited because implied entry costs are substantially higher in the US.]]></description><author>Sharat Ganapati, Rebecca McKibbin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29206</guid></item><item><title>Collusion, Mergers, and Related Antitrust Issues</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29175</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This survey examines recent developments in economic research relating to antitrust, paying specific attention to research in the areas of collusion and merger enforcement.   Research relating to both collusion and mergers has made significant advances in the last twenty years. With respect to collusion, this includes important theoretical and empirical work on the sustainability, structure, and impact of collusive schemes. With respect to mergers, this includes important work on the impact of enforcement institutions, both theoretical and empirical work on unilateral effects, and theoretical work on the selection of which mergers get proposed to antitrust agencies and optimal policy in the face of that selection. A feature of recent research is the increasing complementarity between empirical work (ranging from observational studies to model-based measurement) and theoretical work in advancing our understanding of collusive and merger-related phenomena.]]></description><author>John Asker, Volker Nocke</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29175</guid></item></channel></rss>