<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Country Studies</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Country Studies</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 11:17:23 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Gender Gap in Preferences: Evidence from 45,397 Facebook Interests</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> This paper uses information on the frequency of 45,397 Facebook interests to study how the difference in preferences between men and women changes with a country's degree of gender equality. For preference dimensions that are systematically biased toward the same gender across the globe, differences between men and women are larger in more gender-equal countries. In contrast, for preference dimensions with a gender bias that varies across countries, the opposite holds. This finding takes an important step toward reconciling evolutionary psychology and social role theory as they relate to gender.]]></description><author>Ángel Cuevas, Rubén Cuevas, Klaus Desmet, Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</guid></item><item><title>The Plant-Level View of an Industrial Policy: The Korean Heavy Industry Drive of 1973</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29252</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Does industrial policy work? This is a subject of long-standing debates among economists and policymakers. Using newly digitized microdata, we evaluate the Korean government's policy that promoted heavy and chemical industries between 1973 and 1979 by cutting taxes and building new industrial complexes for them. We show that output, input use, and labor productivity of the targeted industries and regions grew significantly faster than those of non-targeted ones. While the plant-level total factor productivity also grew faster in targeted industries and regions, the misallocation of resources within them got significantly worse, especially among the entrants, so that the total factor productivity at the industry-region level did not increase relative to the non-targeted industries and regions. In addition, we provide new evidence on how industrial policy reshapes the economy: (i) The establishment size distribution of targeted industries and regions shifted to the right with thicker tails due to the entry of large establishments and (ii) the targeted industries became more important in the economy's input-output structure in the sense that their output multipliers increased significantly more.]]></description><author>Minho Kim, Munseob Lee, Yongseok Shin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29252</guid></item><item><title>Bundling Stress Tolerant Seeds and Insurance for More Resilient and Productive Small-scale Agriculture</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29234</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Risk often inhibits on-farm investment by smallholder farmers. Recent evidence indicates that index insurance and stress tolerant seeds can separately and partially offset this risk effect. In this study, we explore whether the complementarities between these two risk management technologies can be harnessed to underwrite a resilient, high productivity small farm sector. Utilizing a multi-year randomized control trial that spanned two countries and exploits natural variation in weather shocks, we find that drought tolerant maize seeds mitigate the impact of mid-season drought. Compared to farms in control villages, where shocks have persistent effects that reduce future investment and productivity, those with access to both drought tolerant seeds and multi-peril index insurance show greater resilience and immediately bounce back from shocks. Experiential learning is key to realizing this resilience effect: Farmers who experienced shocks intensify their subsequent use of the technologies and exhibit what we call resilience-plus, while those who did not experience shocks disadopt. Together these findings showcase important complementarities between these risk mitigating technologies and the crucial role learning plays in tapping their potential stochastic and dynamic benefits to small farmers.]]></description><author>Stephen R. Boucher, Michael R. Carter, Jon Einar Flatnes, Travis J. Lybbert, Jonathan G. Malacarne, Paswel Marenya, Laura A. Paul</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29234</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Returns and the Evolution of Cognitive Skills: Theory and Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29135</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> A large literature in cognitive science studies the puzzling "Flynn effect" of rising fluid intelligence (reasoning skill) in rich countries. We develop an economic model in which a cohort's mix of skills is determined by different skills' relative returns in the labor market and by the technology for producing skills. We estimate the model using administrative data from Sweden. Combining data from exams taken at military enlistment with earnings records from the tax register, we document an increase in the relative labor market return to logical reasoning skill as compared to vocabulary knowledge. The estimated model implies that changes in labor market returns explain 36 percent of the measured increase in reasoning skill, and can also explain the decline in knowledge. An original survey of parents, an analysis of trends in school curricula, and an analysis of occupational characteristics show evidence of increasing emphasis on reasoning as compared to knowledge.]]></description><author>Santiago Hermo, Miika M. Päällysaho, David G. Seim, Jesse M. Shapiro</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29135</guid></item></channel></rss>