<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Labor Supply and Demand</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Labor Supply and Demand</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 09:53:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Business Cycles and Healthcare Employment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29799</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Erkmen G. Aslim, Shin-Yi Chou, Kuhelika De.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Is healthcare employment recession proof? We examine the hypothesis that healthcare employment is stable across the business cycle. We explicitly distinguish between negative aggregate demand and supply shocks in studying how healthcare employment responds to recessions, and show that this response depends largely on the type of the exogenous shock triggering the recession. We find that healthcare employment responds procyclically to demand-induced recessions; and the reduction is driven by layoffs and discharges rather than voluntary quits. In evaluating additional mechanisms, we find evidence of a reduction in real personal healthcare expenditures resulting from an adverse demand shock. By contrast, we find that healthcare employment is fairly stable and even responds countercyclically to supply-induced recessions, suggesting compositional changes such as downskilling particularly in nursing sectors. Our findings establish that employment responses during economic downturns are heterogeneous across healthcare sub-sectors. More generally, by isolating the impact of the structural demand shock from supply shock on healthcare employment, we provide new empirical evidence that healthcare employment is not recession proof.]]></description><author>Erkmen G. Aslim, Shin-Yi Chou, Kuhelika De</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29799</guid></item><item><title>Asset Prices and Unemployment Fluctuations: A Resolution of the Unemployment Volatility Puzzle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29794</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Patrick J. Kehoe, Pierlauro Lopez, Virgiliu Midrigan, Elena Pastorino.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Recent work has demonstrated that existing solutions of the unemployment volatility puzzle are at odds with the procylicality of the opportunity cost of employment, the cyclicality of wages, and the volatility of risk-free rates. We propose a model of business cycles that is immune to these critiques by incorporating two key features. First, we allow for preferences that generate time-varying risk over the business cycle to account for observed fluctuations in asset prices. Second, we introduce human capital acquisition consistent with the evidence on how wages grow with experience in the labor market. Our model reproduces the observed fluctuations in unemployment because hiring a worker is a risky investment with long-duration returns. As in the data, the price of risk in our model sharply increases in recessions. The benefit from hiring new workers therefore greatly declines, leading to a large decrease in job vacancies and an increase in unemployment of the same magnitude as in the data. We show that our results extend to versions of the model that include physical capital, a life cycle for workers, and alternative preference structures common in the asset-pricing literature.]]></description><author>Patrick J. Kehoe, Pierlauro Lopez, Virgiliu Midrigan, Elena Pastorino</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29794</guid></item><item><title>The Long-Run Labor Market Effects of the Canada-U.S. Free Trade Agreement</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29793</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Brian K. Kovak, Peter M. Morrow.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> This paper assesses the long-run effects of the 1988 Canada-U.S. Free Trade Agreement (CUSFTA) on the Canadian labor market using matched longitudinal administrative data for the years 1984-2004. We simultaneously examine the labor market effects of increased export expansion and import competition, generally finding adverse effects of Canadian tariff cuts and favorable effects of U.S. cuts, though both effects are small.   Workers initially employed in industries that experienced larger Canadian tariff concessions exhibit a heightened probability of layoffs at large firms, but little impact on long-run cumulative earnings. Lower earnings and years worked at the initial employer are offset by gains in other manufacturing industries, construction, and services.  Canadian workers quickly transitioned out of industries facing import competition, with the majority of industry adjustment occurring among new entrants to the labor market.]]></description><author>Brian K. Kovak, Peter M. Morrow</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29793</guid></item><item><title>Has the Willingness to Work Fallen during the Covid Pandemic?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29784</link><description><![CDATA[<i>R. Jason Faberman, Andreas I. Mueller, Ayşegül Şahin.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We examine the effect of the Covid pandemic on willingness to work along both the extensive and intensive margins of labor supply. Special survey questions in the Job Search Supplement of the Survey of Consumer Expectations (SCE) allow us to elicit information about individuals’ desired work hours for the 2013-2021 period. Using these questions, along with workers’ actual labor market participation, we construct a labor market underutilization measure, the Aggregate Hours Gap (AHG), following Faberman et al. (2020). The AHG captures changes in labor market underutilization for the full population along both the extensive and intensive margins using data on desired work hours as a measure of their potential labor supply. We find that the sharp increase in the AHG during the Covid pandemic essentially disappeared by the end of 2021. We also document a sharp decline in desired work hours during the pandemic that persists through the end of 2021 and is roughly double the drop in the labor force participation rate. Ignoring the decline in desired hours overstates the degree of underutilization by 2.5 percentage points (12.5%). Our findings suggest that, as of 2021Q4, the labor market is tighter than suggested by the unemployment rate and the adverse labor supply effect of the pandemic is more pronounced than implied by the labor force participation rate. These discrepancies underscore the importance of taking into account the intensive margin for both labor market underutilization and potential labor supply.]]></description><author>R. Jason Faberman, Andreas I. Mueller, Ayşegül Şahin</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29784</guid></item><item><title>Human Capital Reallocation Across Firms: Evidence from Idiosyncratic Shocks</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29782</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Erik P. Gilje, Jérôme P. Taillard, Linghang Zeng.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We study human capital reallocation following firm-specific idiosyncratic shocks. Theory offers diverging predictions as to whether human capital gets reallocated to its most productive use following these shocks. To empirically test these predictions, we focus on relegation battles in the English Premier League. This setting offers well identified idiosyncratic shocks as well as both individual-level and firm-level productivity metrics. We find that human capital exits firms after a negative idiosyncratic shock. Specifically, we find that more productive players move to more productive clubs and maintain their long-term productivity. They get replaced with lower productivity players. Overall, our results show that in a setting with highly transferable skills, idiosyncratic shocks lead to a reallocation of human capital that moves an industry towards a better overall match between individual-level and firm-level productivity.]]></description><author>Erik P. Gilje, Jérôme P. Taillard, Linghang Zeng</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29782</guid></item><item><title>Integrating Refugees by Addressing Labor Shortages? A Policy Evaluation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29781</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Mette Foged, Janis Kreuder, Giovanni Peri.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We evaluate the effect on newly arrived refugees' employment of a policy, introduced in Denmark in 2013, that matched refugees to occupations with local labor shortages after basic training for those jobs. Leveraging the staggered roll-out across municipalities, we find that the policy increased employment by 5-6 percentage points one year after arrival and 10 percentage points two years after. The policy was especially effective for male refugees and refugees with some secondary education. The findings suggest that this type of policy could alleviate long-term labor shortages and integrate low-skilled immigrants, while having minimal competition effects on natives.]]></description><author>Mette Foged, Janis Kreuder, Giovanni Peri</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29781</guid></item><item><title>Gifted Children Programs’ Short and Long-Term Impact: Higher Education, Earnings, and the Knowledge-Economy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29779</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Victor Lavy, Yoav Goldstein.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We estimate the effects of gifted children programs (GCP) in high schools in Israel. We selected a comparison group of equally gifted students from other cities where GCP was not offered at the time. Based on administrative data, we follow 22 cohorts and measure treatment effects on outcomes, ranging from high school to the labor market in their 30s and 40s. We find tiny impact on academic achievements in high school, in contrast to the abundance of educational resources enjoyed by GCP participants. In the longer run, we find meaningful effects of GCP on higher education attainment. GCP participants study more math, computer, and physical sciences but engage less in engineering programs. The net effect on STEM degrees is, therefore, zero. However, a much higher share of GCP participants graduated with two STEM majors. This evidence suggests that GCP enhances the impact of “multipotentiality,” which characterizes many gifted adolescents. The effect on getting a Ph.D. is positive, too. Lastly, we find no effect of GCP on employment and earnings. Nor do we find that GCP participants work more than other equally talented children in the knowledge economy. These results are very similar for females and males gifted children.]]></description><author>Victor Lavy, Yoav Goldstein</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29779</guid></item><item><title>Conditional Cash Transfers for Education</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29758</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sandra García, Juan Saavedra.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> This chapter reviews the extensive literature to date on CCTs for education. Section 2 provides background on the origins and expansion of CCTs globally, and describes basic design features and variation in characteristics across programs. Section 3 presents a theory of change and an economic household decision-making model highlighting key comparative statics and empirical predictions for the introduction of an education CCT program. Section 4 discusses key methodological challenges in evaluating the impacts of education CCTs. Section 5 integrates and updates the extensive evidence to date on the impacts of education CCTs on various outcome domains over the life cycle, and provides the most comprehensive view to date on learning impacts by meta-analyzing new evidence from more than 30 studies—substantially more than prior reviews of the literature. Section 6 reviews the evidence on indirect and general equilibrium effects. Section 7 presents a simple model of costs commonly used in the literature, which we extend to analyze cost-effectiveness for a subset of programs. Section 8 concludes and highlights open questions for future research.]]></description><author>Sandra García, Juan Saavedra</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29758</guid></item><item><title>Children and the US Social Safety Net: Balancing Disincentives for Adults and Benefits for Children</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29754</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anna Aizer, Hilary W. Hoynes, Adriana Lleras-Muney.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Economic research on the safety net has evolved significantly over time, moving away from a near exclusive focus on the negative incentive effects of means-tested assistance on employment, earnings, marriage and fertility to include examination of the potential positive benefits of such programs to children.  Initially, this research on benefits to children focused on short run impacts, but as we accumulated knowledge about skill production and better data became available, the research evolved further to include important long run economic outcomes such as employment, earnings and mortality.  Once the positive long-run benefits to children are considered, many safety net programs are cost-effective.  However, the current government practice of limiting the time horizon for cost-benefit calculations of major policy initiatives reduces the influence of the most current economic research on the long run benefits. We conclude with a discussion of why the rate of child poverty in the US is still higher than most OECD countries and how research on children and the safety net can better inform policy-making going forward.]]></description><author>Anna Aizer, Hilary W. Hoynes, Adriana Lleras-Muney</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29754</guid></item><item><title>Valuing the Time of the Self-Employed</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29752</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel J. Agness, Travis Baseler, Sylvain Chassang, Pascaline Dupas, Erik Snowberg.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> People’s value for their own time is a key input in evaluating public policies: evaluations should account for time taken away from work or leisure as a result of policy. Using rich choice data collected from farming households in western Kenya, we show that households exhibit non-transitive preferences consistent with behavioral features such as loss aversion and self-serving bias. As a result, neither market wages nor standard valuation techniques (such as the Becker-DeGroot-Marschak—BDM—mechanism of Becker et al., 1964) correctly measure participants’ value of time. Using a structural model, we identify the mix of behavioral features driving our choice data. We find that these features distort choices when exchanging cash either for time or for goods. Our model estimates suggest that valuing the time of the self-employed at 60% of the market wage is a reasonable rule of thumb.]]></description><author>Daniel J. Agness, Travis Baseler, Sylvain Chassang, Pascaline Dupas, Erik Snowberg</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29752</guid></item><item><title>How Tight are U.S. Labor Markets?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29739</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alex Domash, Lawrence H. Summers.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Since the outset of the Covid-19 pandemic, labor market indicators that traditionally move together have been sending different signals about the degree of slack in the U.S. labor market. While some indicators on the supply-side, such as the prime-age employment-to-population ratio, suggest that there is still some slack in the labor market, other indicators on the demand-side, such as the job vacancy rate and the quits rate, imply that the labor market is already very tight. In light of these divergent signals, this paper compares alternative labor market indicators as predictors of wage inflation. Using national time series and state cross-section data, we find (i) unemployment is a better predictor of wage inflation than non-employment and (ii) vacancy rates and quit rates have substantial predictive power for wage inflation. We highlight the fact that vacancy and quit rates currently experienced in the United States correspond to a degree of labor market tightness previously associated with sub-2 percent unemployment rates. Finally, we show that predicted firm-side unemployment has dominant explanatory power with respect to subsequent inflation. Our results, along with a cursory analysis of labor force participation information, suggest that labor market tightness is likely to contribute significantly to inflationary pressure in the United States for some time to come.]]></description><author>Alex Domash, Lawrence H. Summers</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29739</guid></item><item><title>The Unequal Cost of Job Loss across Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29727</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Antoine Bertheau, Edoardo Maria Acabbi, Cristina Barcelo, Andreas Gulyas, Stefano Lombardi, Raffaele Saggio.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We document the consequences of losing a job across countries using a harmonized research design. Workers in Denmark and Sweden experience the lowest earnings declines following job displacement, while workers in Italy, Spain, and Portugal experience losses three times as high. French and Austrian workers face earnings losses somewhere in-between. Key to these differences is that Southern European workers are less likely to find employment following displacement. Loss of employer-specific wage premiums accounts for 40% to 95% of within-country wage declines. The use of active labor market policies predicts a significant portion of the cross-country heterogeneity in earnings losses.]]></description><author>Antoine Bertheau, Edoardo Maria Acabbi, Cristina Barcelo, Andreas Gulyas, Stefano Lombardi, Raffaele Saggio</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29727</guid></item><item><title>Empirical Strategies in Economics: Illuminating the Path from Cause to Effect</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29726</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Angrist.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> The view that empirical strategies in economics should be transparent and credible now goes almost without saying. The local average treatment effects (LATE) framework for causal inference helped make this so. The LATE theorem tells us for whom particular instrumental variables (IV) and regression discontinuity estimates are valid. This lecture uses several empirical examples, mostly involving charter and exam schools, to highlight the value of LATE. A surprising exclusion restriction, an assumption central to the LATE interpretation of IV estimates, is shown to explain why enrollment at Chicago exam schools reduces student achievement. I also make two broader points: IV exclusion restrictions formalize commitment to clear and consistent explanations of reduced-form causal effects; compelling applications demonstrate the power of simple empirical strategies to generate new causal knowledge.]]></description><author>Joshua Angrist</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29726</guid></item><item><title>The Transformation of Self Employment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29725</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Innessa Colaiacovo, Margaret G. Dalton, Sari Pekkala Kerr, William R. Kerr.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Over the past half-century, while self-employment has consistently accounted for around one in ten of the United States workforce, its composition has changed. Since 1970, industries with high startup capital requirements have declined from 53% of self-employment to 23%. This same time period also witnessed declines in "hometown" local entrepreneurship and the probability of the self-employed being among top earners. Using 2016 data, we show that high startup capital requirements are linked with lower profitability at small scales. The transition away from high startup capital industries appears most closely linked to changes in small business production functions and less due to advantageous reallocation to other opportunities, growth in returns-to-scale among large businesses, or a worsening of financing conditions and debt levels.]]></description><author>Innessa Colaiacovo, Margaret G. Dalton, Sari Pekkala Kerr, William R. Kerr</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29725</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Fluidity and Human Capital Accumulation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29698</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Niklas Engbom.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Using panel data from 23 OECD countries, I document that wages grow more over the life-cycle in countries where job-to-job mobility is more common. A life-cycle theory of job shopping and accumulation of skills on the job highlights that a more fluid labor market allows workers to faster relocate to jobs where they can better use their skills, incentivizing accumulation of skills. Lower labor market fluidity reduces life-cycle wage growth by 20 percent and aggregate labor productivity by nine percent across the OECD relative to the US. I derive a set of testable predictions for training and confront them with comparable cross-country training data, finding support for the theory.]]></description><author>Niklas Engbom</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29698</guid></item><item><title>Robots and Firm Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29676</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Efraim Benmelech, Michal Zator.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Automation technologies, and robots in particular, are thought to be massively displacing workers and transforming the future of work. We study firm investment in automation using cross-country data on robotization as well as administrative data from Germany with information on firm-level automation decisions. Our findings suggest that the impact of robots on firms has been limited. First, investment in robots is small and highly concentrated in a few industries, accounting for less than 0.30% of aggregate expenditures on equipment. Second, recent increases in robotization do not resemble the explosive growth observed for IT technologies in the past, and are driven mostly by catching-up of developing countries. Third, robot adoption by firms endogenously responds to labor scarcity, alleviating potential displacement of existing workers. Fourth, firms that invest in robots increase employment, while total employment effect in exposed industries and regions is negative, but modest in magnitude. We contrast robots with other digital technologies that are more widespread. Their importance in firms’ investment is significantly higher, and their link with labor markets, while sharing some similarities with robots, appears markedly different.]]></description><author>Efraim Benmelech, Michal Zator</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29676</guid></item><item><title>Slowing Women's Labor Force Participation: The Role of Income Inequality</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29675</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefania Albanesi, María José Prados.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The entry of married women into the labor force and the rise in women's relative wages are amongst the most notable economic developments of the twentieth century. The growth in these indicators was particularly pronounced in the 1970s and 1980s, but it stalled since the early 1990s, especially for college graduates. In this paper, we argue that the discontinued growth in female labor supply and wages since the 1990s is a consequence of growing inequality. Our hypothesis is that the growth in top incomes for men generated a negative income effect on the labor supply of their spouses, which reduced their participation and wages. We show that the slowdown in participation and wage growth was concentrated among women married to highly educated and high income husbands, whose earnings grew dramatically over this period. We then develop a model of household labor supply with returns to experience that qualitatively reproduces this effect. A calibrated version of the model can account for a large fraction of the decline relative to trend in married women's participation in 1995-2005 particularly for college women. The model can also account for the rise in the gender wage gap for college graduates relative to trend in the same period.]]></description><author>Stefania Albanesi, María José Prados</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29675</guid></item><item><title>Understanding Rural Households’ Time Use in a Developing Setting: Validating a Low-Cost Time Use Module</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29671</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Erica M. Field, Rohini Pande, Natalia Rigol, Simone G. Schaner, Elena M. Stacy, Charity M. Troyer Moore.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Time use data facilitate deeper understanding of individual labor supply choices, especially for women, who are more likely to engage in unpaid care and home production. However, traditional time use data collection methods are time-consuming, expensive and susceptible to significant attrition. To address these concerns, we develop an abbreviated, low-cost time use survey module designed for low-literacy populations. It captures contextually-determined broad time use categories of interest to researchers - in our case, time allocations across market work, household labor, and leisure. Using survey experiments in the field, we show that, relative to the widely-used assisted diary approach, the new module is lower cost and relatively more accurate in capturing individuals’ average time use. Its primary shortcomings are its limited ability to capture short duration activities and simultaneous activities. Using the example of passive childcare, we show how module design can provide accurate information on multitasking for an identified category of interest.]]></description><author>Erica M. Field, Rohini Pande, Natalia Rigol, Simone G. Schaner, Elena M. Stacy, Charity M. Troyer Moore</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29671</guid></item><item><title>Public School Access or Stay-at-Home Partner: Factors Mitigating the Adverse Effects of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Academic Parents</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29668</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tatyana Deryugina, Olga Shurchkov, Jenna E. Stearns.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic created unexpected and prolonged disruptions to childcare access. Using survey evidence on time use by academic researchers before and after the pandemic, we analyze the extent to which greater access to either school-based or partner-provided childcare mitigated the severe disruptions to research observed among parents during COVID-19. We find that access to public schools offset the research time loss to a greater extent among mothers of young children relative to fathers, narrowing the emerging post-pandemic gender gap. Having a stay-at-home partner reduced the disruptions to research time equally for both genders.]]></description><author>Tatyana Deryugina, Olga Shurchkov, Jenna E. Stearns</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29668</guid></item><item><title>Health Insurance for Whom? The ‘Spill-up’ Effects of Children’s Health Insurance on Mothers</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29661</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel S. Grossman ⓡ, Sebastian Tello-Trillo ⓡ, Barton Willage ⓡ.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> A rich literature documents the benefits of social safety net programs for children. This paper focuses on an unexplored margin: how children’s programs impact parents’ well-being. We explore changes in children’s public health insurance and its effects on parents’ economic and behavioral outcomes. Using a simulated eligibility for Medicaid eligibility expansions in the 1980s and 1990s, we isolate variation in children’s Medicaid eligibility due to changes in government policies. We find that increases in children’s Medicaid eligibility increases the likelihood a mother is married, decreases her labor market participation, and reduces her smoking and alcohol consumption. Our findings suggest improved maternal well-being as measured by the Center for Epidemiological Studies-Depression score, a proxy for mental health. These results uncover a new link that provides an important mechanism, parental well-being, for interpreting the literature’s findings on the long-term, short-term, and intergenerational effects of Medicaid coverage.]]></description><author>Daniel S. Grossman ⓡ, Sebastian Tello-Trillo ⓡ, Barton Willage ⓡ</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29661</guid></item><item><title>Schools, Job Flexibility, and Married Women's Labor Supply: Evidence From the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29660</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin Hansen, Joseph J. Sabia, Jessamyn Schaller.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This study explores the effect of school reopenings during the COVID-19 pandemic on married women's labor supply. We proxy for in-person attendance at US K-12 schools using smartphone data from Safegraph and measure female employment, hours, and remote work using the Current Population Survey. Difference-in-differences estimates show that K-12 reopenings are associated with significant increases in employment and hours among married women with school-aged children, with no measurable effects on labor supply in comparison groups. Employment effects of school reopenings are concentrated among mothers of older school-aged children, while remote work may mitigate effects for mothers of younger children.]]></description><author>Benjamin Hansen, Joseph J. Sabia, Jessamyn Schaller</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29660</guid></item><item><title>The Variability and Volatility of Sleep: An ARCHetypal Behavior</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29658</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel S. Hamermesh, Gerard A. Pfann.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Using Dutch time-diary data from 1975-2005 covering over 10,000 respondents for 7 consecutive days each, we show that individuals’ sleep time exhibits both variability and volatility characterized by stationary autoregressive conditional heteroscedasticity: The absolute values of deviations from a person’s average sleep on one day are positively correlated with those on the next day. Sleep is more variable on weekends and among people with less education, who are younger and who do not have young children at home. Volatility is greater among parents with young children, slightly greater among men than women, but independent of other demographics. A theory of economic incentives to minimize the dispersion of sleep predicts that higher-wage workers will exhibit less dispersion, a result demonstrated using extraneous estimates of earnings equations to impute wage rates. Volatility in sleep spills over onto volatility in other personal activities, with no reverse causation onto sleep. The results illustrate a novel dimension of economic inequality and could be applied to a wide variety of human behavior and biological processes.]]></description><author>Daniel S. Hamermesh, Gerard A. Pfann</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29658</guid></item><item><title>Inequalities in the Times of a Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29657</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefanie Stantcheva.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper summarizes the research on some of the major inequalities that have been exacerbated by the COVID-19 pandemic across OECD countries. It reviews findings related to inequalities across the income distribution, sectors and regions, gender, and inequalities in education inputs for children from different socioeconomic backgrounds.]]></description><author>Stefanie Stantcheva</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29657</guid></item><item><title>Planning for the “Expected Unexpected”: Work and Retirement in the U.S. After the COVID-19 Pandemic Shock</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29653</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Richard B. Freeman.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This chapter analyzes the implications of the unexpected 2020-2021 COVID-19 pandemic for work and retirement in the U.S.  The pandemic induced the greatest loss of jobs in the shortest period of time in U.S. history.  A slow economic recovery would surely have endangered work longer/retire later policies that seek to adjust the finances of Social Security retirement to an aging population.  Boosted by the huge CARES (March 2020) and ARPA (April 2021) rescue packages, the early recovery from the COVID-19 recession was faster and stronger than the recovery from the 2007-2009 Great Recession.  Even so, the pandemic greatly altered the job market, with workers suffering from long COVID having difficulty returning to work and more workers working from home.  In its immediate effect and potential long-run impact, the pandemic recession/recovery is a wake-up call to the danger that shocks from the natural world pose to work and retirement.  Realistic planning for the future of work and retirement should go beyond analyzing socioeconomic trends to analyzing expected unexpected changes from the natural world as well.]]></description><author>Richard B. Freeman</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29653</guid></item><item><title>Inclusive Monetary Policy: How Tight Labor Markets Facilitate Broad-Based Employment Growth</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29651</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nittai Bergman, David A. Matsa, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper analyzes the heterogeneous effects of monetary policy on workers with differing levels of labor force attachment. Exploiting variation in labor market tightness across metropolitan areas, we show that the employment of populations with lower labor force attachment—Blacks, high school dropouts, and women—is more responsive to expansionary monetary policy in tighter labor markets. The effect builds up over time and is long lasting. We develop a New Keynesian model with heterogeneous workers that rationalizes these results. The model shows that expansionary monetary shocks lead to larger increases in the employment of less attached workers when the central bank follows an average inflation targeting rule and when the Phillips curve is flatter. These findings suggest that, by tightening labor markets, the Federal Reserve's recent move from a strict to an average inflation targeting framework especially benefits workers with lower labor force attachment.]]></description><author>Nittai Bergman, David A. Matsa, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29651</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of School and Childcare Closures on Labor Market Outcomes during the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29641</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kairon Shayne D. Garcia, Benjamin W. Cowan.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> A substantial fraction of schools and childcare facilities in the United States closed their in-person operations during the COVID-19 pandemic. These closures may carry substantial costs to the families of affected children. In this paper, we examine the impact of school and childcare closures on parental labor market outcomes during the COVID-19 pandemic. In particular, we test whether COVID-19 school closures have a disproportionate impact on parents of school-age children (age 5-17 years old) and whether childcare closures affect parents of young children (age &lt;5 years old) relative to others. Our results suggest that while closures have had little impact on whether parents work at all, they have had significant effects on whether parents work full time (at least 35 hours) and the number of hours worked per week. These effects are concentrated among low-educated parents, suggesting that such individuals had a more difficult time adjusting their work life to closures.]]></description><author>Kairon Shayne D. Garcia, Benjamin W. Cowan</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29641</guid></item><item><title>Trade, Human Capital, and Income Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29612</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Liuchun Deng, Pravin Krishna, Mine Zeynep Senses, Jens Stegmaier.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> In this paper, we empirically assess the causal links between trade and individual income risk and study the role that human capital plays in this relationship using a rich, worker-level, longitudinal data set from Germany spanning 1976 to 2012. Our estimates suggest substantial heterogeneity in labor income risk across workers in different entry cohorts and across workers with different levels of industry- and occupation-specific human capital. Our findings suggest that within-industry changes in imports and exports are causally related to income risk: Imports increase risk and exports decrease risk, and they do so in an economically significant manner. Importantly, we find there to be a complex interplay between human capital and the linkage between trade and risk: While, on average, individuals with higher levels of industry- or occupation-specific human capital experience lower income risk, a given increase in net-imports exposure in an industry increases risk for workers with higher levels of industry tenure more than it does for workers with lower levels of industry tenure. High levels of industry-specific human capital can be costly for workers in highly trade-exposed industries. By contrast, we find no evidence of any interaction between risk, industry trade exposure, and occupation-specific human capital.]]></description><author>Liuchun Deng, Pravin Krishna, Mine Zeynep Senses, Jens Stegmaier</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29612</guid></item><item><title>College Majors and Skills: Evidence from the Universe of Online Job Ads</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29605</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Steven W. Hemelt, Brad Hershbein, Shawn M. Martin, Kevin M. Stange.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We document the skill content of college majors as perceived by employers and expressed in the near universe of U.S. online job ads. Social and organizational skills are general in that they are sought by employers of almost all college majors, whereas other skills are more specialized. In turn, general majors––Business and General Engineering––have skill profiles similar to all majors; Nursing and Education are specialized. These cross-major differences in skill profiles explain considerable wage variation, with little role for within-major differences in skills across areas. College majors can thus be reasonably conceptualized as portable bundles of skills.]]></description><author>Steven W. Hemelt, Brad Hershbein, Shawn M. Martin, Kevin M. Stange</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29605</guid></item><item><title>Labor Reallocation and Remote Work During COVID-19: Real-time Evidence from GitHub</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29598</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Grant R. McDermott, Benjamin Hansen.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on labor activity using real-time data from millions of GitHub users around the world. We show that the pandemic triggered a sharp pattern of labor reallocation at both the global and regional level. Users were more likely to work on weekends and outside of traditional 9 am to 6 pm hours, especially during the early phase of the pandemic. We also document considerable heterogeneity between different user groups and locations. Some locations show a steady reversion back to historical work patterns, while others have experienced persistent trend deviations in the wake of COVID-19. The pattern of labor reallocation is slightly more pronounced among males in our sample, suggesting that men may have benefited more from the increased flexibility provided by remote work than women. Finally, we show that the pattern of reallocation was accompanied by a simultaneous increase in overall activity, though this effect is more transient. We discuss several potential mechanisms and draw tentative conclusions for broader workplace trends given our study population.]]></description><author>Grant R. McDermott, Benjamin Hansen</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29598</guid></item><item><title>Forced Displacement and Human Capital: Evidence from Separated Siblings</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29589</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Giorgio Chiovelli, Stelios Michalopoulos, Elias Papaioannou, Sandra Sequeira.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We examine the impact of conflict-driven displacement on human capital. We focus on the Mozambican civil war (1977–1992), during which more than four million civilians fled to the countryside, cities, and refugee camps and settlements in neighboring countries. We leverage the full post-war census to compare siblings separated during the war, using those who stayed behind as a counterfactual to one’s displacement path. Uprooted children register higher investments in education. Second, we quantify the relative importance of place-based and displacement effects. The latter increases education and decreases attachment to agriculture by the same rate as being exposed to an environment approximately one standard deviation more developed than one’s birthplace. Third, we conduct a survey in Nampula, whose population doubled during the civil war. Those who fled to the city have significantly higher education than their siblings who remained in the countryside and they converged to the levels of schooling of non-mover urban-born individuals. However, those displaced exhibit significantly lower social/civic capital and have worse mental health, even three decades after the war. These findings reveal that displacement shocks can trigger human capital investments, breaking links with subsistence agriculture, but at the cost of long-lasting, social, and psychological traumas.]]></description><author>Giorgio Chiovelli, Stelios Michalopoulos, Elias Papaioannou, Sandra Sequeira</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29589</guid></item><item><title>Organizational Frictions and Increasing Returns to Automation: Lessons from AT&amp;T in the Twentieth Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29580</link><description><![CDATA[<i>James J. Feigenbaum, Daniel P. Gross.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> AT&amp;T was the largest U.S. firm for most of the 20th century. Telephone operators once comprised over 50% of its workforce, but in the late 1910s it initiated a decades-long process of automating telephone operation with mechanical call switching—a technology first invented in the 1880s. We study what drove AT&amp;T to do so, and why it took one firm nearly a century to automate this one basic function. Interdependencies between operators and nearly every other part of the business were obstacles: the manual switchboard was the fulcrum of a complex system which had developed around it, and automation only began after the firm and automatic technology were adapted to work together. Even then, automatic switching was only profitable for AT&amp;T in larger markets—hence diffusion expanded as costs declined and service areas grew. We show that automation supported AT&amp;T's continued growth, generating a positive feedback loop between scale and automation that reinforced AT&amp;T's high market share in local markets.]]></description><author>James J. Feigenbaum, Daniel P. Gross</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29580</guid></item><item><title>Time Use and Gender in Africa in Times of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29571</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Taryn Dinkelman, L. Rachel Ngai.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Many African countries are still in the early stages of structural transformation. Typically, as economies move through the structural transformation, activities once conducted within the household are outsourced to the market. This has particular implications for women’s time use. In this paper, we document that current patterns of female time use in home production in several African countries closely resemble historical time use patterns in the US. We highlight two stylized facts about women’s time use in Africa. First, in North Africa, women spend very few hours in market work and female labor force participation overall is extremely low. Second, although extensive margin participation of women is high in sub-Saharan Africa, women tend to work in the market for only a few hours each week, with the rest of their work hours spent in home production. These two facts suggest two types of constraints that could slow down the reallocation of female time from home to market as economies grow: Social norms related to women’s market work, and a lack of infrastructure (e.g. household infrastructure and childcare facilities) to facilitate marketizing home production. We discuss recent empirical evidence related to each set of constraints and highlight new avenues for research.]]></description><author>Taryn Dinkelman, L. Rachel Ngai</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29571</guid></item><item><title>STEM Employment Resiliency During Recessions: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29568</link><description><![CDATA[<i>James C. Davis, Holden A. Diethorn, Gerald R. Marschke, Andrew J. Wang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Employment in STEM occupations suffered smaller peak-to-trough percentage declines than non-STEM occupations during the Great Recession and COVID-19 recession, suggesting a relative resiliency of STEM employment.  We exploit the sudden peak-to-trough declines in STEM and non-STEM employment during the COVID-19 recession to measure STEM recession-resiliency, decomposing our difference-in-differences estimate into parts explained by various sources.  We find that STEM knowledge importance on the job explains the greatest share of STEM employment resiliency, and that workers in non-STEM occupations who nonetheless use STEM knowledge experienced better employment outcomes. STEM employment resiliency may explain the mild effects of COVID-19 on innovative activity.]]></description><author>James C. Davis, Holden A. Diethorn, Gerald R. Marschke, Andrew J. Wang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29568</guid></item><item><title>Job Training Through Turmoil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29565</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Adriana D. Kugler, Mikko I. Silliman.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We follow the labor market outcomes of applicants who were randomized into job training a year and a half before the pandemic through the subsequent economic turmoil that resulted from COVID-19. Despite persistently improved labor market outcomes of training participants prior to March 2020, we show that job losses resulting from the pandemic washed away all the benefits of the program. A year and a half after the initial scars of the pandemic, there are no visible signs of recovery of trainees’ labor market outcomes.]]></description><author>Felipe Barrera-Osorio, Adriana D. Kugler, Mikko I. Silliman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29565</guid></item><item><title>When (and Why) Providers Do Not Respond to Changes in Reimbursement Rates</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29564</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marcus Dillender, Lu G. Jinks, Anthony T. Lo Sasso.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> High health care prices contribute to the United States spending more on health care than any other country, but policies that reduce health care payments have the potential to lead to health care access issues if providers reduce their supply in response to reimbursement rate reductions.  In this paper, we examine the impact of reimbursement rates on health care supply by studying a policy that reduced reimbursement rates by 30% in one of the highest-reimbursing workers' compensation insurance systems in the nation. Despite the large decrease in reimbursement rates, we find no evidence that the policy affected the amount of health care that injured workers receive or recoveries after injuries. Our estimates suggest that the policy reduced annual workers' compensation medical costs by over $400 million and indicate that providers may be operating on the inelastic portion of the supply curve for care paid for by high-reimbursing payers.]]></description><author>Marcus Dillender, Lu G. Jinks, Anthony T. Lo Sasso</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29564</guid></item><item><title>Making Teaching Last: Long-Run Value-Added</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29555</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Gilraine, Nolan G. Pope.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Teacher value-added (VA) measures how teachers improve their students' contemporaneous test scores. Many teachers, however, argue that contemporaneous test scores are a poor proxy for their permanent influence on students.  This paper considers a new VA measure -- 'long-run VA' -- that captures teachers' contributions that persist by replacing contemporaneous test scores with subsequent test scores in VA estimation.  We find that students assigned to high long-run VA teachers fare substantially better in terms of long-term outcomes.  Policy simulations indicate that the use of long-run VA improves policy effectiveness by a factor of two compared to traditional VA measures.]]></description><author>Michael Gilraine, Nolan G. Pope</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29555</guid></item><item><title>Technology-Skill Complementarity and Labor Displacement: Evidence from Linking Two Centuries of Patents with Occupations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29552</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leonid Kogan, Dimitris Papanikolaou, Lawrence D. W. Schmidt, Bryan Seegmiller.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We construct new technology indicators using textual analysis of patent documents and occupation task descriptions that span almost two centuries (1850–2010). At the industry level, improvements in technology are associated with higher labor productivity but a decline in the labor share. Exploiting variation in the extent certain technologies are related to specific occupations, we show that technological innovation has been largely associated with worse labor market outcomes—wages and employment—for incumbent workers in related occupations using a combination of public-use and confidential administrative data. Panel data on individual worker earnings reveal that less educated, older, and more highly-paid workers experience significantly greater declines in average earnings and earnings risk following related technological advances. We reconcile these facts with the standard view of technology-skill complementarity using a model that allows for skill displacement.]]></description><author>Leonid Kogan, Dimitris Papanikolaou, Lawrence D. W. Schmidt, Bryan Seegmiller</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29552</guid></item><item><title>Productivity and Pay in the US and Canada</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29548</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jacob Greenspon, Anna M. Stansbury, Lawrence H. Summers.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study the productivity-pay relationship in the United States and Canada along two dimensions. The first is divergence: the degree to which the levels of productivity and pay have diverged. The second is delinkage: the degree to which incremental increases in the rate of productivity growth translate into incremental increases in the rate of growth of pay, holding all else equal. We show that in both countries the pay of typical workers has diverged substantially from average labor productivity over recent decades, driven by both rising labor income inequality and a declining labor share of income. Even as the levels of productivity and pay have grown further apart, we find evidence for some linkage between productivity and pay in both countries: a one percentage point increase in the rate of productivity growth is associated with a positive increase in the rate of pay growth, holding all else equal. This linkage appears stronger in the US than in Canada. Overall, our findings lead us to tentatively conclude that policies or trends which lead to incremental increases in productivity growth, particularly in large relatively closed economies like the USA, will tend to raise middle class incomes. At the same time, other factors orthogonal to productivity growth have been driving productivity and typical pay further apart, emphasizing that much of the evolution in middle class living standards will depend on measures bearing on relative incomes.]]></description><author>Jacob Greenspon, Anna M. Stansbury, Lawrence H. Summers</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29548</guid></item><item><title>The Effects of Fiscal Decentralization on Publicly Provided Services and Labor Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29538</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicola Bianchi, Michela Giorcelli, Enrica Maria Martino.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies how fiscal decentralization affects local services. It explores a 1993 reform that increased the fiscal autonomy of Italian municipalities by replacing government transfers with revenues from a local property tax. Our identifica- tion leverages cross-municipal variation in the degree of decentralization that stems from differences in the average age of buildings caused by bombings during WWII. Decentralization reduced local spending but expanded municipal services, such as nursery schools. These effects are larger in areas with greater political competition. The paper also investigates how the reform affected labor markets. Decentralization increased female labor supply—probably through expanded availability of nursery schools—thereby reducing the gender gap in employment.]]></description><author>Nicola Bianchi, Michela Giorcelli, Enrica Maria Martino</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29538</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of Health and Education on Labor Force Participation in Aging Societies – Projections for the United States and Germany from a Dynamic Microsimulation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29534</link><description><![CDATA[<i>René Böheim, Thomas Horvath, Thomas Leoni, Martin Spielauer.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Using a highly stylized dynamic microsimulation model, we project the labor force of the United States up to the year 2060 and contrast these projections with projections for Germany to assess differential effects on outcomes The projections are consistent with the U S Census Bureau’s and Eurostat’s demographic projections. Our modeling approach allows to show and quantify how policy changes the future size of the labor force, which we assess with a series of what-if scenarios.<br />
Both the US and Germany are expected to undergo demographic aging, but their demographic fundamentals differ starkly. This has strong implications for their labor force developments. According to our microsimulation, the US labor force will, despite population aging, increase by 16.2 percent in the age groups 15 to 74 (corresponding to 25.2 million workers) between 2020 and 2060, while Germany will experience a decline by 10.7 percent (4.4 million workers). In these baseline projections, improvements in the education structure will add about two million persons to the US labor force and about half a million persons to the German labor force by 2060.<br />
In the what-if scenarios, we examine the implications of improvements in the educational structure of the population and of policies which address the health impediments for labor force participation. Of the educational scenarios that we evaluate, increasing the number of persons who achieve more than lower education has the strongest positive impact on labor force participation, relative to the number of additional years of schooling implied by the various scenarios. Shifting people from intermediate to higher education levels also increases labor force participation in higher age groups, however, this is partially offset by lock in effects at younger ages.<br />
Our projections highlight that improvements in the labor market integration of people with health limitations provide a particularly promising avenue to increase labor force participation rates and thus help to address the challenges posed by demographic aging. If the health gap in participation rates in the United States were similar to that currently observed in Sweden, the labor force in 2060 would be larger by about 14.9 million persons.]]></description><author>René Böheim, Thomas Horvath, Thomas Leoni, Martin Spielauer</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29534</guid></item><item><title>“Golden Ages”: A Tale of the Labor Markets in China and the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29523</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hanming Fang, Xincheng Qiu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the labor markets in China and the United States, the two largest economies in the world, by examining the evolution of their cross-sectional age-earnings profiles during the past thirty years. We find that, first, the peak age in the cross-sectional age-earnings profiles, which we refer to as the “golden age,” stayed almost constant at around 45-50 in the U.S., but decreased sharply from 55 to around 35 in China; second, the age-specific earnings grew drastically in China, but stayed almost stagnant in the U.S.; third, the cross-sectional and life-cycle age-earnings profiles were remarkably similar in the U.S., but differed substantially in China. We propose and empirically implement a decomposition framework to infer from the repeated cross-sectional earnings data the experience effect (i.e., human capital accumulation over the life cycle), the cohort effect (i.e., inter-cohort human capital growth), and the time effect (i.e., changes in the human capital rental prices over time), under an identifying assumption that the growth of the experience effect stops at the end of one's working career. The decomposition suggests that China has experienced a much larger inter-cohort productivity growth and higher increase in the rental price to human capital, but lower returns to experience, compared to the U.S. We also use the inferred components to revisit several important and classical applications in macroeconomics and labor economics, including growth accounting and the estimation of TFP growth, and the college wage premium and skill-biased technical change.]]></description><author>Hanming Fang, Xincheng Qiu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29523</guid></item><item><title>Headstrong Girls and Dependent Boys: Gender Differences in the Labor Market Returns to Child Behavior</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29509</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Robert Kaestner, Ofer Malamud.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The authors use data from the Children of the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth (C-NLSY79) to examine gender differences in the associations between child behavioral problems and early adult earnings. They find large and significant earnings penalties for women who exhibited more headstrong behavior and for men who exhibited more dependent behavior as children. In contrast, there are no penalties for men who were headstrong or for women who were dependent. While other child behavioral problems are also associated with labor market earnings, their associations are not significantly different by gender. The gender differences in headstrong and dependent behavior are not explained by education, marriage, depression, self-esteem, health, or adult personality traits. However, one potential explanation is that these gender differences are a consequence of deviations from gender norms and stereotypes in the workplace.]]></description><author>Robert Kaestner, Ofer Malamud</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29509</guid></item><item><title>Capital Investment and Labor Demand</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29485</link><description><![CDATA[<i>E. Mark Curtis, Daniel G. Garrett, Eric C. Ohrn, Kevin A. Roberts, Juan Carlos Suárez Serrato.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study how tax policies that lower the cost of capital impact investment and labor demand. Diﬀerence-in-diﬀerences estimates using conﬁdential US Census Data on manufacturing establishments show that tax policies increased both investment and employment, but did not lead to wage or productivity gains. Using a structural model, we show that the primary eﬀect of the policy was to increase the use of all inputs by lowering overall costs of production. The policy further stimulated production employment due to the complementarity of production labor and capital. Supporting this conclusion, we ﬁnd that investment is greater in plants with lower labor costs. Our results show that recent tax policies that incentivize capital investment do not lead manufacturing plants to replace workers with machines.]]></description><author>E. Mark Curtis, Daniel G. Garrett, Eric C. Ohrn, Kevin A. Roberts, Juan Carlos Suárez Serrato</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29485</guid></item><item><title>Who Benefits from Online Gig Economy Platforms?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29477</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher T. Stanton, Catherine Thomas.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper estimates the magnitude and distribution of surplus from the knowledge worker gig economy using data from an online labor market. Labor demand elasticities determine workers’ wages, and buyers’ past market experience shapes both their job posting frequency and hiring rates. We ﬁnd that workers on the supply side capture around 40% of the surplus from ﬁlled jobs. Under counterfactual policies that resemble traditional employment regulation, buyers post fewer online jobs and ﬁll posted jobs less often, reducing expected surplus for all market participants. We ﬁnd negligible substitution on the demand side between online and oﬄine jobs by assessing how changes in local oﬄine minimum wages aﬀect online hiring. The results suggest that neither online or oﬄine knowledge workers will beneﬁt from applying traditional employment regulation to the online gig economy.]]></description><author>Christopher T. Stanton, Catherine Thomas</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29477</guid></item><item><title>Some Children Left Behind: Variation in the Effects of an Educational Intervention</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29459</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Julie Buhl-Wiggers, Jason T. Kerwin, Juan S. Muñoz-Morales, Jeffrey A. Smith, Rebecca Thornton.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We document substantial variation in the effects of a highly-effective literacy pro-gram in northern Uganda. The program increases test scores by 1.40 SDs on average, but standard statistical bounds show that the impact standard deviation exceeds 1.0SD. This implies that the variation in effects across our students is wider than the spread of mean effects across all randomized evaluations of developing country education interventions in the literature. This very effective program does indeed leave some students behind. At the same time, we do not learn much from our analyses that attempt to determine which students benefit more or less from the program. We reject rank preservation, and the weaker assumption of stochastic increasingness leaves wide bounds on quantile-specific average treatment effects. Neither conventional nor machine-learning approaches to estimating systematic heterogeneity capture more than a small fraction of the variation in impacts given our available candidate moderators.]]></description><author>Julie Buhl-Wiggers, Jason T. Kerwin, Juan S. Muñoz-Morales, Jeffrey A. Smith, Rebecca Thornton</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29459</guid></item><item><title>Women in Science. Lessons from the Baby Boom</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29436</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Scott Daewon Kim, Petra Moser.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> How do children affect women in science? We investigate this question using rich biographical data, linked with patents and publications, for 83,000 American scientists in 1956 at the height of the baby boom. Our analyses reveal a unique life-cycle pattern of productivity for mothers. While other scientists peak in their mid-thirties, mothers become more productive after age 35 and maintain high productivity in their 40s and 50s. Event studies show that the output of mothers increases after 15 years of marriage, while other scientists peak in the first 10 years. Differences in the timing of productivity have important implications for tenure and participation. Just 27% of mothers who are academic scientists get tenure, compared with 48% of fathers and 46% of women without children. Mothers face comparable tenure rates to other assistant professors for the first six years but fall behind afterwards, suggesting that they face higher standards of early productivity. Mothers who survive in science are extremely positively selected: Compared with other married women, mothers patent (publish) 2.5 (1.4) times more before the median age at marriage. Compared with men, female scientists are more educated, half as likely to marry, one-third as likely to have children, but half as likely to survive in science. Employment records indicate that a generation of baby boom mothers was lost to science.]]></description><author>Scott Daewon Kim, Petra Moser</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29436</guid></item><item><title>The Geography of Retirement</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29433</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Courtney Coile.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> As Americans work longer in response to a changing retirement landscape, it is important to ask whether there are groups being left out of this trend. Geography is a natural lens through which to examine this question, given regional disparities in the employment of prime-age individuals. In this study, we explore the geography of retirement using data from the U.S. Census/American Community Survey and other sources. We find large differences across U.S. commuting zones in employment rates at older ages, with a gap of about 20 percentage points between areas at the 90th and 10th percentiles of employment. Low-employment areas are systematically different, with a less educated and more diverse population, more low-wage jobs and import competition from China, poorer health outcomes and health care access, lower government spending, and more income inequality. Although these correlations are not necessarily causal, these factors collectively can explain about four-fifths of the geographic variation in employment at older ages.]]></description><author>Courtney Coile</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29433</guid></item><item><title>Mental Health, Creativity, and Wealth</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29422</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Barbara Biasi, Michael S. Dahl, Petra Moser.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Focusing on bipolar disorder (BD), we investigate the link between mental health, creativity, and wealth. Analyzing population data for Denmark, we find that people with BD are more likely to be musicians, but less likely to hold other creative jobs than the population. Healthy siblings of people with BD, however, are consistently more likely to work in creative jobs. We also show people in the top decile of parental wealth are seven times as likely to work in creative professions compared with the bottom decile. Yet, wealth differences only explain a small portion of the link between BD and creativity.]]></description><author>Barbara Biasi, Michael S. Dahl, Petra Moser</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29422</guid></item><item><title>Mental Health Therapy as a Core Strategy for Increasing Human Capital: Evidence from Ghana</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the impact of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) for individuals selected from the general population of poor households in rural Ghana. Results from 2-3 months after a randomized intervention show strong impacts on mental and physical health, cognitive and socioemotional skills, and downstream economic outcomes. We find no evidence of heterogeneity by baseline mental distress; we argue that this is because CBT can improve human capital for a general population of poor individuals through two pathways. First, CBT reduces vulnerability to deteriorating mental health; and second, CBT directly improves bandwidth, increasing cognitive and socioemotional skills and hence economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</guid></item><item><title>On the Persistence of the China Shock</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29401</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Autor, David Dorn, Gordon H. Hanson.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Abstract We evaluate the duration of the China trade shock and its impact on a wide range of outcomes over the period 2000 to 2019. The shock plateaued in 2010, enabling analysis of its effects for nearly a decade past its culmination. Adverse impacts of import competition on manufacturing employment, overall employment-population ratios, and income per capita in more trade-exposed U.S. commuting zones are present out to 2019. Over the full study period, greater import competition implies a reduction in the manufacturing employment-population ratio of 1.54 percentage points, which is 55% of the observed change in the value, and the absorption of 86% of this net job loss via a corresponding decrease in the overall employment rate. Reductions in population headcounts, which indicate net out-migration, register only for foreign-born workers and the native-born 25-39 years old, implying that exit from work is a primary means of adjustment to trade-induced contractions in labor demand. More negatively affected regions see modest increases in the uptake of government transfers, but these transfers primarily take the form of Social Security and Medicare benefits. Adverse outcomes are more acute in regions that initially had fewer college-educated workers and were more industrially specialized. Impacts are qualitatively—but not quantitatively—similar to those caused by the decline of employment in coal production since the 1980s, indicating that the China trade shock holds lessons for other episodes of localized job loss. Import competition from China induced changes in income per capita across local labor markets that are much larger than the spatial heterogeneity of income effects predicted by standard quantitative trade models. Even using higher-end estimates of the consumer benefits of rising trade with China, a substantial fraction of commuting zones appears to have suffered absolute declines in average real incomes.]]></description><author>David Autor, David Dorn, Gordon H. Hanson</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29401</guid></item><item><title>The Human Side of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We document that nearly half of the global decline in agricultural employment during the 20th-century was driven by new cohorts entering the labor market. A newly compiled dataset of policy reforms supports an interpretation of these cohort effects as human capital. Through the lens of a model of frictional labor reallocation, we conclude that human capital growth, both as a mediating factor and as an independent driver, led to a sharp decline in the agricultural labor supply. This decline accounts, at fixed prices, for 40% of the decrease in agricultural employment. This aggregate effect is roughly halved in general equilibrium.]]></description><author>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</guid></item><item><title>Effects of Opioid-Related Policies on Opioid Utilization, Nature of Medical Care, and Duration of Disability</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29371</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Neumark, Bogdan Savych.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We examine the effects of must-access prescription drug monitoring programs (PDMPs) and recent regulations limiting the duration of initial opioid prescriptions on care received by patients with work-related injuries, focusing on opioid utilization and medical care related to pain management. We find that must-access PDMPs contributed to declines in opioid utilization, while regulations limiting duration of initial opioid prescriptions had little effect on whether workers receive opioids, but reduced opioid use among those with prescriptions. We find limited evidence that must-access PDMPs affected utilization of other medical care related to pain management, and that must-access PDMPs and limits on initial prescriptions had little impact on the duration of temporary disability benefits captured at 12 months of maturity.]]></description><author>David Neumark, Bogdan Savych</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29371</guid></item><item><title>Early Childhood Development, Human Capital and Poverty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29362</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Orazio Attanasio, Sarah Cattan, Costas Meghir.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Children's experiences during early childhood are critical for their cognitive and socio-emotional development, two key dimensions of human capital. However, children from low income backgrounds often grow up lacking stimulation and basic investments, leading to developmental deficits that are difficult, if not impossible, to reverse later in life without intervention. The existence of these deficits are a key driver of inequality and contribute to the intergenerational transmission of poverty. In this paper, we discuss the framework used in economics to model parental investments and early childhood development and use it as an organizing tool to review some of the empirical evidence on early childhood research. We then present results from various important early childhoods interventions with emphasis on developing countries. Bringing these elements together we draw conclusions on what we have learned and provide some directions for future research.]]></description><author>Orazio Attanasio, Sarah Cattan, Costas Meghir</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29362</guid></item><item><title>“Beauty Too Rich for Use”*: Billionaires’ Assets and Attractiveness</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29361</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel S. Hamermesh, Andrew Leigh.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We examine how the net worth of billionaires relates to their looks, as rated by 16 people of different gender and ethnicity. Surprisingly, their financial assets are unrelated to their beauty; nor are they related to their educational attainment. As a group, however, billionaires are both more educated and better-looking than average for their age. Men, people who reside in Western countries, and those who inherited substantial wealth, are wealthier than other billionaires. The results do not arise from measurement error or nonrandom sample selectivity. They are consistent with econometric theory about the impact of truncating a sample to include observations only from the extreme tail of the dependent variable. The point is underscored by comparing estimates of earnings equations using all employees in the 2018 American Community Survey to those using a sample of the top 0.1 percent. The findings suggest the powerful role of luck within the extremes of the distributions of economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Daniel S. Hamermesh, Andrew Leigh</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29361</guid></item><item><title>Outsourcing, Inequality and Aggregate Output</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Outsourced workers experience large wage declines, yet domestic outsourcing may raise aggregate productivity. To study this equity-efficiency trade-off, we contribute a framework in which firms either hire many imperfectly substitutable worker types in-house by posting wages along a job ladder, or rent labor services from contractors who hire in the same frictional labor markets. Three implications arise. First, more productive firms are more likely to outsource to save on higher wage premia. Second, outsourcing raises output at the firm level. Third, contractors endogenously locate at the bottom of the job ladder, implying that outsourced workers receive lower wages. Using firm-level instruments for outsourcing and revenue productivity, we find empirical support for all three predictions in French administrative data. After structurally estimating the model, we find that the rise in outsourcing in France between 1996 and 2007 raised aggregate output by 3% and reduced the labor share by 0.7 percentage points. A 9% minimum wage increase stabilizes the labor share and maintains two thirds of the output gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</guid></item><item><title>Why do people stay poor?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clare A. Balboni, Oriana Bandiera, Robin Burgess, Maitreesh Ghatak, Anton Heil.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> There are two broad views as to why people stay poor. One emphasizes differences in fundamentals, such as ability, talent or motivation. The other, the poverty traps view, differences in opportunities which stem from access to wealth. To test between these two views, we exploit a large-scale, randomized asset transfer and an 11-year panel on 6000 households who begin in extreme poverty. The setting is rural Bangladesh and the asset is cows. The data supports the poverty traps view - we identify a threshold level of initial assets above which households accumulate assets, take on better occupations (from casual labor in agriculture or domestic services to running small livestock businesses) and grow out of poverty. The reverse happens for those below the threshold. Structural estimation of an occupational choice model reveals that almost all beneficiaries are misallocated in the work they do at baseline and that the gains arising from eliminating misallocation would far exceed the program costs. Our findings imply that large transfers which create better jobs for the poor are an effective means of getting people out of poverty traps and reducing global poverty.]]></description><author>Clare A. Balboni, Oriana Bandiera, Robin Burgess, Maitreesh Ghatak, Anton Heil</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</guid></item><item><title>Task Allocation and On-the-job Training</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29312</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Mariagiovanna Baccara, SangMok Lee, Leeat Yariv.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study dynamic task allocation when providers' expertise evolves endogenously through training. We characterize optimal assignment protocols and compare them to discretionary procedures, where it is the clients who select their service providers. Our results indicate that welfare gains from centralization are greater when tasks arrive more rapidly, and when training technologies improve. Monitoring seniors' backlog of clients always increases welfare but may decrease training. Methodologically, we explore a matching setting with endogenous types, and illustrate useful adaptations of queueing theory techniques for such environments.]]></description><author>Mariagiovanna Baccara, SangMok Lee, Leeat Yariv</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29312</guid></item><item><title>The Evolution of Skill Use Within and Between Jobs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29302</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Costas Cavounidis, Vittoria Dicandia, Kevin Lang, Raghav Malhotra.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We develop a tractable general equilibrium model for understanding within- and between-occupation changes in skill use over time. We apply the model to skill-use measures from the third, fourth, and revised fourth editions of the Dictionary of Occupational Titles and data from the 1960, 1970, and 1980 Censuses and March Current Population Surveys. We recover changes in skill productivity by exploiting between-occupation movements. Most importantly, finger-dexterity productivity grew rapidly while abstract-skill productivity lagged. We leverage these findings to estimate an inelastic relation between abstract and routine inputs and explain within-occupation shifts in skill use.]]></description><author>Costas Cavounidis, Vittoria Dicandia, Kevin Lang, Raghav Malhotra</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29302</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Nationalization Policies and Exporting Firm Outcomes: Evidence from Saudi Arabia</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29283</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Patricia Cortés, Semiray Kasoolu, Carolina Pan.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> In the last decade, Gulf countries have imposed hiring quotas to promote the participation of natives in the private sector and address high levels of unemployment, particularly among women and the youth. This paper explores how one such policy, Nitaqat in Saudi Arabia, affected the outcomes of exporting firms, the most productive sector of the non-oil economy.  We find that whereas the policy was successful in increasing the employment of Saudi nationals by these firms, it came at a high cost. In the year following the announcement of the policy, relative to firms above the quota, firms below the quota were 1.5 percentage points more likely to exit the market, 7 percentage points less likely to export, and conditional on exporting, the value of their exports fell by 14 percent. Additionally, surviving treated firms reduced their labor force by 10 percent. We find that to comply with the policy, firms hired mostly lower-wage, low-skilled Saudis. The policy doubled the share of women in treated firms. Importantly, we find that these short-term effects persisted for at least three years after the policy’s implementation.]]></description><author>Patricia Cortés, Semiray Kasoolu, Carolina Pan</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29283</guid></item><item><title>The Returns to College(s): Relative Value-Added and Match Effects in Higher Education</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29276</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jack Mountjoy, Brent R. Hickman.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Students who attend different colleges in the U.S. end up with vastly different economic outcomes. We study the role of relative value-added across colleges within student choice sets in producing these outcome disparities. Linking high school, college, and earnings registries spanning the state of Texas, we identify relative college value-added by comparing the outcomes of students who apply to and are admitted by the same set of institutions, as this approach strikingly balances observable student potential across college treatments and renders our extensive set of covariates irrelevant as controls. Methodologically, we develop a framework for identifying and interpreting value-added under varying assumptions about match effects and sorting gains. Empirically, we estimate a relatively tight, though non-degenerate, distribution of relative value-added across the wide diversity of Texas public universities. Selectivity poorly predicts value-added within student choice sets, with only a fleeting selectivity earnings premium fading to zero after a few years in the labor market. Non-peer college inputs like instructional spending more strongly predict value-added, especially conditional on selectivity. Colleges that boost BA completion, especially in STEM majors, also tend to boost earnings. Finally, we probe the potential for (mis)match effects by allowing value-added schedules to vary by student characteristics.]]></description><author>Jack Mountjoy, Brent R. Hickman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29276</guid></item></channel></rss>