<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Development and Growth</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Development and Growth</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 15:13:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Share Pledging in China: Funding Listed Firms or Funding Entrepreneurship?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29731</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhiguo He, Bibo Liu, Feifei Zhu.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> This paper studies the connection between share pledging and entrepreneurial activities in China, challenging the common wisdom that share pledging funds circle back to the listed firms. Share pledging funds are at the discretion of the shareholders who pledge their publicly traded shares, and survey evidence shows that a majority of the largest shareholders (67.3%) used pledging funds outside the listed firms. By linking firm registration data with share pledging data, we show a positive relation between shareholders’ pledging transactions and entrepreneurial activities. Utilizing the launch of the exchange market in 2013 as a quasi-natural experiment that favors share pledging by natural person shareholders against that by legal entity shareholders, our difference-in-differences (DiD) analysis shows natural person shareholders increased their entrepreneurial activities significantly in response to the policy shock, relative to legal entity shareholders. In addition to various robustness checks, we also show that shareholders with better access to share pledging invest more heavily in industries with above-median growth potential.]]></description><author>Zhiguo He, Bibo Liu, Feifei Zhu</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29731</guid></item><item><title>E-commerce During Covid: Stylized Facts from 47 Economies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29729</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joel Alcedo, Alberto Cavallo, Bricklin Dwyer, Prachi Mishra, Antonio Spilimbergo.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We study e-commerce across 47 economies and 26 industries during the COVID-19 pandemic using aggregated and anonymized transaction-level data from Mastercard, scaled to represent total consumer spending. The share of online transactions in total consumption increased more in economies with higher pre-pandemic e-commerce shares, exacerbating the digital divide across economies. Overall, the latest data suggest that these spikes in online spending shares are dissipating at the aggregate level, though there is variation across industries. In particular, the share of online spending in professional services and recreation has fallen below its pre-pandemic trend, but we observe a longer-lasting shift to digital in retail and restaurants.]]></description><author>Joel Alcedo, Alberto Cavallo, Bricklin Dwyer, Prachi Mishra, Antonio Spilimbergo</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29729</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Economic Advantage</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29724</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Francesco Bova, Avi Goldfarb, Roger G. Melko.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> A quantum computer exhibits a quantum advantage when it can perform a calculation that a classical computer is unable to complete. It follows that a company with a quantum computer would be a monopolist in the market for solving such a calculation if its only competitor was a company with a classical computer. Conversely, economic outcomes are unclear in settings where quantum computers do not exhibit a quantum advantage. We model a duopoly where a quantum computing company competes against a classical computing company. The model features an asymmetric variable cost structure between the two companies and the potential for an asymmetric fixed cost structure, where each firm can invest in scaling its hardware to expand its respective market. We find that even if: 1) the companies can complete identical calculations, and thus there is no quantum advantage, and 2) it is more expensive to scale the quantum computer, the quantum computing company can not only be more profitable but also invest more in market creation. The results suggest that quantum computers may not need to display a quantum advantage to be able to generate a quantum economic advantage for the companies that develop them.]]></description><author>Francesco Bova, Avi Goldfarb, Roger G. Melko</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29724</guid></item><item><title>Omnia Juncta in Uno: Foreign Powers and Trademark Protection in Shanghai's Concession Era</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29721</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Laura Alfaro, Cathy Ge Bao, Maggie X. Chen, Junjie Hong, Claudia Steinwender.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We investigate how firms adapt to trademark protection, an extensively used but underexamined form of IP protection, by exploring a historical precedent: China's trademark law of 1923---an unanticipated and disapproved response to end foreign privileges in China. By exploiting a unique, newly digitized firm-employee-level dataset from Shanghai in 1872-1941, we show that the trademark law shaped firm dynamics on all sides of trademark conflicts. The law spurred growth and brand investment among Western firms with greater dependence on trademark protection. In contrast, Japanese businesses, which had frequently been accused of counterfeiting, experienced contractions while attempting to build their own brands after the law. The trademark law also led to new linkages with domestic agents, both within and outside the boundaries of Western firms, and the growth of Chinese intermediaries. At the aggregate level, trademark-intensive industries witnessed a net growth in employment and the number of product categories. A comparison with previous attempts by foreign powers---such as extraterritorial rights, bilateral treaties, and an unenforced trademark code---shows that those alternative institutions were ultimately unsuccessful.]]></description><author>Laura Alfaro, Cathy Ge Bao, Maggie X. Chen, Junjie Hong, Claudia Steinwender</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29721</guid></item><item><title>The Value of Piped Water and Sewers: Evidence from 19th Century Chicago</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29718</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Coury, Toru Kitagawa, Allison Shertzer, Matthew Turner.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We estimate the impact of piped water and sewers on property values in mid-19th century Chicago. The cost of sewer construction depends sensitively on imperceptible variation in grade, and such variations in grade delay water and sewer service to part of the city. This delay provides quasi-random variation for causal estimates. We extrapolate ATE estimates from our natural experiment to the area treated with water and sewer service during 1874-1880 using a new estimator. Water and sewer access increases property values by more than a factor of two. This exceeds costs by about a factor of 60.]]></description><author>Michael Coury, Toru Kitagawa, Allison Shertzer, Matthew Turner</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29718</guid></item><item><title>Traditional Supernatural Beliefs and Prosocial Behavior</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29695</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Etienne Le Rossignol, Sara Lowes, Nathan Nunn.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> In sub-Saharan Africa, traditional supernatural beliefs, including belief in witchcraft, black magic, or fetishism, are widespread. Some have hypothesized that these beliefs help to sustain cooperative behavior in a setting where the state is often absent. Others have documented that, at least at a macro-level, such beliefs are negatively associated with prosocial behavior. We contribute to a better understanding of the causal effects of these traditional supernatural beliefs by using lab-in-the-field experiments in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Participants complete a range of experimental tasks where one player chooses whether to act in a prosocial manner towards another player. Participants are randomly assigned to another player that has either a strong or weak belief in witchcraft, and this information is known by the players. We find that participants act less prosocially towards randomly-assigned partners who believe more strongly in witchcraft. We also find that antisocial behavior is more socially acceptable and prosocial behavior less socially acceptable when playing with a partner who believes more strongly in witchcraft. Our findings suggest that the negative relationship between witchcraft and prosocial outcomes observed in the data may, in fact, be due to the causal effect of the presence of traditional supernatural beliefs on people’s behavior.]]></description><author>Etienne Le Rossignol, Sara Lowes, Nathan Nunn</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29695</guid></item><item><title>State-building on the Margin: An Urban Experiment in Medellín</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29692</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher Blattman, Gustavo Duncan, Benjamin Lessing, Santiago Tobon.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Medellín's government wanted to raise its efficacy, legitimacy, and control. The city identified 80 neighborhoods with weak state presence and competing armed actors. In half, they increased non-police street presence tenfold for two years, offering social services and dispute resolution. In places where the state was initially weakest, the intervention did not work, mainly because the government struggled to deliver on its promises. Where the state began stronger, the government raised opinions of its services and legitimacy. If there are indeed low marginal returns to investing in capacity in the least-governed areas, this could produce increasing returns to state-building.]]></description><author>Christopher Blattman, Gustavo Duncan, Benjamin Lessing, Santiago Tobon</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29692</guid></item><item><title>The Second World War, Inequality and the Social Contract in England</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29677</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leander Heldring, James A. Robinson, Parker J. Whitfill.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> What is the impact of warfare on inequality and the social contract? Using local data on bombing, the evolution of wealth inequality and vote shares for the Labour Party in England around World War II we establish two results. First, on average, we find no impact of bombing on inequality. However, there is considerable heterogeneity and this result is driven by the south. In the north of England bombing led to significant falls in inequality. Second, heavier bombing led to a significant increase in the vote share for Labour after the War everywhere, but this effect is transitory in the south while it is permanent in the north. Our results obtain both in a simple difference-in-differences framework as well as in a panel-regression discontinuity framework in which we exploit the limited range of German fighter escort planes. Our results provide novel causal evidence for the inequality reducing impact of warfare and we interpret them as consistent with the notion that the impact of the War also led to a reconfiguration of the social contract in England.]]></description><author>Leander Heldring, James A. Robinson, Parker J. Whitfill</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29677</guid></item><item><title>Understanding Rural Households’ Time Use in a Developing Setting: Validating a Low-Cost Time Use Module</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29671</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Erica M. Field, Rohini Pande, Natalia Rigol, Simone G. Schaner, Elena M. Stacy, Charity M. Troyer Moore.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Time use data facilitate deeper understanding of individual labor supply choices, especially for women, who are more likely to engage in unpaid care and home production. However, traditional time use data collection methods are time-consuming, expensive and susceptible to significant attrition. To address these concerns, we develop an abbreviated, low-cost time use survey module designed for low-literacy populations. It captures contextually-determined broad time use categories of interest to researchers - in our case, time allocations across market work, household labor, and leisure. Using survey experiments in the field, we show that, relative to the widely-used assisted diary approach, the new module is lower cost and relatively more accurate in capturing individuals’ average time use. Its primary shortcomings are its limited ability to capture short duration activities and simultaneous activities. Using the example of passive childcare, we show how module design can provide accurate information on multitasking for an identified category of interest.]]></description><author>Erica M. Field, Rohini Pande, Natalia Rigol, Simone G. Schaner, Elena M. Stacy, Charity M. Troyer Moore</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29671</guid></item><item><title>Land Security and Mobility Frictions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29666</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tasso Adamopoulos, Loren Brandt, Chaoran Chen, Diego Restuccia, Xiaoyun Wei.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Developing countries are characterized by frictions that impede the mobility of workers across occupations and space. We disentangle the role of insecure property rights from other labor mobility frictions for the reallocation of labor from agriculture to non-agriculture and from rural to urban areas. We combine rich household and individual-level panel data from China and an equilibrium quantitative framework that features the sorting of workers across locations and occupations. We explicitly model the farming household and the endogenous decisions of who operates the family farm and who potentially migrates, capturing an additional channel of selection within the household. We find that land insecurity has substantial negative effects on agricultural productivity and structural change, raising the share of households operating farms by almost 30 percentage points and depressing agricultural productivity by more than 10 percent. Quantitatively, land insecurity is as important as all other labor mobility frictions. We measure a sharp reduction in overall labor mobility barriers over 2004-2018 in the Chinese economy, all of which can be accounted for by improved land security, consistent with reforms covering rural land in China during the period.]]></description><author>Tasso Adamopoulos, Loren Brandt, Chaoran Chen, Diego Restuccia, Xiaoyun Wei</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29666</guid></item><item><title>Caught In The Middle: The Bias Against Startup Innovation With Technical And Commercial Challenges</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29654</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ashish Arora, Andrea Fosfuri, Thomas Roende.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Startups in IT and life sciences appear to be flourishing. However, startups in other sectors, such as new materials, automation, and eco-innovations, which are often called "deep tech", seem to struggle. We argue that innovations with both technical and commercial challenges, typical of deep tech innovations, are especially disadvantaged in a startup-based innovation system. We develop an analytical model where startups are more efficient at solving technical challenges and incumbents are more efficient at solving commercial challenges. We find that the startup-based system works better for "specialized" innovations, where only one type of challenges is significant. Startups which face both technical and commercial challenges are disadvantaged because they capture a smaller fraction of the value they create. We discuss the implications for various public policies that have been proposed to encourage deep-tech.]]></description><author>Ashish Arora, Andrea Fosfuri, Thomas Roende</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29654</guid></item><item><title>How Distortive are Turnover Taxes? Evidence from Replacing Turnover Tax with VAT</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29650</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jing Xing, Katarzyna A. Bilicka, Xipei Hou.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> In this paper, we investigate distortions created by turnover taxes. As a natural experiment, we explore a reform that replaced turnover taxes with value-added taxes for some service industries in China, while the taxation of manufacturing industries remained unchanged. The reform increased sales, R&amp;D investment, and employment for affected service firms, which is primarily driven by outsourcing from downstream manufacturing firms. We document that smaller and less innovative manufacturing firms outsource more, and reallocation increases the quality of innovation for affected service firms. Our study provides new evidence on the negative impact of turnover taxes imposed on business inputs.]]></description><author>Jing Xing, Katarzyna A. Bilicka, Xipei Hou</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29650</guid></item><item><title>Large Firms, Consumer Heterogeneity and the Rising Share of Profits</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29646</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Robert C. Feenstra, Luca Macedoni, Mingzhi Xu.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We examine the relationship between large firms and the rising profit share in a model that features oligopolistic competition and consumer heterogeneity. Conditional on the sales distribution, the presence of consumer heterogeneity increases the profit share because it increases firm-level markups. Using data on purchases at the household-barcode level from Nielsen, we quantify the role of consumer heterogeneity, finding that the aggregate markup and the profit share are 8 and 3 percentage points larger than those predicted by a model of a representative consumer. Furthermore, we find that the profit share has been increasing over time and that firm targeting of consumer types plays a role in explaining this rise.]]></description><author>Robert C. Feenstra, Luca Macedoni, Mingzhi Xu</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29646</guid></item><item><title>Technology and Resilience</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29644</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Diego A. Comin, Marcio Cruz, Xavier Cirera, Kyung Min Lee, Jesica Torres.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper estimates the impact of technology sophistication pre-COVID-19 on the performance of firms during the early stages of the pandemic. We exploit a unique data covering firms from Brazil, Senegal, and Vietnam using a treatment effect mediation framework to decompose the results into a direct and an indirect effect. Increasing pre-pandemic technology sophistication by one standard deviation is associated with 3.8pp higher sales. Both effects are positive, but the direct effect is about 5 times larger than the indirect effect. The total effect on sales is markedly nonlinear with significantly smaller estimates of the reduction in sales for firms with more sophisticated pre-pandemic technology. Our results are robust to different measures of digital responses and matching estimators.]]></description><author>Diego A. Comin, Marcio Cruz, Xavier Cirera, Kyung Min Lee, Jesica Torres</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29644</guid></item><item><title>Agrarian Origins of Individualism and Collectivism</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29643</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Fiszbein, Yeonha Jung, Dietrich Vollrath.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We study the influence of agricultural labor intensity on individualism across U.S. counties. To measure historical labor intensity in agriculture we combine data on crop-specific labor requirements and county-specific crop mix around 1900. To address endogeneity we exploit climate-induced variation in crop mix. Our estimates indicate that an increase of one standard deviation in labor intensity is associated with a reduction of 0.2-0.4 standard deviations in individualism (as captured by the share of children with infrequent names). We further document consistent patterns using within-county changes in labor intensity over time due to both mechanization and the boll weevil shock. While culture transformed in response to changes in labor intensity, we also find that historical agricultural patterns had a lasting imprint that influences geographic variation in individualism today.]]></description><author>Martin Fiszbein, Yeonha Jung, Dietrich Vollrath</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29643</guid></item><item><title>How Do Top Acquirers Compare in Technology Mergers? New Evidence from an S&amp;P Taxonomy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29642</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ginger Zhe Jin, Mario Leccese, Liad Wagman.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Some argue that large platforms, such as Alphabet/Google, Amazon, Apple, Facebook and Microsoft (or GAFAM), are unusual in their number, pace and concentration of technology mergers, with the potential to harm market competition. Using a unique taxonomy developed by S&amp;P Global Market Intelligence, we compare the M&amp;A activities of GAFAM to other top acquirers from 2010 to 2020. We find: (i) GAFAM completed more tech acquisitions per firm than other groups of top acquirers, and acquired younger and more consumer-facing firms on average. (ii) The top 25 private equity firms outpaced GAFAM in tech acquisitions per firm since 2018. (iii) GAFAM acquisitions are less concentrated across tech categories than other top acquirer groups, due, in part, to an “acquire-adjacent-and-then-expand” strategy. (iv) Over time, more and more GAFAM and other top acquirers acquire in the same categories. (v) No evidence suggesting that a GAFAM acquisition in a category, compared to similar categories without GAFAM acquisitions, is correlated with a slowdown in the number of new acquirers acquiring in that category. Overall, we find that technology acquisitions do not shield GAFAM from competition, at least not from other GAFAM members or other firms that acquire in the same categories.]]></description><author>Ginger Zhe Jin, Mario Leccese, Liad Wagman</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29642</guid></item><item><title>Information versus Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29636</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stephen J. Terry, Toni M. Whited, Anastasia A. Zakolyukina.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We quantify the real implications of trade-offs between firm information disclosure and long-term investment efficiency. We estimate a dynamic equilibrium model in which firm managers confront realistic incentives to misreport earnings and distort their real investment choices. The model implies a socially optimal level of disclosure regulation that exceeds the estimated value. Counterfactual analysis reveals that eliminating earnings misreporting completely through disclosure regulation incentivizes managers to distort real investment. Lower earnings informativeness raises the cost of capital, which results in a 5.7% drop in average firm value, but more modest effects on social welfare and aggregate growth.]]></description><author>Stephen J. Terry, Toni M. Whited, Anastasia A. Zakolyukina</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29636</guid></item><item><title>Global Innovation and Knowledge Diffusion</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29629</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nelson Lind, Natalia Ramondo.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We develop a Ricardian model of trade in which countries innovate ideas that diffuse across the globe. In this model, the forces of innovation and diffusion combine to shape trade substitution patterns. Innovation makes a country technologically distinct, reducing their substitutability with other countries, while diffusion between countries generates technological similarity and increases head-to-head competition. In the special case of an innovation-only model where countries do not share ideas, productivities are independent across space, and the demand system is CES. As a consequence, departures from CES expenditure reveal diffusion patterns. Our theoretical results provide a mapping between the dynamics of observable trade flows and the dynamics of innovation and knowledge diffusion.]]></description><author>Nelson Lind, Natalia Ramondo</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29629</guid></item><item><title>Revealing Corruption: Firm and Worker Level Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29627</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Emanuele Colonnelli, Spyridon Lagaras, Jacopo Ponticelli, Mounu Prem, Margarita Tsoutsoura.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We study how the disclosure of corrupt practices affects the growth of firms involved in illegal interactions with the government using randomized audits of public procurement in Brazil. On average, firms exposed by the anti-corruption program grow larger after the audits, despite experiencing a decrease in procurement contracts. We manually collect new data on the details of thousands of corruption cases, through which we uncover a large heterogeneity in our firm-level effects depending on the degree of involvement in corruption cases. Using investment-, loan-, and worker- level data, we show that the average exposed firms adapt to the loss of government contracts by changing their investment strategy. They increase capital investment and borrow more to finance such investment, while there is no change in their internal organization.  We provide qualitative support to our results by conducting new face-to-face surveys with business owners of government-dependent firms.]]></description><author>Emanuele Colonnelli, Spyridon Lagaras, Jacopo Ponticelli, Mounu Prem, Margarita Tsoutsoura</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29627</guid></item><item><title>Vertical Differentiation in Frictional Product Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29618</link><description><![CDATA[<i>James Albrecht, Guido Menzio, Susan Vroman.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We consider a version of the imperfect competition model of Butters (1977), Varian (1980) and Burdett and Judd (1983) in which sellers make an ex-ante investment in the quality of their variety of the product. Equilibrium exists, is unique and is efficient. In equilibrium, search frictions not only cause sellers to offer different surpluses to buyers but also cause sellers to choose different qualities for their varieties. That is, equilibrium involves endogenous vertical differentiation. As search frictions decline, the market becomes more and more unequal as a smaller and smaller fraction of sellers produces varieties of increasing quality, offers increasing surplus to their customers, and captures an increasing share of the market, while a growing fraction of sellers produces varieties of decreasing quality. Gains from trade and welfare grow. Under some conditions, the growth rate of gains from trade and welfare is constant.]]></description><author>James Albrecht, Guido Menzio, Susan Vroman</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29618</guid></item><item><title>The Price of Nails since 1695: A Window into Economic Change</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29617</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel E. Sichel.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper focuses on the price of nails since 1695 and the proximate source of changes in those prices. Why nails? They are a basic manufactured product whose form and quality have changed relatively little over the last three centuries, yet the process for producing them has changed dramatically. Accordingly, nails provide a useful prism through which to examine a wide range of economic and technological developments that touch on multiple areas of both micro- and macroeconomics. Several conclusions emerge. First, from the late 1700s to the mid 20th century real nail prices fell by a factor of about 10 relative to overall consumer prices. These declines had important effects on downstream industries, most notably construction. Second, while declining materials prices contribute to reductions in nail prices, the largest proximate source of the decline during this period was multifactor productivity growth in nail manufacturing, highlighting the role of the specialization of labor and re-organization of production processes. Third, the share of nails in GDP dropped back from 0.4 percent of GDP in 1810—comparable to today’s share of household purchases of personal computers—to a de minimis share more recently; accordingly, nails played a bigger role in American life in that earlier period. Finally, real nail prices have increased since the mid 20th century, reflecting in part an upturn in materials prices and a shift toward specialty nails in the wake of import competition, though the introduction of nail guns partly offset these increases for the price of installed nails.]]></description><author>Daniel E. Sichel</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29617</guid></item><item><title>International Trade and Innovation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29611</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ufuk Akcigit, Marc Melitz.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This chapter was prepared for the Handbook of International Economics (Vol. 5) edited by Gita Gopinath, Elhanan Helpman, and Kenneth Rogoff. We provide a review of the recent literature -- both theoretical and empirical -- analyzing the multi-dimensional connections between globalization and innovation. We develop a model that features many of those mechanisms that connect trade and innovation. It features the joint selection of firms into innovation and international market participation (in our model, we restrict that participation to exports). Our model also highlights how exposure to international markets affects the incentives for innovation.]]></description><author>Ufuk Akcigit, Marc Melitz</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29611</guid></item><item><title>Blackouts in the Developing World: The Role of Wholesale Electricity Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29610</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Akshaya Jha ⓡ, Louis Preonas ⓡ, Fiona Burlig ⓡ.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Blackouts impose substantial economic costs in developing countries. This paper advances a new explanation for their continued prevalence: unlike in high-income countries, where regulatory mandates require utilities to satisfy all electricity demand, utilities in developing countries respond to wholesale electricity prices. As a result, misallocation of output across power plants can decrease the quantity of electricity supplied to end-users. We provide empirical support for this explanation using novel data from India, home to the world’s third-largest electricity sector. In contrast to the developed world, we find that Indian wholesale demand is downward-sloping. Reducing supply-side misallocation would increase electricity supply for the average household by 1.7 percent (enough to power 4.6 million additional households). Justifying a mandate that utilities must satisfy all end-use demand would require consumers to value electricity far above the cost of diesel backup generation. However, such a mandate would likely be cost-effective if paired with supply-side reforms.]]></description><author>Akshaya Jha ⓡ, Louis Preonas ⓡ, Fiona Burlig ⓡ</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29610</guid></item><item><title>Innovation Networks and Innovation Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29607</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ernest Liu, Song Ma.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study the optimal allocation of R&amp;D resources in an endogenous growth model with an innovation network, through which one sector’s past innovations may benefit other sectors’ future innovations. First, we provide closed-form sufficient statistics for the optimal path of R&amp;D resource allocation, and we show that planners valuing long-term growth should allocate more R&amp;D toward key sectors that are upstream in the innovation network. Second, we extend to an open-economy setting and illustrate an incentive for countries to free-ride on fundamental technologies: an economy more reliant on foreign knowledge spillovers has less incentive to direct resources toward innovation-upstream sectors, leading to cross-country differences in unilaterally optimal R&amp;D allocations across sectors. Third, we build the global innovation network based on over 30 million global patents and establish its empirical importance for knowledge spillovers. Fourth, we apply the model to evaluate R&amp;D allocations across countries and time. Adopting optimal R&amp;D allocations can generate substantial welfare improvements across the globe. For the United States, R&amp;D misallocation accounts for about 0.68 percentage points of missing annual growth since the 2000s.]]></description><author>Ernest Liu, Song Ma</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29607</guid></item><item><title>Labor Reallocation and Remote Work During COVID-19: Real-time Evidence from GitHub</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29598</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Grant R. McDermott, Benjamin Hansen.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on labor activity using real-time data from millions of GitHub users around the world. We show that the pandemic triggered a sharp pattern of labor reallocation at both the global and regional level. Users were more likely to work on weekends and outside of traditional 9 am to 6 pm hours, especially during the early phase of the pandemic. We also document considerable heterogeneity between different user groups and locations. Some locations show a steady reversion back to historical work patterns, while others have experienced persistent trend deviations in the wake of COVID-19. The pattern of labor reallocation is slightly more pronounced among males in our sample, suggesting that men may have benefited more from the increased flexibility provided by remote work than women. Finally, we show that the pattern of reallocation was accompanied by a simultaneous increase in overall activity, though this effect is more transient. We discuss several potential mechanisms and draw tentative conclusions for broader workplace trends given our study population.]]></description><author>Grant R. McDermott, Benjamin Hansen</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29598</guid></item><item><title>Inequality in India Declined During COVID</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29597</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Arpit Gupta, Anup Malani, Bartosz Woda.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We use a large, representative panel data set from India with monthly data on household finances to examine the incidence of economic harms during the COVID pandemic.  We observe a sharp spike in poverty, peaking during India's sharp but short lockdown.  However, there was a striking decrease in income inequality outside the lockdown.  There was a smaller decrease in consumption inequality, likely due to consumption smoothing.  Evidence supports two mechanisms for the decline in income inequality: the capital income of top-quartile earners covaries more with aggregate income, and demand for labor fell more for higher quartiles.]]></description><author>Arpit Gupta, Anup Malani, Bartosz Woda</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29597</guid></item><item><title>International Evidence of Strengthening Taxes and Spending For Sustainable Development</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29594</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Donghyun Park.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We trace the linkages between the episodes of fiscal expansion and consolidation in 72 advanced and emerging and developing economies. The findings suggest that fiscal expansions are positively associated with economic growth, which in turn is positively linked with better sustainable development outcomes. The association between fiscal consolidation and growth as well as the sustainable development indicators, however, is not clear-cut. Jointly, more tax revenues and expenditures, together with better governance help explain the association between economic growth and inclusive development. High-income, high-tax-revenue, and manufacture-exporting economies have made significant progress on reducing disease-linked mortality and improving environment protection along with economic growth. Meanwhile, emerging and developing, low-tax-revenue, and commodity-exporting economies have gained notable improvement in poverty reduction, pre-primary enrolment and access to basic sanitation services and clean cooking fuels and technologies, and lowering bribery incidence. On average, the sampled economies have persistently achieved better primary goals such as sanitation, clean fuels and technologies. Achievements in mortality reduction, and environmental protection goals are shown more recently.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Donghyun Park</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29594</guid></item><item><title>Forced Displacement and Human Capital: Evidence from Separated Siblings</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29589</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Giorgio Chiovelli, Stelios Michalopoulos, Elias Papaioannou, Sandra Sequeira.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We examine the impact of conflict-driven displacement on human capital. We focus on the Mozambican civil war (1977–1992), during which more than four million civilians fled to the countryside, cities, and refugee camps and settlements in neighboring countries. We leverage the full post-war census to compare siblings separated during the war, using those who stayed behind as a counterfactual to one’s displacement path. Uprooted children register higher investments in education. Second, we quantify the relative importance of place-based and displacement effects. The latter increases education and decreases attachment to agriculture by the same rate as being exposed to an environment approximately one standard deviation more developed than one’s birthplace. Third, we conduct a survey in Nampula, whose population doubled during the civil war. Those who fled to the city have significantly higher education than their siblings who remained in the countryside and they converged to the levels of schooling of non-mover urban-born individuals. However, those displaced exhibit significantly lower social/civic capital and have worse mental health, even three decades after the war. These findings reveal that displacement shocks can trigger human capital investments, breaking links with subsistence agriculture, but at the cost of long-lasting, social, and psychological traumas.]]></description><author>Giorgio Chiovelli, Stelios Michalopoulos, Elias Papaioannou, Sandra Sequeira</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29589</guid></item><item><title>Information, Intermediaries, and International Migration</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29588</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Samuel Bazzi, Lisa Cameron, Simone G. Schaner, Firman Witoelar.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Job seekers often face substantial information frictions related to potential job quality. This is especially true in international labor markets, where intermediaries match prospective migrants with employers abroad. We conducted a randomized trial in Indonesia to explore how information about intermediary quality shapes migration choices and outcomes. Information reduces the migration rate, lowering use of low-quality intermediaries. However, workers who migrate receive better pre-departure preparation and have higher-quality job experiences abroad, despite no change in occupation or destination. Information does not change intentions to migrate or beliefs about the return to migration or intermediary quality. Nor does selection explain the improved outcomes for workers who choose to migrate with the information. Together, our findings are consistent with an increase in the option value of search: with better ability to differentiate offer quality, workers become choosier and ultimately have better migration experiences. This offers a new perspective on the importance of information and matching frictions in global labor markets.]]></description><author>Samuel Bazzi, Lisa Cameron, Simone G. Schaner, Firman Witoelar</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29588</guid></item><item><title>Private but Misunderstood? Evidence on Measuring Intimate Partner Violence via Self-Interviewing in Rural Liberia and Malawi</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29584</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Sungho Park, Shilpa Aggarwal, Dahyeon Jeong, Naresh Kumar, Jonathan Robinson, Alan Spearot.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Women may under-report intimate partner violence (IPV) in surveys due to a variety of social and psychological factors. To understand if anonymized interviewing can allay this concern, we conduct a measurement experiment in rural Liberia and Malawi in which women were asked IPV questions via either self-interviewing (SI) or face-to-face interviewing (FTFI) with an enumerator. We find that about a third of women incorrectly answer basic screening questions over SI, and that it generates placebo effects on innocuous questions even for those who "pass" screening. Because the probability of responding "yes" to any specific IPV question is less than 50%, and that IPV is typically reported as an index (reporting yes to at least one question in a category of violence), such misunderstanding will tend to increase IPV reporting. In Malawi, we find that SI dramatically increases reported IPV, with the incidence of any type of IPV increasing by 13 percentage points on a base of 20%; in Liberia, we find an insignificant and modest increase of 4 percentage points on a base of 39%. Our results suggest SI may spuriously increase reported IPV rates.]]></description><author>David Sungho Park, Shilpa Aggarwal, Dahyeon Jeong, Naresh Kumar, Jonathan Robinson, Alan Spearot</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29584</guid></item><item><title>Organizational Frictions and Increasing Returns to Automation: Lessons from AT&amp;T in the Twentieth Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29580</link><description><![CDATA[<i>James J. Feigenbaum, Daniel P. Gross.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> AT&amp;T was the largest U.S. firm for most of the 20th century. Telephone operators once comprised over 50% of its workforce, but in the late 1910s it initiated a decades-long process of automating telephone operation with mechanical call switching—a technology first invented in the 1880s. We study what drove AT&amp;T to do so, and why it took one firm nearly a century to automate this one basic function. Interdependencies between operators and nearly every other part of the business were obstacles: the manual switchboard was the fulcrum of a complex system which had developed around it, and automation only began after the firm and automatic technology were adapted to work together. Even then, automatic switching was only profitable for AT&amp;T in larger markets—hence diffusion expanded as costs declined and service areas grew. We show that automation supported AT&amp;T's continued growth, generating a positive feedback loop between scale and automation that reinforced AT&amp;T's high market share in local markets.]]></description><author>James J. Feigenbaum, Daniel P. Gross</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29580</guid></item><item><title>Effect of Health Insurance in India: A Randomized Controlled Trial</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29576</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anup Malani, Phoebe Holtzman, Kosuke Imai, Cynthia Kinnan, Morgen Miller, Shailender Swaminathan, Alessandra Voena, Bartosz Woda, Gabriella Conti.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We report on a large randomized controlled trial of hospital insurance for above-poverty-line Indian households.  Households were assigned to free insurance, sale of insurance, sale plus cash transfer, or control.  To estimate spillovers, the fraction of households offered insurance varied across villages.  The opportunity to purchase insurance led to 59.91% uptake and access to free insurance to 78.71% uptake.  Access increased insurance utilization. Positive spillover effects on utilization suggest learning from peers.  Many beneficiaries were unable to use insurance, demonstrating hurdles to expanding access via insurance.  Across a range of health measures, we estimate no significant impacts on health.]]></description><author>Anup Malani, Phoebe Holtzman, Kosuke Imai, Cynthia Kinnan, Morgen Miller, Shailender Swaminathan, Alessandra Voena, Bartosz Woda, Gabriella Conti</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29576</guid></item><item><title>Peltzman Revisited: Quantifying 21st Century Opportunity Costs of FDA Regulation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29574</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Casey B. Mulligan.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> This paper revisits Peltzman (1973) in light of two recent opportunities to quantitatively assess tradeoffs in drug regulation.  First, reduced regulatory barriers to drug manufacturing associated with the 2017 reauthorization of Generic Drug User Fee Amendments were followed by significantly more entry and lower consumer prices for prescription drugs.  Using a simple and versatile industry model and historical data on entry, I find that easing generic restrictions discourages innovation, but this welfare cost is more than offset by consumer benefits from enhanced competition, especially after 2016.  Second, accelerated vaccine approval in 2020 had unprecedented net benefits as it not only improved health but substantially changed the trajectory of the wider economy.  The evidence suggests that cost-benefit analysis of FDA regulation is incomplete without accounting for substitution toward potentially unsafe and ineffective treatments that are both outside FDA jurisdiction and heavily utilized prior to FDA approval.  Moreover, the policy processes initiating these 21st century regulatory changes show a clear influence of Peltzman’s 1973 findings.]]></description><author>Casey B. Mulligan</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29574</guid></item><item><title>Is Digital Credit Filling a Hole or Digging a Hole? Evidence from Malawi</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29573</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Valentina Brailovskaya, Pascaline Dupas, Jonathan Robinson.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Digital credit has expanded rapidly in Africa, mostly in the form of short-term, high-interest loans offered via mobile money. Loan terms are often opaque and consumer financial literacy is low, providing opportunities for predatory lending. A regression discontinuity analysis shows no negative effect of access to digital loans on financial well-being, but the majority of borrowers fail to repay on time and incur high late fees. We randomize exposure to a short phone-based financial literacy intervention. The intervention improved knowledge and marginally improved loan repayment but increased loan demand, increasing overall default risk.]]></description><author>Valentina Brailovskaya, Pascaline Dupas, Jonathan Robinson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29573</guid></item><item><title>Time Use and Gender in Africa in Times of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29571</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Taryn Dinkelman, L. Rachel Ngai.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Many African countries are still in the early stages of structural transformation. Typically, as economies move through the structural transformation, activities once conducted within the household are outsourced to the market. This has particular implications for women’s time use. In this paper, we document that current patterns of female time use in home production in several African countries closely resemble historical time use patterns in the US. We highlight two stylized facts about women’s time use in Africa. First, in North Africa, women spend very few hours in market work and female labor force participation overall is extremely low. Second, although extensive margin participation of women is high in sub-Saharan Africa, women tend to work in the market for only a few hours each week, with the rest of their work hours spent in home production. These two facts suggest two types of constraints that could slow down the reallocation of female time from home to market as economies grow: Social norms related to women’s market work, and a lack of infrastructure (e.g. household infrastructure and childcare facilities) to facilitate marketizing home production. We discuss recent empirical evidence related to each set of constraints and highlight new avenues for research.]]></description><author>Taryn Dinkelman, L. Rachel Ngai</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29571</guid></item><item><title>Labor Productivity Growth and Industrialization in Africa</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29570</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Margaret S. McMillan, Albert Zeufack.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Manufacturing has made an important contribution to raising living standards in many parts of the world. Concerns about premature deindustrialization have made some observers skeptical about the potential for manufacturing to play this role in Africa. But employment in African manufacturing has grown rapidly over the past 20 years. These employment gains have been accompanied by: (i) large increases in the number of small manufacturing firms; (ii) limited employment gains in large firms; and (iii) robust labor productivity growth in Africa’s large firms. Limited employment growth in Africa’s large manufacturing firms is partly a result of the capital intensity of the manufacturing sub-sectors in which African countries are most engaged – the processing of resources, and partly a result of rising capital intensity in manufacturing. The potential for manufacturing to raise living standards in Africa depends on indirect job creation by large firms through backward and forward linkages and increasing labor productivity in small firms.]]></description><author>Margaret S. McMillan, Albert Zeufack</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29570</guid></item><item><title>STEM Employment Resiliency During Recessions: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29568</link><description><![CDATA[<i>James C. Davis, Holden A. Diethorn, Gerald R. Marschke, Andrew J. Wang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Employment in STEM occupations suffered smaller peak-to-trough percentage declines than non-STEM occupations during the Great Recession and COVID-19 recession, suggesting a relative resiliency of STEM employment.  We exploit the sudden peak-to-trough declines in STEM and non-STEM employment during the COVID-19 recession to measure STEM recession-resiliency, decomposing our difference-in-differences estimate into parts explained by various sources.  We find that STEM knowledge importance on the job explains the greatest share of STEM employment resiliency, and that workers in non-STEM occupations who nonetheless use STEM knowledge experienced better employment outcomes. STEM employment resiliency may explain the mild effects of COVID-19 on innovative activity.]]></description><author>James C. Davis, Holden A. Diethorn, Gerald R. Marschke, Andrew J. Wang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29568</guid></item><item><title>Randomization for Causality, Ethnography for Mechanisms: Illiquid Savings for Liquor in an Autarkic Society</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29566</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ricardo Godoy, Dean Karlan, Jonathan Zinman.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> What should researchers do when confronted with surprising results? Financial access innovations usually leave “temptation” spending unaffected or reduced. However, we found that promotion of savings lockboxes in a largely autarkic society increased alcohol consumption and blood pressure, despite no one reporting intentions to save for alcohol. To probe mechanisms that could explain this pattern, we then used ethnographic methods, including direct observations of drinking (“scans”) and debriefing interviews to discuss the earlier trial results. We learn that sponsoring drinks confers prestige, but the stigma attached to drinking by outsiders likely discouraged reporting intentions to save for it.]]></description><author>Ricardo Godoy, Dean Karlan, Jonathan Zinman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29566</guid></item><item><title>Customers and Retail Growth</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29561</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Liran Einav, Peter J. Klenow, Jonathan D. Levin, Raviv Murciano-Goroff.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Using Visa debit and credit card transactions in the U.S. from 2016 to 2019, we document the importance of customers in accounting for sales variation across merchants, across stores within retail chains, and over time for individual merchants and stores.  Customers, as opposed to transactions per customer or dollar sales per transaction, consistently account for about 80% of sales variation. The top 1% of growing and shrinking merchants account for about 70% of customer and sales reallocation in a given year. In order to illustrate some of the potential implications, we write down an endogenous growth model with and without the customer margin. In the context of this model, we find that the customer margin dramatically increases the size and growth contribution of the largest firms, but lowers the aggregate growth rate by diverting resources from research to customer acquisition activities.]]></description><author>Liran Einav, Peter J. Klenow, Jonathan D. Levin, Raviv Murciano-Goroff</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29561</guid></item><item><title>Technology-Skill Complementarity and Labor Displacement: Evidence from Linking Two Centuries of Patents with Occupations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29552</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leonid Kogan, Dimitris Papanikolaou, Lawrence D. W. Schmidt, Bryan Seegmiller.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We construct new technology indicators using textual analysis of patent documents and occupation task descriptions that span almost two centuries (1850–2010). At the industry level, improvements in technology are associated with higher labor productivity but a decline in the labor share. Exploiting variation in the extent certain technologies are related to specific occupations, we show that technological innovation has been largely associated with worse labor market outcomes—wages and employment—for incumbent workers in related occupations using a combination of public-use and confidential administrative data. Panel data on individual worker earnings reveal that less educated, older, and more highly-paid workers experience significantly greater declines in average earnings and earnings risk following related technological advances. We reconcile these facts with the standard view of technology-skill complementarity using a model that allows for skill displacement.]]></description><author>Leonid Kogan, Dimitris Papanikolaou, Lawrence D. W. Schmidt, Bryan Seegmiller</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29552</guid></item><item><title>Unlocking the Benefits of Credit through Saving</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29542</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sanghamitra W. Mukherjee, Lauren F. Bergquist, Marshall Burke, Edward Miguel.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Access to microcredit has been shown to generate only modest average benefits for recipient households. We study whether other financial market frictions—in particular, lack of access to a safe place to save—might limit credit's benefits. Working with Kenyan farmers, we cross-randomize access to a simple savings product with a harvest-time loan. Among farmers offered a loan, the additional offer of a savings lockbox increased farm investment by 11% and household consumption by 7%. Results suggest that financial market frictions can interact in important ways and that multifaceted financial access programs might unlock dynamic household gains.]]></description><author>Sanghamitra W. Mukherjee, Lauren F. Bergquist, Marshall Burke, Edward Miguel</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29542</guid></item><item><title>Race and Economic Well-Being in the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29539</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jean-Felix Brouillette, Charles I. Jones, Peter J. Klenow.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We construct a measure of consumption-equivalent welfare for Black and White Americans. Our statistic incorporates life expectancy, consumption, leisure, and inequality, with mortality rates playing a key role quantitatively. According to our estimates, welfare for Black Americans was 43% of that for White Americans in 1984 and rose to 60% by 2019. Going back further in time (albeit with more limited data), the gap was even larger, with Black welfare equal to just 28% of White welfare in 1940. On the one hand, there has been remarkable progress for Black Americans: the level of their consumption-equivalent welfare increased by a factor of 28 between 1940 and 2019, when aggregate consumption per person rose a more modest 5-fold. On the other hand, despite this remarkable progress, the welfare gap in 2019 remains disconcertingly large. Mortality from COVID-19 has temporarily reversed a decade of progress, lowering Black welfare by 17% while reducing White welfare by 10%.]]></description><author>Jean-Felix Brouillette, Charles I. Jones, Peter J. Klenow</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29539</guid></item><item><title>Reconstruction Aid, Public Infrastructure, and Economic Development: The Case of the Marshall Plan in Italy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29537</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michela Giorcelli, Nicola Bianchi.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The Marshall Plan (1948–1952) was the largest aid transfer in history. This paper estimates its effects on Italy’s postwar economic development. It exploits differences between Italian provinces in the value of reconstruction grants they received. Provinces that could modernize more their infrastructure experienced higher increases in agricultural production, especially for perishable crops. In the same provinces, we observe larger investments in labor-saving machines, the entry of more firms into the industrial sector, and a larger expansion of the industrial and service workforce.]]></description><author>Michela Giorcelli, Nicola Bianchi</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29537</guid></item><item><title>“Golden Ages”: A Tale of the Labor Markets in China and the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29523</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hanming Fang, Xincheng Qiu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the labor markets in China and the United States, the two largest economies in the world, by examining the evolution of their cross-sectional age-earnings profiles during the past thirty years. We find that, first, the peak age in the cross-sectional age-earnings profiles, which we refer to as the “golden age,” stayed almost constant at around 45-50 in the U.S., but decreased sharply from 55 to around 35 in China; second, the age-specific earnings grew drastically in China, but stayed almost stagnant in the U.S.; third, the cross-sectional and life-cycle age-earnings profiles were remarkably similar in the U.S., but differed substantially in China. We propose and empirically implement a decomposition framework to infer from the repeated cross-sectional earnings data the experience effect (i.e., human capital accumulation over the life cycle), the cohort effect (i.e., inter-cohort human capital growth), and the time effect (i.e., changes in the human capital rental prices over time), under an identifying assumption that the growth of the experience effect stops at the end of one's working career. The decomposition suggests that China has experienced a much larger inter-cohort productivity growth and higher increase in the rental price to human capital, but lower returns to experience, compared to the U.S. We also use the inferred components to revisit several important and classical applications in macroeconomics and labor economics, including growth accounting and the estimation of TFP growth, and the college wage premium and skill-biased technical change.]]></description><author>Hanming Fang, Xincheng Qiu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29523</guid></item><item><title>Harvesting the Rain: The Adoption of Environmental Technologies in the Sahel</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29518</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jenny C. Aker, Kelsey Jack.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Many agricultural and environmental technologies require large upfront investments in exchange for longer-term benefits. This time profile of costs and benefits makes adoption particularly sensitive to liquidity and credit constraints, which are prevalent in low-income settings. We test the importance of these barriers to the adoption of an agricultural technique that helps reduce land degradation and restore soil fertility in Niger. We find little evidence that liquidity or credit constraints deter adoption: instead, providing farmers with training increases the share of adopters by over 90 percentage points, whereas adding conditional or unconditional cash transfers has no additional effect. Adoption increases agricultural output, reduces land turnover and leads to adoption spillovers up to three years after treatment. These results imply that training can be a cost-effective and scalable means of promoting the adoption of profitable technologies.]]></description><author>Jenny C. Aker, Kelsey Jack</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29518</guid></item><item><title>Technological Obsolescence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29504</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Song Ma.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper proposes a new measure of technological obsolescence using detailed patent data. Using this measure, we present two sets of results. First, firms' technological obsolescence foreshadows substantially lower growth, productivity, and reallocation of capital. This finding applies mainly for obsolescence of core innovation and embodied innovation, and it is stronger in competitive product markets. Second, in stock markets, high-obsolescence firms under-perform low-obsolescence firms by 7 percent annually. Using analyst forecast data, we show this is due to a systematic overestimation of future profits of obsolescent firms. The measure contains incremental information about firm innovation relative to measures focusing on new innovation.]]></description><author>Song Ma</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29504</guid></item><item><title>Globalization and the Ladder of Development: Pushed to the Top or Held at the Bottom?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29500</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Atkin, Arnaud Costinot, Masao Fukui.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the relationship between international trade and development in a model where countries differ in their capability, goods differ in their complexity, and capability growth is a function of a country’s pattern of specialization. Theoretically, we show that it is possible for international trade to increase capability growth in all countries and, in turn, to push all countries up the development ladder. This occurs because: (i) the average complexity of a country’s industry mix raises its capability growth, and (ii) foreign competition is tougher in less complex sectors for all countries. Empirically, we provide causal evidence consistent with (i) using the entry of countries into the World Trade Organization as an instrumental variable for other countries’ patterns of specialization. The opposite of (ii), however, appears to hold in the data. Through the lens of our model, these two empirical observations imply dynamic welfare losses from trade that are small for the median country, but pervasive and large among a number of African countries.]]></description><author>David Atkin, Arnaud Costinot, Masao Fukui</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29500</guid></item><item><title>Converging to Convergence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29484</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Kremer, Jack Willis, Yang You.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Empirical tests in the 1990s found little evidence of poor countries catching up with rich - unconditional convergence - since the 1960s, and divergence over longer periods. This stylized fact spurred several developments in growth theory, including AK models, poverty trap models, and the concept of convergence conditional on determinants of steady-state income. We revisit these findings, using the subsequent 25 years as an out-of-sample test, and document a trend towards unconditional convergence since 1990 and convergence since 2000, driven by both faster catch-up growth and slower growth of the frontier. During the same period, many of the correlates of growth - human capital, policies, institutions, and culture - also converged substantially and moved in the direction associated with higher income. Were these changes related? Using the omitted variable bias formula, we decompose the gap between unconditional and conditional convergence as the product of two cross-sectional slopes. First, correlate-income slopes, which remained largely stable since 1990. Second, growth-correlate slopes controlling for income - the coefficients of growth regressions - which remained stable for fundamentals of the Solow model (investment rate, population growth, and human capital) but which flattened substantially for other correlates, leading unconditional convergence to converge towards conditional convergence.]]></description><author>Michael Kremer, Jack Willis, Yang You</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29484</guid></item><item><title>Deindustrialization and Industry Polarization</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29483</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Sposi, Kei-Mu Yi, Jing Zhang.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We add to recent evidence on deindustrialization and document a new pattern: increasing industry polarization over time. We assess whether these patterns can be explained by a dynamic open economy model of structural change in which the two primary driving forces are sector-biased productivity growth and sectoral trade integration. We calibrate the model to the same countries used to document our patterns. We find that sector-biased productivity growth is important for deindustrialization, and sectoral trade integration is important for industry polarization through specialization. The interaction of these two driving forces is also essential. The key transmission channel is the declining relative price of manufacturing goods to services over time.]]></description><author>Michael Sposi, Kei-Mu Yi, Jing Zhang</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29483</guid></item><item><title>“If you compete with us, we shan't marry you” The (Mary Paley and) Alfred Marshall Lecture</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29481</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rohini Pande, Helena Roy.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Alfred Marshall and Mary Paley Marshall are often described as the first academic economist couple. Both studied at Cambridge University, where Paley became one of the first women to take the Tripos exam and the first female lecturer in economics, with Marshall’s encouragement. But in later life, Marshall opposed granting Cambridge degrees to women and their participation in academic economics. This paper recounts Alfred Marshall’s use of gender norms, born out of a separate spheres ideology, to promote and ingrain women’s exclusion in academic economics and beyond. We demonstrate the persistence of this ideology and resultant norms, drawing parallels between gendered inequities in labor market outcomes for Cambridge graduates in the UK post-Industrial Revolution and those apparent in cross-country data today. We argue that the persistence of the norms produced by separate spheres ideologies is likely to reflect, at least in part, the rents associated with preferential access to better paid, high-skilled labor market opportunities. In doing so, we ask who benefits from gender norms, who enforces them, and suggest relevant policy work and areas for future research.]]></description><author>Rohini Pande, Helena Roy</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29481</guid></item><item><title>Demographic Transitions Across Time and Space</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29480</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Matthew J. Delventhal, Jesús Fernández-Villaverde, Nezih Guner.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The demographic transition --the move from a high fertility/high mortality regime into a low fertility/low mortality regime-- is one of the most fundamental transformations that countries undertake. To study demographic transitions across time and space, we compile a data set of birth and death rates for 186 countries spanning more than 250 years. We document that (i) a demographic transition has been completed or is ongoing in nearly every country; (ii) the speed of transition has increased over time; and (iii) having more neighbors that have started the transition is associated with a higher probability of a country beginning its own transition. To account for these observations, we build a quantitative model in which parents choose child quantity and educational quality. Countries differ in geographic location, and improved production and medical technologies diffuse outward from Great Britain. Our framework replicates well the timing and increasing speed of transitions. It also produces a correlation between the speeds of fertility transition and increases in schooling similar to the one in the data.]]></description><author>Matthew J. Delventhal, Jesús Fernández-Villaverde, Nezih Guner</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29480</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Dynamics When Ideas are Harder to Find</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29479</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal, Niklas Engbom, Simon Mongey, Giovanni L. Violante.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper evaluates the impact of slowing economic growth on labor market dynamism and misallocation. It provides a model of endogenous growth via imitation in a frictional labor market. The framework accounts for rich data on worker job-to-job transitions as well as stochastic and lifecycle properties of firm growth and job reallocation. High productivity entrants gradually replace obsolescing incumbents by poaching their workers, a process that is intermediated via a frictional labor market. When the likelihood of entrants imitating technologies in the tail of the distribution falls (ideas are harder to find), so does growth. Consistent with US data over the past 30 years, firm entry, incumbents’ employment response to productivity shocks, and job-to-job transitions decline, while the share of old firms increases. With lower imitation, however, there is less misallocation, because the slower aggregate rate of obsolescence induces productive firms to invest more in costly hiring and grow faster to their optimal size.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal, Niklas Engbom, Simon Mongey, Giovanni L. Violante</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29479</guid></item><item><title>Cooperation in the Commons: Community-based Rangeland Management in Namibia</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29469</link><description><![CDATA[<i>D. Layne Coppock, Lucas Crowley, Susan L. Durham, Dylan Groves, Julian C. Jamison, Dean Karlan, Brien E. Norton, R. Douglas Ramsey.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Classic theories suggest that common pool resources are subject to overexploitation. Community-based resource management approaches may ameliorate “tragedy of the commons” effects. Using a randomized evaluation in Namibia’s communal rangelands, we find that a comprehensive four-year program to support community-based rangeland and cattle management led to persistent and large improvements for eight of thirteen indices of social and behavioral outcomes. Effects on rangeland health, cattle productivity and household economics, however, were either negative or nil. Positive impacts on community resource management may have been offset by communities’ inability to control grazing by non-participating herds and inhibited by an unresponsive rangeland sub-system. This juxtaposition, in which measurable improvements in community resource management did not translate into better outcomes for households or rangeland health, demonstrates the fragility of the causal pathway from program implementation to intended socioeconomic and environmental outcomes. It also points to challenges for improving climate change–adaptation strategies.]]></description><author>D. Layne Coppock, Lucas Crowley, Susan L. Durham, Dylan Groves, Julian C. Jamison, Dean Karlan, Brien E. Norton, R. Douglas Ramsey</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29469</guid></item><item><title>AI-tocracy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29466</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Beraja, Andrew Kao, David Y. Yang, Noam Yuchtman.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Can frontier innovation be sustained under autocracy? We argue that innovation and autocracy can be mutually reinforcing when: (i) the new technology bolsters the autocrat’s power; and (ii) the autocrat’s demand for the technology stimulates further innovation in applications beyond those benefiting it directly. We test for such a mutually reinforcing relationship in the context of facial recognition AI in China. To do so, we gather comprehensive data on AI firms and government procurement contracts, as well as on social unrest across China during the last decade. We first show that autocrats benefit from AI: local unrest leads to greater government procurement of facial recognition AI, and increased AI procurement suppresses subsequent unrest. We then show that AI innovation benefits from autocrats’ suppression of unrest: the contracted AI firms innovate more both for the government and commercial markets. Taken together, these results suggest the possibility of sustained AI innovation under the Chinese regime: AI innovation entrenches the regime, and the regime’s investment in AI for political control stimulates further frontier innovation.]]></description><author>Martin Beraja, Andrew Kao, David Y. Yang, Noam Yuchtman</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29466</guid></item><item><title>Firm-Level Upgrading in Developing Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29461</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Eric Verhoogen.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In principle, firms in developing countries benefit from the fact that advanced technologies and products have already been developed in industrialized countries and can simply be adopted, a process often referred to as industrial upgrading. But for many firms this advantage remains elusive. What is getting in the way? This paper reviews recent firm-level empirical research on the determinants of upgrading in developing countries. The first part focuses on how to define and measure various dimensions of upgrading --- learning, quality upgrading, technology adoption, and product innovation. The second part takes stock of recent micro-empirical evidence on the drivers of upgrading, classifying them as output-side drivers, input-side drivers, or drivers of know-how. The review concludes with some thoughts about promising directions for research in the area.]]></description><author>Eric Verhoogen</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29461</guid></item><item><title>Does Social Media cause Polarization? Evidence from access to Twitter Echo Chambers during the 2019 Argentine Presidential Debate</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29458</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rafael Di Tella, Ramiro H. Gálvez, Ernesto Schargrodsky.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study how two groups, those inside vs those outside echo chambers, react to a political event when we vary social media status (Twitter). Our treatments mimic two strategies often suggested as a way to limit polarization on social media: they expose people to counter-attitudinal data, and they get people to switch off social media. Our main result is that subjects that started inside echo chambers became more polarized when these two strategies were implemented. The only scenario where they did not become more polarized is when they did not even experience the political event. Interestingly, subjects that were outside echo chambers before our study began experienced no change (or a reduction) in polarization. We also study a group of non-Twitter users in order to have a simple, offline benchmark of the debate’s impact on polarization.]]></description><author>Rafael Di Tella, Ramiro H. Gálvez, Ernesto Schargrodsky</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29458</guid></item><item><title>Winner Takes All? Tech Clusters, Population Centers, and the Spatial Transformation of U.S. Invention</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29456</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Brad Chattergoon, William R. Kerr.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> U.S. invention has become increasingly concentrated around major tech centers since the 1970s, with implications for how much cities across the country share in concomitant local benefits. Is invention becoming a winner-takes-all race? We explore the rising spatial concentration of patents and identify an underlying stability in their distribution. Software patents have exploded to account for about half of patents today, and these patents are highly concentrated in tech centers. Tech centers also account for a growing share of non-software patents, but the reallocation, by contrast, is entirely from the five largest population centers in 1980. Non-software patenting is stable for most cities, with anchor tenants like universities playing important roles, suggesting the growing concentration of invention may be nearing its end. Immigrant inventors and new businesses aided in the spatial transformation.]]></description><author>Brad Chattergoon, William R. Kerr</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29456</guid></item><item><title>Technology Transfer and Early Industrial Development: Evidence from the Sino-Soviet Alliance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29455</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michela Giorcelli, Bo Li.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the causal effect of technology and knowledge transfers on early industrial development. Between 1950 and 1957, the Soviet Union supported the “156 Projects” in China for the construction of technologically advanced, large-scale, capital-intensive industrial facilities. We exploit idiosyncratic delays in project completion and the unexpected end of the Sino-Soviet Alliance, due to which some projects received Soviet technology embedded in capital goods and know-how, while others were eventually realized by China alone using domestic technology. We find that receiving both Soviet technology and know-how had large, persistent effects on plant performance, while the effects of receiving only Soviet capital goods were short-lived. The intervention generated horizontal and vertical spillovers, as well as production reallocation from state-owned to privately owned companies since the late 1990s.]]></description><author>Michela Giorcelli, Bo Li</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29455</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Gap in Preferences: Evidence from 45,397 Facebook Interests</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ángel Cuevas, Rubén Cuevas, Klaus Desmet, Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses information on the frequency of 45,397 Facebook interests to study how the difference in preferences between men and women changes with a country's degree of gender equality. For preference dimensions that are systematically biased toward the same gender across the globe, differences between men and women are larger in more gender-equal countries. In contrast, for preference dimensions with a gender bias that varies across countries, the opposite holds. This finding takes an important step toward reconciling evolutionary psychology and social role theory as they relate to gender.]]></description><author>Ángel Cuevas, Rubén Cuevas, Klaus Desmet, Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</guid></item><item><title>Water Treatment and Child Mortality: Evidence from Kenya</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29447</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Johannes Haushofer, Michael Kremer, Ricardo Maertens, Brandon Joel Tan.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Each year, around 500,000 children under 5 die from diarrhea, making it the third-leading cause of death in this age group. More than 80 percent of these deaths are attributable to unsafe drinking water. Drinking water can be made safe through dilute chlorine solution, but take-up of this technology has been low. Previous work has shown that free community-wide provision of dilute chlorine solution through “dispensers” – reservoirs of chlorine solution at water sources that make chlorination easy and free – increases take-up of chlorination. However, it has remained unclear whether this increase also translates into reduced mortality. Here we show that four years of community-wide provision of dilute chlorine solution in rural Kenya reduces all-cause under-5 mortality by 1.4 percentage points (95% CI: 0.3 pp, 2.5 pp), a 63% reduction relative to control. We estimate that at USD 25 per DALY averted, free provision of chlorine solution is twenty times more cost-effective than the WHO “highly cost-effective” threshold.]]></description><author>Johannes Haushofer, Michael Kremer, Ricardo Maertens, Brandon Joel Tan</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29447</guid></item><item><title>Estimating the Economic Value of Zoning Reform</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29440</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Santosh Anagol, Fernando V. Ferreira, Jonah M. Rexer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We develop a framework to estimate the economic value of a recent zoning reform in the city of Sao Paulo, which altered maximum permitted construction at the city-block level. Using a spatial regression discontinuity design, we find that developers file for more multi-family construction permits in blocks with higher allowable densities. We incorporate these micro-estimates into an equilibrium model of housing supply and demand to estimate the long term impact of zoning changes. Supply responses from the reform produce a 2.2 percent increase in the total housing stock, leading to a 0.5% reduction in prices on average, with substantial heterogeneity across neighborhoods. Consumer welfare gains due to price reductions are small, but increase 4-fold once we account for changes in the built environment, with more gains accruing to college-educated and higher income households. However, nominal house price losses faced by existing homeowners and landlords overshadow all consumer welfare gains.]]></description><author>Santosh Anagol, Fernando V. Ferreira, Jonah M. Rexer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29440</guid></item><item><title>The Economics of Medical Procedure Innovation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29438</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Dranove, Craig Garthwaite, Christopher Heard, Bingxiao Wu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper explores the economic incentives for medical procedure innovation. Using a proprietary dataset on billing code applications for emerging medical procedures, we highlight two mechanisms that could hinder innovation. First, the administrative hurdle of securing permanent, reimbursable billing codes substantially delays innovation diffusion. We find that Medicare utilization of innovative procedures increases nearly nine-fold after the billing codes are promoted to permanent (reimbursable) from provisional (non-reimbursable). However, only 29 percent of the provisional codes are promoted within the five-year probation period. Second, medical procedures lack intellectual property rights, especially those without patented devices. When appropriability is limited, specialty medical societies lead the applications for billing codes. We indicate that the ad hoc process for securing billing codes for procedure innovations creates uncertainty about both the development process and the allocation and enforceability of property rights. This stands in stark contrast to the more deliberate regulatory oversight for pharmaceutical innovations.]]></description><author>David Dranove, Craig Garthwaite, Christopher Heard, Bingxiao Wu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29438</guid></item><item><title>Women in Science. Lessons from the Baby Boom</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29436</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Scott Daewon Kim, Petra Moser.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> How do children affect women in science? We investigate this question using rich biographical data, linked with patents and publications, for 83,000 American scientists in 1956 at the height of the baby boom. Our analyses reveal a unique life-cycle pattern of productivity for mothers. While other scientists peak in their mid-thirties, mothers become more productive after age 35 and maintain high productivity in their 40s and 50s. Event studies show that the output of mothers increases after 15 years of marriage, while other scientists peak in the first 10 years. Differences in the timing of productivity have important implications for tenure and participation. Just 27% of mothers who are academic scientists get tenure, compared with 48% of fathers and 46% of women without children. Mothers face comparable tenure rates to other assistant professors for the first six years but fall behind afterwards, suggesting that they face higher standards of early productivity. Mothers who survive in science are extremely positively selected: Compared with other married women, mothers patent (publish) 2.5 (1.4) times more before the median age at marriage. Compared with men, female scientists are more educated, half as likely to marry, one-third as likely to have children, but half as likely to survive in science. Employment records indicate that a generation of baby boom mothers was lost to science.]]></description><author>Scott Daewon Kim, Petra Moser</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29436</guid></item><item><title>"Potential Capital”, Working From Home, and Economic Resilience</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29431</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Janice C. Eberly, Jonathan Haskel, Paul Mizen.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The impact of an economic shock depends both on its severity and the resilience of the economic response. Resilience can include the ability to relocate factors, for example, even when new technologies or skills are not yet at the ready. This resilience per se buffers production and has an economic value, which we estimate. The COVID-19 pandemic caused a widespread decline in recorded GDP. Yet, as catastrophic as the collapse was, it was buffered by an unprecedented and spontaneous deployment of what we call “Potential Capital,” the dwelling/residential capital and connective technologies used alongside working from home. Together potential capital and labor working from home provided additional output margins and capacity. We estimate the contribution of this capital, and the remote work that it facilitated, to have roughly halved the decline in GDP in the US reducing the fall in GDP to 9.4 log points in 2020Q2 at the trough of the recession. Similar effects are seen in the 6 OECD countries for which data are available, output fell by 14 log points, but would have fallen by 26 log points had only workplace inputs been available. Accounting for the contribution of “Potential Capital” also revises downwards estimated total productivity gains in the business sector during the pandemic from 8 log points to 5 log points in 2020Q2. We also find an output elasticity of domestic non-dwellings capital to be similar to that of workplace ICT capital, reflecting its role as productive capital. Turning to the future, changes in working from home depend upon relative costs, relative technologies and, crucially, the elasticity of substitution between home and work tasks. We estimate that that elasticity to be more than unity, meaning that the growth of ICT will raise the share of work done remotely.]]></description><author>Janice C. Eberly, Jonathan Haskel, Paul Mizen</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29431</guid></item><item><title>Loan Officers Impede Graduation from Microfinance: Strategic Disclosure in a Large Microfinance Institution</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29427</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Natalia Rigol, Benjamin N. Roth.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> One of the most important puzzles in microfinance is the low rate of borrower graduation to larger, more flexible loans. Utilizing observational and experimental data from a large Chilean microfinance institution, we demonstrate that loan officers impede borrower graduation due to common features of their compensation contracts. Our partner lender offers both microloans and larger, more flexible graduation loans, and relies on loan officer endorsements to determine borrower graduation. Loan officers are rewarded for the size of their portfolio and repayment, and so are implicitly penalized when good borrowers graduate. In an experiment designed to isolate strategic disclosure, we modify compensation to reduce this implicit penalty and document that loan officers withheld endorsements of their most qualified borrowers prior to the shift. Graduated borrowers endorsed after the shift are 34% more profitable for our partner lender than those endorsed beforehand. A back-of-the- envelope calculation suggests that strategic behavior of loan officers accounts for $4.8-29.2 billion in lost social value from forgone borrower graduations in microfinance worldwide. Our experimental design may prove useful for other experiments within firms.]]></description><author>Natalia Rigol, Benjamin N. Roth</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29427</guid></item><item><title>Population Growth and Firm Dynamics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29424</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Peters, Conor Walsh.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Population growth has declined markedly in almost all major economies since the 1970s. We argue this trend has important consequences for the process of firm dynamics and aggregate growth. We study a rich semi-endogenous growth model of firm dynamics, and show analytically that a decline in population growth reduces creative destruction, increases average firm size and concentration, raises market power and misallocation, and lowers aggregate growth in the long-run. We also show lower population growth has positive effects on the level of productivity, making the short-run welfare impacts ambiguous. In a quantitative application to the U.S, we find that the slowdown in population growth since the 1980s and the projected continuation of this trend accounts for a substantial share of the fall in the entry and exit rates and the increase in firm size. By contrast, the impact on markups is modest. The effect on aggregate growth is positive for around two decades, before turning negative thereafter.]]></description><author>Michael Peters, Conor Walsh</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29424</guid></item><item><title>Mental Health, Creativity, and Wealth</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29422</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Barbara Biasi, Michael S. Dahl, Petra Moser.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Focusing on bipolar disorder (BD), we investigate the link between mental health, creativity, and wealth. Analyzing population data for Denmark, we find that people with BD are more likely to be musicians, but less likely to hold other creative jobs than the population. Healthy siblings of people with BD, however, are consistently more likely to work in creative jobs. We also show people in the top decile of parental wealth are seven times as likely to work in creative professions compared with the bottom decile. Yet, wealth differences only explain a small portion of the link between BD and creativity.]]></description><author>Barbara Biasi, Michael S. Dahl, Petra Moser</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29422</guid></item><item><title>Does Research Save Lives? The Local Spillovers of Biomedical Research on Mortality</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29420</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rebecca McKibbin, Bruce A. Weinberg.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper investigates the local impact of biomedical research on mortality in the USA. Causally estimating the marginal value of biomedical research is challenging due to a lack of micro data linking health outcomes to plausibly exogenous variation in research. We create a new linkage between a research database (PubMed) and administrative death records that enables research to be related to mortality at the geographic, disease and time level. We then estimate the marginal impact of biomedical research on mortality using hospital market (HRR) level shocks to research activity by disease. Our identification strategy builds on the literature on the dissemination of knowledge, specifically that of local knowledge spillovers. By utilizing variation across diseases, time and distance from research we control for additional trends relative to the current literature. Our results show that an additional research publication on average reduces local mortality from a disease by 0.35%. Our results also provide novel evidence that there are health benefits to the local communities (local spillovers) in which biomedical research is conducted.]]></description><author>Rebecca McKibbin, Bruce A. Weinberg</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29420</guid></item><item><title>Immigration and Occupational Comparative Advantage</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29418</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gordon H. Hanson, Chen Liu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Job choice by high-skilled foreign-born workers in the US correlates strongly with country of origin. We apply a Fréchet-Roy model of occupational choice to evaluate the causes of immigrant sorting. In a gravity specification, we find that revealed comparative advantage in the US is stronger for workers from countries with higher education quality in occupations that are more intensive in cognitive reasoning, and for workers from countries that are more linguistically similar to the US in occupations that are more intensive in communication. Our findings hold for immigrants who arrived in the US at age 18 or older (who received their K-12 education abroad) but not for immigrants who arrived in the US as children (who received their K-12 education domestically). We obtain similar results for immigrant sorting in Canada, which supports our interpretation that origin-country education quality, rather than US immigration policy, is what drives sorting patterns. In counterfactual analysis, we evaluate the consequences of reallocating visas for college-educated immigrants according to origin-country education quality.]]></description><author>Gordon H. Hanson, Chen Liu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29418</guid></item><item><title>Mental Health Therapy as a Core Strategy for Increasing Human Capital: Evidence from Ghana</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the impact of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) for individuals selected from the general population of poor households in rural Ghana. Results from 2-3 months after a randomized intervention show strong impacts on mental and physical health, cognitive and socioemotional skills, and downstream economic outcomes. We find no evidence of heterogeneity by baseline mental distress; we argue that this is because CBT can improve human capital for a general population of poor individuals through two pathways. First, CBT reduces vulnerability to deteriorating mental health; and second, CBT directly improves bandwidth, increasing cognitive and socioemotional skills and hence economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Consequences of the Opium War</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29404</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Wolfgang Keller, Carol H. Shiue.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the economic consequences of the West’s foray into China after the Opium War (1839-42), when Western colonial influence was introduced in dozens of so-called treaty ports. We document a turnaround during the 19th century in the nature of China’s capital markets. Whereas before the Opium War, coastal cities were of relatively minor importance, the treaty port system of the West transformed China into an economy focused on coastal areas and on international trade that aligned with the trading interests of the West. We show, first, that the West had a positive impact on China’s economy during the 19th century. It brought down local interest rates, and regions under Western influence exhibited both higher rates of industry growth and technology adoption. Second, the geographic scope of influence went far beyond the ports, impacting most of China. Interest rates fell by more than a quarter in the immediate vicinity of the ports and still by almost ten percent at distances of 450 kilometers from treaty ports. The development of China was not simply propelled by its own pre-1800 history, or by post-1978 reforms. The nearly 100 years of semi-colonization have shaped China’s economy today as one focused on the coastal areas.]]></description><author>Wolfgang Keller, Carol H. Shiue</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29404</guid></item><item><title>Policy Experimentation in China: the Political Economy of Policy Learning</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29402</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Shaoda Wang, David Y. Yang.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Many governments have engaged in policy experimentation in various forms to resolve uncertainty and facilitate learning. However, little is understood about the characteristics of policy experimentation, and how the structure of experimentation may affect policy learning and policy outcomes. We aim to describe and understand China’s policy experimentation since 1980, among the largest and most systematic in recent history. We collect comprehensive data on policy experimentation conducted in China over the past four decades. We find three main results. First, more than 80% of the experiments exhibit positive sample selection in terms of a locality’s economic development, and much of this can be attributed to misaligned incentives across political hierarchies. Second, local politicians allocate more resources to ensure the experiments’ success, and such effort is not replicable when policies roll out to the entire country. Third, the presence of sample selection and strategic effort is not fully accounted for by the central government, thus affecting policy learning and distorting national policies originating from the experimentation. Taken together, these results suggest that while China’s bureaucratic and institutional conditions make policy experimentation at such scale possible, the complex political environments can also limit the scope and bias the direction of policy learning.]]></description><author>Shaoda Wang, David Y. Yang</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29402</guid></item><item><title>The Human Side of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We document that nearly half of the global decline in agricultural employment during the 20th-century was driven by new cohorts entering the labor market. A newly compiled dataset of policy reforms supports an interpretation of these cohort effects as human capital. Through the lens of a model of frictional labor reallocation, we conclude that human capital growth, both as a mediating factor and as an independent driver, led to a sharp decline in the agricultural labor supply. This decline accounts, at fixed prices, for 40% of the decrease in agricultural employment. This aggregate effect is roughly halved in general equilibrium.]]></description><author>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</guid></item><item><title>Household Credit as Stimulus? Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> From 2011 to 2014, the Brazilian government conducted a heavily advertised major credit expansion program through government banks as part of its effort to stimulate the economy. Using administrative data on individual-level borrowing and spending, we find that the program led to a substantial rise in borrowing by government employees, especially those with low financial literacy. We trace the impact of credit stimulus on borrowers' consumption through the 2011-16 business cycle, and find that the credit stimulus resulted in higher consumption volatility and lower average consumption over the cycle. Our results suggest a potential downside of using household credit as stimulus in emerging markets.]]></description><author>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</guid></item><item><title>Fleshing Out the Olive? On Income Polarization in China</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29383</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Ravallion, Shaohua Chen.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> In a rare example of an explicit national goal for income distribution besides reducing poverty, China’s leadership has recently committed to expanding the middle-income share—moving to a less polarized “olive-shaped” distribution. Recognizing the potential trade-offs, the paper asks whether China’s experience indicates that income-polarization was a by-product of past economic progress, including poverty reduction. The paper does not find robust time-series evidence of polarizing effects alongside either economic growth or population urbanization (including among those below the national median). There was strong co-movement between polarization and inequality. Larger urban-rural gaps in mean incomes are strongly polarizing in China.]]></description><author>Martin Ravallion, Shaohua Chen</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29383</guid></item><item><title>Misallocation in Indian Agriculture</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29363</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marijn A. Bolhuis, Swapnika R. Rachapalli, Diego Restuccia.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We exploit substantial variation in land-market institutions across Indian states and detailed micro household-level panel data to assess the effect of distortions in land rental markets on agricultural productivity. We provide empirical evidence that states with more rental-market activity feature less misallocation and reallocate land more efficiently over time. We develop a model of heterogeneous farms and land rentals to estimate land-market distortions in each state. Land rentals have substantial positive effects on agricultural productivity: an efficient reallocation of land increases agricultural productivity by 38 percent on average and by more than 50 percent in states with highly distorted rental markets. Both farm and state-level land market distortions are quantitatively important, with state-level wedges accounting for a significant fraction of rental market participation differences across states. Land market distortions contribute about one-third to the large differences in agricultural total factor productivity across Indian states.]]></description><author>Marijn A. Bolhuis, Swapnika R. Rachapalli, Diego Restuccia</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29363</guid></item><item><title>Early Childhood Development, Human Capital and Poverty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29362</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Orazio Attanasio, Sarah Cattan, Costas Meghir.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Children's experiences during early childhood are critical for their cognitive and socio-emotional development, two key dimensions of human capital. However, children from low income backgrounds often grow up lacking stimulation and basic investments, leading to developmental deficits that are difficult, if not impossible, to reverse later in life without intervention. The existence of these deficits are a key driver of inequality and contribute to the intergenerational transmission of poverty. In this paper, we discuss the framework used in economics to model parental investments and early childhood development and use it as an organizing tool to review some of the empirical evidence on early childhood research. We then present results from various important early childhoods interventions with emphasis on developing countries. Bringing these elements together we draw conclusions on what we have learned and provide some directions for future research.]]></description><author>Orazio Attanasio, Sarah Cattan, Costas Meghir</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29362</guid></item><item><title>The Effects of Taxes on Innovation: Theory and Empirical Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29359</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefanie Stantcheva.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Income taxes are typically set to raise revenues and redistribute income at the lowest possible efficiency costs, which result from the distortions in individual behaviors that taxes entail. Individuals can respond along many margins, such as labor supply, tax avoidance and evasion, and geographic mobility. But one margin that taxes may affect — innovation — is less frequently considered. Conceptually, taxes reduce the expected net returns to innovation inputs and can reduce innovation. Much like other margins of responses to taxes, this efficiency cost must be taken into account. Innovation is done by a relatively small number of people, but it is nevertheless likely to have widespread benefits. While inventors may have divergent motivations, such as social recognition or the love of discovery, they also face an economic reality. How strongly innovation responds to taxes is an empirical question that has been the subject of a growing body of recent work. In this paper, I study how to account for innovation when setting personal income and capital taxation. I distinguish between two cases: one in which the government can set a differentiated tax on inventors and one in which the government is constrained to set the same tax on all agents. I provide a model that flexibly accounts for the spillovers generated by innovation and the non-pecuniary benefits inventors receive from innovation and derive tax formulas expressed in terms of estimable sufficient statistics. The second part of the paper discusses the empirical evidence on the effects of taxes on the quantity, quality, and location of innovation, as well as tax avoidance and income shifting done through innovation.]]></description><author>Stefanie Stantcheva</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29359</guid></item><item><title>Economic Production and Biodiversity in the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29357</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yuanning Liang, Ivan J. Rudik, Eric Zou.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Species extinctions and ecological degradation are accelerating to a degree unprecedented in human history. We present causal evidence on the economic drivers of biodiversity loss using a novel panel dataset on the types and quantities of wildlife at thousands of locations across the U.S. from 1960-2015. Exploiting fiscal and regulatory shocks to local economic output, we document large, negative impacts of GDP on abundance and diversity of species spanning multiple taxa. The adverse effects of production are mitigated by conservation and air emission abatement efforts, which points toward habitat losses and pollution as underlying contributors to contemporaneous biodiversity declines.]]></description><author>Yuanning Liang, Ivan J. Rudik, Eric Zou</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29357</guid></item><item><title>Closing the Innovation Gap in Pink and Black</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29354</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Lisa D. Cook, Janet Gerson, Jennifer Kuan.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Recent research shows the negative impact of discrimination not only on the targets of discrimination but also on the economy as a whole. Racial and gender inequality can limit the entire economy's productive capacity and innovation outcomes. Using new data from NSF's Survey of Earned Doctorates on the scientific workforce from 1980 to 2019, as well as patenting and commercialization data, we examine racial and gender disparities at each stage of the innovation process—education and training, the practice of invention, and commercialization. While improving along certain dimensions over time, we find persistent racial and gender disparities consistent with the current literature. To reverse the negative effects on productive capacity and long-run economic growth, we also discuss the literature on mitigating discriminatory practices at each juncture, which could have significant distributional effects as access to good jobs expands.]]></description><author>Lisa D. Cook, Janet Gerson, Jennifer Kuan</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29354</guid></item><item><title>Outsourcing, Inequality and Aggregate Output</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Outsourced workers experience large wage declines, yet domestic outsourcing may raise aggregate productivity. To study this equity-efficiency trade-off, we contribute a framework in which firms either hire many imperfectly substitutable worker types in-house by posting wages along a job ladder, or rent labor services from contractors who hire in the same frictional labor markets. Three implications arise. First, more productive firms are more likely to outsource to save on higher wage premia. Second, outsourcing raises output at the firm level. Third, contractors endogenously locate at the bottom of the job ladder, implying that outsourced workers receive lower wages. Using firm-level instruments for outsourcing and revenue productivity, we find empirical support for all three predictions in French administrative data. After structurally estimating the model, we find that the rise in outsourcing in France between 1996 and 2007 raised aggregate output by 3% and reduced the labor share by 0.7 percentage points. A 9% minimum wage increase stabilizes the labor share and maintains two thirds of the output gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</guid></item><item><title>Why do people stay poor?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clare A. Balboni, Oriana Bandiera, Robin Burgess, Maitreesh Ghatak, Anton Heil.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> There are two broad views as to why people stay poor. One emphasizes differences in fundamentals, such as ability, talent or motivation. The other, the poverty traps view, differences in opportunities which stem from access to wealth. To test between these two views, we exploit a large-scale, randomized asset transfer and an 11-year panel on 6000 households who begin in extreme poverty. The setting is rural Bangladesh and the asset is cows. The data supports the poverty traps view - we identify a threshold level of initial assets above which households accumulate assets, take on better occupations (from casual labor in agriculture or domestic services to running small livestock businesses) and grow out of poverty. The reverse happens for those below the threshold. Structural estimation of an occupational choice model reveals that almost all beneficiaries are misallocated in the work they do at baseline and that the gains arising from eliminating misallocation would far exceed the program costs. Our findings imply that large transfers which create better jobs for the poor are an effective means of getting people out of poverty traps and reducing global poverty.]]></description><author>Clare A. Balboni, Oriana Bandiera, Robin Burgess, Maitreesh Ghatak, Anton Heil</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</guid></item><item><title>The Economics of the COVID-19 Pandemic in Poor Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29339</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Edward Miguel, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic has upended health and living standards around the world. This article provides an interim overview of these effects, with a particular focus on low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). Economists have explained how the pandemic is likely to have differential consequences for LMICs, and demand distinct policy responses, compared to rich countries. We survey the rapidly expanding body of empirical research that documents its many adverse economic and non-economic effects in terms of living standards, education, health, and gender equality, which appear to be unprecedented in depth and scale. We also review research on successful and failed policy responses, including the failure to ensure widespread vaccine coverage in LMICs, which is needed to end the pandemic. We close with a discussion of implications for public policy in LMICs, and for the institutions of international governance, given the likelihood of future pandemics and other major shocks (e.g., climate).]]></description><author>Edward Miguel, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29339</guid></item><item><title>Creative Destruction, Distance to Frontier, and Economic Development</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29333</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Peters, Fabrizio Zilibotti.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We construct a model of creative destruction with endogenous firm dynamics. We integrate the theory into a general equilibrium multi-country model of technological convergence where countries interact via international spillovers. We derive implications for both firm dynamics and aggregate productivity dynamics. In richer economies, firms are on average larger and the best firms grow larger over time. In poorer economies, there is little creative destruction, low selection, and firms remain small. We estimate the parameters of the model using firm-level data for India and the United States. We study the effect of counterfactual policy reforms. Industrial policy that selectively targets the more productive firms can be beneficial in poor countries while being harmful in countries close to the economic frontier. The findings echo Acemoglu et al. (2006).]]></description><author>Michael Peters, Fabrizio Zilibotti</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29333</guid></item><item><title>Market Size and Spatial Growth - Evidence from Germany’s Post-War Population Expulsions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29329</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Peters.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Virtually all theories of economic growth predict a positive relationship between population size and productivity. In this paper I study a particular historical episode to provide direct evidence for the empirical relevance of such scale effects. In the aftermath of the Second World War about 8m ethnic Germans were expelled from their domiciles in Eastern Europe and transferred to West Germany. This inflow increased the German population by almost 20%. Using variation across counties I show that the settlement of refugees had a large and persistent effect on the size of the local population, manufacturing employment and income per capita. I show that these findings are quantitatively consistent with an idea-based model of spatial growth if population mobility is subject to frictions and productivity spillovers occur locally. The model implies that the refugee settlement increased aggregate income per capita by about 12% after 25 years and that the historical settlement rule triggered persistent industrialization of rural areas.]]></description><author>Michael Peters</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29329</guid></item><item><title>Economic Growth and Bank Innovation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29326</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gary B. Gorton, Ping He.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Based on archival and survey data we show that the maturity of U.S. business loans has been continuously increasing since the mid-1930s when banks invented the term loan. Concurrently, bank innovation first involved the invention of credit analysis and covenant design. Later, bank innovation included the advent of loan sales, increased loan syndications, the opening of the leveraged loan market, and the securitization of loans in collateralized loan obligations. We estimate and calibrate a model of bank innovation to determine the quantitative contribution of bank innovation to economic growth.]]></description><author>Gary B. Gorton, Ping He</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29326</guid></item><item><title>Big Loans to Small Businesses: Predicting Winners and Losers in an Entrepreneurial Lending Experiment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We experimentally study the impact of substantially larger enterprise loans, in collaboration with an Egyptian lender. Larger loans generate small average impacts, but machine learning using psychometric data reveals dramatic heterogeneity. Top-performers (i.e., those with the highest predicted treatment effects) substantially increase profits, whereas profits for poor-performers drop. The magnitude of this difference implies that an individual lender’s credit allocation choices matter for aggregate income. Evidence on two fronts suggests large loans would be misallocated: top-performers are predicted by loan officers to have higher default rates; and, top-performers grow less than others when given small loans, implying that allocating larger loans based on prior performance is not efficient. Our results have important implications for credit expansion policy and our understanding of entrepreneurial talent: on the former, the use of psychometric data to identify top-performers suggests a pathway towards better allocation that revolves around entrepreneurial type more than firm type; on the latter, the reversal of fortune for poor-performers, who do well with small loans but not large, indicates a type of entrepreneur that we call a “go-getter” who performs well when constrained but poorly when not.]]></description><author>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</guid></item><item><title>Electoral Violence and Supply Chain Disruptions in Kenya's Floriculture Industry</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29297</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher Ksoll, Rocco Macchiavello, Ameet Morjaria.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Violent conflicts, particularly at election times in Africa, are a common cause of instability and economic disruption. This paper studies how firms react to electoral violence using the case of Kenyan flower exporters during the 2008 post-election violence as an example. The violence induced a large negative supply shock that reduced exports primarily through workers' absence and had heterogeneous effects: larger firms and those with direct contractual relationships in export markets suffered smaller production and losses of workers. On the demand side, global buyers were not able to shift sourcing to Kenyan exporters located in areas not directly affected by the violence nor to neighboring Ethiopian suppliers. Consistent with difficulties in insuring against supply-chain risk disruptions caused by electoral violence, firms in direct contractual relationships ramp up shipments just before the subsequent 2013 presidential election to mitigate risk.]]></description><author>Christopher Ksoll, Rocco Macchiavello, Ameet Morjaria</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29297</guid></item><item><title>Privatization of Public Goods: Evidence from the Sanitation Sector in Senegal</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29295</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua W. Deutschmann, Jared E. Gars, Jean-François Houde, Molly Lipscomb, Laura A. Schechter.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Privatization of a public good (the management of sewage treatment centers in Dakar, Senegal) leads to an increase in the productivity of downstream sewage dumping companies and a decrease in downstream prices of the services they provide to households. We use the universe of legal dumps of sanitation waste from May 2009 to November 2018 to show that legal dumping increased substantially following privatization–on average an increase of 61.7%, or an increase of about 14,000 cubic meters each month. This is due to increased productivity of all trucks, not just those associated with the company managing the treatment centers. Household-level survey data shows that prices of legal sanitary dumping decreased by ten percent following privatization, and DHS data show that diarrhea rates among children under five decreased in Dakar relative to secondary cities in Senegal following privatization with no similar effect on respiratory illness as a placebo.]]></description><author>Joshua W. Deutschmann, Jared E. Gars, Jean-François Houde, Molly Lipscomb, Laura A. Schechter</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29295</guid></item><item><title>Social and Financial Incentives for Overcoming a Collective Action Problem</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29294</link><description><![CDATA[<i>M. Mehrab Bakhtiar, Raymond Guiteras, James A. Levinsohn, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Addressing public health externalities often requires community-level collective action. Each person’s sanitation behavior can affect the health of neighbors. We report on a cluster randomized controlled trial conducted with 19,000 households in rural Bangladesh where we randomized (1) either group financial incentives or a non-financial “social recognition” reward, and (2) asking each household to make either a private pledge or a public pledge to maintain hygienic latrines. The group financial reward has the strongest impact in the short term (3 months), inducing a 7.5-12.5 percentage point increase in hygienic latrine ownership. Getting people to publicly commit to maintaining and using a hygienic latrine in front of their neighbors induced a 4.2-6.1 percentage point increase in hygienic latrine ownership in the short term. In the medium term (15 months), the effect of the financial reward dissipates while the effect of the public commitment persists. Neither social recognition nor private commitments produce effects statistically distinguishable from zero.]]></description><author>M. Mehrab Bakhtiar, Raymond Guiteras, James A. Levinsohn, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29294</guid></item><item><title>Bank Mergers, Acquirer Choice and Small Business Lending: Implications for Community Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29284</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Bernadette A. Minton, Alvaro G. Taboada, Rohan Williamson.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We examine the effects of bank merger and local market characteristics on local small business lending.  Mergers involving small, in-state acquirers are positively associated with small business loan (SBL) originations in counties where target banks are located.  Conversely, mergers involving large, out-of-state acquirers are associated with fewer SBL originations.  The analysis suggests that the results are driven by acquirer’s choice of target.  Small and in-state acquirers target banks that focus more on SBL and targets with strong relationships while large, out-of-state acquirers pursue better performing banks with stronger balance sheets and less focus on SBL.  Results are particularly strong in counties with a large number of small firms.  Post-merger activity supports banks expanding on their acquisition strategy decisions.  The findings suggest that acquirer strategy is important for evaluating the impact of acquisitions on local community development and that one-size-fits-all policy solutions for bank mergers may not produce common local outcomes.]]></description><author>Bernadette A. Minton, Alvaro G. Taboada, Rohan Williamson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29284</guid></item></channel></rss>