<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Country Studies</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Country Studies</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 11:08:40 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Assessing Misallocation in Agriculture: Plots versus Farms</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29749</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Fernando M. Aragón, Diego Restuccia, Juan Pablo Rud.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We assess the extent and cost of misallocation in agriculture in less-developed countries comparing the analysis at the plot and farm levels. Using detailed data from Uganda, we show that the plot-level analysis leads to extremely large estimates of reallocation gains, even after adjusting for measurement error and unobserved heterogeneity. These results reflect two empirical limitations of the plot as unit of analysis: excess measurement error and near constant returns to scale production estimates. We find limited evidence of substantial measurement error at the farm level.]]></description><author>Fernando M. Aragón, Diego Restuccia, Juan Pablo Rud</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29749</guid></item><item><title>Share Pledging in China: Funding Listed Firms or Funding Entrepreneurship?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29731</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhiguo He, Bibo Liu, Feifei Zhu.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> This paper studies the connection between share pledging and entrepreneurial activities in China, challenging the common wisdom that share pledging funds circle back to the listed firms. Share pledging funds are at the discretion of the shareholders who pledge their publicly traded shares, and survey evidence shows that a majority of the largest shareholders (67.3%) used pledging funds outside the listed firms. By linking firm registration data with share pledging data, we show a positive relation between shareholders’ pledging transactions and entrepreneurial activities. Utilizing the launch of the exchange market in 2013 as a quasi-natural experiment that favors share pledging by natural person shareholders against that by legal entity shareholders, our difference-in-differences (DiD) analysis shows natural person shareholders increased their entrepreneurial activities significantly in response to the policy shock, relative to legal entity shareholders. In addition to various robustness checks, we also show that shareholders with better access to share pledging invest more heavily in industries with above-median growth potential.]]></description><author>Zhiguo He, Bibo Liu, Feifei Zhu</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29731</guid></item><item><title>The Second World War, Inequality and the Social Contract in England</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29677</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leander Heldring, James A. Robinson, Parker J. Whitfill.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> What is the impact of warfare on inequality and the social contract? Using local data on bombing, the evolution of wealth inequality and vote shares for the Labour Party in England around World War II we establish two results. First, on average, we find no impact of bombing on inequality. However, there is considerable heterogeneity and this result is driven by the south. In the north of England bombing led to significant falls in inequality. Second, heavier bombing led to a significant increase in the vote share for Labour after the War everywhere, but this effect is transitory in the south while it is permanent in the north. Our results obtain both in a simple difference-in-differences framework as well as in a panel-regression discontinuity framework in which we exploit the limited range of German fighter escort planes. Our results provide novel causal evidence for the inequality reducing impact of warfare and we interpret them as consistent with the notion that the impact of the War also led to a reconfiguration of the social contract in England.]]></description><author>Leander Heldring, James A. Robinson, Parker J. Whitfill</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29677</guid></item><item><title>Large Firms, Consumer Heterogeneity and the Rising Share of Profits</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29646</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Robert C. Feenstra, Luca Macedoni, Mingzhi Xu.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We examine the relationship between large firms and the rising profit share in a model that features oligopolistic competition and consumer heterogeneity. Conditional on the sales distribution, the presence of consumer heterogeneity increases the profit share because it increases firm-level markups. Using data on purchases at the household-barcode level from Nielsen, we quantify the role of consumer heterogeneity, finding that the aggregate markup and the profit share are 8 and 3 percentage points larger than those predicted by a model of a representative consumer. Furthermore, we find that the profit share has been increasing over time and that firm targeting of consumer types plays a role in explaining this rise.]]></description><author>Robert C. Feenstra, Luca Macedoni, Mingzhi Xu</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29646</guid></item><item><title>Inequality in India Declined During COVID</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29597</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Arpit Gupta, Anup Malani, Bartosz Woda.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We use a large, representative panel data set from India with monthly data on household finances to examine the incidence of economic harms during the COVID pandemic.  We observe a sharp spike in poverty, peaking during India's sharp but short lockdown.  However, there was a striking decrease in income inequality outside the lockdown.  There was a smaller decrease in consumption inequality, likely due to consumption smoothing.  Evidence supports two mechanisms for the decline in income inequality: the capital income of top-quartile earners covaries more with aggregate income, and demand for labor fell more for higher quartiles.]]></description><author>Arpit Gupta, Anup Malani, Bartosz Woda</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29597</guid></item><item><title>Time Use and Gender in Africa in Times of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29571</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Taryn Dinkelman, L. Rachel Ngai.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Many African countries are still in the early stages of structural transformation. Typically, as economies move through the structural transformation, activities once conducted within the household are outsourced to the market. This has particular implications for women’s time use. In this paper, we document that current patterns of female time use in home production in several African countries closely resemble historical time use patterns in the US. We highlight two stylized facts about women’s time use in Africa. First, in North Africa, women spend very few hours in market work and female labor force participation overall is extremely low. Second, although extensive margin participation of women is high in sub-Saharan Africa, women tend to work in the market for only a few hours each week, with the rest of their work hours spent in home production. These two facts suggest two types of constraints that could slow down the reallocation of female time from home to market as economies grow: Social norms related to women’s market work, and a lack of infrastructure (e.g. household infrastructure and childcare facilities) to facilitate marketizing home production. We discuss recent empirical evidence related to each set of constraints and highlight new avenues for research.]]></description><author>Taryn Dinkelman, L. Rachel Ngai</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29571</guid></item><item><title>Labor Productivity Growth and Industrialization in Africa</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29570</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Margaret S. McMillan, Albert Zeufack.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Manufacturing has made an important contribution to raising living standards in many parts of the world. Concerns about premature deindustrialization have made some observers skeptical about the potential for manufacturing to play this role in Africa. But employment in African manufacturing has grown rapidly over the past 20 years. These employment gains have been accompanied by: (i) large increases in the number of small manufacturing firms; (ii) limited employment gains in large firms; and (iii) robust labor productivity growth in Africa’s large firms. Limited employment growth in Africa’s large manufacturing firms is partly a result of the capital intensity of the manufacturing sub-sectors in which African countries are most engaged – the processing of resources, and partly a result of rising capital intensity in manufacturing. The potential for manufacturing to raise living standards in Africa depends on indirect job creation by large firms through backward and forward linkages and increasing labor productivity in small firms.]]></description><author>Margaret S. McMillan, Albert Zeufack</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29570</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Gap in Preferences: Evidence from 45,397 Facebook Interests</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ángel Cuevas, Rubén Cuevas, Klaus Desmet, Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses information on the frequency of 45,397 Facebook interests to study how the difference in preferences between men and women changes with a country's degree of gender equality. For preference dimensions that are systematically biased toward the same gender across the globe, differences between men and women are larger in more gender-equal countries. In contrast, for preference dimensions with a gender bias that varies across countries, the opposite holds. This finding takes an important step toward reconciling evolutionary psychology and social role theory as they relate to gender.]]></description><author>Ángel Cuevas, Rubén Cuevas, Klaus Desmet, Ignacio Ortuño-Ortín</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29451</guid></item></channel></rss>