<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER working group Insurance</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER working group Insurance</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 22:16:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Gender Differences in Medical Evaluations: Evidence from Randomly Assigned Doctors</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29541</link><description><![CDATA[<b>December 2021</b> <p> While a growing body of evidence documents large gender disparities in health care and related social insurance programs, little is known about what drives these disparities.  We leverage administrative data and random assignment of doctors to patients inherent within the workers’ compensation insurance claim dispute resolution process to study the impact of gender match between doctors and patients on medical evaluations and subsequent social insurance benefits received. Compared to differences among their male patient counterparts, female patients randomly assigned a female doctor rather than a male doctor are 5.0% more likely to be evaluated as disabled and receive 8.5% more subsequent cash benefits on average. There is no analogous gender-match effect for male patients. The magnitude of these effects implies that having female doctors evaluate patients entirely offsets the observed gender gap in the likelihood of being evaluated as disabled when male doctors evaluate patients. We explore mechanisms through further analysis of the administrative data and complementary survey evidence. In addition, we present broader evidence on gender gaps in workers' compensation insurance and gender homophily in patients' selections of doctors in settings where patients have choice. Combining this evidence, we conduct policy counterfactuals illustrating how policies increasing gender diversity among doctors or increasing gender homophily in patient-doctor matches may impact gender gaps in evaluated disability. Our findings indicate that policies increasing the share of female patients evaluated by female doctors may substantially shrink gender gaps in medical evaluations and associated outcomes.]]></description><author>Marika Cabral, Marcus Dillender</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29541</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of Provider Payments on Health Care Utilization: Evidence from Medicare and Medicaid</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29471</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Provider payments are the key determinant of insurance generosity within many health insurance programs covering low-income populations. This paper analyzes the effects of a large, federally-mandated provider payment increase for primary care services provided to low-income elderly and disabled individuals.  Drawing upon comprehensive administrative payment and utilization data, we leverage variation across beneficiaries and across providers in the policy-induced payment increase in difference-in-differences and triple differences research designs. The estimates indicate that the provider payment reform led to a 6.3% increase in the targeted services provided to eligible beneficiaries, indicating an implied payment elasticity of 1.3.  Further, the provider payment reform decreased the fraction of low-income beneficiaries with no primary care visit in a year by 9%, completely closing the gap relative to higher-income beneficiaries with the same observable characteristics. Additionally, the results indicate that the payment reform caused an increase in established patient visits, with no increase in new patient visits. Heterogeneity analysis indicates that the payment increase led to an expansion of utilization for many subgroups, with somewhat larger effects among beneficiaries who are younger, are white, and live in areas with many primary care providers per capita.]]></description><author>Marika Cabral, Colleen Carey, Sarah Miller</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29471</guid></item><item><title>A Social Insurance Perspective on Pandemic Fiscal Policy: Implications for Unemployment Insurance and Hazard Pay</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> This paper considers fiscal policy during the pandemic through the lens of optimal social insurance. We develop a simple framework to analyze how government taxes and transfers could mimic the insurance against pandemic income losses that people would like to have had. Permutations of the framework provide insight into how unemployment insurance should be structured, when and how much hazard pay is called for, and whether fiscal policy should aim just to redistribute income or also to stimulate aggregate demand during a pandemic. When we use the insights from the model to evaluate unemployment insurance measures taken during the pandemic, we find that some, but far from all, of the implications of the social insurance framework were followed. In the case of hazard pay, we find that the proposal for a national program (the never-implemented HEROES Act) was both broader and more generous than a social insurance perspective would call for. We suggest that the social insurance perspective on fiscal policy is likely to become increasingly relevant as pandemics and climate-related natural disasters become more common causes of unemployment and recessions.]]></description><author>Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</guid></item><item><title>Market Segmentation and Competition in Health Insurance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29406</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> In the United States, households obtain health insurance through distinct market segments. We explore the economics of this segmentation by comparing coverage provided through small employers versus the individual marketplace. Using data from Oregon, we find households with group coverage spend 26% less on covered health care than households with individual coverage yet face higher markups. We develop a model of plan choice and health spending to estimate preferences in both markets and evaluate integration policies. In our setting, pooling can both mitigate adverse selection in the individual market and benefit small group households without raising taxpayer costs.]]></description><author>Michael J. Dickstein, Kate Ho, Nathaniel D. Mark</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29406</guid></item><item><title>Measuring the Welfare Cost of Asymmetric Information in Consumer Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Information asymmetries are known in theory to lead to inefficiently low credit provision, yet empirical estimates of the resulting welfare losses are scarce. This paper leverages a randomized experiment conducted by a large fintech lender to estimate welfare losses arising from asymmetric information in the market for online consumer credit. Building on methods from the insurance literature, we show how exogenous variation in interest rates can be used to estimate borrower demand and lender cost curves and recover implied welfare losses. While asymmetric information generates large equilibrium price distortions, we find only small overall welfare losses, particularly for high-credit-score borrowers.]]></description><author>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</guid></item><item><title>The Affordable Care Act After a Decade: Its Impact on the Labor Market and the Macro Economy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29240</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The Affordable Care Act (ACA) is one of the most important reforms of the US health insurance system since the introduction of Medicare. Since employment is a main source of health insurance for the working age population in the United States, this sweeping health insurance reform also has important implications for the labor market and the macro economy. In this paper, we survey the prototype models that are used in the macro and labor literature, extended to integrate health and health insurance, to study the short- and long-run consequences of the ACA. We also suggest open areas for future research.]]></description><author>Hanming Fang, Dirk Krueger</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29240</guid></item><item><title>Opportunity Unraveled: Private Information and the Missing Markets for Financing Human Capital</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29214</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Investing in college carries high returns, but comes with considerable risk. Financial products like equity contracts can mitigate this risk, yet college is typically financed through non­dischargeable, government-backed student loans. This paper argues that adverse selection has unraveled private markets for college-financing contracts that mitigate risk. We use survey data on students' expected post-college outcomes to estimate their knowledge about future outcomes, and we translate these estimates into their implication for adverse selection of equity contracts and several state-contingent debt contracts. We find students hold significant private knowledge of their future earnings, academic persistence, employment, and loan repayment likelihood, beyond what is captured by observable characteristics. For example, our empirical results imply that a typical college-goer must expect to pay back $1.64 in present value for every $1 of equity financing to cover the financier's costs of covering those who would adversely select their contract. We estimate that college-goers are not willing to accept these terms so that private markets unravel. Nonetheless, our framework quantifies significant welfare gains from government subsidies that would open up these missing markets and partially insure college-going risks.]]></description><author>Daniel Herbst, Nathaniel Hendren</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29214</guid></item><item><title>Hedging and Competition</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29207</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study how risk management through hedging impacts firms and competition among firms in the life insurance industry - an industry with over 7 Trillion in assets and over 1,000 private and public firms. We show that firms that are likely to face costly external finance increase hedging after staggered state-level financial reform that reduces the costs of hedging. Post reform impacted firms have lower risk and fewer negative income shocks. Product market competition is also impacted. Firms that previously are more likely to face costly external finance, lower price, increase policy sales and increase their market share post reform. The results are consistent with hedging allowing firms that face potential costly financial distress to decrease risk and become more competitive.]]></description><author>Erasmo Giambona, Anil Kumar, Gordon M. Phillips</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29207</guid></item><item><title>The Affordable Care Act After a Decade: Industrial Organization of the Insurance Exchanges</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29178</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The regulated insurance exchanges set up in the Affordable Care Act (ACA) were designed to deliver affordable, efficient health coverage through private insurers. It is crucial to study the complex industrial organization (IO) of these exchanges in order to assess their impacts to date, during the first decade of the ACA, and in order to project their impacts going forward. We revisit the inherent market failures in health care markets that necessitate key ACA exchange regulations and investigate whether they have succeeded in their goals of expanding coverage, creating robust marketplaces, providing product variety, and generating innovation in health care delivery. We discuss empirical IO research to date and also highlight shortcomings in the existing research that can be addressed moving forward. We conclude with a discussion of IO research-based policy lessons for the ACA exchanges and, more generally, for managed competition of private insurance in health care.]]></description><author>Benjamin R. Handel, Jonathan T. Kolstad</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29178</guid></item><item><title>Fairness in Incomplete Information Bargaining: Theory and Widespread Evidence from the Field</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29111</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper uses detailed data on sequential offers from seven vastly different real-world bargaining settings to document a robust pattern: agents favor offers that split the difference between the two most recent offers on the table. Our settings include negotiations for used cars, insurance injury claims, a TV game show, auto rickshaw rides, housing, international trade tariffs, and online retail. We demonstrate that this pattern can arise in a perfect Bayesian equilibrium of an alternating-offer game with two-sided incomplete information, but this equilibrium is far from unique. We then provide a robust-inference argument to explain why agents may view the two most recent offers as corresponding to the potential surplus. Split-the-difference offers under this weaker, robust inference can then be viewed as fair. We present a number of other patterns in each data setting that point to split-the-difference offers as a strong social norm, whether in high-stakes or low-stakes negotiations.]]></description><author>Daniel Keniston, Bradley J. Larsen, Shengwu Li, J.J. Prescott, Bernardo S. Silveira, Chuan Yu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29111</guid></item></channel></rss>