<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic International Finance</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic International Finance</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 14:03:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Bank Runs, Fragility, and Credit Easing</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29397</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We present a tractable dynamic macroeconomic model of self-fulfilling bank runs. A bank is vulnerable to a run when a loss of investors' confidence triggers deposit withdrawals and leads the bank to default on its obligations.  We analytically characterize how the vulnerability of an individual bank depends on macroeconomic aggregates and how the number of banks facing a run affects macroeconomic aggregates in turn. In general equilibrium, runs can be partial or complete, depending on aggregate leverage and the dynamics of asset prices. Our normative analysis shows that the effectiveness of credit easing and its welfare implications depend on whether a financial crisis is driven by fundamentals or by self-fulfilling runs.]]></description><author>Manuel Amador, Javier Bianchi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29397</guid></item><item><title>Blockchain Analysis of the Bitcoin Market</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29396</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> In this paper, we provide detailed analyses of the Bitcoin network and its main participants. We build a novel database using a large number of public and proprietary sources to link Bitcoin addresses to real entities and develop an extensive suite of algorithms to extract information about the behavior of the main market participants. We conduct three major pieces of analysis of the Bitcoin eco-system. First, we analyze the transaction volume and network structure of the main participants on the blockchain. Second, we document the concentration and regional composition of the miners which are the backbone of the verification protocol and ensure the integrity of the blockchain ledger. Finally, we analyze the ownership concentration of the largest holders of Bitcoin.]]></description><author>Igor Makarov, Antoinette Schoar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29396</guid></item><item><title>Is Stock Index Membership for Sale?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29365</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> While major stock market indices are followed by large monetary investments, we document that membership decisions for the S&amp;P 500 index have a nontrivial amount of discretion. We show that firms’ purchases of S&amp;P ratings appear to improve their chance of entering the index (but purchases of Moody’s ratings do not). Furthermore, firms tend to purchase more S&amp;P ratings when there are openings in the index membership. Such a pattern is also confirmed by an event study that explores a rule change on index membership in 2002. Finally, discretionary additions exhibit subsequent deterioration in financial performance relative to rule-based additions.]]></description><author>Kun Li, Xin (Kelly) Liu, Shang-Jin Wei</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29365</guid></item><item><title>Rethinking Exchange Rate Regimes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29347</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper employs an updated algorithm and database for classifying exchange rate and anchor currency choice, to explore the evolution of the global exchange rate system, including parallel rates, capital controls and reserves. In line with a large recent literature, we find that the dollar has become ever-more central as the de facto anchor or reference currencies for much of the world. Our discussion encompasses the history of anchor currency choice, methods for classifying exchange rate regimes, a detailed discussion of the evolution of regimes, the growing substitution of reserves for capital controls as a tool for exchange rate stabilization, the modern Triffin dilemma, and the surprising recent trend decline in volatility of exchange rates at the core of the system. It concludes with issues surrounding the rise of China.]]></description><author>Ethan Ilzetzki, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29347</guid></item><item><title>Macroprudential Policy during COVID-19: The Role of Policy Space</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper uses the initial phase of the COVID-19 pandemic to examine how macroprudential frameworks developed over the past decade performed during a period of heightened financial and economic stress. It discusses a new measure of the macroprudential stance that better captures the intensity of different policies across countries and time. Then it shows that macroprudential policy has been used countercyclically—with stances tightened during the 2010’s and eased in response to COVID-19 by more than previous risk-off periods. Countries that tightened macroprudential policy more aggressively before COVID, as well as those that eased more during the pandemic, experienced less financial and economic stress. Countries’ ability to use macroprudential policy, however, was significantly constrained by the extent of existing “policy space”, i.e., by how aggressively policy was tightened before COVID-19. The use of macroprudential tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use other policy tools (such as fiscal policy, monetary policy, FX intervention, and capital flow management measures), and the use of other tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use macroprudential policy. This suggests that although macroprudential tools are being used countercyclically and should therefore help stabilize economies and financial markets, there appears to be an opportunity to better integrate the use of macroprudential tools with other policies in the future.]]></description><author>Katharina Bergant, Kristin Forbes</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</guid></item><item><title>Decrypting New Age International Capital Flows</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29337</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper employs high frequency transactions data on the world’s oldest and most extensive centralized peer-to-peer Bitcoin market, which enables trade in the currencies of more than 135 countries.  We develop an algorithm that allows, with high probability, the detection of “crypto vehicle transactions” in which crypto currency is used to move capital across borders or facilitate domestic transactions. In contrast to previous work which has used “on-chain” data, our approach enables one to investigate parts of the vastly larger pool of “off-chain” transactions. We find that, as a conservative lower bound, over 7 percent of the 45 million trades on the exchange we explore represent crypto vehicle transactions in which Bitcoin is used to make payment in fiat currency.  Roughly 20 percent of these represent international capital flight/flows/remittances.  Although our work cannot be used to put a price on cryptocurrencies, it provides the first systematic quantitative evidence that the transactional use of cryptocurrencies constitutes a fundamental component of their value, at least under the current regulatory regime.]]></description><author>Clemens Graf von Luckner, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29337</guid></item><item><title>The Global Financial Cycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29327</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We review the literature on the empirical characteristics of the global financial cycle and associated stylized facts on international capital flows, asset prices, risk aversion and liquidity in the financial system. We analyse the co-movements of global factors in asset prices and capital flows with commodity prices, international trade and world output as well as the sensitivity of different parts of the world to the Global Financial Cycle.  We present evidence of the causal effects of the monetary policies of the US Federal Reserve, the European Central Bank and of the People's Bank of China on the Global Financial Cycle.  We then assess whether the 2008 financial crisis has altered the transmission channels of monetary policies on the Global Financial Cycle. Finally, we discuss the theoretical modelling of the Global Financial Cycle and avenues for future research.]]></description><author>Silvia Miranda-Agrippino, Hélène Rey</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29327</guid></item><item><title>Foreign Investors and U.S. Treasuries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29313</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> While foreigners are prominent in the Treasury market and in theoretical and empirical work, little is known about the nature of their Treasury portfolios. We provide novel evidence on foreigners' U.S. Treasury portfolios based on data not yet used by researchers: the security-level Treasury portfolios of foreigners and private U.S. investors. We find that private foreign investors earn above market returns and on a risk-adjusted basis both foreign private and foreign official investors outperform U.S. investors. Moreover, while foreign officials, with their broader objective functions, may well have inelastic demand, private foreign investors increase purchases of Treasuries and increase the duration of their Treasury portfolios when their sovereign yields are low or decrease relative to Treasury yields (that is, when CIP deviations decrease). Our results are so different from existing results that we close with a reconciliation exercise that provides a useful assessment of different sources of data on flows and holdings.]]></description><author>Alexandra M. Tabova, Francis E. Warnock</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29313</guid></item><item><title>International Reserve Management, Global Financial Shocks, and Firms’ Investment in Emerging Market Economies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29303</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We examine the effects of active international reserve management (IRM) conducted by central banks of emerging market economies (EMEs) on firm investment in the presence of global financial shocks. Using firm level data from 46 EMEs from 2000 to 2018, we document four findings. First, active IRM positively affects firm investment - the effect strengthens with the magnitude of adverse external financial shocks. Second, financially constrained firms, compared with unconstrained ones, are less responsive to active IRM. Third, our results suggest that the country credit spread is a plausible causal channel of the positive IRM effect on firm investment. Fourth, the policies of capital controls and exchange rate managements are complementary to the IRM – it is beneficial to form a macro policy mix including active IRM to safeguard firm investment against global financial shocks. Further, our results indicate the IRM effect on firm investment is both statistical and economical significance and is relevant to the aggregate economy.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yin-Wong Cheung, Xingwang Qian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29303</guid></item><item><title>From Hermit Kingdom to Miracle on the Han: Policy Decisions that Transformed South Korea into an Export Powerhouse</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29299</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> In 1960, South Korea’s exports were about 1 percent of GDP, and the country’s ability to import depended almost entirely on US aid. After changing its foreign exchange and trade policies in the mid-1960s, Korea saw a surge in exports to more than 10 percent of GDP by the end of the decade. What factors account for the shift in policy that enabled this dramatic export growth to occur? The United States helped initiate the process by withholding financial assistance, pressuring Korea to devalue its currency and reform its foreign exchange regime. Initially, the Korean government resisted taking these steps, but in 1964 it became firmly committed to an export promotion strategy to boost foreign exchange earnings and end its dependence on American aid.]]></description><author>Douglas A. Irwin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29299</guid></item><item><title>How Economic Ideas Led to Taiwan’s Shift to Export Promotion in the 1950s</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29298</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Taiwan was perhaps the first developing country to adopt an export-oriented trade strategy after World War II. The factors usually associated with big shifts in policy—a macroeconomic crisis, a change in political power or institutions, lobbying by export interests, pressure from international financial institutions—were not present; it was ideas that were key. In 1954, economist S. C. Tsiang proposed that Taiwan boost export earnings rather than squeeze import spending to deal with its chronic shortage of foreign exchange. He recommended a currency devaluation to establish a realistic exchange rate and a market-based system of foreign exchange allocation to end the inefficient rationing by the government. Four years later, a leading policymaker, K. Y. Yin, fought for the adoption of Tsiang’s proposal, helping clear the way for Taiwan’s phenomenal growth in trade.]]></description><author>Douglas A. Irwin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29298</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Policy in the Age of COVID: Does it ‘Get in all of the Cracks?’</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the effects of fiscal policy in response to the COVID-19 pandemic at the firm, sector, country and global level. First, we estimate the impact of COVID-19 and policy responses on small and medium sized enterprise (SME) business failures. We combine firm-level financial data from 50 sectors in 27 countries, a detailed I-O network, real-time data on lockdown policies and mobility patterns, and a rich model of firm behavior that allows for several dimensions of heterogeneity. We find: (a) Absent government support, the failure rate of SMEs would have increased by 9 percentage points, significantly more so in emerging market economies (EMs). With policy support it only increased by 4.3 percentage points, and even decreased in advanced economies (AEs). (b) Fiscal policy was poorly targeted: most of the funds disbursed went to firms who did not need it. (c) Nevertheless, we find little evidence of the policy merely postponing mass business failures or creating many ‘zombie’ firms: failure rates rise only slightly in 2021 once policy support is removed. Next, we build a tractable global intertemporal general equilibrium I-O model with fiscal policy. We calibrate the model to 64 countries and 36 sectors. We find that: (d) a sizable share of the global economy is demand-constrained under COVID-19, especially so in EMs. (e) Globally, fiscal policy helped offset about 8% of the downturn in COVID, with a low ‘traditional’ fiscal multiplier. Yet it significantly reduced the share of demand- constrained sectors, preserving employment in these sectors. (f) Fiscal policy exerted small and negative spillovers to output in other countries but positive spillovers on employment. (g) A two-speed recovery would put significant upwards pressure on global interest rates which imposes an additional headwind on the EM recovery. (h) Corporate and sovereign spreads rise when global rates increase, suggesting that EM may face challenging external funding conditions as AEs economies normalize.]]></description><author>Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, Ṣebnem Kalemli-Özcan, Veronika Penciakova, Nick Sander</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</guid></item><item><title>External Balance Sheets and the COVID-19 Crisis</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29277</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> At the onset of the COVID-19 economic crisis, as in other crisis episodes, the flight to safety was accompanied by a rapid appreciation of “safe haven” currencies. We quantify currency-induced balance sheet effects for total external positions as well as for individual asset classes using new data on the currency composition of cross-border stocks for 48 countries for the first quarter as well as for the full year 2020. We also conduct the stock-flow reconciliation of net international investment positions to measure overall valuation effects. We show that for many countries currency-induced valuation gains mitigated losses that resulted from declining asset prices in the first quarter of 2020. Moreover, for countries with excess capital out flows during this period, the impact on external balance sheet positions was mitigated by valuation gains. This is because, in contrast with past financial crises, many emerging markets did not experience negative external balance sheet effects from their currency depreciation, partly due to currency-induced valuation gains on equity positions offsetting losses on debt positions, partly due to reduced currency mismatch on their external debt positions.]]></description><author>Galina Hale, Luciana Juvenal</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29277</guid></item><item><title>The Aftermath of Debt Surges</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29266</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Debt in emerging market and developing economies (EMDEs) is at its highest level in half a century. In about nine out of 10 EMDEs, debt is higher now than it was in 2010 and, in half of the EMDEs, debt is more than 30 percentage points of gross domestic product higher. Historically, elevated debt levels increased the incidence of debt distress, particularly in EMDEs and particularly when financial market conditions turned less benign. This paper reviews an encompassing menu of options that have, in the past, helped lower debt burdens. Specifically, it examines orthodox options (enhancing growth, fiscal consolidation, privatization, and wealth taxation) and heterodox options (inflation, financial repression, debt default and restructuring). The mix of feasible options depends on country characteristics and the type of debt. However, none of these options comes without political, economic, and social costs. Some options may ultimately be ineffective unless vigorously implemented. Policy reversals in difficult times have been common. The challenges associated with debt reduction raise questions of global governance, including to what extent advanced economies can cast their net wider to cushion prospective shocks to EMDEs.]]></description><author>M. Ayhan Kose, Franziska L. Ohnsorge, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29266</guid></item><item><title>A Theory of the Global Financial Cycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29217</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We develop a theory to account for changes in prices of risky and safe assets and gross and net capital flows over the global financial cycle (GFC). The multi-country model features global risk-aversion shocks and heterogeneity of investors both within and across countries. Within-country heterogeneity is needed to account for the drop in gross capital flows during a negative GFC shock (higher global risk-aversion). Cross-country heterogeneity is needed to account for the differential vulnerability of countries to a negative GFC shock. The key vulnerability is associated with leverage. In both the data and the theory, leveraged countries (net borrowers of safe assets) deleverage through negative net outflows of risky assets and positive net outflows of safe assets, experience a rise in the current account and a greater than average drop in risky asset prices. The opposite is the case for non-leveraged countries (net lenders of safe assets).]]></description><author>J. Scott Davis, Eric van Wincoop</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29217</guid></item><item><title>Are Collateral-Constraint Models Ready for Macroprudential Policy Design?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29204</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the design of macroprudential policies based on quantitative collateral-constraint models. We show that the desirability of macroprudential policies critically depends on the specific form of collateral used in debt contracts: While inefficiencies arise when current prices affect collateral---a frequent benchmark used to guide policies---they do not when only future prices affect collateral. Since the microfoundations and quantitative predictions of models with future-price collateral constraints do not appear less plausible than those using current prices, we conclude that additional empirical work is essential for the use of these models in macroprudential policy design.]]></description><author>Pablo Ottonello, Diego J. Perez, Paolo Varraso</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29204</guid></item><item><title>Sovereign Spreads and the Political Leaning of Nations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29197</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Using data from 56 nations over 45 years, we find that nations that are more likely to elect left wing governments face higher (and more volatile) sovereign spreads. To explain these facts, we build a sovereign default model in which two policymakers (left and right) alternate in power. The probability of an incumbent staying in power is increasing in the share of government spending. We parametrize the left policymaker as having a higher marginal political gain from increasing government spending than the right does, a feature found in our data. Model economies in which the left is more frequently in power face worse borrowing terms due to higher default risk, a greater reluctance for fiscal austerity in bad times, and a higher share of government spending on average. These features imply large welfare losses for households.]]></description><author>Ionut Cotoc, Alok Johri, César Sosa-Padilla</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29197</guid></item><item><title>Do Central Banks Rebalance Their Currency Shares?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29190</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Do central banks rebalance their currency shares? The answer matters because the dollar’s predominant role in large official reserve holdings means that widespread rebalancing requires central banks to buy (sell) a depreciating (appreciating) dollar, stabilising its value against other major currencies. We hypothesise that larger reserve holdings have led central banks to approach their investment more systematically and to make rebalancing in the face of exchange rate changes the norm. We illustrate the choice with two polar case studies: the US clearly does not rebalance its small FX reserves; Switzerland does rebalance its very large reserves, so that changes in exchange rates do not move its currency allocation. Our hypothesis finds partial support in global aggregated data. They reject both no rebalancing and full rebalancing and point to emerging market economies as the source of the aggregate result. We also test for rebalancing with panel data and find that our sample economies on average again behave in intermediate fashion, partially but not fully rebalancing. However, when observations are weighted by the size of reserves, the panel analysis finds full rebalancing. A variety of control variables and splits of the panel sample do not alter the thrust of these findings. Central banks rebalance their FX reserves extensively but not uniformly.]]></description><author>Menzie D. Chinn, Hiro Ito, Robert N. McCauley</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29190</guid></item></channel></rss>