<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Environment</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Environment</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 10:02:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Minimax-Regret Climate Policy with Deep Uncertainty in Climate Modeling and Intergenerational Discounting</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29716</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stephen J. DeCanio, Charles F. Manski, Alan H. Sanstad.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Integrated assessment models have become the primary tools for comparing climate policies that seek to reduce greenhouse gas emissions. Policy comparisons have often been performed by considering a planner who seeks to make optimal trade-offs between the costs of carbon abatement and the economic damages from climate change. The planning problem has been formalized as one of optimal control, the objective being to minimize the total costs of abatement and damages over a time horizon. Studying climate policy as a control problem presumes that a planner knows enough to make optimization feasible, but physical and economic uncertainties abound. Manski, Sanstad, and DeCanio (2021) proposed and studied use of the minimax-regret (MMR) decision criterion to account for deep uncertainty in climate modeling. Here we study choice of climate policy that minimizes maximum regret with deep uncertainty regarding both the correct climate model and the appropriate time discount rate to use in intergenerational assessment of policy consequences. The analysis specifies a range of discount rates to express both empirical and normative uncertainty about the appropriate rate. The findings regarding climate policy are novel and informative. The MMR analysis points to use of a relatively low discount rate of 0.02 for climate policy. The MMR decision rule keeps the maximum future temperature increase below 2°C above the 1900-10 level for most of the parameter values used to weight costs and damages.]]></description><author>Stephen J. DeCanio, Charles F. Manski, Alan H. Sanstad</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29716</guid></item><item><title>Caught In The Middle: The Bias Against Startup Innovation With Technical And Commercial Challenges</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29654</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ashish Arora, Andrea Fosfuri, Thomas Roende.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Startups in IT and life sciences appear to be flourishing. However, startups in other sectors, such as new materials, automation, and eco-innovations, which are often called "deep tech", seem to struggle. We argue that innovations with both technical and commercial challenges, typical of deep tech innovations, are especially disadvantaged in a startup-based innovation system. We develop an analytical model where startups are more efficient at solving technical challenges and incumbents are more efficient at solving commercial challenges. We find that the startup-based system works better for "specialized" innovations, where only one type of challenges is significant. Startups which face both technical and commercial challenges are disadvantaged because they capture a smaller fraction of the value they create. We discuss the implications for various public policies that have been proposed to encourage deep-tech.]]></description><author>Ashish Arora, Andrea Fosfuri, Thomas Roende</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29654</guid></item><item><title>Bounds, Benefits, and Bad Air: Welfare Impacts of Pollution Alerts</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29637</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael L. Anderson, Minwoo Hyun, Jaecheol Lee.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Though air-quality alert systems (AQAS) cover more than 1.7 billion people worldwide, there has been little welfare analysis of these systems. This paper presents a theoretical framework for deriving lower bounds on the net benefits of an AQAS and applies it to a South Korean system currently covering over 51 million people. Estimating a regression discontinuity design, we find that an alert issuance reduced youth respiratory expenditures by 30% and adult cardiovascular expenditures by 23%. The overall system reduced externalized health expenditures by 28.6 million dollars during 2016–2017, with a minimum benefit-cost ratio of 7.1:1. Including dynamic impacts of alerts increases the minimum benefits (benefit-cost ratio) to 36.7 million dollars (9.2:1). Our findings imply that the AQAS generates significant net benefits and suggests that manipulation of air quality data, which has been observed in other contexts, may negatively impact social welfare.]]></description><author>Michael L. Anderson, Minwoo Hyun, Jaecheol Lee</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29637</guid></item><item><title>Mandated vs. Voluntary Adaptation to Natural Disasters: The Case of U.S. Wildfires</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29621</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Patrick W. Baylis, Judson Boomhower.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Despite escalating disaster losses and predicted increases in weather-related catastrophes, takeup of protective technologies and behaviors appears limited by myopia, externalities, and other factors. One response to such frictions is to mandate adaptive investment. We measure the effect of California's wildfire building codes on own- and neighboring structure survival using administrative damage and assessment data for most US homes experiencing wildfires since 2000. Differences across jurisdictions and vintages reveal remarkable resilience effects of building codes initially prompted by the deadly 1991 Oakland Firestorm. Codes also benefit neighbors. We use the results to estimate net social benefits of wildfire building standards.]]></description><author>Patrick W. Baylis, Judson Boomhower</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29621</guid></item><item><title>Collateral Damage: The Impact of Shale Gas on Mortgage Lending</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29494</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yanyou Chen, James W. Roberts, Christopher D. Timmins, Ashley Vissing.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We analyze mortgage lenders’ behavior with respect to shale gas risk during the period of the U.S. shale gas boom, which coincided with fluctuations in the U.S. housing market and increased scrutiny in the lending industry.  Shale gas operations have the potential to place affected houses into technical default such that government sponsored enterprises like Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac are unable to maintain them in their portfolios.  We find that lenders changed from being willing to pay $814 on average to avoid one unit of shale risk before the financial distress of 2008 and subsequent increased scrutiny, to $3,137, or 1.6% of profit earned on an average mortgage, afterwards.  Our approach provides an alternative to the traditional property value hedonic measurement of the disamenities associated with shale gas development by looking at the decisions of mortgage professionals.]]></description><author>Yanyou Chen, James W. Roberts, Christopher D. Timmins, Ashley Vissing</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29494</guid></item><item><title>Environmental Justice and Coasian Bargaining: The Role of Race and Income in Lease Negotiations for Shale Gas</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29487</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher Timmins, Ashley Vissing.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Using a unique combination of datasets and estimation techniques, we test whether private lease negotiations to extract oil and natural gas exhibit features of Coasian efficiency. We demonstrate that measures of wealth (including income, house square footage, and land acreage), typically determinants of willingness to pay for environmental quality, do affect bargaining outcomes. However, race, ethnicity, and language also play important roles after conditioning upon these variables, suggesting an environmental injustice and a breakdown of efficient Coasian bargaining. We further demonstrate that failure to negotiate protections in leases leads to increased risk of future drilling violations, which are not offset by local ordinance restrictions.]]></description><author>Christopher Timmins, Ashley Vissing</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29487</guid></item><item><title>Pollution Trends and US Environmental Policy: Lessons from the Last Half Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29478</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joseph S. Shapiro.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This article proposes and evaluates four hypotheses about US pollution and environmental policy over the last half century. First, air and water pollution have declined substantially, although greenhouse gas emissions have not. Second, environmental policy explains a large share of these trends. Third, much of the regulation of air and drinking water pollution has benefits that exceed costs, although the evidence for surface water pollution regulation is less clear. Fourth, while the distribution of pollution across social groups is unequal, market-based environmental policies and command-and-control policies do not appear to produce systematically different distributions of environmental outcomes. I also discuss recent innovations in methods and data that can be used to evaluate pollution trends and policies, including the increased use of environmental administrative data, statistical cost-benefit comparisons, analysis of previously understudied policies, more sophisticated analyses of pollution transport, micro-macro frameworks, and a focus on the distribution of environmental outcomes.]]></description><author>Joseph S. Shapiro</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29478</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Firm Environmental Performance to Inform Asset Management and Standardized Disclosure</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicholas Z. Muller.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Investing according to environmental, social, and governance (ESG) criteria is gaining momentum. Most environmental performance indices focus only on the tonnage of carbon dioxide (CO₂) emissions. This paper proposes an index covering eight pollutants expressed in monetary damage. Inclusion of multiple pollutants reflects a broader range of reputational and regulatory risks. Monetization appropriately weights emissions. CO₂ dominates the mass of other pollutants, yet the marginal damages from other pollutants are larger than CO₂. In the U.S. utility sector from 2014 to 2017, indices which only track CO₂ mischaracterize firms’ environmental performance and underestimate its effect on financial outcomes relative to the multipollutant index. Dirtier firms exhibit lower share prices and higher forward returns. The effect is twice as large for the multipollutant index compared to CO₂. Analysts’ earnings forecasts for dirtier firms systematically undershoot actuals. Earnings errors are between three and five times more sensitive to the multipollutant index than to CO₂. The multipollutant index may suggest new management strategies to financial market participants relative to those based on carbon intensity. ESG disclosure standards based on the new index are more likely to affect financial outcomes, capital allocation decisions, and firm behavior than disclosure of carbon intensity.]]></description><author>Nicholas Z. Muller</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</guid></item><item><title>Exposures and Behavioral Responses to Wildfire Smoke</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29380</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marshall Burke, Sam Heft-Neal, Jessica Li, Anne Driscoll, Patrick W. Baylis, Matthieu Stigler, Joakim Weill, Jennifer Burney, Jeff Wen, Marissa Childs, Carlos Gould.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The impacts of environmental change on human outcomes often depend on local exposures and behavioral responses that are challenging to observe with traditional administrative or sensor data. We show how data from private pollution sensors, cell phones, social media posts, and internet search activity yield new insights on exposures and behavioral responses during large wildfire smoke events across the US, a rapidly-growing environmental stressor. Health-protective behavior, mobility, and sentiment all respond to increasing ambient wildfire smoke concentrations, but responses differ by income.  Indoor pollution monitors provide starkly different estimates of likely personal exposure during smoke events than would be inferred from traditional ambient outdoor sensors, with similar outdoor pollution levels generating &gt;20x differences in average indoor PM2.5 concentrations. Our results suggest that the current policy reliance on self protection to mitigate health risks in the face of rising smoke exposure will result in modest and unequal benefits.]]></description><author>Marshall Burke, Sam Heft-Neal, Jessica Li, Anne Driscoll, Patrick W. Baylis, Matthieu Stigler, Joakim Weill, Jennifer Burney, Jeff Wen, Marissa Childs, Carlos Gould</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29380</guid></item><item><title>Economic Production and Biodiversity in the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29357</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yuanning Liang, Ivan J. Rudik, Eric Zou.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Species extinctions and ecological degradation are accelerating to a degree unprecedented in human history. We present causal evidence on the economic drivers of biodiversity loss using a novel panel dataset on the types and quantities of wildlife at thousands of locations across the U.S. from 1960-2015. Exploiting fiscal and regulatory shocks to local economic output, we document large, negative impacts of GDP on abundance and diversity of species spanning multiple taxa. The adverse effects of production are mitigated by conservation and air emission abatement efforts, which points toward habitat losses and pollution as underlying contributors to contemporaneous biodiversity declines.]]></description><author>Yuanning Liang, Ivan J. Rudik, Eric Zou</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29357</guid></item><item><title>Environmental Drivers of Agricultural Productivity Growth: CO₂ Fertilization of US Field Crops</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29320</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Charles A. Taylor, Wolfram Schlenker.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We assess the CO₂ fertilization effect on US agriculture using spatially-varying CO₂ data from NASA's Orbiting Carbon Observatory-2 (OCO-2) satellite covering the majority of US cropland under actual growing conditions. This study complements the many CO₂ enrichment experiments that have found important interactions between CO₂ and local environmental conditions in controlled settings.  We use three empirical strategies: (i) a panel of CO₂ anomalies and county yields, (ii) a panel of spatial first-differences between neighboring counties, and (iii) a cross-sectional spatial first-difference. We find consistently high fertilization effects: a 1 ppm increase in CO₂ equates to a 0.5%, 0.6%, and 0.8% yield increase for corn, soybeans, and wheat, respectively. Viewed retrospectively, 10%, 30%, and 40% of each crop's yield improvements since 1940 are attributable to rising CO₂.]]></description><author>Charles A. Taylor, Wolfram Schlenker</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29320</guid></item><item><title>Social and Financial Incentives for Overcoming a Collective Action Problem</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29294</link><description><![CDATA[<i>M. Mehrab Bakhtiar, Raymond Guiteras, James A. Levinsohn, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Addressing public health externalities often requires community-level collective action. Each person’s sanitation behavior can affect the health of neighbors. We report on a cluster randomized controlled trial conducted with 19,000 households in rural Bangladesh where we randomized (1) either group financial incentives or a non-financial “social recognition” reward, and (2) asking each household to make either a private pledge or a public pledge to maintain hygienic latrines. The group financial reward has the strongest impact in the short term (3 months), inducing a 7.5-12.5 percentage point increase in hygienic latrine ownership. Getting people to publicly commit to maintaining and using a hygienic latrine in front of their neighbors induced a 4.2-6.1 percentage point increase in hygienic latrine ownership in the short term. In the medium term (15 months), the effect of the financial reward dissipates while the effect of the public commitment persists. Neither social recognition nor private commitments produce effects statistically distinguishable from zero.]]></description><author>M. Mehrab Bakhtiar, Raymond Guiteras, James A. Levinsohn, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29294</guid></item></channel></rss>