<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Labor and Health History</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Labor and Health History</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 14:03:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Mobility for All: Representative Intergenerational Mobility Estimates over the 20th Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29289</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We present the first estimates of long-run trends in intergenerational relative mobility for samples that are representative of the full U.S.-born population.  Harmonizing all surveys that ask about father's occupation and own family income, we develop a mobility measure that allows for the inclusion of non-whites and women for the 1910s–1970s birth cohorts.  We show a robust increase in mobility between the 1910s and 1940s cohorts, about half of which is driven by absolute convergence in racial income gaps. We also find that excluding Black Americans, particularly Black women, considerably overstates mobility throughout the 20th century.]]></description><author>Elisa Jácome, Ilyana Kuziemko, Suresh Naidu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29289</guid></item><item><title>Life Course Effects Of The Lanham Preschools: What The First Government Preschool Effort Can Tell Us About Universal Early Care And Education Today</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29271</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We examine the effects WWII Lanham Act Nursery Schools (LNS) on high school and young adult educational and labor outcomes of participants in the landmark Project Talent (PT) study. All PT places that received funding for LNS schools and all PT places that did not were identified by examining program records and contemporaneous newspaper accounts. Focusing on students who in 1960 attended high school in the same city or town where they were born, we estimate intent to treat effects of access to LNS preschool on high school academic and social emotional outcomes and on educational attainment and labor outcomes at five and eleven years following high school graduation. Preschool boosts high school academic outcomes for men and (in at least one specification) income 11 years after high school graduation. For women, preschool exposure had a negative effect on some social emotional outcomes in high school. We found no or inconsistent effects for other outcomes. The Lanham experience demonstrates that even with the less sophisticated understanding of child development of the early 1940s, the first universal, government-funded preschool program had positive impacts on boys’ outcomes at least through high school. Given today’s expanded understanding of child development and focus on the quality of early care and education programming, these findings provide some optimism as communities, states, and the federal government contemplate expanding funding for today’s early learning environments.]]></description><author>Taletha M. Derrington, Alison Huang, Joseph P. Ferrie</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29271</guid></item><item><title>Intergenerational Mobility in American History: Accounting for Race and Measurement Error</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29256</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> A large body of evidence finds that relative mobility in the US has declined over the past 150 years. However, long-run mobility estimates are usually based on white samples and therefore do not account for the limited opportunities available for non-white families. Moreover, historical data measure the father’s status with error, which biases estimates toward greater mobility. Using linked census data from 1850-1940, I show that accounting for race and measurement error can double estimates of intergenerational persistence. Updated estimates imply that there is greater equality of opportunity today than in the past, mostly because opportunity was never that equal.]]></description><author>Zachary Ward</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29256</guid></item><item><title>Eclipses and the Memory of Revolutions: Evidence from China</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29182</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Why are certain communities more prone to anti-government protests than others? Do past rebellions lead to more protests today? We study the historical roots of social unrest using the experience of China. We document that counties with higher incidence of peasant uprisings against local government officials during the Qing dynasty period (1644-1912) also have higher incidence of anti-government protests in present-day China. To generate plausibly exogenous variation in the incidence of past protests, we exploit differences in the visibility and magnitude of solar eclipses during the Qing dynasty period. In the Confucian tradition, solar eclipses are considered a negative divine signal on the legitimacy of the ruler, facilitating the coordination of protest actions. We test this mechanism using detailed data on the timing and location of anti-government rebellions extracted from local chronicles. Counties within the totality zone of a solar eclipse were significantly more likely to experience a rebellion in the eclipse year. Leaders of early anti-Qing rebellions were recorded in popular culture and celebrated in temples, favoring the transmission of the memory of their actions across generations. The persistent effect of past protests is stronger in counties with such temples and memorials, consistent with a long-term memory of revolutions.]]></description><author>Meng Miao, Jacopo Ponticelli, Yi Shao</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29182</guid></item></channel></rss>