<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Innovation and R&amp;amp;D</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Innovation and R&amp;amp;D</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 13:50:33 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Effects of Taxes on Innovation: Theory and Empirical Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29359</link><description>Income taxes are typically set to raise revenues and redistribute income at the lowest possible efficiency costs, which result from the distortions in individual behaviors that taxes entail. Individuals can respond along many margins, such as labor supply, tax avoidance and evasion, and geographic mobility. But one margin that taxes may affect — innovation — is less frequently considered. Conceptually, taxes reduce the expected net returns to innovation inputs and can reduce innovation. Much like other margins of responses to taxes, this efficiency cost must be taken into account. Innovation is done by a relatively small number of people, but it is nevertheless likely to have widespread benefits. While inventors may have divergent motivations, such as social recognition or the love of discovery, they also face an economic reality. How strongly innovation responds to taxes is an empirical question that has been the subject of a growing body of recent work. In this paper, I study how to account for innovation when setting personal income and capital taxation. I distinguish between two cases: one in which the government can set a differentiated tax on inventors and one in which the government is constrained to set the same tax on all agents. I provide a model that flexibly accounts for the spillovers generated by innovation and the non-pecuniary benefits inventors receive from innovation and derive tax formulas expressed in terms of estimable sufficient statistics. The second part of the paper discusses the empirical evidence on the effects of taxes on the quantity, quality, and location of innovation, as well as tax avoidance and income shifting done through innovation.</description><author>Stefanie Stantcheva</author></item><item><title>Closing the Innovation Gap in Pink and Black</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29354</link><description>Recent research shows the negative impact of discrimination not only on the targets of discrimination but also on the economy as a whole. Racial and gender inequality can limit the entire economy's productive capacity and innovation outcomes. Using new data from NSF's Survey of Earned Doctorates on the scientific workforce from 1980 to 2019, as well as patenting and commercialization data, we examine racial and gender disparities at each stage of the innovation process—education and training, the practice of invention, and commercialization. While improving along certain dimensions over time, we find persistent racial and gender disparities consistent with the current literature. To reverse the negative effects on productive capacity and long-run economic growth, we also discuss the literature on mitigating discriminatory practices at each juncture, which could have significant distributional effects as access to good jobs expands.</description><author>Lisa D. Cook, Janet Gerson, Jennifer Kuan</author></item><item><title>Economic Growth and Bank Innovation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29326</link><description>Based on archival and survey data we show that the maturity of U.S. business loans has been continuously increasing since the mid-1930s when banks invented the term loan. Concurrently, bank innovation first involved the invention of credit analysis and covenant design. Later, bank innovation included the advent of loan sales, increased loan syndications, the opening of the leveraged loan market, and the securitization of loans in collateralized loan obligations. We estimate and calibrate a model of bank innovation to determine the quantitative contribution of bank innovation to economic growth.</description><author>Gary B. Gorton, Ping He</author></item><item><title>The Rise of Scientific Research in Corporate America</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29260</link><description>Corporate science in America emerged in the interwar period, as some companies set up state-of-the-art corporate laboratories, hired trained scientists, and embarked upon basic research of the kind we would associate today with academic institutions. Using a newly assembled dataset on U.S. companies between 1926 and 1940 combining information on corporate ownership, organization, research and innovation, we attempt to explain the rise of corporate research. We argue that it was driven by companies trying to take advantage of opportunities for innovation made possible by scientific advances and an underdeveloped academic research system in the United States. Measuring  field-specific scientific backwardness in several different ways, we find that large firms, business group affiliated firms, and firms close to the technological frontier were more likely to initiate scientific  research. We also find that companies in monopolistic or concentrated industries were more likely to  engage in basic research. Corporate research was positively correlated with novel and valuable patents, and with market-to-book ratios. For companies choosing to do so, investment in corporate research seems to have paid off. The results shed light on the link between corporate organization, market structure and corporate science.
&lt;/p&gt;


              &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;script&gt;
    function getCookieValue(name) {
      var cookies = "; " + document.cookie,
          parts = cookies.split("; " + name + "=");
      if (parts.length == 2) {
        return parts.pop().split(";").shift();
      }
    }
    fetch("/api/v1/auth/317405", { credentials: "include" })
      .then(
        function(response) {
          if (response.status !== 200) {
            console.log('Looks like there was a problem. Status Code: ' + response.status);
            return;
          }
          response.text().then(function(data) {
            var cookieValue = getCookieValue('STYXKEY_expecting_cookie'),
                userEmailInput = document.getElementById('user_email');

            document.getElementById('authorize-banner').innerHTML = data;

            if (userEmailInput) {
              userEmailInput.value = cookieValue ? cookieValue : '';
            }

            window.dataLayer = window.dataLayer || [];
            let can_view = Boolean(response.headers.get('X-NBER-CAN-VIEW-PAPER'));
            let sub_type = response.headers.get('X-NBER-SUBSCRIBER-TYPE');

            dataLayer.push({
              "event": "can_view_paper_response",
              "can_view_paper": can_view,
              "subscriber_type": sub_type,
            });
          });
        }
      )
      .catch(function(err) {
        console.log('Fetch Error :-S', err);
      });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;div id="authorize-banner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="accordion-set"&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;div class="accordion"&gt;
          &lt;button class="accordion__title js-accordion" aria-expanded="false" aria-controls="accordion-body-guid1" id="accordion-button-guid1"&gt;Acknowledgements and Disclosures&lt;/button&gt;
          &lt;div class="accordion__body" id="accordion-body-guid1" aria-labelledby="accordion-button-guid1" style="display: none;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;
We thank seminar participants at Boston University, the ASSA 2021 annual meeting, Strategy Science Conference and Wharton Technology and Innovation Conference, as well as Tim Simcoe, Bhaven Sampat and Tarun Khanna for helpful comments and suggestions. We thank Gioia Blayer for excellent research assistance. All remaining errors are our own.  Arora, Belenzon and Suh acknowledge support from the Fuqua School of Business, Duke University.  Belenzon and Yafeh gratefully acknowledge financial support from the Israel Science Foundation, Grant No. 963-2020. Kosenko is grateful for support from the Bank of Israel. Yafeh also acknowledges financial support from the Krueger Center at the School of Business Administration of the Hebrew Univeresity. The views expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Bureau of Economic Research or the Bank of Israel.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
              &lt;div class="disclosure"&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/people/sharon_belenzon"&gt;Sharon Belenzon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
Israel Science Foundation: ``Corporate Ownership, Corporate Structure and Corporate Science: Evidence from Corporate R&amp;amp;D in America in the Twentieth Century'' (grant #963/2020), Collaborator (with Yishay Yafeh, PI) 2020</description><author>Ashish Arora, Sharon Belenzon, Konstantin Kosenko, Jungkyu Suh, Yishay Yafeh</author></item><item><title>Harms of AI</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29247</link><description>This essay discusses several potential economic, political and social costs of the current path of AI technologies. I argue that if AI continues to be deployed along its current trajectory and remains unregulated, it may produce various social, economic and political harms. These include: damaging competition, consumer privacy and consumer choice; excessively automating work, fueling inequality, inefficiently pushing down wages, and failing to improve worker productivity; and damaging political discourse, democracy's most fundamental lifeblood. Although there is no conclusive evidence suggesting that these costs are imminent or substantial, it may be useful to understand them before they are fully realized and become harder or even impossible to reverse, precisely because of AI's promising and wide-reaching potential. I also suggest that these costs are not inherent to the nature of AI technologies, but are related to how they are being used and developed at the moment - to empower corporations and governments against workers and citizens. As a result, efforts to limit and reverse these costs may need to rely on regulation and policies to redirect AI research. Attempts to contain them just by promoting competition may be insufficient.</description><author>Daron Acemoglu</author></item><item><title>Simulating Endogenous Global Automation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29220</link><description>This paper develops a 17-region, 3-skill group, overlapping generations, computable general equilibrium model to evaluate the global consequences of automation. Automation, modeled as capital- and high-skill biased technological change, is endogenous with regions adopting new technologies when profitable. Our approach captures and quantifies key macro implications of a range of foundational models of automation. In our baseline scenario, automation has a moderate effect on regional outputs and a small effect on world interest rates. However, it has a major impact on inequality, both wage inequality within regions and per capita GDP inequality across regions. We examine two policy responses to technological change -- mandating use of the advanced technology and providing universal basic income to share gains from automation. The former policy can raise a region's output, but at a welfare cost. The latter policy can transform automation into a win-win for all generations in a region.</description><author>Seth G. Benzell, Laurence J. Kotlikoff, Guillermo LaGarda, Victor Yifan Ye</author></item><item><title>Opposing firm-level Responses to the China Shock: Horizontal Competition Versus Vertical Relationships?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29196</link><description>We decompose the “China shock” into two components that induce different adjustments for firms exposed to Chinese exports: a horizontal shock affecting firms selling goods that compete with similar imported Chinese goods, and a vertical shock affecting firms using inputs similar to the imported Chinese goods. Combining French accounting, customs, and patent information at the firm-level, we show that the horizontal shock is detrimental to firms’ sales, employment, and innovation. Moreover, this negative impact is concentrated on low-productivity firms. By contrast, we find a positive effect - although often not significant - of the vertical shock on firms’ sales, employment, and innovation.</description><author>Philippe Aghion, Antonin Bergeaud, Matthieu Lequien, Marc Melitz, Thomas Zuber</author></item></channel></rss>