<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Labor Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Labor Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 14:59:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Mental Health Therapy as a Core Strategy for Increasing Human Capital: Evidence from Ghana</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We study the impact of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) for individuals selected from the general population of poor households in rural Ghana. Results from 2-3 months after a randomized intervention show strong impacts on mental and physical health, cognitive and socioemotional skills, and downstream economic outcomes. We find no evidence of heterogeneity by baseline mental distress; we argue that this is because CBT can improve human capital for a general population of poor individuals through two pathways. First, CBT reduces vulnerability to deteriorating mental health; and second, CBT directly improves bandwidth, increasing cognitive and socioemotional skills and hence economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Nathan Barker, Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Angela Ofori-Atta, Christopher R. Udry</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29407</guid></item><item><title>On the Persistence of the China Shock</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29401</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Abstract We evaluate the duration of the China trade shock and its impact on a wide range of outcomes over the period 2000 to 2019. The shock plateaued in 2010, enabling analysis of its effects for nearly a decade past its culmination. Adverse impacts of import competition on manufacturing employment, overall employment-population ratios, and income per capita in more trade-exposed U.S. commuting zones are present out to 2019. Over the full study period, greater import competition implies a reduction in the manufacturing employment-population ratio of 1.54 percentage points, which is 55% of the observed change in the value, and the absorption of 86% of this net job loss via a corresponding decrease in the overall employment rate. Reductions in population headcounts, which indicate net out-migration, register only for foreign-born workers and the native-born 25-39 years old, implying that exit from work is a primary means of adjustment to trade-induced contractions in labor demand. More negatively affected regions see modest increases in the uptake of government transfers, but these transfers primarily take the form of Social Security and Medicare benefits. Adverse outcomes are more acute in regions that initially had fewer college-educated workers and were more industrially specialized. Impacts are qualitatively—but not quantitatively—similar to those caused by the decline of employment in coal production since the 1980s, indicating that the China trade shock holds lessons for other episodes of localized job loss. Import competition from China induced changes in income per capita across local labor markets that are much larger than the spatial heterogeneity of income effects predicted by standard quantitative trade models. Even using higher-end estimates of the consumer benefits of rising trade with China, a substantial fraction of commuting zones appears to have suffered absolute declines in average real incomes.]]></description><author>David Autor, David Dorn, Gordon H. Hanson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29401</guid></item><item><title>The Rise of Pass-Throughs and the Decline of the Labor Share</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29400</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the coevolution of the fall in the US corporate sector labor share and the rise of business activity in tax-preferred, pass-through form. Reallocating activity to the form it would have taken prior to the Tax Reform Act of 1986 accounts for one third of the decline in the corporate sector labor share between 1978 and 2017. Our adjustments are concentrated among mid-market firms in services, leaving a larger role for the manufacturing sector and superstar firms in driving the remaining decline in the labor share. Our findings highlight the importance of tax policy when measuring factor shares.]]></description><author>Matthew Smith, Danny Yagan, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29400</guid></item><item><title>The Geography of Job Creation and Job Destruction</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29399</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Spatial differences in labor market performance are large and highly persistent. Using data from the United States, Germany, and the United Kingdom, we document striking similarities in spatial differences in unemployment, vacancies, job finding, and job filling within each country. This robust set of facts guides and disciplines the development of a theory of local labor market performance. We find that a spatial version of a Diamond-Mortensen-Pissarides model with endogenous separations and on-the-job search quantitatively accounts for all the documented empirical regularities. The model also quantitatively rationalizes why differences in job-separation rates have primary importance in inducing differences in unemployment across space while changes in the job-finding rate are the main driver in unemployment fluctuations over the business cycle.]]></description><author>Moritz Kuhn, Iourii Manovskii, Xincheng Qiu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29399</guid></item><item><title>It All Starts with Beliefs: Addressing the Roots of Educational Inequities by Shifting Parental Beliefs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29394</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Socioeconomic inequalities in child development crystallize at early stages, with associated disparities in parental investment in children. A key to understanding the data patterns is to document the sources underlying the observed inequalities. We first show that there are dramatic differences in parental beliefs across socioeconomic backgrounds (SES), with parents of higher SES being more likely to believe that parental investments impact child development. We then use two field experiments targeted to low-SES families to explore the mutability of such beliefs and their link to parental investments. In both cases, we find that parental beliefs about child development are malleable. The less intensive version of the program based on educational videos changes parental beliefs, but fails to lastingly increase parental investments and child outcomes. By contrast, in the more intensive version of our program combining home visits and feedback, the augmented beliefs are associated with enriched parent-child interactions and improved vocabulary, math, and social-emotional skills for the children. Together, these results suggest that changing parental beliefs can be an important pathway to raising parental investments and reducing socioeconomic gaps in children’s skills, but that simple informational policies may not be sufficient.]]></description><author>John A. List, Julie Pernaudet, Dana Suskind</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29394</guid></item><item><title>Inflation, Interest, and the Secular Rise in Wealth Inequality in the U.S.: Is the Fed Responsible?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29392</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Two hallmarks of U.S. monetary policy since the 1981-1982 recession have been declining interest rates and moderation in inflation. Coincident with these trends has been a surge in U.S. wealth inequality, with the Gini coefficient up by 0.070 between 1983 and 2019. This paper analyzes the connection between these two developments on the basis of the Survey of Consumer Finances. Contrary to expectations, the paper finds that these two monetary effects have reduced wealth inequality rather than increasing it. The effect is sizeable, with the Gini coefficient declining by 0.045 over these years. Asset price changes and debt devaluation accounted for 72.6 percent of the advance of mean wealth over 1983-2019. They also would have led to a 204.9 percent gain in median wealth, compared to the actual rise of 23.4 percent. Moreover, they have helped lower the racial wealth gap rather than enlarging it. These results are at odds with previous literature in which estimates range from a weak negative effect on inequality to neutral, small positive, and strong positive. In terms of methodology, this paper differs from previous work by focusing on only the direct effects of interest rate changes and inflation on the household balance sheet.]]></description><author>Edward N. Wolff</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29392</guid></item><item><title>The Human Side of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We document that nearly half of the global decline in agricultural employment during the 20th-century was driven by new cohorts entering the labor market. A newly compiled dataset of policy reforms supports an interpretation of these cohort effects as human capital. Through the lens of a model of frictional labor reallocation, we conclude that human capital growth, both as a mediating factor and as an independent driver, led to a sharp decline in the agricultural labor supply. This decline accounts, at fixed prices, for 40% of the decrease in agricultural employment. This aggregate effect is roughly halved in general equilibrium.]]></description><author>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</guid></item><item><title>A (Dynamic) Investigation of Stereotypes, Belief-Updating, and Behavior</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29382</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Many decisions – such as what educational or career path to pursue – are dynamic in nature, with individuals receiving feedback at one point in time and making decisions later. Using a controlled experiment, with two sessions one week apart, we analyze the dynamic effects of feedback on beliefs about own performance and decision-making across two different domains (verbal skills and math). We find significant gender gaps in beliefs and choices before feedback: men are more optimistic about their performance and more willing to compete than women in both domains, but the gaps are significantly larger in math. Feedback significantly shifts individuals' beliefs and choices. Despite this, we see substantial persistence of gender gaps over time. This is particularly true among the set of individuals who receive negative feedback. We find that, holding fixed performance and decisions before feedback, women update their beliefs and choices more negatively than men do after bad news. Our results highlight the challenges involved in overcoming gender gaps in dynamic settings.]]></description><author>Katherine B. Coffman, Paola Ugalde Araya, Basit Zafar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29382</guid></item><item><title>Occupational Choice and the Intergenerational Mobility of Welfare</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29381</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Based on responses in the General Social Survey, we construct an index that captures non-monetary qualities of occupations, such as respect, learning, and work hazards, relevant to the well-being of workers. Using the Panel Study of Income Dynamics and National Longitudinal Survey of Youth data, we document that the children of richer US parents are more likely to select into occupations that rank higher in terms of this index. We rationalize this fact by introducing occupational choice with preferences over the intrinsic qualities of occupations into a standard theory of intergenerational mobility. Estimating the model allows us to infer the equivalent monetary compensation each worker receives from the intrinsic qualities of their chosen occupation. Earnings adjusted to reflect this additional compensation show substantially larger persistence of income from parents to children. Our model further predicts that the trends in the composition of labor demand in the US over the past three decades decreased intergenerational persistence, and also led to higher growth in the welfare of the average worker than that implied by observed earnings.]]></description><author>Corina Boar, Danial Lashkari</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29381</guid></item><item><title>Pay, Productivity and Management</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29377</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Using confidential Census matched employer-employee earnings data we find that employees at more productive firms, and firms with more structured management practices, have substantially higher pay, both on average and across every percentile of the pay distribution. This pay-performance relationship is particularly strong amongst higher paid employees, with a doubling of firm productivity associated with 11% more pay for the highest-paid employee (likely the CEO) compared to 4.7% for the median worker. This pay-performance link holds in public and private firms, although it is almost twice as strong in public firms for the highest-paid employees. Top pay volatility is also strongly related to productivity and structured management, suggesting this performance-pay relationship arises from more aggressive monitoring and incentive practices for top earners.]]></description><author>Nicholas Bloom, Scott W. Ohlmacher, Cristina J. Tello-Trillo, Melanie Wallskog</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29377</guid></item><item><title>The Economics of Walking About and Predicting US Downturns</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29372</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Economic shocks are notoriously difficult to predict but recent research suggests qualitative metrics about economic actors’ expectations are predictive of downturns.  We show consumer expectations indices from both the Conference Board and the University of Michigan predict economic downturns up to 18 months in advance in the United States, both at national and at state-level.  All the recessions since the 1980s have been predicted by at least 10 and sometimes many more point drops in these expectations indices.  A single monthly rise of at least 0.3 percentage points in the unemployment rate also predicts recession, as does two consecutive months of employment rate declines.  The economic situation in 2021 is exceptional, however, since unprecedented direct government intervention in the labor market through furlough-type arrangements has enabled employment rates to recover quickly from the huge downturn in 2020.  However, downward movements in consumer expectations in the last six months suggest the economy in the United States is entering recession now (Autumn 2021) even though employment and wage growth figures suggest otherwise.]]></description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29372</guid></item><item><title>Effects of Opioid-Related Policies on Opioid Utilization, Nature of Medical Care, and Duration of Disability</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29371</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We examine the effects of must-access prescription drug monitoring programs (PDMPs) and recent regulations limiting the duration of initial opioid prescriptions on care received by patients with work-related injuries, focusing on opioid utilization and medical care related to pain management. We find that must-access PDMPs contributed to declines in opioid utilization, while regulations limiting duration of initial opioid prescriptions had little effect on whether workers receive opioids, but reduced opioid use among those with prescriptions. We find limited evidence that must-access PDMPs affected utilization of other medical care related to pain management, and that must-access PDMPs and limits on initial prescriptions had little impact on the duration of temporary disability benefits captured at 12 months of maturity.]]></description><author>David Neumark, Bogdan Savych</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29371</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Access to Small Business Credit: Evidence from the Paycheck Protection Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We explore the sources of racial disparities in small business lending by studying the $806 billion Paycheck Protection Program (PPP), which was designed to support small business jobs during the COVID-19 pandemic. PPP loans were administered by private lenders but federally guaranteed, largely eliminating unobservable credit risk as a factor in explaining differential lending by race. We document that even after controlling for a firm’s zip code, industry, loan size, PPP approval date, and other characteristics, Black-owned businesses were 12.1 percentage points (70% of the mean) more likely to obtain their PPP loan from a fintech lender than a traditional bank. Among conventional lenders, smaller banks were much less likely to lend to Black-owned firms, while the Top-4 banks exhibited little to no disparity after including controls. We use novel data to show that the disparity is not primarily explained by differences in pre-existing bank or credit relationships, firm financial positions, fintech affinity, or borrower application behavior. In contrast, we document that Black-owned businesses’ higher rate of borrowing from fintechs compared to smaller banks is particularly large in places with high racial animus, pointing to a potential role for discrimination in explaining some of the racial disparities in small business lending. We find evidence that when small banks automate their lending processes, and thus reduce human involvement in the loan origination process, their rate of PPP lending to Black-owned businesses increases, with larger effects in places with more racial animus.]]></description><author>Sabrina T. Howell, Theresa Kuchler, David Snitkof, Johannes Stroebel, Jun Wong</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</guid></item><item><title>Early Childhood Development, Human Capital and Poverty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29362</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Children's experiences during early childhood are critical for their cognitive and socio-emotional development, two key dimensions of human capital. However, children from low income backgrounds often grow up lacking stimulation and basic investments, leading to developmental deficits that are difficult, if not impossible, to reverse later in life without intervention. The existence of these deficits are a key driver of inequality and contribute to the intergenerational transmission of poverty. In this paper, we discuss the framework used in economics to model parental investments and early childhood development and use it as an organizing tool to review some of the empirical evidence on early childhood research. We then present results from various important early childhoods interventions with emphasis on developing countries. Bringing these elements together we draw conclusions on what we have learned and provide some directions for future research.]]></description><author>Orazio Attanasio, Sarah Cattan, Costas Meghir</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29362</guid></item><item><title>“Beauty Too Rich for Use”*: Billionaires’ Assets and Attractiveness</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29361</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We examine how the net worth of billionaires relates to their looks, as rated by 16 people of different gender and ethnicity. Surprisingly, their financial assets are unrelated to their beauty; nor are they related to their educational attainment. As a group, however, billionaires are both more educated and better-looking than average for their age. Men, people who reside in Western countries, and those who inherited substantial wealth, are wealthier than other billionaires. The results do not arise from measurement error or nonrandom sample selectivity. They are consistent with econometric theory about the impact of truncating a sample to include observations only from the extreme tail of the dependent variable. The point is underscored by comparing estimates of earnings equations using all employees in the 2018 American Community Survey to those using a sample of the top 0.1 percent. The findings suggest the powerful role of luck within the extremes of the distributions of economic outcomes.]]></description><author>Daniel S. Hamermesh, Andrew Leigh</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29361</guid></item><item><title>Gender Preferences in Job Vacancies and Workplace Gender Diversity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29350</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> In spring 2005, Austria launched a campaign to inform employers and newspapers that gender preferences in job advertisements were illegal. At the time over 40% of openings on the nation’s largest job-board specified a preferred gender.  Over the next year the fraction fell to under 5%. We merge data on filled vacancies to linked employer-employee data to study how the elimination of gender preferences affected hiring and job outcomes. Prior to the campaign, most stated preferences were concordant with the firm’s existing gender composition, but a minority targeted the opposite gender - a subset we call non-stereotypical vacancies. Vacancies with a gender preference were very likely (&gt;90%) to be filled by someone of that gender. We use pre-campaign vacancies to predict the probabilities of specifying preferences for females, males, or neither gender. We then conduct event studies of the effect of the campaign on the predicted preference groups. We find that the elimination of gender preferences led to a rise in the fraction of women hired for jobs that were likely to be targeted to men (and vice versa), increasing the diversity of hiring workplaces. Partially offsetting this effect, we find a reduction in the success of non-stereotypical vacancies in hiring the targeted gender, and indications of a decline in the efficiency of matching.  For the much larger set of stereotypical vacancies, however, vacancy filling times, wages, and job durations were largely unaffected by the campaign, suggesting that the elimination of stated preferences had at most small consequences on overall job match efficiency.]]></description><author>David Card, Fabrizio Colella, Rafael Lalive</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29350</guid></item><item><title>Outsourcing, Inequality and Aggregate Output</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Outsourced workers experience large wage declines, yet domestic outsourcing may raise aggregate productivity. To study this equity-efficiency trade-off, we contribute a framework in which firms either hire many imperfectly substitutable worker types in-house by posting wages along a job ladder, or rent labor services from contractors who hire in the same frictional labor markets. Three implications arise. First, more productive firms are more likely to outsource to save on higher wage premia. Second, outsourcing raises output at the firm level. Third, contractors endogenously locate at the bottom of the job ladder, implying that outsourced workers receive lower wages. Using firm-level instruments for outsourcing and revenue productivity, we find empirical support for all three predictions in French administrative data. After structurally estimating the model, we find that the rise in outsourcing in France between 1996 and 2007 raised aggregate output by 3% and reduced the labor share by 0.7 percentage points. A 9% minimum wage increase stabilizes the labor share and maintains two thirds of the output gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</guid></item><item><title>The Psychosocial Effects of the Flint Water Crisis on School-Age Children</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29341</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Lead poisoning has well-known impacts for the developing brain of young children, with a large literature documenting the negative effects of elevated blood lead levels on academic and behavioral outcomes. In April of 2014, the municipal water source in Flint, Michigan was changed, causing lead from aging pipes to leach into the city’s drinking water. In this study, we use Michigan’s universe of longitudinal, student-level education records, combined with home water service line inspection data containing the location of lead pipes, to empirically examine the effect of the Flint Water Crisis on educational outcomes of Flint public school children. We leverage parallel causal identification strategies, a between-district synthetic control analysis and a within-Flint difference-in-differences analysis, to separate out the direct health effects of lead exposure from the broad effects of living in a community experiencing a crisis. Our results highlight a less well-appreciated consequence of the Flint Water Crisis – namely, the psychosocial effects of the crisis on the educational outcomes of school-age children. These findings suggest that cost estimates which rely only on the negative impact of direct lead exposure substantially underestimate the overall societal cost of the crisis.]]></description><author>Sam Trejo, Gloria Yeomans-Maldonado, Brian Jacob</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29341</guid></item><item><title>Why do people stay poor?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> There are two broad views as to why people stay poor. One emphasizes differences in fundamentals, such as ability, talent or motivation. The other, the poverty traps view, differences in opportunities which stem from access to wealth. To test between these two views, we exploit a large-scale, randomized asset transfer and an 11-year panel on 6000 households who begin in extreme poverty. The setting is rural Bangladesh and the asset is cows. The data supports the poverty traps view - we identify a threshold level of initial assets above which households accumulate assets, take on better occupations (from casual labor in agriculture or domestic services to running small livestock businesses) and grow out of poverty. The reverse happens for those below the threshold. Structural estimation of an occupational choice model reveals that almost all beneficiaries are misallocated in the work they do at baseline and that the gains arising from eliminating misallocation would far exceed the program costs. Our findings imply that large transfers which create better jobs for the poor are an effective means of getting people out of poverty traps and reducing global poverty.]]></description><author>Clare A. Balboni, Oriana Bandiera, Robin Burgess, Maitreesh Ghatak, Anton Heil</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29340</guid></item><item><title>Minimum Wages and Teenage Childbearing: New Estimates Using a Dynamic Difference-in-Differences Approach</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29334</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> The minimum wage is increasingly viewed as an important tool for improving public health outcomes, including reducing childbearing among teenagers. Taken at face value, recently reported estimates suggest that raising the federal minimum wage to $15 per hour could reduce the number of teenage births by 35,000 per year. Using an event study framework that accounts for dynamic and heterogeneous treatment effects, we find little evidence that minimum wages are causally related to teenage childbearing. Moreover, the estimated effects of minimum wages on teenage sexual behaviors, including contraception use, abstinence, and number of partners are consistently small and statistically insignificant.]]></description><author>Daniel I. Rees, Joseph J. Sabia, Rebecca Margolit</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29334</guid></item><item><title>The US Pretrial System: Balancing Individual Rights and Public Interests</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29332</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> In this article, we review a growing empirical literature on the effectiveness and fairness of the US pretrial system and discuss its policy implications. Despite the importance of this stage of the criminal legal process, researchers have only recently begun to explore how the pretrial system balances individual rights and public interests. We describe the empirical challenges that have prevented progress in this area and how recent work has made use of new data sources and quasi-experimental approaches to credibly estimate both the individual harms (such as loss of employment or government assistance) and public benefits (such as preventing non-appearance at court and new crimes) of cash bail and pretrial detention. These new data and approaches show that the current pretrial system imposes substantial short- and long-term economic harms on detained defendants in terms of lost earnings and government assistance, while providing little in the way of decreased criminal activity for the public interest. Non-appearances at court do significantly decrease for detained defendants, but the magnitudes cannot justify the economic harms to individuals observed in the data. A second set of studies shows that these costs of cash bail and pretrial detention are disproportionately borne by Black and Hispanic individuals, giving rise to large and unfair racial differences in cash bail and detention that cannot be explained by underlying differences in pretrial misconduct risk. We then turn to policy implications and describe areas of future work that would enable a deeper understanding of what drives these undesirable outcomes.]]></description><author>Will S. Dobbie, Crystal Yang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29332</guid></item><item><title>Mortality Rates by College Degree Before and During COVID-19</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29328</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> It is now established that mortality and excess mortality from COVID-19 differed across racial and ethnic groups in 2020. Less is known about educational differences in mortality during the pandemic. We examine mortality rates by BA status within sex, age, and race/ethnic groups comparing 2020 with 2019. Mortality rates have increasingly differed by BA status in the US in recent years and there are good reasons to expect the gap to have widened further during the pandemic. Using publicly available provisional data from the National Center for Health Statistics we find that mortality rates increased in 2020 over 2019 for those with and without a BA, irrespective of age, sex, or race/ethnicity. Although mortality rates increased by more for those without a BA, the ratio of mortality rates for those with and without a BA changed surprisingly little from 2019 to 2020. Among 60 groups (sex by race/ethnicity by age) that are available in the data, the ratio of mortality rates of those without a BA to those with a BA fell for more than half of the groups. Our results suggest that differences in the risk of infection were less important in structuring mortality by education than differences in the risk of death conditional on infection.]]></description><author>Anne Case, Angus Deaton</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29328</guid></item><item><title>Task Allocation and On-the-job Training</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29312</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study dynamic task allocation when providers' expertise evolves endogenously through training. We characterize optimal assignment protocols and compare them to discretionary procedures, where it is the clients who select their service providers. Our results indicate that welfare gains from centralization are greater when tasks arrive more rapidly, and when training technologies improve. Monitoring seniors' backlog of clients always increases welfare but may decrease training. Methodologically, we explore a matching setting with endogenous types, and illustrate useful adaptations of queueing theory techniques for such environments.]]></description><author>Mariagiovanna Baccara, SangMok Lee, Leeat Yariv</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29312</guid></item><item><title>Recovery from the COVID-19 Recession: Uneven Effects among Young Workers?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29307</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We test for heterogeneity in the effects of the COVID-19 recession on young workers by estimating month-by-month effects of the pandemic on labor market outcomes among workers aged 15-19 and aged 20-24. We use CPS data from January 2016 to June 2021, limiting the sample to childless individuals who lack a college degree. In the younger group (aged 15-19), we observe the expected sharp reduction in outcomes at the start of the pandemic, followed by a return to pre-pandemic levels of work hours, employment, and labor force participation starting in September 2020, with outcomes even surpassing pre-pandemic levels in April and May 2021. In the older age group (20-24-year-olds), however, work hours, employment, and labor force participation were still lagging below pre-pandemic levels as of June 2021. As of June 2021, weekly earnings and hourly wages were higher than typical pre-pandemic levels for that month for both age groups. Although we cannot test directly whether enhanced UI programs have played a role in these differences by age group, our findings show that within the 15-24-year-old age group, there is significant heterogeneity in labor market recovery from the COVID-19 recession.]]></description><author>Pinka Chatterji, Yue Li</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29307</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Housing Returns</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29306</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We document the existence of a racial gap in realized housing returns that is an order of magnitude larger than disparities arising from housing costs alone, and is driven almost entirely by differences in distressed home sales (i.e. foreclosures and short sales). Black and Hispanic homeowners are both more likely to experience a distressed sale and to live in neighborhoods where distressed sales erase more house value. Importantly, absent financial distress, houses owned by minorities do not appreciate at slower rates than houses owned by non-minorities. Racial differences in income stability and liquid wealth explain a large share of the differences in distress. We use quasi-experimental variation in loan modifications to show that policies that restructure mortgages for distressed minorities can increase housing returns and reduce the racial wealth gap.]]></description><author>Amir Kermani, Francis Wong</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29306</guid></item><item><title>The Evolution of Skill Use Within and Between Jobs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29302</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We develop a tractable general equilibrium model for understanding within- and between-occupation changes in skill use over time. We apply the model to skill-use measures from the third, fourth, and revised fourth editions of the Dictionary of Occupational Titles and data from the 1960, 1970, and 1980 Censuses and March Current Population Surveys. We recover changes in skill productivity by exploiting between-occupation movements. Most importantly, finger-dexterity productivity grew rapidly while abstract-skill productivity lagged. We leverage these findings to estimate an inelastic relation between abstract and routine inputs and explain within-occupation shifts in skill use.]]></description><author>Costas Cavounidis, Vittoria Dicandia, Kevin Lang, Raghav Malhotra</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29302</guid></item><item><title>The Sahm Rule and Predicting the Great Recession Across OECD Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29300</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We examine the start date of the Great Recession across OECD countries based on two successive quarters of negative GDP growth recession.  For most OECD countries this establishes the start of recession in Q22008 or Q32008.  We find that the Sahm Rule identifies the start of recession in the US to the beginning of 2008 but in other OECD countries it identifies the start in almost every case, after that identified by GDP.  But the GDP and labor market data are subject to major revisions, so the turn is not apparent in most countries for some time.  We establish our own rule for predicting recession using the fear of unemployment series to predict recession.  It involves looking for a ten-point rise in the series compared to its previous twelve month low.  These surveys are timely and have the major advantage they are not subject to revision. Across the OECD we confirm this finding with other types of qualitative data and especially so in the UK.  Qualitative surveys, we show, in the US in 2006 and 2007 predicted the subsequent recession and they did the same in Europe at the end of 2007 and in the early part of 2008.]]></description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29300</guid></item><item><title>Effect of the Jamaica Early Childhood Stimulation Intervention on Labor Market Outcomes at Age 31</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29292</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We report the labor market effects of the Jamaica Early Childhood Stimulation intervention at age 31. The study is a small-sample randomized early childhood education stimulation intervention targeting stunted children living in the poor neighborhoods of Kingston, Jamaica. Implemented in 1987-1989, treatment consisted of a two-year home-based intervention designed to improve nutrition and the quality of mother-child interactions to foster cognitive, language and psycho-social skills. The original sample is 127 stunted children between 9 and 24 months old. Our study is able to track and interview 75% of the original sample 30 years after the intervention, both still living in Jamaica and migrated abroad. We find large and statistically significant effects on income and schooling; the treatment group had 43% higher hourly wages and 37% higher earnings than the control group. This is a substantial increase over the treatment effect estimated for age 22 where we observed a 25% increase in earnings. The Jamaican Study is a rare case of a long-term follow up for an early childhood development (ECD) intervention implemented in a less-developed country. Our results confirm large economic returns to an early childhood intervention that targeted disadvantaged families living in poverty in the poor neighborhoods of Jamaica. The Jamaican intervention is being replicated around the world. Our analysis provides justification for expanding ECD interventions targeting disadvantaged children living in poor countries around the world.]]></description><author>Paul Gertler, James J. Heckman, Rodrigo Pinto, Susan M. Chang, Sally Grantham-McGregor, Christel Vermeersch, Susan Walker, Amika Wright</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29292</guid></item><item><title>Sorting with Team Formation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29290</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We fully solve an assignment problem with heterogeneous firms and multiple heterogeneous workers whose skills are imperfect substitutes, that is, when production is submodular. We show that sorting is neither positive nor negative and is characterized sufficiently by two regions. In the first region, mediocre firms sort with mediocre workers and coworkers such that output losses are equal across all these pairings (complete mixing). In the second region, high skill workers sort with a low skill coworker and a high productivity firm, while high productivity firms employ a low skill worker and a high skill coworker (pairwise countermonotonicity). The equilibrium assignment is also necessarily characterized by product countermonotonicity, meaning that sorting is negative for each dimension of heterogeneity with the product of heterogeneity in the other dimensions. The equilibrium assignment as well as wages and firm values are completely characterized in closed form. We illustrate our theory with an application to show that our model is consistent with the observed dispersion of earnings within and across U.S. firms. Our counterfactual analysis gives evidence that the change in the firm project distribution between 1981 and 2013 has a larger effect on the observed change in earnings dispersion than the change in the worker skill distribution.]]></description><author>Job Boerma, Aleh Tsyvinski, Alexander P. Zimin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29290</guid></item><item><title>Mobility for All: Representative Intergenerational Mobility Estimates over the 20th Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29289</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We present the first estimates of long-run trends in intergenerational relative mobility for samples that are representative of the full U.S.-born population.  Harmonizing all surveys that ask about father's occupation and own family income, we develop a mobility measure that allows for the inclusion of non-whites and women for the 1910s–1970s birth cohorts.  We show a robust increase in mobility between the 1910s and 1940s cohorts, about half of which is driven by absolute convergence in racial income gaps. We also find that excluding Black Americans, particularly Black women, considerably overstates mobility throughout the 20th century.]]></description><author>Elisa Jácome, Ilyana Kuziemko, Suresh Naidu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29289</guid></item><item><title>Is Healthcare Employment Resilient and “Recession Proof”?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29287</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Conventional wisdom often holds that the healthcare sector fares better than other sectors during economic downturns. However, little research has examined the relationship between local economic conditions and healthcare employment. Understanding how the healthcare sector responds to economic conditions is important for policy makers seeking to ensure an adequate supply of healthcare workers, as well as for those directing displaced workers into new jobs. We examine the impact of macroeconomic conditions on both the healthcare labor market and the pipeline of healthcare workers receiving healthcare degrees during a pre-COVID time period, 2005-2017. Our results indicate that the healthcare sector is stable across past business cycles. If anything, when areas experience more severe local economic downturns, healthcare employment increases. Much remains unknown about the adjustments and lasting impacts for the healthcare sector associated with the COVID era. Our study represents an important backdrop as policy makers consider ways to sustain the healthcare sector during economic and public health turbulence.]]></description><author>Marcus Dillender, Andrew I. Friedson, Cong T. Gian, Kosali I. Simon</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29287</guid></item><item><title>The Puzzle of Falling US Birth Rates Since the Great Recession</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29286</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper documents a set of facts about the dramatic decline in birth rates in the United States between 2007 and 2020 and explores possible explanations. The overall reduction in the birth rate reflects declines across many groups of women, including women who differ by race and ethnicity, age, and level of education. The Great Recession contributed to the decline in the early part of this period, but we are unable to identify any other economic, policy, or social factor that has changed since 2007 that is responsible for much of the decline beyond that. Mechanically, the falling birth rate can be attributed to changes in birth patterns across recent cohorts of women moving through childbearing age. We conjecture that the “shifting priorities” of more recent cohorts, reflecting changes in preferences for having children, aspirations for life, and parenting norms, may be responsible. We conclude with a brief discussion about the societal consequences for a declining birth rate and what the United States might do about it.]]></description><author>Melissa Schettini Kearney, Phillip B. Levine, Luke W. Pardue</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29286</guid></item><item><title>The Initial Effects of the Expanded Child Tax Credit on Material Hardship</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The transformation of the Child Tax Credit (CTC) into a more generous, inclusive monthly payment marks a historic (temporary) shift in U.S. treatment of low-income families. To investigate the initial impact of these payments, we apply a series of difference-in-difference estimates using Census Household Pulse Survey microdata collected from April 14 through August 16, 2021. Our findings offer three primary conclusions regarding the initial effects of the monthly CTC. First, payments strongly reduced food insufficiency: the initial payments led to a 7.5 percentage point (25 percent) decline in food insufficiency among low-income households with children. Second, the effects on food insufficiency are concentrated among families with 2019 pre-tax incomes below $35,000, and the CTC strongly reduces food insufficiency among low-income Black, Latino, and White families alike. Third, increasing the CTC coverage rate would be required in order for material hardship to be reduced further. Self-reports suggest the lowest-income households were less likely than higher-income families to receive the first CTC payments. As more children receive the benefit in future months, material hardship may decline further. Even with imperfect coverage, however, our findings suggest that the first CTC payments were largely effective at reducing food insufficiency among low-income families with children.]]></description><author>Zachary Parolin, Elizabeth Ananat, Sophie M. Collyer, Megan Curran, Christopher Wimer</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Nationalization Policies and Exporting Firm Outcomes: Evidence from Saudi Arabia</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29283</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> In the last decade, Gulf countries have imposed hiring quotas to promote the participation of natives in the private sector and address high levels of unemployment, particularly among women and the youth. This paper explores how one such policy, Nitaqat in Saudi Arabia, affected the outcomes of exporting firms, the most productive sector of the non-oil economy.  We find that whereas the policy was successful in increasing the employment of Saudi nationals by these firms, it came at a high cost. In the year following the announcement of the policy, relative to firms above the quota, firms below the quota were 1.5 percentage points more likely to exit the market, 7 percentage points less likely to export, and conditional on exporting, the value of their exports fell by 14 percent. Additionally, surviving treated firms reduced their labor force by 10 percent. We find that to comply with the policy, firms hired mostly lower-wage, low-skilled Saudis. The policy doubled the share of women in treated firms. Importantly, we find that these short-term effects persisted for at least three years after the policy’s implementation.]]></description><author>Patricia Cortés, Semiray Kasoolu, Carolina Pan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29283</guid></item><item><title>The Returns to College(s): Relative Value-Added and Match Effects in Higher Education</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29276</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Students who attend different colleges in the U.S. end up with vastly different economic outcomes. We study the role of relative value-added across colleges within student choice sets in producing these outcome disparities. Linking high school, college, and earnings registries spanning the state of Texas, we identify relative college value-added by comparing the outcomes of students who apply to and are admitted by the same set of institutions, as this approach strikingly balances observable student potential across college treatments and renders our extensive set of covariates irrelevant as controls. Methodologically, we develop a framework for identifying and interpreting value-added under varying assumptions about match effects and sorting gains. Empirically, we estimate a relatively tight, though non-degenerate, distribution of relative value-added across the wide diversity of Texas public universities. Selectivity poorly predicts value-added within student choice sets, with only a fleeting selectivity earnings premium fading to zero after a few years in the labor market. Non-peer college inputs like instructional spending more strongly predict value-added, especially conditional on selectivity. Colleges that boost BA completion, especially in STEM majors, also tend to boost earnings. Finally, we probe the potential for (mis)match effects by allowing value-added schedules to vary by student characteristics.]]></description><author>Jack Mountjoy, Brent R. Hickman</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29276</guid></item><item><title>Red Scare? A Study of Ethnic Prejudice in the Prosecutions under the Economic Espionage Act</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29272</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We empirically test whether the Department of Justice (DOJ) engages in ethnic prejudice against Chinese in its prosecutorial decisions under the Economic Espionage Act (EEA) of 1996. Using data of EEA cases from November 1996 to June 2021, we conduct Becker's outcome test for evidence of ethnic prejudice. We find that Chinese-named defendants were more likely to be dismissed by trial or acquitted by jury, and were found guilty on fewer counts, and on average received harsher indictments. These results are robust regardless of whether we consider all cases or only arguably ``marginal'' cases. We also find that, for those publicly listed victim firms whose trade secrets were allegedly stolen by the charged defendants, the stock market reaction was much more muted to the news on the case filing date if the charged defendants are of Chinese descent. Our study provides the first systematic evidence that the DOJ's prosecutorial decisions in the application of the EEA may have been tainted by ethnic prejudice against Chinese, including American citizens of Chinese descent.]]></description><author>Hanming Fang, Ming Li</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29272</guid></item><item><title>Life Course Effects Of The Lanham Preschools: What The First Government Preschool Effort Can Tell Us About Universal Early Care And Education Today</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29271</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We examine the effects WWII Lanham Act Nursery Schools (LNS) on high school and young adult educational and labor outcomes of participants in the landmark Project Talent (PT) study. All PT places that received funding for LNS schools and all PT places that did not were identified by examining program records and contemporaneous newspaper accounts. Focusing on students who in 1960 attended high school in the same city or town where they were born, we estimate intent to treat effects of access to LNS preschool on high school academic and social emotional outcomes and on educational attainment and labor outcomes at five and eleven years following high school graduation. Preschool boosts high school academic outcomes for men and (in at least one specification) income 11 years after high school graduation. For women, preschool exposure had a negative effect on some social emotional outcomes in high school. We found no or inconsistent effects for other outcomes. The Lanham experience demonstrates that even with the less sophisticated understanding of child development of the early 1940s, the first universal, government-funded preschool program had positive impacts on boys’ outcomes at least through high school. Given today’s expanded understanding of child development and focus on the quality of early care and education programming, these findings provide some optimism as communities, states, and the federal government contemplate expanding funding for today’s early learning environments.]]></description><author>Taletha M. Derrington, Alison Huang, Joseph P. Ferrie</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29271</guid></item><item><title>The Geography of Unemployment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Unemployment rates differ widely across local labor markets. I offer new empirical evidence that high local unemployment emerges because of elevated local job losing rates. Local employers, rather than local workers, account for most of spatial gaps in job stability. I then propose a theory in which spatial differences in job loss arise endogenously, due to the spatial sorting of heterogeneous employers across local labor markets.  Labor market frictions induce productive employers to over-value locating close to each other. The optimal policy incentivizes them to relocate to areas with high job losing rates, providing a rationale for commonly used place-based policies. I estimate the model using French administrative data. The estimated model accounts for over three fourths of the cross-sectional dispersion in unemployment rates, as well as for the respective contributions of job losing and job finding rates. Employers' inefficient location choices amplify spatial unemployment differentials five-fold. Both real-world and optimal place-based policies can yield sizable local and aggregate welfare gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</guid></item><item><title>The Heterogeneous Effects of Large and Small Minimum Wage Changes: Evidence over the Short and Medium Run Using a Pre-Analysis Plan</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29264</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper advances the use of pre-analysis plans in non-experimental research settings. In a study of recent minimum wage changes, we demonstrate how analyses of medium- and long-run impacts of policy interventions can be pre-specified as extensions to short-run analyses. Further, our pre-analysis plan includes comparisons of the effects of large vs. small minimum wage increases, which is a theoretically motivated dimension of heterogeneity. We discuss how these use cases harness the strengths of pre-analysis plans while mitigating their weaknesses. This project’s initial analyses explored CPS and ACS data from 2011 through 2015. Alongside these analyses, we pre-committed to analyses incorporating CPS and ACS data extending through 2019. Averaging across the specifications in our pre-analysis plan, we estimate that relatively large minimum wage increases reduced employment rates among low-skilled individuals by just over 2.5 percentage points. Our estimates of the effects of relatively small minimum wage increases vary across data sets and specifications but are, on average, both economically and statistically indistinguishable from zero. We estimate that medium-run effects exceed short-run effects and that the elasticity of employment with respect to the minimum wage is substantially more negative for large minimum wage increases than for small increases.]]></description><author>Jeffrey Clemens, Michael R. Strain</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29264</guid></item><item><title>Intergenerational Mobility in American History: Accounting for Race and Measurement Error</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29256</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> A large body of evidence finds that relative mobility in the US has declined over the past 150 years. However, long-run mobility estimates are usually based on white samples and therefore do not account for the limited opportunities available for non-white families. Moreover, historical data measure the father’s status with error, which biases estimates toward greater mobility. Using linked census data from 1850-1940, I show that accounting for race and measurement error can double estimates of intergenerational persistence. Updated estimates imply that there is greater equality of opportunity today than in the past, mostly because opportunity was never that equal.]]></description><author>Zachary Ward</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29256</guid></item><item><title>Community Colleges and Upward Mobility</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29254</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Two-year community colleges enroll nearly half of all first-time undergraduates in the United States, but to ambiguous effect: low persistence rates and the potential for diverting students from 4-year institutions cast ambiguity over 2-year colleges' contributions to upward mobility. This paper develops a new instrumental variables approach to identifying causal effects along multiple treatment margins, and applies it to linked education and earnings registries to disentangle the net impacts of 2-year college access into two competing causal margins: significant value-added for 2-year entrants who otherwise would not have attended college, but negative impacts on students diverted from immediate 4-year entry.]]></description><author>Jack Mountjoy</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29254</guid></item><item><title>The Gender Gap in Earnings Losses after Job Displacement</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29251</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Existing research has shown that job displacement leads to large and persistent earnings losses for men, but evidence for women is scarce. Using administrative data from Germany, we apply an event study design in combination with propensity score matching and a reweighting technique to directly compare men and women who are displaced from similar jobs and firms. Our results show that after a mass layoff, women’s earnings losses are about 35% higher than men’s, with the gap persisting five years after job displacement. This is partly explained by a higher propensity of women to take up part-time or marginal employment following job loss, but even full-time wage losses are almost 50% (or 5 percentage points) higher for women than for men. We then show that on the household level there is no evidence of an added worker effect, independent of the gender of the job loser. Finally, we document that parenthood magnifies the gender gap sharply: while fathers of young children have smaller earnings losses than men in general, mothers of young children have much larger earnings losses than other women.]]></description><author>Hannah Illing, Johannes F. Schmieder, Simon Trenkle</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29251</guid></item><item><title>Inequality in Early Care Experienced by U.S. Children</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29249</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Using every major nationally-representative dataset on parental and non-parental care provided to children up to age 6, we quantify differences in American children’s care experiences by socioeconomic status (SES), proxied primarily with maternal education. Increasingly, higher-SES children spend less time with their parents and more time in the care of others. Non-parental care for high-SES children is more likely to be in childcare centers, where average quality is higher, and less likely to be provided by relatives where average quality is lower. Even within types of childcare, higher-SES children tend to receive care of higher measured quality and higher cost. Inequality is evident at home as well: measures of parental enrichment at home, from both self-reports and outside observers, are on average higher for higher-SES children. We also find that parental and non-parental quality is reinforcing: children who receive higher quality non-parental care also tend to receive higher quality parental care. Head Start, one of the largest government care subsidy programs for low-income households, reduces inequality in care provided, but it is mainly limited to older children and to the lowest income households. Our evidence is from the pre-COVID-19 period, and the latest year we examine is 2019.]]></description><author>Sarah Flood, Joel F.S. McMurry, Aaron Sojourner, Matthew J. Wiswall</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29249</guid></item><item><title>Why is Workplace Sexual Harassment Underreported? The Value of Outside Options Amid the Threat of Retaliation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29248</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Why is workplace sexual harassment chronically underreported? We hypothesize that employers coerce victims into silence through the threat of a retaliatory firing, and test this theory by estimating whether external shocks that reduce the value of a worker's outside options exacerbate underreporting. Under mild assumptions, a rise in the severity of formal complaints is indicative of increased underreporting. Combining this insight with an objective measure of the quality of charges filed with the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC), we perform two analyses. First, we assess whether workers report sexual harassment more selectively during recessions, when outside labor market options are limited. We estimate the fraction of sexual harassment charges deemed to have merit by the EEOC increases by 0.5-0.7% for each one percentage point increase in a state-industry's monthly unemployment rate. The effect is amplified in industries employing a larger fraction of men and in establishments with a higher share of male managers. Second, we test whether less generous UI benefits create economic incentives for victims of workplace sexual harassment to remain silent. We find the selectivity of sexual harassment charges increases by more than 30% in response to a 50% cut to North Carolina's Unemployment Insurance (UI) program following the Great Recession.]]></description><author>Gordon B. Dahl, Matthew M. Knepper</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29248</guid></item><item><title>Harms of AI</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29247</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This essay discusses several potential economic, political and social costs of the current path of AI technologies. I argue that if AI continues to be deployed along its current trajectory and remains unregulated, it may produce various social, economic and political harms. These include: damaging competition, consumer privacy and consumer choice; excessively automating work, fueling inequality, inefficiently pushing down wages, and failing to improve worker productivity; and damaging political discourse, democracy's most fundamental lifeblood. Although there is no conclusive evidence suggesting that these costs are imminent or substantial, it may be useful to understand them before they are fully realized and become harder or even impossible to reverse, precisely because of AI's promising and wide-reaching potential. I also suggest that these costs are not inherent to the nature of AI technologies, but are related to how they are being used and developed at the moment - to empower corporations and governments against workers and citizens. As a result, efforts to limit and reverse these costs may need to rely on regulation and policies to redirect AI research. Attempts to contain them just by promoting competition may be insufficient.]]></description><author>Daron Acemoglu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29247</guid></item><item><title>The Dynamics of Referral Hiring and Racial Inequality: Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29246</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study how referral hiring contributes to racial inequality in firm-level labor demand over the firm's life cycle using data from Brazil. We consider a search model where referral networks are segregated, firms are more informed about the match quality of referred candidates, and some referrals are made by non-referred employees. Consistent with the model, we find that firms are more likely to hire candidates and less likely to dismiss employees of the same race as the founder, but these differences diminish as firms' cumulative hires increase. Referral hiring helps to explain racial differences in dismissals, seniority, and employer size.]]></description><author>Conrad Miller, Ian M. Schmutte</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29246</guid></item><item><title>Perceptions of Racial Gaps, their Causes, and Ways to Reduce Them</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29245</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Using new large-scale survey and experimental data, we investigate how respondents perceive racial inequities between Black and white Americans, what they believe causes them, and what interventions, if any, they think should be implemented to reduce them. We intentionally over-sample Black respondents, cover many US cities, and survey both adults and young people of ages 13 through 17. In the experimental parts, we consider the causal impact of information on racial inequities (such as the evolution of the Black-white earnings gap or the diﬀerences in mobility for Black and white children) and explanations for these inequities (i.e., the deep-seated roots and long-lasting consequences of systemic racism) on respondents’ views. Although there is heterogeneity in how respondents perceive the magnitude of current racial gaps in economic conditions and opportunities, the biggest discrepancies are in how they explain them. There is a stark partisan gap among white respondents, particularly in the perceived causes of racial inequities and what should be done about them. White Democrats and Black respondents are much more likely to attribute racial inequities to adverse past and present circumstances and want to act on them with race-targeted and general redistribution policies. White Republicans are more likely to attribute racial gaps to individual actions. These views are already deeply entrenched in teenagers, based on their race and their parents’ political aﬃliation. A policy decomposition shows that the perceived causes of racial inequities correlate most strongly with support for race-targeted or general redistribution policies, a ﬁnding conﬁrmed by the experimental results.]]></description><author>Alberto Alesina, Matteo F. Ferroni, Stefanie Stantcheva</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29245</guid></item><item><title>Police Officer Assignment and Neighborhood Crime</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29243</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We develop an empirical model of the mechanism used to assign police officers to Chicago districts and examine the efficiency and equity of alternative allocations. We document that the current bidding process, which grants priority based on seniority, results in the assignment of more experienced officers to less violent and high-income neighborhoods. Our empirical model combines estimates of heterogeneous officer preferences underlying the bidding process with causal estimates of the effects of officer experience on neighborhood crime. Equalizing officer seniority across districts would reduce violent crime rate by 4.6 percent and significantly decrease inequality in crime, discretionary arrests, and officer use of force across neighborhoods. Moreover, this assignment can be achieved in a revenue-neutral way while resulting in small welfare gains for police officers, implying that it is more equitable and efficient.]]></description><author>Bocar Ba, Patrick Bayer, Nayoung Rim, Roman Rivera, Modibo Sidibé</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29243</guid></item><item><title>The Great Divide: Education, Despair and Death</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29241</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Deaths of despair, morbidity and emotional distress continue to rise in the US. The increases are largely borne by those without a four-year college degree—the majority of American adults. For many less-educated Americans, the economy and society are no longer providing the basis for a good life. Concurrently, all-cause mortality in the US is diverging by education—falling for the college-educated and rising for those without a degree—something not seen in other rich countries. We review the rising prevalence of pain, despair, and suicide among Americans without a BA. Pain and despair created a baseline demand for opioids, but the escalation of addiction came from pharma and its political enablers. We examine “the politics of despair,” how less-educated people have abandoned and been abandoned by the Democratic Party. While healthier states once voted Republican in presidential elections, now the least-healthy states do. We review the evidence on whether or not deaths of despair have risen during the COVID pandemic. More broadly, excess mortality from COVID has not increased the ratio of all-cause mortality rates for those with and without a four-year degree, but has instead replicated the pre-existing mortality ratio.]]></description><author>Anne Case, Angus Deaton</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29241</guid></item><item><title>The Affordable Care Act After a Decade: Its Impact on the Labor Market and the Macro Economy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29240</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The Affordable Care Act (ACA) is one of the most important reforms of the US health insurance system since the introduction of Medicare. Since employment is a main source of health insurance for the working age population in the United States, this sweeping health insurance reform also has important implications for the labor market and the macro economy. In this paper, we survey the prototype models that are used in the macro and labor literature, extended to integrate health and health insurance, to study the short- and long-run consequences of the ACA. We also suggest open areas for future research.]]></description><author>Hanming Fang, Dirk Krueger</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29240</guid></item><item><title>Does Education Prevent Job Loss During Downturns? Evidence from Exogenous School Assignments and COVID-19 in Barbados</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29231</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Canonical human capital theories posit that education, by enhancing worker skills, reduces the likelihood that a worker will be laid-off during times of economic change. Yet, this has not been demonstrated causally. We link administrative education records from 1987 through 2002 to nationally representative surveys conducted before and after COVID-19 onset in Barbados to explore the causal impact of improved education on job loss during this period. Using a regression discontinuity (RD) design, Beuermann and Jackson (2020) show that females (but not males) who score just above the admission threshold for more selective schools in Barbados attain more years of education than those that scored just below (essentially holding initial ability fixed). Here, in follow-up data, we show that these same females (but not males) are much less likely to have lost a job after the onset of COVID-19. We show that these effects are not driven by sectoral changes, or changes in labor supply. Because employers observe incumbent worker productivity, these patterns are inconsistent with pure education signalling, and suggest that education enhances worker skill.]]></description><author>Diether W. Beuermann, Nicolas L. Bottan, Bridget Hoffmann, C. Kirabo Jackson, Diego A. Vera Cossio</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29231</guid></item><item><title>Maximum Employment and the Participation Cycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29222</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We investigate the source, magnitude, and unevenness of the procyclical forces that shape labor force participation, i.e., the participation cycle, which are important for the implementation of the maximum employment mandate. We show that these forces can be analyzed in real time using a flow decomposition of the changes in the labor force participation rate. The decomposition reveals that the source of the participation cycle is fluctuations in job-loss and job-finding rates, rather than cyclical movements in labor force entry and exit rates. The magnitude of the participation cycle is large. Cyclical downward pressures on employment from participation are two-thirds that of unemployment. Moreover, the participation cycle delays the recovery in employment because it lags the unemployment cycle. It also amplifies the unevenness of the impact of recessions. Groups that see large increases in their unemployment rates also experience more pronounced participation cycles. Despite differences in their magnitudes, the source of the participation cycle is the same for all groups. Application of our method to the COVID-19 Recession suggests that, as of June 2021, the bulk of the drop in the participation rate since the onset of the pandemic is cyclical and that the cyclical recovery in participation likely will trail that of the unemployment rate.]]></description><author>Bart Hobijn, Ayşegül Şahin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29222</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of Healthcare IT on Clinical Quality, Productivity and Workers</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29218</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Adoption of health information and communication technologies (“HICT”) has surged over the past two decades. We survey the medical and economic literature on HICT adoption and its impact on clinical outcomes, productivity and labor.  We find that HICT improves clinical outcomes and lowers healthcare costs, but (i) the effects are modest so far, (ii) it takes time for these effects to materialize, and (iii) there is much variation in the impact. More evidence on the causal effects of HICT on productivity is needed to guide further adoption. There is little econometric work directly investigating the impact of HICT on labor, but what there is suggests no substantial negative effects on employment and earnings. Overall, while healthcare is “exceptional” in many ways, we are struck by the similarities to the wider findings on ICT and productivity stressing the importance of complementary factors (e.g. management and skills) in determining HICT impacts.]]></description><author>Ari Bronsoler, Joseph J. Doyle Jr., John Van Reenen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29218</guid></item><item><title>The Employment and Redistributive Effects of Reducing or Eliminating Minimum Wage Tip Credits</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29213</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Recent policy debate on minimum wages has focused not only on raising the minimum wage, but on eliminating the tip credit for restaurant workers. We use data on past variation in tip credits – or minimum wages for restaurant workers – to provide evidence on the potential impacts of eliminating (or reducing) the tip credit. Our evidence points to higher tipped minimum wages (smaller tip credits) reducing jobs among tipped restaurant workers, without earnings effects on those who remain employed sufficiently large to raise total earnings in this sector. And most of our evidence provides no indication that higher tipped minimum wages would be well targeted to poor or low-income families or reduce the likelihood of being poor or very low income.]]></description><author>David Neumark, Maysen Yen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29213</guid></item><item><title>Inequality in Mortality between Black and White Americans by Age, Place, and Cause, and in Comparison to Europe, 1990-2018</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29203</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Although there is a large gap between Black and White American life expectancies, the gap fell 48.9% between 1990-2018, mainly due to mortality declines among Black Americans. We examine age-specific mortality trends and racial gaps in life expectancy in rich and poor U.S. areas and with reference to six European countries.<br />
Inequalities in life expectancy are starker in the U.S. than in Europe. In 1990 White Americans and Europeans in rich areas had similar overall life expectancy, while life expectancy for White Americans in poor areas was lower.  But since then even rich White Americans have lost ground relative to Europeans. Meanwhile, the gap in life expectancy between Black Americans and Europeans decreased by 8.3%.<br />
Black life expectancy increased more than White life expectancy in all U.S. areas, but improvements in poorer areas had the greatest impact on the racial life expectancy gap. The causes that contributed the most to Black mortality reductions included: Cancer, homicide, HIV, and causes originating in the fetal or infant period.<br />
Life expectancy for both Black and White Americans plateaued or slightly declined after 2012, but this stalling was most evident among Black Americans even prior to the COVID-19 pandemic. If improvements had continued at the 1990-2012 rate, the racial gap in life expectancy would have closed by 2036. European life expectancy also stalled after 2014. Still, the comparison with Europe suggests that mortality rates of both Black and White Americans could fall much further across all ages and in both rich and poor areas.]]></description><author>Hannes Schwandt, Janet Currie, Marlies Bär, James Banks, Paola Bertoli, Aline Bütikofer, Sarah Cattan, Beatrice Zong-Ying Chao, Claudia Costa, Libertad Gonzalez, Veronica Grembi, Kristiina Huttunen, René Karadakic, Lucy Kraftman, Sonya Krutikova, Stefano Lombardi, Peter Redler, Carlos Riumallo-Herl, Ana Rodríguez-González, Kjell Salvanes, Paula Santana, Josselin Thuilliez, Eddy van Doorslaer, Tom Van Ourti, Joachim Winter, Bram Wouterse, Amelie Wuppermann</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29203</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Channel of Wage Rigidity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29201</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> I propose a financial channel of wage rigidity. In recessions, rather than propping up marginal (new hires’) costs of labor, rigid average wages squeeze cash flows, forcing firms to cut hiring due to financial constraints. Indeed, empirical cash flows and profits would turn acyclical if wages were only moderately more procyclical. I study this channel in a search and matching model with financial constraints and rigid wages among incumbent workers, while new hires’ wages are flexible. Individually, each feature generates no amplification. By contrast, their interaction can account for much of the empirical labor market fluctuations—breaking the neutrality of incumbents’ wages for hiring, and showing that financial amplification of business cycles requires wage rigidity.]]></description><author>Benjamin Schoefer</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29201</guid></item><item><title>The Long-Run Impacts of Mexican-American School Desegregation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29200</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We present the first quantitative analysis of the impact of ending de jure segregation of Mexican-American school children in the United States by examining the effects of the 1947 Mendez v. Westminster court decision on long-run educational attainment for Hispanics and non-Hispanic whites in California. Our identification strategy relies on comparing individuals across California counties that vary in their likelihood of segregating and across birth cohorts that vary in their exposure to the Mendez court ruling based on school start age. Results point to a significant increase in educational attainment for Hispanics who were fully exposed to school desegregation.]]></description><author>Francisca M. Antman, Kalena Cortes</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29200</guid></item><item><title>Income-Contingent Loans As an Unemployment Benefit</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29198</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Imperfections in risk and capital markets imply that individuals who lose jobs suffer from imperfect smoothing of consumption across states and times. Compared to the first best, there will be too little search. Optimal unemployment programs, which balance the marginal benefit of consumption smoothing vs. the marginal cost of the insurance externality, increase welfare and may even increase GDP. Our analytical results suggest that welfare is higher if the unemployment benefits program includes income-contingent unemployment loans (ICL), where the amount repaid depends on the individual’s future income. Such loans can be financed by a risk premium imposed on the unemployed who avail themselves of the loans, and partially substitute for unemployment insurance (UI) benefits. Optimal unemployment benefits programs (UB) with ICL do a better job of smoothing consumption across states and time, and in particular total benefits when unemployed increase. We analyze how changes in key parameters, such as the degree of risk aversion and the nature of post-employment work, affect the design of the optimal UB program and the magnitude of the incremental benefits from including income-contingent loans.]]></description><author>Haaris Mateen ⓡ, Joseph E. Stiglitz ⓡ, Jungyoll Yun</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29198</guid></item><item><title>Job Displacement and Job Mobility: The Role of Joblessness</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29187</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Who is harmed by and who benefits from worker reallocation?  We investigate the earnings consequences of changing jobs and find a wide dispersion in outcomes. This dispersion is driven not by whether the worker was displaced, but by the duration of joblessness between job spells. Job movers who experience joblessness suffer a persistent reduction in earnings and tend to move to lower-paying firms, suggesting that job ladder models offer a useful lens through which to understand the negative consequences of job separations.]]></description><author>Bruce Fallick, John C. Haltiwanger, Erika McEntarfer, Matthew Staiger</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29187</guid></item><item><title>The Value of Statistical Life: A Meta-analysis of Meta-analyses</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29185</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The Value of Statistical Life (VSL) is arguably the most important number in benefit-cost analyses of environmental, health, and transportation policies.  However, agencies have used a wide range of VSL values.  One reason may be the embarrassment of riches when it comes to VSL studies.  While meta-analysis is a standard way to synthesize information across studies, we now have multiple competing meta-analyses and reviews.  Thus, to analysts, picking one such meta-analysis may feel as hard as picking a single "best study."  This paper responds by taking the meta-analysis another step, estimating a meta-analysis (or mixture distribution) of six meta-analyses.  The baseline model yields a central VSL of $7.0m, with a 90% confidence interval of $2.4m to $11.2m.  The provided code allows users to easily change subjective weights on the studies, add new studies, or change adjustments for income, inflation, and latency.]]></description><author>H. Spencer Banzhaf</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29185</guid></item><item><title>Marginalized and Overlooked? Minoritized Groups and the Adoption of New Scientific Ideas</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29179</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The rapid diffusion and use of new ideas are critical for advancing and realizing the value of innovation. This paper explores the impact of demographic characteristics of innovators and potential adopters on the adoption of important new scientific ideas through networks. Using rich, population-level data on the biomedical researchers and their networks, natural language processing, and a novel two-way fixed effects strategy, we find that new ideas introduced by female scientists are under-utilized, which can be explain by two factors. First, female innovators are not as well-connected in networks; second, even at a short network distances, researchers (especially men) are less likely to adopt women’s ideas. Ideas from underrepresented racial and ethnic minorities are also less widely used.]]></description><author>Wei Cheng, Bruce A. Weinberg</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29179</guid></item><item><title>Does Money Still Matter? Attainment and Earnings Effects of Post-1990 School Finance Reforms</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29177</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Card and Krueger (1992a,b) used labor market outcomes to study the productivity of school spending. Following their lead, we examine effects of post-1990 school finance reforms on students’ educational attainment and labor market outcomes. Lafortune et al. (2018) show that these reforms increased school spending and narrowed spending and achievement gaps between high- and low-income districts. Using a state-by-cohort panel design, we find that reforms increased high school completion and college-going, concentrated among Black students and women, and raised annual earnings. They also increased the return to education, particularly for Black students and men and driven by the return to high school.]]></description><author>Jesse Rothstein, Diane Whitmore Schanzenbach</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29177</guid></item><item><title>The Economics of Walking About and Predicting Unemployment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29172</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Unemployment is notoriously difficult to predict.  In previous studies, once country fixed effects are added to panel estimates, few variables predict changes in unemployment rates.  Using panel data for 29 European countries over 439 months between 1985 and 2021 in an unbalanced country*month panel of just over 10000 observations, we predict changes in the unemployment rate 12 months in advance based on individuals’ fears of unemployment, their perceptions of the economic situation and their own household financial situation.  Fear of unemployment predicts subsequent changes in unemployment 12 months later in the presence of country fixed effects and lagged unemployment.  Individuals’ perceptions of the economic situation in the country and their own household finances also predict unemployment 12 months later. Business sentiment (industry fear of unemployment) is also predictive of unemployment 12 months later.  The findings underscore the importance of the “economics of walking about”. The implication is that these social survey data are informative in predicting economic downturns and should be used more extensively in forecasting.  We also generate a 29 country-level annual panel on life satisfaction from 1985-2020 from the World Database of Happiness and show that the consumer level fear of unemployment variable lowers well-being over and above the negative impact of the unemployment rate itself.  Qualitative survey metrics were able to predict the Great Recession and the economic slowdown in Europe just prior to the COVID19 pandemic.]]></description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29172</guid></item><item><title>Demographics, Wealth, and Global Imbalances in the Twenty-First Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29161</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We use a sufficient statistic approach to quantify the general equilibrium effects of population aging on wealth accumulation, expected asset returns, and global imbalances. Combining population forecasts with household survey data from 25 countries, we measure the compositional effect of aging: how a changing age distribution affects wealth-to-GDP, holding the age profiles of assets and labor income fixed. In a baseline overlapping generations model this statistic, in conjunction with cross-sectional information and two standard macro parameters, pins down general equilibrium outcomes. Since the compositional effect is positive, large, and heterogeneous across countries, our model predicts that population aging will increase wealth-to- GDP ratios, lower asset returns, and widen global imbalances through the twenty-first century. These conclusions extend to a richer model in which bequests, individual savings, and the tax-and-transfer system all respond to demographic change.]]></description><author>Adrien Auclert, Hannes Malmberg, Frederic Martenet, Matthew Rognlie</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29161</guid></item><item><title>Shifting Punishment on Minorities: Experimental Evidence of Scapegoating</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29157</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper provides experimental evidence showing that members of a majority group systematically shift punishment on innocent members of an ethnic minority.  We develop a new incentivized task, the Punishing the Scapegoat Game, to measure how injustice affecting a member of one’s own group shapes punishment of an unrelated bystander (“a scapegoat”). We manipulate the ethnic identity of the scapegoats and study interactions between the majority group and the Roma minority in Slovakia. We find that when no harm is done, there is no evidence of discrimination against the ethnic minority. In contrast, when a member of one’s own group is harmed, the punishment ”passed” on innocent individuals more than doubles when they are from the minority, as compared to when they are from the dominant group. These results illuminate how individualized tensions can be transformed into a group conflict, dragging minorities into conflicts in a way that is completely unrelated to their behavior.]]></description><author>Michal Bauer, Jana Cahlíková, Julie Chytilová, Gérard Roland, Tomas Zelinsky</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29157</guid></item><item><title>Congestion on the Information Superhighway: Does Economics Have a Working Papers Problem?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29153</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Publishing takes a long time in economics. Consequently, many authors release “working” versions of their papers. Using data on the NBER working paper series, we show that the dissemination of economics research suffers from an overcrowding problem: An increase in the number of weekly released working papers on average reduces downloads, abstract views, and media attention for each paper. Subsequent publishing and citation outcomes are harmed as well. Furthermore, descriptive evidence on viewership and downloads suggests working papers significantly substitute for the dissemination function of publication. These results highlight inefficiencies in the dissemination of economic research even among the most exclusive working paper series and suggest large social losses due to the slow publication process.]]></description><author>Lester R. Lusher, Winnie Yang, Scott E. Carrell</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29153</guid></item><item><title>Contract Labor and Firm Growth in India</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29151</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> India's Industrial Disputes Act (IDA) of 1947 requires firm with more than 100 workers to pay large costs if they shrink their employment. Since the early 2000s, large Indian manufacturing firms have increasingly relied on contract workers who are not subject to the IDA. By 2015, contract workers accounted for 38% of total employment at firms with more than 100 workers compared to 20% in 2000. Over the same time period, the thickness of the right tail of the firm size distribution in formal Indian manufacturing plants increased, the average product of labor for large firms declined, the job creation rate for large firms increased, and the probability that large firms introduce new products rose.  We provide evidence that these outcomes were caused by an increased reliance on contract labor among large establishments. A model of firm growth subject to firing costs suggests the rise of contract labor increased TFP in Indian manufacturing by 7.6%, occurring all through a one-time reduction in misallocation between large and small firms with negligible change in the long-run growth rate.]]></description><author>Marianne Bertrand, Chang-Tai Hsieh, Nick Tsivanidis</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29151</guid></item><item><title>Can Restorative Justice Conferencing Reduce Recidivism? Evidence From the Make-it-Right Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29150</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the effect of a restorative justice intervention targeted at youth ages 13 to 17 facing felony charges of medium severity (e.g., burglary, assault).  Eligible youths were randomly assigned to participate in the Make-it-Right (MIR) restorative justice program or to a control group in which they faced criminal prosecution.  We estimate the effects of MIR on the likelihood that a youth will be rearrested in the four years following randomization. Assignment to MIR reduces the likelihood of a rearrest within six months by 19 percentage points, a 44 percent reduction relative to the control group.  Moreover, the reduction in recidivism persists even four years after randomization.  Thus, our estimates show that juvenile restorative justice conferencing can reduce recidivism among youth charged with relatively serious offenses and can be an effective alternative to traditional criminal justice practices.]]></description><author>Yotam Shem-Tov, Steven Raphael, Alissa Skog</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29150</guid></item><item><title>Treatment and Selection Effects of Formal Workplace Mentorship Programs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29148</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> While formal mentorship programs are ubiquitous, less is known about who gains from receiving mentorship. In this paper, we report the outcome of a Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT) carried out in a US-based inbound sales call center where one branch of the experiment assigned a random subset of new hires to mentors (Broad-Mentoring), whereas a second branch (Selective-Mentoring) gave new hires the opportunity to opt into a mentoring relationship before assigning a random subset to mentors. In the Broad-Mentoring branch, mentored sales agents outperformed non-mentored agents by over 18% in the first six months on the job. Among agents who opt into the program in the Selective-Mentoring branch, those who received mentorship had negligible performance gains. The differences between the two branches indicates that formal mentorship program treatment effects are largest for workers who would otherwise opt out of these programs. Demographic and personality characteristics are relatively weak predictors of selection into the program, suggesting broad-based programs are likely more effective than alternative targeting rules.]]></description><author>Jason Sandvik, Richard Saouma, Nathan Seegert, Christopher T. Stanton</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29148</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Returns and the Evolution of Cognitive Skills: Theory and Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29135</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> A large literature in cognitive science studies the puzzling "Flynn effect" of rising fluid intelligence (reasoning skill) in rich countries. We develop an economic model in which a cohort's mix of skills is determined by different skills' relative returns in the labor market and by the technology for producing skills. We estimate the model using administrative data from Sweden. Combining data from exams taken at military enlistment with earnings records from the tax register, we document an increase in the relative labor market return to logical reasoning skill as compared to vocabulary knowledge. The estimated model implies that changes in labor market returns explain 36 percent of the measured increase in reasoning skill, and can also explain the decline in knowledge. An original survey of parents, an analysis of trends in school curricula, and an analysis of occupational characteristics show evidence of increasing emphasis on reasoning as compared to knowledge.]]></description><author>Santiago Hermo, Miika M. Päällysaho, David G. Seim, Jesse M. Shapiro</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29135</guid></item><item><title>Return on Student Loans in Canada</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29130</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper uses new administrative data with detailed borrower information and lengthy repayment histories from the Canada Student Loans Program (CSLP) to measure rates of return on undergraduate student loans. We document substantial heterogeneity in returns based on information available at the time loans were disbursed, including province of residence, field of study, and institution of attendance. Field of study is a particularly important determinant of rates of return, explaining 22% of the variation in predicted returns across borrowers.  We explore the implications of this variation for CSLP cross-subsidization across borrowers and potential risk-based loan limits. Given the variation in ex ante predicted returns across borrowers, using all available information at the time of loan disbursement, we study the implications of potential cream-skimming of high-return borrowers by private lenders.]]></description><author>Lance Lochner, Qian Liu, Martin Gervais</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29130</guid></item><item><title>Obedience in the Labor Market and Social Mobility: A Socio-Economic Approach</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29125</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper presents an analysis of what types of values, especially in regards to obedience vs. independence, families impart to their children and how these values interact with social mobility. In the model, obedience is a useful characteristic for employers, especially when wages are low, because independent workers require more incentives (when wages are high, these incentives are automatic). Hence, in low-wage environments, low-income families will impart values of obedience to their children to prevent disadvantaging them in the labor market. To the extent that independence is useful for entrepreneurial activities, this then depresses their social mobility. High-income and privileged parents, on the other hand, always impart values of independence, since they expect that their children can enter into higher-income entrepreneurial (or managerial) activities thanks to their family resources and privileges. I also discuss how political activity can be hampered when labor market incentives encourage greater obedience and how this can generate multiple steady states with different patterns of social hierarchy and mobility.]]></description><author>Daron Acemoglu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29125</guid></item><item><title>What We Teach About Race and Gender: Representation in Images and Text of Children’s Books</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29123</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Books shape how children learn about society and social norms, in part through the representation of different characters. To better understand the messages children encounter in books, we introduce new artificial intelligence methods for systematically converting images into data. We apply these image tools, along with established text analysis methods, to measure the representation of race, gender, and age in children’s books commonly found in US schools and homes over the last century. We find that more characters with darker skin color appear over time, but "mainstream" award-winning books, which are twice as likely to be checked out from libraries, persistently depict more lighter-skinned characters even after conditioning on perceived race. Across all books, children are depicted with lighter skin than adults. Over time, females are increasingly present but are more represented in images than in text, suggesting greater symbolic inclusion in pictures than substantive inclusion in stories. Relative to their growing share of the US population, Black and Latinx people are underrepresented in the mainstream collection; males, particularly White males, are persistently overrepresented. Our data provide a view into the "black box" of education through children’s books in US schools and homes, highlighting what has changed and what has endured.]]></description><author>Anjali Adukia, Alex Eble, Emileigh Harrison, Hakizumwami Birali Runesha, Teodora Szasz</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29123</guid></item><item><title>Women's Well-Being During a Pandemic and its Containment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29121</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic brought the dual crises of disease and the containment policies designed to mitigate it. Yet, there is little evidence on the impacts of these policies on women, who are likely to be especially vulnerable, in lower-income countries. We conduct a large phone survey and leverage India's geographically-varying containment policies to estimate the association between both the pandemic and its containment policies, and measures of women's well-being, including mental health and food security. On aggregate, the pandemic resulted in dramatic income losses, increases in food insecurity, and declines in female mental health. While potentially crucial to stem the spread of COVID-19 cases, we find that greater prevalence of containment policies is associated with increased food insecurity, particularly for women, and with reduced female mental health. Average containment levels are associated with a 39-40% increase in the likelihood of sadness, depression, and hopelessness among women and with an increase in the likelihood that women feel more worried by 45% of the variable mean. Particularly vulnerable groups of women, those with daughters and those living in female-headed households, experience larger declines in mental health.]]></description><author>Natalie Bau, Gaurav Khanna, Corinne Low, Manisha Shah, Sreyashi Sharmin, Alessandra Voena</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29121</guid></item><item><title>Native Americans’ Experience of Chronic Distress in the USA</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29119</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Four million Native Americans who identify as single race live in the USA.  Another three million identify as Native American in combination with another race.  Yet they are rarely the focus of detailed research.  We provide the first evidence that levels of consistently poor mental health, or chronic distress, among Native peoples were greater in every year between 1993 and 2020 than among White or Black Americans.  We find this to be present among those over the age of thirty but less so for the young.  Over time we demonstrate there has been a rise in chronic distress among Native Americans and multi-race individuals.  However, chronic distress seems to be lowest among Native peoples living in the seven states with the largest Native American populations of Alaska, Arizona, Montana, New Mexico, North Dakota, South Dakota and Oklahoma.  In our judgment these facts are important and not widely known.  This stands in stark contrast to the enormous scholarly and media interest in declining physiological well-being among White Americans.]]></description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Donna Feir</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29119</guid></item><item><title>What Happens When Employers Can No Longer Discriminate in Job Ads?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29116</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> When employers’ explicit gender requests were unexpectedly removed from a Chinese job board overnight, pools of successful applicants became more integrated: women’s (men’s) share of call-backs to jobs that had requested men (women) rose by 63 (146) percent. The removal ‘worked’ in this sense because it generated a large increase in gender-mismatched applications, and because those applications were treated surprisingly well by employers.  The removal had little or no effect on aggregate matching frictions.  The job titles that were integrated however, were not the most gendered ones, and were disproportionately lower-wage jobs.]]></description><author>Peter J. Kuhn, Kailing Shen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29116</guid></item><item><title>Economic Consequences of Hospital Closures</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29110</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Hospitals anchor much of US health care and receive a third of all medical spending, including various subsidies. Nevertheless, some become insolvent and exit the market. Research has documented subsequent access problems; however, less is understood about broader implications. We examine over 100 rural hospital closures spanning 2005-2017 to quantify the effects on the local economy. We find sharp and persistent reductions in employment, but these localize to health care occupations and are largely driven by areas experiencing complete closures. Aggregate consumer financial health is only modestly affected, and housing markets were already depressed prior to hospital closures.]]></description><author>Diane E. Alexander, Michael R. Richards</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29110</guid></item></channel></rss>