<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Money and Interest Rates</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Money and Interest Rates</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:21:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Sovereign Risk and Financial Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29501</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Simon Gilchrist, Bin Wei, Vivian Z. Yue, Egon Zakrajšek.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we study the interplay between sovereign risk and global financial risk. We show that a substantial portion of the comovement among sovereign spreads is accounted for by changes in global financial risk. We construct bond-level sovereign spreads for dollar-denominated bonds issued by over 50 countries from 1995 to 2020 and use various indicators to measure global financial risk. Through panel regressions and local projection analysis, we find that an increase in global financial risk causes a large and persistent widening of sovereign bond spreads. These effects are strongest when measuring global risk using the excess bond premium – a measure of the risk-bearing capacity of U.S. financial intermediaries. The spillover effects of global financial risk are more pronounced for speculative-grade sovereign bonds.]]></description><author>Simon Gilchrist, Bin Wei, Vivian Z. Yue, Egon Zakrajšek</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29501</guid></item><item><title>Skewness and Time-Varying Second Moments in a Nonlinear Production Network: Theory and Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29499</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ian Dew-Becker, Alireza Tahbaz-Salehi, Andrea Vedolin.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies asymmetry in economic activity over the business cycle. It develops a tractable multisector model of the economy in which complementarity across inputs causes aggregate activity to be left skewed with countercyclical volatility. We then examine implications of the model regarding the time-series skewness of activity at the sector level, cyclicality of dispersion and skewness across sectors, and the conditional covariances of sector growth rates, finding support for each in the data. The empirical skewness of employment growth, industrial production growth, and stock returns increases with the level of aggregation, which is consistent with the model's implication that it is the nonlinearity in the production structure of the economy that generates the skewness. Other prominent models of asymmetry are not able to simultaneously match the range of empirical facts that the production network model can.]]></description><author>Ian Dew-Becker, Alireza Tahbaz-Salehi, Andrea Vedolin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29499</guid></item><item><title>Learning About the Long Run</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29495</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leland Farmer, Emi Nakamura, Jón Steinsson.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Forecasts of professional forecasters are anomalous: they are biased, forecast errors are autocorrelated, and forecast revisions predict forecast errors. Sticky or noisy information models seem like unlikely explanations for these anomalies: professional forecasters pay attention constantly and have precise knowledge of the data in question. We propose that these anomalies arise because professional forecasters don’t know the model that generates the data. We show that Bayesian agents learning about hard-to-learn features of the data generating process (low frequency behavior) can generate all the prominent aggregate anomalies emphasized in the literature. We show this for two applications: professional forecasts of nominal interest rates for the sample period 1980-2019 and CBO forecasts of GDP growth for the sample period 1976- 2019. Our learning model for interest rates also provides an explanation for deviations from the expectations hypothesis of the term structure that does not rely on time-variation in risk premia.]]></description><author>Leland Farmer, Emi Nakamura, Jón Steinsson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29495</guid></item><item><title>Central Bank Digital Currencies and The Emerging Markets: The Currency Substitution Challenge</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29489</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sebastian Edwards.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, I discuss the implications for emerging countries of the adoption of central bank digital currencies (CBDCs) in advanced jurisdictions, such as the United States, the United Kingdom, and the Euro Zone. The analysis identifies benefits as well as costs. Among the former, one of the most important is lower costs for migrants’ remittances. Some of the costs of global CBDCs are associated with currency substitution, sudden currency depreciations, and lower seigniorage. At the global level, a smooth rollout of CBDCs in center countries requires international coordination. In addition, emerging countries will benefit from the implementation of stronger macroprudential regulations]]></description><author>Sebastian Edwards</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29489</guid></item><item><title>FinTech as a Financial Liberator</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Greg Buchak, Jiayin Hu, Shang-Jin Wei.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> A binding interest rate cap on household savings is a common form of financial repression in developing economies and typically benefits banks. Using proprietary data from a leading Chinese FinTech company, we study Fintech's role in ending financial repression in China through the introduction of a money market fund with deposit-like features available through an already widely-adopted household payment platform.  Cities and banks whose depositor base is more exposed to FinTech see greater deposit outflows. Importantly, exposed banks respond to FinTech competition by offering competing products with market interest rates. FinTech thus facilitates a bottom-up interest rate liberalization.]]></description><author>Greg Buchak, Jiayin Hu, Shang-Jin Wei</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</guid></item><item><title>The Debt Capacity of a Government</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Bernard Dumas, Paul Ehling, Chunyu Yang.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In a deterministic overlapping-generations economy with production and physical capital, the price of debt can be positive without any budget surpluses being in the offing, because debt incorporates a rational bubble. Yet the dynamics of debt remain a function of the dynamics of the primary budget deficit. As a way to study their joint behavior, we endogenize a structural deficit in the form of an underfunded social-security scheme. We define debt capacity as the level of debt that can be just sustained without a change of policy all the way to an unstable steady state. When it starts below the capacity, the debt converges to a stable steady state, in which the bubble is sustained. Above capacity the bubble unravels and the deficit cannot be financed. In several realistic scenarios occurring in economies, we calculate the needed policy response, which is the true "fiscal cost" of exceeding debt capacity.]]></description><author>Bernard Dumas, Paul Ehling, Chunyu Yang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</guid></item><item><title>Bank Runs, Fragility, and Credit Easing</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29397</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Manuel Amador, Javier Bianchi.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We present a tractable dynamic macroeconomic model of self-fulfilling bank runs. A bank is vulnerable to a run when a loss of investors' confidence triggers deposit withdrawals and leads the bank to default on its obligations.  We analytically characterize how the vulnerability of an individual bank depends on macroeconomic aggregates and how the number of banks facing a run affects macroeconomic aggregates in turn. In general equilibrium, runs can be partial or complete, depending on aggregate leverage and the dynamics of asset prices. Our normative analysis shows that the effectiveness of credit easing and its welfare implications depend on whether a financial crisis is driven by fundamentals or by self-fulfilling runs.]]></description><author>Manuel Amador, Javier Bianchi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29397</guid></item><item><title>Firms' Inflation Expectations: New Evidence from France</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29376</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Frédérique Savignac, Erwan Gautier, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Olivier Coibion.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Using a new survey of firms’ inflation expectations in France, we provide novel evidence about the measurement and formation of inflation expectations on the part of firms. First, French firms report inflation expectations with a smaller, but still positive, bias than households and display less disagreement. Second, we characterize the extent and manner in which the wording of questions matters for the measurement of firms’ inflation expectations. Third, we document whether and how the position of the respondent within the firm affects the provided responses. Fourth, because our survey measures firms’ expectations about aggregate and firm-level wage growth along with their inflation expectations, we are able to show that expectations about wages are even more condensed than firms’ inflation expectations and almost completely uncorrelated with them, indicating that firms perceive little link between price and wage inflation. Finally, an experimental treatment indicates that an exogenous change in firms’ inflation expectations has no effect on their aggregate wage expectations.]]></description><author>Frédérique Savignac, Erwan Gautier, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Olivier Coibion</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29376</guid></item><item><title>Tax Policy Design with Low Interest Rates</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29352</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alan J. Auerbach, William Gale.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Interest rates on government debt have fallen in many countries over the last several decades, with markets indicating that rates may stay low well into the future.  It is by now well understood that sustained low interest rates can change the nature of long-run fiscal policy choices.  In this paper, we examine a related issue: the implications of sustained low interest rates for the structure of tax policy.  We show that low interest rates (a) reduce the differences between consumption and income taxes; (b) make wealth taxes less efficient relative to capital income taxes, at given rates of tax; (c) reduce the value of firm-level investment incentives, and (d) substantially raise the valuation of benefits of carbon abatement policies relative to their costs.]]></description><author>Alan J. Auerbach, William Gale</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29352</guid></item><item><title>Decrypting New Age International Capital Flows</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29337</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clemens Graf von Luckner, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper employs high frequency transactions data on the world’s oldest and most extensive centralized peer-to-peer Bitcoin market, which enables trade in the currencies of more than 135 countries.  We develop an algorithm that allows, with high probability, the detection of “crypto vehicle transactions” in which crypto currency is used to move capital across borders or facilitate domestic transactions. In contrast to previous work which has used “on-chain” data, our approach enables one to investigate parts of the vastly larger pool of “off-chain” transactions. We find that, as a conservative lower bound, over 7 percent of the 45 million trades on the exchange we explore represent crypto vehicle transactions in which Bitcoin is used to make payment in fiat currency.  Roughly 20 percent of these represent international capital flight/flows/remittances.  Although our work cannot be used to put a price on cryptocurrencies, it provides the first systematic quantitative evidence that the transactional use of cryptocurrencies constitutes a fundamental component of their value, at least under the current regulatory regime.]]></description><author>Clemens Graf von Luckner, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29337</guid></item><item><title>The Flight to Safety and International Risk Sharing</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29238</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rohan Kekre, Moritz Lenel.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study a business cycle model of the international monetary system featuring a time-varying demand for safe dollar bonds, greater risk-bearing capacity in the U.S. than the rest of the world, and nominal rigidities.  A flight to safety generates a dollar appreciation and decline in global output.  Dollar bonds thus command a negative risk premium and the U.S. holds a levered portfolio of capital financed in dollars.  We quantify the effects of safety shocks and heterogeneity in risk-bearing capacity for global macroeconomic volatility; U.S. external adjustment; and the international transmission of monetary and fiscal policies, including dollar swap lines.]]></description><author>Rohan Kekre, Moritz Lenel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29238</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Market Expectations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29232</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christiane Baumeister.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Asset prices are a valuable source of information about financial market participants' expectations about key macroeconomic variables. However, the presence of time-varying risk premia requires an adjustment of market prices to obtain the market's rational assessment of future price and policy developments. This paper reviews empirical approaches for recovering market-based expectations. It starts by laying out the two canonical modeling frameworks that form the backbone for estimating risk premia and highlights the proliferation of risk pricing factors that result in a wide range of different asset-price-based expectation measures. It then describes a key methodological innovation to evaluate the empirical plausibility of risk premium estimates and to identify the most accurate market-based expectation measure. The usefulness of this general approach is illustrated for price expectations in the global oil market. Then, the paper provides an overview of the body of empirical evidence for monetary policy and inflation expectations with a special emphasis on market-specific characteristics that complicate the quest for the best possible market-based expectation measure. Finally, it discusses a number of economic applications where market expectations play a key role for evaluating economic models, guiding policy analysis, and deriving shock measures.]]></description><author>Christiane Baumeister</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29232</guid></item><item><title>Market Freezes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29210</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Chao Gu, Guido Menzio, Randall Wright, Yu Zhu.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> During the financial crisis apparently centralized markets continued to function while trade in OTC markets froze. We use search-and-bargaining theory to ascertain conditions that allow trade to temporarily freeze in decentralized markets, focusing on the roles of liquidity and self-fulfilling prophecies. We show standard models can have recurrent, belief-driven hot and cold spells, but not freezes and thaws. A simple specification that has freezes assumes negative returns. A more realistic one incorporates information frictions (costly asset-quality verification). Another uses different frictions to get credit freezes. We also discuss policy implications, and go into detail on the nature of OTC markets.]]></description><author>Chao Gu, Guido Menzio, Randall Wright, Yu Zhu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29210</guid></item><item><title>Are Collateral-Constraint Models Ready for Macroprudential Policy Design?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29204</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pablo Ottonello, Diego J. Perez, Paolo Varraso.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study the design of macroprudential policies based on quantitative collateral-constraint models. We show that the desirability of macroprudential policies critically depends on the specific form of collateral used in debt contracts: While inefficiencies arise when current prices affect collateral---a frequent benchmark used to guide policies---they do not when only future prices affect collateral. Since the microfoundations and quantitative predictions of models with future-price collateral constraints do not appear less plausible than those using current prices, we conclude that additional empirical work is essential for the use of these models in macroprudential policy design.]]></description><author>Pablo Ottonello, Diego J. Perez, Paolo Varraso</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29204</guid></item><item><title>Central Bank Digital Currency in Historical Perspective: Another Crossroad in Monetary History</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29171</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael D. Bordo.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Digitalization of Money is a crossroad in monetary history. Advances in technology has led to the development of new forms of money: virtual (crypto) currencies like bitcoin; stable coins like libra/diem; and central bank digital currencies (CBDC) like the Bahamian sand dollar. These innovations in money and finance have resonance to earlier shifts in monetary history: 1) The shift in the eighteenth and nineteenth century from commodity money (gold and silver coins) to convertible fiduciary money and inconvertible fiat money; 2) the shift in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries from central bank notes to a central bank monopoly; 3) Then evolution since the seventeenth century of central banks and the tools of monetary policy. </p>
<p>This paper analyzes the arguments for a CBDC through the lens of monetary history. The bottom line is that the history of transformations in monetary systems suggests that technical change in money is inevitably driven by the financial incentives of a market economy. Government has always had a key role in the provision of outside money, which is a public good. Government has also regulated inside money provided by the private sector. This held for fiduciary money and will likely hold for digital money. CBDC could make monetary policy more efficient, and it could transform the international monetary and payments systems.]]></description><author>Michael D. Bordo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29171</guid></item><item><title>Mr. Keynes and the “Classics”; A Suggested Reinterpretation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29158</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gauti B. Eggertsson, Cosimo Petracchi.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> This paper revisits and proposes a resolution to an empirical and theoretical controversy between Keynes and the “classics” (or monetarists). The controversy dates to Keynes’s General Theory (1936)—most famously formalized in Hicks’s (1937) classic Econometrica article, in which the IS-LM model is first formally stated. We first replicate empirical tests formulated in the late 1960s and ’70s and show that more recent data have more statistical power and resolve the empirical debate in favor of the Keynesians, at least according to the criteria of the literature at that time. We then show, using a simple dynamic stochastic general equilibrium (DSGE) model, that the empirical tests suffer from the Lucas (1976) critique, as the conclusion fundamentally depends upon the assumed policy regime. Nevertheless, we argue, this new empirical result is useful: it provides evidence for the existence of a “Keynesian policy regime” according to which traditional monetary expansion loses its impact in the absence of a policy regime change, in the sense of Sargent (1982).]]></description><author>Gauti B. Eggertsson, Cosimo Petracchi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29158</guid></item><item><title>Financial crises: A survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29155</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Amir Sufi, Alan M. Taylor.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Financial crises have large deleterious effects on economic activity, and as such have been the focus of a large body of research. This study surveys the existing literature on financial crises, exploring how crises are measured, whether they are predictable, and why they are associated with economic contractions. Historical narrative techniques continue to form the backbone for measuring crises, but there have been exciting developments in using quantitative data as well. Crises are predictable with growth in credit and elevated asset prices playing an especially important role; recent research points convincingly to the importance of behavioral biases in explaining such predictability. The negative consequences of a crisis are due to both the crisis itself but also to the imbalances that precede a crisis. Crises do not occur randomly, and, as a result, an understanding of financial crises requires an investigation into the booms that precede them.]]></description><author>Amir Sufi, Alan M. Taylor</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29155</guid></item><item><title>Can Monetary Policy Create Fiscal Capacity?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29129</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Vadim Elenev, Tim Landvoigt, Patrick J. Shultz, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Governments around the world have gone on a massive fiscal expansion in response to the Covid crisis, increasing government debt to levels not seen in 75 years. How will this debt be repaid? What role do conventional and unconventional monetary policy play? We investigate debt sustainability in a New Keynesian model with an intermediary sector, realistic fiscal and monetary policy, endogenous convenience yields, and substantial risk premia. When conventional monetary policy is constrained by the ZLB during an economic crisis, increased government spending and lower tax revenue lead to a large rise in government debt and raise the risk of future tax increases. We find that quantitative easing (QE), forward guidance, and an expansion in government discretionary spending all contribute to lowering debt/GDP ratio and reducing this fiscal risk. A transitory QE policy deployed during a crisis stimulates aggregate demand.]]></description><author>Vadim Elenev, Tim Landvoigt, Patrick J. Shultz, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29129</guid></item></channel></rss>