<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Game Theory</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Game Theory</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 23:20:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Group Corruption via Sequential Bargaining in a Hierarchical Organization</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29759</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Fan-chin Kung, Ping Wang, Quan Wen.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We develop a framework of group corruption via back-door negotiations between an outside initiator and an authority of decision-makers in a hierarchical organization. We examine the role played by the architecture of a multi-tier authority and determine under such a structure how bargaining proceeds, in what order, and when it breaks down. We verify that equilibrium bargaining sequence proceeds as a chain through decision-making agents, regardless of the hierarchy of the organization. We prove the existence of a compromised equilibrium, where the decision of the authority is compromised, and establish sufficient conditions under which the most natural bottom-up bargaining configuration arises in equilibrium where a proposer negotiates with an immediately higher ranked respondent, starting with the initiator bargaining with the lowest ranked decision-maker in the organization. We then show the circumstances under which a top-down or a non-monotonic equilibrium configuration may emerge, and those under which the deal may break down. This enables us to capture a rich array of group corruptive configurations as observed. We conclude by investigating the extension to multi-tier authorities with multiple agents of the same rank in each tier, such as in a tree hierarchy.]]></description><author>Fan-chin Kung, Ping Wang, Quan Wen</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29759</guid></item><item><title>Inattention and Inequity in School Matching</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29586</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefan F. Bucher, Andrew Caplin.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The attractive properties of the Deferred Acceptance (DA) algorithm rest on the assumption of perfect information. Yet field studies of school matching show that information is imperfect, particularly for disadvantaged students. We model costly strategic learning when schools are ex ante symmetric, agree on their ranking of students, and learning is rationally inattentive. Our analytic solution quantifies how each student’s rank, learning costs and prior beliefs interact to determine their gross and net welfare as well as the extent and form of mistakes they make. In line with the evidence, we find that lower-ranked students are affected disproportionately more by information costs, generally suffering a larger welfare loss than higher-ranked students. Interactions between mechanism design, inattention and inequity are thus of first order importance.]]></description><author>Stefan F. Bucher, Andrew Caplin</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29586</guid></item><item><title>Market Design</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29367</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nikhil Agarwal, Eric Budish.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This Handbook chapter seeks to introduce students and researchers of industrial organization (IO) to the field of market design. We emphasize two important points of connection between the IO and market design fields: a focus on market failures—both understanding sources of market failure and analyzing how to fix them—and an appreciation of institutional detail.<br />
Section II reviews theory, focusing on introducing the theory of matching and assignment mechanisms to a broad audience. It introduces a novel “taxonomy” of market design problems, covers the key mechanisms and their properties, and emphasizes several points of connection to traditional economic theory involving prices and competitive equilibrium.<br />
Section III reviews structural empirical methods that build on this theory. We describe how to estimate a workhorse random utility model under various data environments, ranging from data on reported preference data such as rank-order lists to data only on observed matches. These methods enable a quantification of trade-offs in designing markets and the effects of new market designs.<br />
Section IV discusses a wide variety of applications. We organize this discussion into three broad aims of market design research: (i) diagnosing market failures; (ii) evaluating and comparing various market designs; (iii) proposing new, improved designs. A point of emphasis is that theoretical and empirical analysis have been highly complementary in this research.]]></description><author>Nikhil Agarwal, Eric Budish</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29367</guid></item><item><title>Task Allocation and On-the-job Training</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29312</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Mariagiovanna Baccara, SangMok Lee, Leeat Yariv.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study dynamic task allocation when providers' expertise evolves endogenously through training. We characterize optimal assignment protocols and compare them to discretionary procedures, where it is the clients who select their service providers. Our results indicate that welfare gains from centralization are greater when tasks arrive more rapidly, and when training technologies improve. Monitoring seniors' backlog of clients always increases welfare but may decrease training. Methodologically, we explore a matching setting with endogenous types, and illustrate useful adaptations of queueing theory techniques for such environments.]]></description><author>Mariagiovanna Baccara, SangMok Lee, Leeat Yariv</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29312</guid></item></channel></rss>