<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Macroeconomics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Macroeconomics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 22:34:51 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>E-commerce During Covid: Stylized Facts from 47 Economies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29729</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joel Alcedo, Alberto Cavallo, Bricklin Dwyer, Prachi Mishra, Antonio Spilimbergo.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We study e-commerce across 47 economies and 26 industries during the COVID-19 pandemic using aggregated and anonymized transaction-level data from Mastercard, scaled to represent total consumer spending. The share of online transactions in total consumption increased more in economies with higher pre-pandemic e-commerce shares, exacerbating the digital divide across economies. Overall, the latest data suggest that these spikes in online spending shares are dissipating at the aggregate level, though there is variation across industries. In particular, the share of online spending in professional services and recreation has fallen below its pre-pandemic trend, but we observe a longer-lasting shift to digital in retail and restaurants.]]></description><author>Joel Alcedo, Alberto Cavallo, Bricklin Dwyer, Prachi Mishra, Antonio Spilimbergo</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29729</guid></item><item><title>Lethal Unemployment Bonuses? Substitution and Income Effects on Substance Abuse, 2020-21</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29719</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Casey B. Mulligan.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Marginal prices fell, and disposable incomes increased, for drug and alcohol consumers during the pandemic.  Most of the amount, timing, and composition of the 240,000 deaths involving alcohol and drugs since early 2020 can be explained by income effects and category-specific price changes.  For alcohol, the pandemic shifted consumption from bars and restaurants to homes, where marginal money prices are lower.  For more dangerous illegal drugs like fentanyl and methamphetamine, the full price of consumption also significantly fell whenever employment became financially less attractive, as it was while unemployment bonuses were elevated.  Both the wage effect and income effects further reduced marginal opioid prices by inducing shifts toward cheap fentanyl.  Drug mortality dipped in the months between the $600 and $300 bonuses, especially for age groups participating most in UI.  A corollary to this analysis is that national employment rates will be slow to recover due to the increased prevalence of alcohol and, especially, drug addiction.]]></description><author>Casey B. Mulligan</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29719</guid></item><item><title>State-Level Economic Policy Uncertainty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29714</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Scott R. Baker, Steven J. Davis, Jeffrey A. Levy.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We quantify and study state-level economic policy uncertainty. Tapping digital archives for nearly 3,500 local newspapers, we construct three monthly indexes for each state: one that captures state and local sources of policy uncertainty (EPU-S), one that captures national and international sources (EPU-N), and a composite index that captures both. EPU-S rises around gubernatorial elections and own-state episodes like the California electricity crisis of 2000-01 and the Kansas tax experiment of 2012. EPU-N rises around presidential elections and in response to 9-11, Gulf Wars I and II, the 2011 debt-ceiling crisis, the 2012 fiscal cliff episode, and federal government shutdowns. Close elections elevate policy uncertainty much more than the average election. The COVID-19 pandemic drove huge increases in policy uncertainty and unemployment, more so in states with stricter government-mandated lockdowns. VAR models fit to pre-COVID data imply that upward shocks to own-state EPU foreshadow weaker economic activity in the state.]]></description><author>Scott R. Baker, Steven J. Davis, Jeffrey A. Levy</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29714</guid></item><item><title>Economic Winners Versus Losers and the Unequal Pandemic Recession</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29713</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Fernando Cirelli, Mark Gertler.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> As is well known, during the pandemic recession firms directly exposed to the virus, i.e. the “contact” sector, contracted sharply and recovered slowly relative to the rest of the economy. Less understood is how firms that “won” by offering safer substitutes for contact sector goods have affected this unequal downturn. Using both firm and industry data, we first construct disaggregated measures of revenue growth that distinguish between contact sector losers, contact sector winners, and the non-contact sector. We show that contact sector losers contracted roughly fifty percent more than the sector average, while winners grew. Further, forecast data suggests that the gap between winners and losers will persist at least through 2022. To explain this evidence, we then develop a simple three sector New Keynesian model with (i) a sector of firms that offers safe substitutes for risky contact sector goods and (ii) learning by doing. Overall, the model captures the unequal sectoral recession. It also accounts for inflation, including the sharp runup in 2021.]]></description><author>Fernando Cirelli, Mark Gertler</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29713</guid></item><item><title>Expectations Formation and Forward Information</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29711</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nathan Goldstein, Yuriy Gorodnichenko.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We propose a model where forecasters have access to noisy signals about the future (forward information). In this setting, information varies not only across agents but also across horizons. As a result, estimated persistence of forecasts deviates from persistence of fundamentals and the ability of forecasts at shorter horizons to explain forecasts at longer horizons is limited. These properties tend to diminish as the forecast horizon increases. We document that this novel pattern is consistent with survey data for professional forecasters. We provide further evidence that time-series and cross-sectional variation in professional forecasts is driven by forward information. We propose a simple method for extracting the forward information component from survey and provide several applications of forward information.]]></description><author>Nathan Goldstein, Yuriy Gorodnichenko</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29711</guid></item><item><title>Making Money</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29710</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gary B. Gorton, Chase P. Ross, Sharon Y. Ross.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> It is difficult for private agents to produce money that circulates at par with no questions asked. We study two cases of privately-produced money: pre-Civil War U.S. private banknotes and modern stablecoins. Private monies are introduced when there are no better alternatives, but they initially carry an inconvenience yield. Over time, these monies may become more money-like, but they do not always achieve a positive convenience yield. Technology advances and reputation formation pushed private banknotes toward a positive convenience yield. We show that the same forces are at work for stablecoins.]]></description><author>Gary B. Gorton, Chase P. Ross, Sharon Y. Ross</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29710</guid></item><item><title>A Goldilocks Theory of Fiscal Deficits</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29707</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Atif R. Mian, Ludwig Straub, Amir Sufi.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper proposes a tractable framework to analyze fiscal space and the dynamics of government debt, with a possibly binding zero lower bound (ZLB) constraint. Without the ZLB, a greater primary deficit unambiguously raises debt. However, debt need not explode: When R &lt; G – φ, where φ is the sensitivity of R – G to debt, a modest permanent increase in the deficit can be sustained forever, a policy we call “free lunch”. With the ZLB, the relationship between deficit and debt can become non-monotone. Both high and low deficits can increase debt, as the latter weaken demand and reduce nominal growth at the ZLB. A rise in income inequality expands fiscal space outside the ZLB, but contracts it at the ZLB. Calibrating the model, we find little space for “free lunch” policies for the United States in 2019, but ample space for Japan.]]></description><author>Atif R. Mian, Ludwig Straub, Amir Sufi</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29707</guid></item><item><title>Why Are Returns to Private Business Wealth So Dispersed?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29705</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Corina Boar, Denis Gorea, Virgiliu Midrigan.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We  use micro data from Orbis on firm level balance sheets and income statements to document that accounting returns for privately held businesses are dispersed, persistent, and negatively correlated with firm equity. We also show that firms experience large, fat-tailed, and partly transitory changes in output that are not fully accompanied by changes in their capital stock and wage bill. This implies that capital and labor choices are risky, as fluctuations in output are accompanied by large changes in firm profits. We interpret this evidence using a model of entrepreneurial dynamics in which return heterogeneity can arise from both limited span of control, as well as from financial frictions which generate differences in financial returns to saving. The model matches the evidence on accounting returns  and predicts that financial returns to saving are half as large and dispersed as accounting returns. Financial returns mostly reflect risk, as opposed to collateral constraints which play a negligible role due to  firms' unwillingness to expand and take on more risk.]]></description><author>Corina Boar, Denis Gorea, Virgiliu Midrigan</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29705</guid></item><item><title>Idiosyncratic Income Risk and Aggregate Fluctuations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29704</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Davide Debortoli, Jordi Galí.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We study the role of idiosyncratic income shocks for aggregate fluctuations within a simple heterogeneous household framework with no binding borrowing constraints. We show that the presence of idiosyncratic income shocks affects the economy’s response to an aggregate shock in a way that can be captured by a consumption weighted average of the changes in uncertainty generated by the shock. We apply this framework to two example economies —an endowment economy and a New Keynesian economy— and show that under plausible calibrations the impact of idiosyncratic income shocks on aggregate fluctuations is quantitatively small, since most of the changes in uncertainty are concentrated among poorer (low consumption) households.]]></description><author>Davide Debortoli, Jordi Galí</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29704</guid></item><item><title>Should We Have Automatic Triggers for Unemployment Benefit Duration And How Costly Would They Be?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29703</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gabriel Chodorow-Reich, Peter Ganong, Jonathan Gruber.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We model automatic trigger policies for unemployment insurance by simulating a weekly panel of individual labor market histories, grouped by state. We reach three conclusions: (i) policies designed to trigger immediately at the onset of a recession result in benefit extensions that occur in less sick labor markets than the historical average for benefit extensions; (ii) the ad hoc extensions in the 2001 and 2007-09 recessions in total cover a similar number of additional weeks as common proposals for automatic triggers, but concentrate coverage more in weaker labor markets; (iii) compared to ex post policy, the cost of common proposals for automatic triggers is close to zero.]]></description><author>Gabriel Chodorow-Reich, Peter Ganong, Jonathan Gruber</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29703</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Fluidity and Human Capital Accumulation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29698</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Niklas Engbom.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Using panel data from 23 OECD countries, I document that wages grow more over the life-cycle in countries where job-to-job mobility is more common. A life-cycle theory of job shopping and accumulation of skills on the job highlights that a more fluid labor market allows workers to faster relocate to jobs where they can better use their skills, incentivizing accumulation of skills. Lower labor market fluidity reduces life-cycle wage growth by 20 percent and aggregate labor productivity by nine percent across the OECD relative to the US. I derive a set of testable predictions for training and confront them with comparable cross-country training data, finding support for the theory.]]></description><author>Niklas Engbom</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29698</guid></item><item><title>Firm Pay Dynamics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29697</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Niklas Engbom, Christian Moser, Jan Sauermann.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We study the nature of firm pay dynamics. To this end, we propose a statistical model that extends the seminal framework by Abowd, Kramarz and Margolis (1999) to allow for idiosyncratically time-varying firm pay policies. We estimate the model using linked employer-employee data for Sweden from 1985 to 2016. By drawing on detailed firm financials data, we show that firms that become more productive and accumulate capital raise pay, whereas firms lower pay as they add workers. A secular increase in firm-year pay dispersion in Sweden since 1985 is accounted for by greater persistence of firm pay among incumbent firms as well as greater dispersion in firm pay among entrant firms, as opposed to more volatile firm pay.]]></description><author>Niklas Engbom, Christian Moser, Jan Sauermann</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29697</guid></item><item><title>Earnings Inequality and Dynamics in the Presence of Informality: The Case of Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29696</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Niklas Engbom, Gustavo Gonzaga, Christian Moser, Roberta Olivieri.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Using rich administrative and household survey data spanning 34 years from 1985 to 2018, we document a series of new facts on earnings inequality and dynamics in a developing country with a large informal sector: Brazil. Since the mid-1990s, both inequality and volatility of earnings have declined significantly in Brazil’s formal sector. Higher-order moments of the distribution of earnings changes show cyclical movements in Brazil that are similar to those in developed countries like the US. Relative to the formal sector, the informal sector is associated with a significant earnings penalty and higher earnings volatility for identical workers. Earnings changes of workers who switch from formal to informal (from informal to formal) employment are relatively negative (positive) and large in magnitude, dispersed, negatively (positively) skewed, and less leptokurtic. Our results suggest that informal employment is an imperfect insurance mechanism.]]></description><author>Niklas Engbom, Gustavo Gonzaga, Christian Moser, Roberta Olivieri</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29696</guid></item><item><title>Liquidity, Liquidity Everywhere, Not a Drop to Use - Why Flooding Banks with Central Bank Reserves May Not Expand Liquidity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29680</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Viral V. Acharya, Raghuram Rajan.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Central bank balance sheet expansion is financed by commercial banks. It involves not just a substitution of liquid central bank reserves for other assets held by commercial banks, but also a counterpart alteration in commercial bank liabilities, such as in short-term deposits issued to finance reserves and in off-balance-sheet encumbrances pledged against reserves, which are also claims on liquidity. In ordinary times, when these claims are not called on, central bank balance sheet expansion will typically enhance the net availability of liquidity to the system. However, in times of stress when these offsetting claims on liquidity are exercised, the demand for liquidity can be significantly more. Furthermore, liquid commercial banks, desiring to maintain unimpeachable balance sheets, may provide only limited re-intermediation of liquidity and contribute significantly to liquidity shortages. Commercial banks do not fully internalize prospective stress ex ante or take sufficient steps to avoid it. Consequently, central bank balance sheet expansion need not eliminate episodes of stress; it may even exacerbate them. This may also attenuate any positive effects of central bank balance sheet expansion on economic activity.]]></description><author>Viral V. Acharya, Raghuram Rajan</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29680</guid></item><item><title>Robots and Firm Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29676</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Efraim Benmelech, Michal Zator.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Automation technologies, and robots in particular, are thought to be massively displacing workers and transforming the future of work. We study firm investment in automation using cross-country data on robotization as well as administrative data from Germany with information on firm-level automation decisions. Our findings suggest that the impact of robots on firms has been limited. First, investment in robots is small and highly concentrated in a few industries, accounting for less than 0.30% of aggregate expenditures on equipment. Second, recent increases in robotization do not resemble the explosive growth observed for IT technologies in the past, and are driven mostly by catching-up of developing countries. Third, robot adoption by firms endogenously responds to labor scarcity, alleviating potential displacement of existing workers. Fourth, firms that invest in robots increase employment, while total employment effect in exposed industries and regions is negative, but modest in magnitude. We contrast robots with other digital technologies that are more widespread. Their importance in firms’ investment is significantly higher, and their link with labor markets, while sharing some similarities with robots, appears markedly different.]]></description><author>Efraim Benmelech, Michal Zator</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29676</guid></item><item><title>Slowing Women's Labor Force Participation: The Role of Income Inequality</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29675</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefania Albanesi, María José Prados.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The entry of married women into the labor force and the rise in women's relative wages are amongst the most notable economic developments of the twentieth century. The growth in these indicators was particularly pronounced in the 1970s and 1980s, but it stalled since the early 1990s, especially for college graduates. In this paper, we argue that the discontinued growth in female labor supply and wages since the 1990s is a consequence of growing inequality. Our hypothesis is that the growth in top incomes for men generated a negative income effect on the labor supply of their spouses, which reduced their participation and wages. We show that the slowdown in participation and wage growth was concentrated among women married to highly educated and high income husbands, whose earnings grew dramatically over this period. We then develop a model of household labor supply with returns to experience that qualitatively reproduces this effect. A calibrated version of the model can account for a large fraction of the decline relative to trend in married women's participation in 1995-2005 particularly for college women. The model can also account for the rise in the gender wage gap for college graduates relative to trend in the same period.]]></description><author>Stefania Albanesi, María José Prados</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29675</guid></item><item><title>Average Inflation Targeting: Time Inconsistency and Intentional Ambiguity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29673</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Chengcheng Jia, Jing Cynthia Wu.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We study the implications of the Fed’s new policy framework of average inflation targeting (AIT) and its ambiguous communication. The central bank has the incentive to deviate from its announced AIT and implement inflation targeting ex post to maximize social welfare. We show two motives for ambiguous communication about the horizon over which the central bank averages inflation as a result of time inconsistency. First, it is optimal for the central bank to announce different horizons depending on the state of the economy. Second, ambiguous communication helps the central bank gain credibility.]]></description><author>Chengcheng Jia, Jing Cynthia Wu</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29673</guid></item><item><title>Spillovers at the Extremes: The Macroprudential Stance and Vulnerability to the Global Financial Cycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29670</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anusha Chari, Karlye Dilts Stedman, Kristin Forbes.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The effects of macroprudential policy on portfolio flows vary considerably across the global financial cycle. A tighter ex-ante macroprudential stance amplifies the impact of global risk shocks on bond and equity flows, increasing outflows significantly more during risk-off episodes and increasing inflows significantly more during risk-on episodes. These amplification effects are more prominent at the “extremes,” especially for extreme risk-off periods and for regulations that target specific risks instead of generalized cyclical buffers. This paper estimates these relationships using a policy-shocks approach that corrects for reverse causality by combining high-frequency risk measures with weekly data on portfolio investment and a new measure of macroprudential regulations that captures the intensity of policy stances. Overall, the results support a growing body of evidence that macroprudential regulation can reduce the volume and volatility of bank flows but shift risks in ways that aggravate vulnerabilities in other parts of the financial system.]]></description><author>Anusha Chari, Karlye Dilts Stedman, Kristin Forbes</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29670</guid></item><item><title>The $800 Billion Paycheck Protection Program: Where Did the Money Go and Why Did it Go There?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29669</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Autor, David Cho, Leland D. Crane, Mita Goldar, Byron Lutz, Joshua K. Montes, William B. Peterman, David D. Ratner, Daniel Villar Vallenas, Ahu Yildirmaz.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The Paycheck Protection Program (PPP) provided small businesses with roughly $800 billion dollars in uncollateralized, low-interest loans during the pandemic, almost all of which will be forgiven. With 93 percent of small businesses ultimately receiving one or more loans, the PPP nearly saturated its market in just two months. We estimate that the program cumulatively preserved between 2 and 3 million job-years of employment over 14 months at a cost of $170K to $257K per job-year retained. These estimates imply that only 23 to 34 percent of PPP dollars went directly to workers who would otherwise have lost jobs; the balance flowed to business owners and shareholders, including creditors and suppliers of PPP-receiving firms. Program incidence was highly regressive, with about three-quarters of PPP funds accruing to the top quintile of households. This compares unfavorably to the other two major pandemic aid programs, enhanced UI benefits and Economic Impact Payments (i.e. stimulus checks). PPP’s breakneck scale-up, its high cost per job saved, and its regressive incidence have a common origin: PPP was essentially untargeted because the United States lacked the administrative infrastructure to do otherwise. The more targeted pandemic business aid programs deployed by other high-income countries exemplify what is feasible with better administrative systems. Building similar capacity in the U.S. would enable greatly improved targeting of either employment subsidies or business liquidity when the next pandemic or other large-scale economic emergency occurs, as it surely will.]]></description><author>David Autor, David Cho, Leland D. Crane, Mita Goldar, Byron Lutz, Joshua K. Montes, William B. Peterman, David D. Ratner, Daniel Villar Vallenas, Ahu Yildirmaz</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29669</guid></item><item><title>Political Constraints and Sovereign Default</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29667</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marina Azzimonti, Nirvana Mitra.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We study how political constraints, characterized by the degree of flexibility to choose fiscal policy, affect the probability of sovereign default. To that end, we relax the assumption that policymakers always repay their debt in the dynamic model of fiscal policy developed by Battaglini and Coate (2008). In our setup, legislators bargain over taxes, general spending, debt repayment, and a local public good that can be targeted to the region they represent. Under tighter political constraints, more legislators have veto power, implying that local public goods need to be provided to a larger number of regions. The resources that are freed after a default have to be shared with a higher number of individuals, which reduces the benefits from defaulting in per-capita terms. This lowers the incentive to default compared to the case with lax political constraints. The model is calibrated to Argentina and the results conform to robust empirical evidence. An event study for the 2001/2002 sovereign debt crisis shows that political constraints had an important role in the buildup that led to the crisis.]]></description><author>Marina Azzimonti, Nirvana Mitra</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29667</guid></item><item><title>Land Security and Mobility Frictions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29666</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tasso Adamopoulos, Loren Brandt, Chaoran Chen, Diego Restuccia, Xiaoyun Wei.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Developing countries are characterized by frictions that impede the mobility of workers across occupations and space. We disentangle the role of insecure property rights from other labor mobility frictions for the reallocation of labor from agriculture to non-agriculture and from rural to urban areas. We combine rich household and individual-level panel data from China and an equilibrium quantitative framework that features the sorting of workers across locations and occupations. We explicitly model the farming household and the endogenous decisions of who operates the family farm and who potentially migrates, capturing an additional channel of selection within the household. We find that land insecurity has substantial negative effects on agricultural productivity and structural change, raising the share of households operating farms by almost 30 percentage points and depressing agricultural productivity by more than 10 percent. Quantitatively, land insecurity is as important as all other labor mobility frictions. We measure a sharp reduction in overall labor mobility barriers over 2004-2018 in the Chinese economy, all of which can be accounted for by improved land security, consistent with reforms covering rural land in China during the period.]]></description><author>Tasso Adamopoulos, Loren Brandt, Chaoran Chen, Diego Restuccia, Xiaoyun Wei</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29666</guid></item><item><title>A Simple Mapping from MPCs to MPXs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29664</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Laibson, Peter Maxted, Benjamin Moll.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Standard consumption models assume a notional consumption flow that does not distinguish between nondurable and durable consumption. Such notional-consumption models generate notional marginal propensities to consume (MPC). By contrast, empirical work and policy discussions often highlight marginal propensities for expenditure (MPX), which incorporate spending on a durable stock. We compare the notional-consumption model to an isomorphic model with a durable stock, and map notional MPCs into MPXs. The mapping is especially simple for a one-period horizon: MPX =  (1 - s + s/(r+d)) x MPC, with durable share s, real interest rate r, and durable depreciation rate d.]]></description><author>David Laibson, Peter Maxted, Benjamin Moll</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29664</guid></item><item><title>Minimum Wages, Efficiency and Welfare</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29662</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David W. Berger, Kyle F. Herkenhoff, Simon Mongey.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> It has long been argued that a minimum wage could alleviate efficiency losses from monopsony power. In a general equilibrium framework that quantitatively replicates results from recent empirical studies, we find higher minimum wages can improve welfare, but most welfare gains stem from redistribution rather than efficiency. Our model features oligopsonistic labor markets with heterogeneous workers and firms and yields analytical expressions that characterize the mechanisms by which minimum wages can improve efficiency, and how these deteriorate at higher minimum wages. We provide a method to separate welfare gains into two channels: efficiency and redistribution. Under both channels and Utilitarian social welfare weights the optimal minimum wage is $15, but alternative weights can rationalize anything from $0 to $31. Under only the efficiency channel, the optimal minimum wage is narrowly around $8, robust to social welfare weights, and generates small welfare gains that recover only 2 percent of the efficiency losses from monopsony power.]]></description><author>David W. Berger, Kyle F. Herkenhoff, Simon Mongey</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29662</guid></item><item><title>Inequalities in the Times of a Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29657</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefanie Stantcheva.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper summarizes the research on some of the major inequalities that have been exacerbated by the COVID-19 pandemic across OECD countries. It reviews findings related to inequalities across the income distribution, sectors and regions, gender, and inequalities in education inputs for children from different socioeconomic backgrounds.]]></description><author>Stefanie Stantcheva</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29657</guid></item><item><title>Inclusive Monetary Policy: How Tight Labor Markets Facilitate Broad-Based Employment Growth</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29651</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nittai Bergman, David A. Matsa, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper analyzes the heterogeneous effects of monetary policy on workers with differing levels of labor force attachment. Exploiting variation in labor market tightness across metropolitan areas, we show that the employment of populations with lower labor force attachment—Blacks, high school dropouts, and women—is more responsive to expansionary monetary policy in tighter labor markets. The effect builds up over time and is long lasting. We develop a New Keynesian model with heterogeneous workers that rationalizes these results. The model shows that expansionary monetary shocks lead to larger increases in the employment of less attached workers when the central bank follows an average inflation targeting rule and when the Phillips curve is flatter. These findings suggest that, by tightening labor markets, the Federal Reserve's recent move from a strict to an average inflation targeting framework especially benefits workers with lower labor force attachment.]]></description><author>Nittai Bergman, David A. Matsa, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29651</guid></item><item><title>Household Spending Responses to the Economic Impact Payments of 2020: Evidence from the Consumer Expenditure Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29648</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan A. Parker, Jake Schild, Laura Erhard, David Johnson.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Using the Consumer Expenditure Survey and variation in amount, receipt, and timing of receipt of Economic Impact Payments (EIPs) authorized by the CARES Act, this paper estimates that people spent less of their EIPs in the few months following arrival than in similar previous policy episodes and than estimated by existing studies using other types of data. Accounting for volatility during the pandemic and comparing the consumer spending behavior of broadly similar households, people spent roughly 10 percent (standard error 3.4) of their EIPs on non-durable goods and services in the three months of arrival, with little evidence of additional spending in the subsequent three months or on  durable goods. People who report mostly spending their EIPs spent 14.3\% (3.7) of their EIPs compared to 5.9\% (8.3) and -1.6\% (5.0) for those who report mostly paying off debt and saving respectively. People with low liquid wealth and people receiving their EIPs on debit cards spent at higher rates: 21.7\% (6.4) and 36.8\% (24.6) respectively, with economically larger estimates for total spending.]]></description><author>Jonathan A. Parker, Jake Schild, Laura Erhard, David Johnson</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29648</guid></item><item><title>The Expected, Perceived, and Realized Inflation of U.S. Households before and during the COVID19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29640</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Weber, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Olivier Coibion.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> As the pandemic spread across the U.S., disagreement among U.S. households about inflation expectations surged along with the mean perceived and expected level of inflation. Simultaneously, the inflation experienced by households became more dispersed. Using matched micro data on spending of households and their macroeconomic expectations, we study the link between the inflation experienced by households in their daily shopping and their perceived and expected levels of inflation both before and during the pandemic. In normal times, realized inflation barely differs across observable dimensions but low income, low education, and Black households experienced a larger increase in realized inflation than other households did. Dispersion in realized and perceived inflation explains a large share of the rise in dispersion in inflation expectations.]]></description><author>Michael Weber, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Olivier Coibion</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29640</guid></item><item><title>Financial Intermediaries and the Macroeconomy: Evidence from a High-Frequency Identification</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29638</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pablo Ottonello, Wenting Song.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We provide empirical evidence of the causal effects of changes in financial intermediaries' net worth in the aggregate economy. Our strategy identifies financial shocks as high-frequency changes in the market value of intermediaries' net worth in a narrow window around their earnings announcements, based on U.S. tick-by-tick data. Using these shocks, we estimate that news of a 1-percent decline in intermediaries' net worth leads to a 0.2-0.4 percent decrease in the market value of nonfinancial firms.  These effects are more pronounced for firms with high default risk and low liquidity and when the aggregate net worth of intermediaries is low.]]></description><author>Pablo Ottonello, Wenting Song</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29638</guid></item><item><title>Cognitive Decline, Limited Awareness, Imperfect Agency, and Financial Well-being</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29634</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John Ameriks, Andrew Caplin, Minjoon Lee, Matthew D. Shapiro, Christopher Tonetti.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Cognitive decline may lead older Americans to make poor financial decisions. Preventing poor decisions may require timely transfer of financial control to a reliable agent. Cognitive decline, however, can develop unnoticed, creating the possibility of suboptimal timing of the transfer of control. This paper presents survey-based evidence that wealthholders regard suboptimal timing of the transfer of control, in particular delay due to unnoticed cognitive decline, as a substantial risk to financial well-being. This paper provides a theoretical framework to model such a lack of awareness and the resulting welfare loss.]]></description><author>John Ameriks, Andrew Caplin, Minjoon Lee, Matthew D. Shapiro, Christopher Tonetti</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29634</guid></item><item><title>Intermediation via Credit Chains</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29632</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhiguo He, Jian Li.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The modern financial system features complicated financial intermediation chains, with each layer performing a certain degree of credit/maturity transformation. We develop a dynamic model in which an entrepreneur borrows from overlapping-generation households via layers of funds, forming a credit chain. Each intermediary fund in the chain faces rollover risks from its lenders, and the optimal debt contracts among layers are time invariant and layer independent. The model delivers new insights regarding the benefits of intermediation via layers: the chain structure insulates interim negative fundamental shocks and protects the underlying cash flows from being discounted heavily during bad times, resulting in a greater borrowing capacity. We show that the equilibrium chain length minimizes the run risk for any given contract and find that restricting credit chain length can improve total welfare once the available funding from households has been endogenized.]]></description><author>Zhiguo He, Jian Li</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29632</guid></item><item><title>Nonprofits in Good Times and Bad Times</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29630</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christine L. Exley, Nils H. Lehr, Stephen J. Terry.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Need fluctuates over the business cycle. We conduct a survey revealing a desire for nonprofit activities to countercyclically expand during downturns. We then demonstrate, using comprehensive US nonprofit data drawn from millions of tax returns, that the public’s hopes are disappointed. Nonprofit expenditure, revenue, and balance sheets fluctuate procyclically: contracting during national and local downturns. This finding is evident even for a narrow group of nonprofits the public most wishes would expand during downturns, e.g., those providing critical needs like food or housing. Our new facts contribute to the charitable giving, nonprofit, and business cycle literatures.]]></description><author>Christine L. Exley, Nils H. Lehr, Stephen J. Terry</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29630</guid></item><item><title>Macroeconomic Research, Present and Past</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29628</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Philip J. Glandon, Kenneth Kuttner, Sandeep Mazumder, Caleb Stroup.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> How is macroeconomic research conducted and what is it trying to accomplish? We explore these questions using information gleaned from 1,894 articles published in ten leading journals. We find that over the past 40 years there has been a growing emphasis on increasingly sophisticated quantitative theory, such as DSGE modeling, and papers employing these methods now account for the majority of articles in macro journals. The shift towards quantitative theory is mirrored by a decline in the use of econometric methods to test economic hypotheses.  Econometric techniques borrowed from applied microeconomics have to a large extent displaced time series methods, and empirical papers increasingly rely on micro and proprietary data sources. Market imperfections are pervasive, and the amount of research involving financial frictions has increased significantly in the past ten years. The frequency with which non-macro JEL codes appear in macro articles indicates a great deal of overlap between macroeconomics and other fields.]]></description><author>Philip J. Glandon, Kenneth Kuttner, Sandeep Mazumder, Caleb Stroup</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29628</guid></item><item><title>Debt as Safe Asset</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29626</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Markus K. Brunnermeier, Sebastian A. Merkel, Yuliy Sannikov.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The price of a safe asset reflects not only the expected discounted future cash flows but also future service flows, since retrading allows partial insurance of idiosyncratic risk in an incomplete markets setting. This lowers the issuers' interest burden and allows the government to run a permanent (primary) deficit without ever paying back its debt. As idiosyncratic risk rises during recessions, so does the value of the service flows bestowing the safe asset with a negative beta. This resolves government debt valuation puzzles. Nevertheless, the government faces a “Debt Laffer Curve”. The paper also has important implications for fiscal debt sustainability.]]></description><author>Markus K. Brunnermeier, Sebastian A. Merkel, Yuliy Sannikov</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29626</guid></item><item><title>Worker Beliefs About Outside Options</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29623</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Simon Jäger, Christopher Roth, Nina Roussille, Benjamin Schoefer.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Workers wrongly anchor their beliefs about outside options on their current wage. In particular, low-paid workers underestimate wages elsewhere. We document this anchoring bias by eliciting workers’ beliefs in a representative survey in Germany and comparing them to measures of actual outside options in linked administrative labor market data. In an equilibrium model, such anchoring can give rise to monopsony and labor market segmentation. In line with the model, misperceptions are particularly pronounced among workers in low-wage firms. If workers had correct beliefs, at least 10% of jobs, concentrated in low-wage firms, would not be viable at current wages.]]></description><author>Simon Jäger, Christopher Roth, Nina Roussille, Benjamin Schoefer</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29623</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Policy in a Networked Economy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29619</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joel P. Flynn, Christina Patterson, John Sturm.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Advanced economies feature complicated networks that connect households, ﬁrms, and regions. How do these structures aﬀect the impact of ﬁscal policy and its optimal targeting? We study these questions in a model with input-output linkages, regional structure, and household heterogeneity in MPCs, consumption baskets, and shock exposures. Theoretically, we derive estimable formulae for the eﬀects of ﬁscal policies on aggregate GDP, or ﬁscal multipliers, and show how network structures determine their size. Empirically, we ﬁnd that multipliers vary substantially across policies, so targeting is important. Beneath these aggregate eﬀects are large spatial and sectoral spillovers from policies directed to any one ﬁrm or household. However, virtually all variation in multipliers stems from diﬀerences in policies’ direct incidence onto households’ MPCs. Thus, while the distributional eﬀects of ﬁscal policy depend on the detailed structure of the economy, maximally expansionary ﬁscal policy simply targets households’ MPCs.]]></description><author>Joel P. Flynn, Christina Patterson, John Sturm</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29619</guid></item><item><title>The Price of Nails since 1695: A Window into Economic Change</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29617</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel E. Sichel.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper focuses on the price of nails since 1695 and the proximate source of changes in those prices. Why nails? They are a basic manufactured product whose form and quality have changed relatively little over the last three centuries, yet the process for producing them has changed dramatically. Accordingly, nails provide a useful prism through which to examine a wide range of economic and technological developments that touch on multiple areas of both micro- and macroeconomics. Several conclusions emerge. First, from the late 1700s to the mid 20th century real nail prices fell by a factor of about 10 relative to overall consumer prices. These declines had important effects on downstream industries, most notably construction. Second, while declining materials prices contribute to reductions in nail prices, the largest proximate source of the decline during this period was multifactor productivity growth in nail manufacturing, highlighting the role of the specialization of labor and re-organization of production processes. Third, the share of nails in GDP dropped back from 0.4 percent of GDP in 1810—comparable to today’s share of household purchases of personal computers—to a de minimis share more recently; accordingly, nails played a bigger role in American life in that earlier period. Finally, real nail prices have increased since the mid 20th century, reflecting in part an upturn in materials prices and a shift toward specialty nails in the wake of import competition, though the introduction of nail guns partly offset these increases for the price of installed nails.]]></description><author>Daniel E. Sichel</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29617</guid></item><item><title>Interest Received by Banks during the Financial Crisis: LIBOR vs Hypothetical SOFR Loans</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29614</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Urban Jermann.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The credit sensitivity of LIBOR helped lenders during the financial crisis. SOFR is not credit-sensitive and would not have provided that support. The cumulative additional interest from LIBOR during the crisis is estimated to be between 1% to 2% of the notional amount of outstanding loans, depending on the tenor and type of SOFR rate used. The amount of LIBOR business loans owned by banks could have been as high as about 2trn, and the overall additional interest income banks received thanks to LIBOR could have been as high as 30bn dollars. The analysis also shows that a compounded SOFR reduces insurance relative to a term SOFR.]]></description><author>Urban Jermann</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29614</guid></item><item><title>Measuring U.S. Core Inflation: The Stress Test of COVID-19</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29609</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Laurence M. Ball, Daniel Leigh, Prachi Mishra, Antonio Spilimbergo.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Large price changes in industries affected by the COVID-19 pandemic have caused erratic fluctuations in the U.S. headline inflation rate. This paper compares alternative approaches to filtering out the transitory effects of these industry price changes and measuring the underlying or core level of inflation over 2020-2021. The Federal Reserve’s preferred measure of core, the inflation rate excluding food and energy prices, has performed poorly: over most of 2020-21, it is almost as volatile as headline inflation. Measures of core that exclude a fixed set of additional industries, such as the Atlanta Fed’s sticky-price inflation rate, have been less volatile, but the least volatile have been measures that filter out large price changes in any industry, such as the Cleveland Fed’s median inflation rate and the Dallas Fed’s trimmed mean inflation rate. These core measures have followed smooth paths, drifting down when the economy was weak in 2020 and then rising as the economy has rebounded.]]></description><author>Laurence M. Ball, Daniel Leigh, Prachi Mishra, Antonio Spilimbergo</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29609</guid></item><item><title>Zombie Lending and Policy Traps</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29606</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Viral V. Acharya, Simone Lenzu, Olivier Wang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We build a model with heterogeneous firms and banks to analyze how policy affects credit allocation and long-term economic outcomes. When firms are hit by small negative shocks, conventional monetary policy can restore efficient bank lending and production by lowering interest rates. Large shocks, however, necessitate unconventional policy such as regulatory forbearance towards banks to stabilize the economy. Aggressive accommodation runs the risk of introducing zombie lending and a “diabolical sorting”, whereby low-capitalization banks extend new credit or evergreen existing loans to low-productivity firms. If shocks reduce the profitability gap between healthy and zombie firms, the optimal forbearance policy is non-monotone in the size of the shock. In a dynamic setting, policy aimed at avoiding short-term recessions can be trapped into protracted low rates and excessive forbearance, due to congestion externalities imposed by zombie lending on healthier firms. The resulting economic sclerosis delays the recovery from transitory shocks, and can even lead to permanent output losses.]]></description><author>Viral V. Acharya, Simone Lenzu, Olivier Wang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29606</guid></item><item><title>Monetary Policy and Endogenous Financial Crises</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29602</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Frederic Boissay, Fabrice Collard, Jordi Galí, Cristina Manea.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study whether a central bank should deviate from its objective of price stability to promote financial stability. We tackle this question within a textbook New Keynesian model augmented with capital accumulation and microfounded endogenous financial crises. We compare several interest rate rules, under which the central bank responds more or less forcefully to inflation and aggregate output. Our main findings are threefold. First, monetary policy affects the probability of a crisis both in the short run (through aggregate demand) and in the medium run (through savings and capital accumulation). Second, a central bank can both reduce the probability of a crisis and increase welfare by departing from strict inflation targeting and responding systematically to fluctuations in output. Third, financial crises may occur after a long period of unexpectedly loose monetary policy as the central bank abruptly reverses course.]]></description><author>Frederic Boissay, Fabrice Collard, Jordi Galí, Cristina Manea</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29602</guid></item><item><title>International Evidence of Strengthening Taxes and Spending For Sustainable Development</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29594</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Donghyun Park.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We trace the linkages between the episodes of fiscal expansion and consolidation in 72 advanced and emerging and developing economies. The findings suggest that fiscal expansions are positively associated with economic growth, which in turn is positively linked with better sustainable development outcomes. The association between fiscal consolidation and growth as well as the sustainable development indicators, however, is not clear-cut. Jointly, more tax revenues and expenditures, together with better governance help explain the association between economic growth and inclusive development. High-income, high-tax-revenue, and manufacture-exporting economies have made significant progress on reducing disease-linked mortality and improving environment protection along with economic growth. Meanwhile, emerging and developing, low-tax-revenue, and commodity-exporting economies have gained notable improvement in poverty reduction, pre-primary enrolment and access to basic sanitation services and clean cooking fuels and technologies, and lowering bribery incidence. On average, the sampled economies have persistently achieved better primary goals such as sanitation, clean fuels and technologies. Achievements in mortality reduction, and environmental protection goals are shown more recently.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Donghyun Park</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29594</guid></item><item><title>The Rise, Fall and Stabilization of U.S. Inflation: Shifting Regimes and Evolving Reputation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29585</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Robert G. King, Yang K. Lu.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The rise, fall, and stabilization of US inflation between 1969 and 2005 is consistent with a model of shifting policy regimes that features a forward-looking New Keynesian Phillips curve, policymakers that can or cannot commit, and private sector learning about policymaker type. Using model-implied inflation forecasting rules to extract state variables from the inflation forecasts in the Survey of Professional Forecasters, we provide evidence that policy regimes without commitment prevailed before 1980 and regimes with commitment prevailed afterward. With theory and quantification, we find that evolution of reputational capital is central to understanding the behavior of inflation.]]></description><author>Robert G. King, Yang K. Lu</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29585</guid></item><item><title>Identifying Monetary Policy Shocks Using the Central Bank's Information Set</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29572</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruediger Bachmann, Isabel Gödl-Hanisch, Eric R. Sims.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We identify monetary policy shocks by exploiting variation in the central bank’s information set. To be specific, we use differences between nowcasts of the output gap and inflation with final, revised estimates of these series to isolate movements in the policy rate unrelated to economic conditions. We then compute the effects of a monetary policy shock on the aggregate economy using local projection methods. We find that a contractionary monetary policy shock has a limited negative effect on output but a persistent negative impact on prices. In contrast to alternative identification approaches, we do not observe a price puzzle when analyzing the period from 1987 to 2008. Further, we validate the identification approach in a simple New Keynesian model, augmented by the assumption that the central bank observes the ingredients of the Taylor rule with error.]]></description><author>Ruediger Bachmann, Isabel Gödl-Hanisch, Eric R. Sims</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29572</guid></item><item><title>Changing Income Risk across the US Skill Distribution: Evidence from a Generalized Kalman Filter</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29567</link><description><![CDATA[<i>J. Carter Braxton, Kyle F. Herkenhoff, Jonathan L. Rothbaum, Lawrence Schmidt.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> For whom has earnings risk changed, and why? To answer these questions, we develop a filtering method that estimates parameters of an income process and recovers persistent and temporary earnings for every individual at every point in time. Our estimation flexibly allows for first and second moments of shocks to depend upon observables as well as spells of zero earnings (i.e., unemployment) and easily integrates into theoretical models. We apply our filter to a unique linkage of 23.5m SSA-CPS records. We first demonstrate that our earnings-based filter successfully captures observable shocks in the SSA-CPS data, such as job switching and layoffs. We then show that despite a decline in overall earnings risk since the 1980s, persistent earnings risk has risen for both employed and unemployed workers, while temporary earnings risk declined. Furthermore, the size of persistent earnings losses associated with full year unemployment has increased by 50%. Using geography, education, and occupation information in the SSA-CPS records, we refute hypotheses related to declining employment prospects among routine and low-skill workers as well as spatial theories related to the decline of the Rust-Belt. We show that rising persistent earnings risk is concentrated among high-skill workers and related to technology adoption. Lastly, we find that rising persistent earnings risk while employed (unemployed) leads to welfare losses equivalent to 1.8% (0.7%) of lifetime consumption, and larger persistent earnings losses while unemployed lead to a 3.3% welfare loss.]]></description><author>J. Carter Braxton, Kyle F. Herkenhoff, Jonathan L. Rothbaum, Lawrence Schmidt</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29567</guid></item><item><title>Customers and Retail Growth</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29561</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Liran Einav, Peter J. Klenow, Jonathan D. Levin, Raviv Murciano-Goroff.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Using Visa debit and credit card transactions in the U.S. from 2016 to 2019, we document the importance of customers in accounting for sales variation across merchants, across stores within retail chains, and over time for individual merchants and stores.  Customers, as opposed to transactions per customer or dollar sales per transaction, consistently account for about 80% of sales variation. The top 1% of growing and shrinking merchants account for about 70% of customer and sales reallocation in a given year. In order to illustrate some of the potential implications, we write down an endogenous growth model with and without the customer margin. In the context of this model, we find that the customer margin dramatically increases the size and growth contribution of the largest firms, but lowers the aggregate growth rate by diverting resources from research to customer acquisition activities.]]></description><author>Liran Einav, Peter J. Klenow, Jonathan D. Levin, Raviv Murciano-Goroff</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29561</guid></item><item><title>Simple Allocation Rules and Optimal Portfolio Choice Over the Lifecycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29559</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Victor Duarte, Julia Fonseca, Aaron S. Goodman, Jonathan A. Parker.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We develop a machine-learning solution algorithm to solve for optimal portfolio choice in a detailed and quantitatively-accurate lifecycle model that includes many features of reality modelled only separately in previous work.  We use the quantitative model to evaluate the consumption-equivalent welfare losses from using simple rules for portfolio allocation across stocks, bonds, and liquid accounts instead of the optimal portfolio choices. We find that the consumption-equivalent losses from using an age-dependent rule as embedded in current target-date/lifecycle funds (TDFs) are substantial, around 2 to 3 percent of consumption, despite the fact that TDF rules mimic average optimal behavior by age closely until shortly before retirement. Our model recommends higher average equity shares in the second half of life than the portfolio of the typical TDF, so that the typical TDF portfolio does not improve on investing an age-independent 2/3 share in equity. Finally, optimal equity shares have substantial heterogeneity, particularly by wealth level, state of the business cycle, and dividend-price ratio, implying substantial gains to further customization of advice or TDFs in these dimensions.]]></description><author>Victor Duarte, Julia Fonseca, Aaron S. Goodman, Jonathan A. Parker</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29559</guid></item><item><title>The Missing Intercept: A Demand Equivalence Approach</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29558</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christian K. Wolf.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> I give conditions under which changes in private spending are accommodated in general equilibrium exactly like changes in aggregate fiscal expenditure. Under such demand equivalence, researchers can use time series evidence on fiscal multipliers to recover the general equilibrium "missing intercept" of shocks to private spending identified in the cross section. I apply this method to deficit-financed stimulus checks, and find a) a large direct consumption spending response, and  b) a fiscal multiplier of one and so a missing intercept close to zero. I also discuss the robustness of this aggregation approach to empirically plausible violations of demand equivalence.]]></description><author>Christian K. Wolf</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29558</guid></item><item><title>Productivity and Pay in the US and Canada</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29548</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jacob Greenspon, Anna M. Stansbury, Lawrence H. Summers.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study the productivity-pay relationship in the United States and Canada along two dimensions. The first is divergence: the degree to which the levels of productivity and pay have diverged. The second is delinkage: the degree to which incremental increases in the rate of productivity growth translate into incremental increases in the rate of growth of pay, holding all else equal. We show that in both countries the pay of typical workers has diverged substantially from average labor productivity over recent decades, driven by both rising labor income inequality and a declining labor share of income. Even as the levels of productivity and pay have grown further apart, we find evidence for some linkage between productivity and pay in both countries: a one percentage point increase in the rate of productivity growth is associated with a positive increase in the rate of pay growth, holding all else equal. This linkage appears stronger in the US than in Canada. Overall, our findings lead us to tentatively conclude that policies or trends which lead to incremental increases in productivity growth, particularly in large relatively closed economies like the USA, will tend to raise middle class incomes. At the same time, other factors orthogonal to productivity growth have been driving productivity and typical pay further apart, emphasizing that much of the evolution in middle class living standards will depend on measures bearing on relative incomes.]]></description><author>Jacob Greenspon, Anna M. Stansbury, Lawrence H. Summers</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29548</guid></item><item><title>Capital Return Jumps and Wealth Distribution</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29544</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jess Benhabib, Wei Cui, Jianjun Miao.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The distributions of wealth in the US and many other countries are strikingly concentrated on the top and skewed to the right. To explain the income and wealth inequality, we provide a tractable heterogeneous-agent model with incomplete markets in continuous time. We separate illiquid capital assets from liquid bond assets and introduce capital return jump risks. Under recursive utility, we derive optimal consumption and wealth in closed form and show that the stationary wealth distribution has an exponential right tail. Our calibrated model can match the income and wealth distributions in the US data including the extreme right tail. We also study the effect of taxes on the distribution of wealth.]]></description><author>Jess Benhabib, Wei Cui, Jianjun Miao</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29544</guid></item><item><title>Macroeconomic Dynamics with Rigid Wage Contracts</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29540</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tobias Broer, Karl Harmenberg, Per Krusell, Erik Öberg.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We adapt the wage contracting structure in Chari (1983) to a dynamic, balanced-growth setting with re-contracting à la Calvo (1983). The resulting wage-rigidity framework delivers a model very similar to that in Jaimovich and Rebelo (2009), with their habit parameter replaced by our probability of wage-contract resetting. That is, if wage contracts can be reset very frequently, labor supply behaves in accordance with King, Plosser, and Rebelo (1988) preferences, whereas if they are sticky for a long time, we obtain the setting in Greenwood, Hercowitz, and Huffman (1988), thus allowing significant responses of hours to wage changes.]]></description><author>Tobias Broer, Karl Harmenberg, Per Krusell, Erik Öberg</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29540</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Multipliers in the COVID19 Recession</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29531</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alan J. Auerbach, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Peter McCrory, Daniel Murphy.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> In response to the record-breaking COVID19 recession, many governments have adopted unprecedented fiscal stimuli. While countercyclical fiscal policy is effective in fighting conventional recessions, little is known about the effectiveness of fiscal policy in the current environment with widespread shelter-in-place (“lockdown”) policies and the associated considerable limits on economic activity. Using detailed regional variation in economic conditions, lockdown policies, and U.S. government spending, we document that the effects of government spending were stronger during the peak of the pandemic recession, but only in cities that were not subject to strong stay-at-home orders. We examine mechanisms that can account for our evidence and place our findings in the context of other recent evidence from microdata.]]></description><author>Alan J. Auerbach, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Peter McCrory, Daniel Murphy</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29531</guid></item><item><title>“Golden Ages”: A Tale of the Labor Markets in China and the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29523</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hanming Fang, Xincheng Qiu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the labor markets in China and the United States, the two largest economies in the world, by examining the evolution of their cross-sectional age-earnings profiles during the past thirty years. We find that, first, the peak age in the cross-sectional age-earnings profiles, which we refer to as the “golden age,” stayed almost constant at around 45-50 in the U.S., but decreased sharply from 55 to around 35 in China; second, the age-specific earnings grew drastically in China, but stayed almost stagnant in the U.S.; third, the cross-sectional and life-cycle age-earnings profiles were remarkably similar in the U.S., but differed substantially in China. We propose and empirically implement a decomposition framework to infer from the repeated cross-sectional earnings data the experience effect (i.e., human capital accumulation over the life cycle), the cohort effect (i.e., inter-cohort human capital growth), and the time effect (i.e., changes in the human capital rental prices over time), under an identifying assumption that the growth of the experience effect stops at the end of one's working career. The decomposition suggests that China has experienced a much larger inter-cohort productivity growth and higher increase in the rental price to human capital, but lower returns to experience, compared to the U.S. We also use the inferred components to revisit several important and classical applications in macroeconomics and labor economics, including growth accounting and the estimation of TFP growth, and the college wage premium and skill-biased technical change.]]></description><author>Hanming Fang, Xincheng Qiu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29523</guid></item><item><title>Mistakes in Future Consumption, High MPCs Now</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29517</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Chen Lian.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In a canonical intertemporal consumption problem, I show how anticipation of future consumption mistakes leads to higher current marginal propensities to consume (MPCs). This result is driven by mistakes in future consumption's response to saving changes (i.e., changes in asset balances) and is independent of their specific behavioral foundations. My framework can accommodate many widely studied behavioral biases, such as inattention, present bias, diagnostic expectations, and near-rationality (epsilon-mistakes). This channel helps explain the empirical puzzle on high-liquidity consumers' high MPCs and can be significant. The same channel can also help explain other puzzles in intertemporal choices, such as violations of the fungibility principle, excess discounting of future income, and large risk aversion. Methodologically, I develop a general approach to study predictions of sophistication (i.e., the anticipation of future mistakes) independent of the underlying behavioral biases.]]></description><author>Chen Lian</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29517</guid></item><item><title>Unemployment Insurance in Macroeconomic Stabilization</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29505</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rohan Kekre.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> I study unemployment insurance (UI) in general equilibrium with incomplete markets, search frictions, and nominal rigidities.  An increase in generosity raises the aggregate demand for consumption if the unemployed have a higher marginal propensity to consume (MPC) than the employed or if agents precautionary save in light of future income risk.  This raises output and employment unless monetary policy raises the nominal interest rate.  In an analysis of the U.S. economy over 2008-2014, UI benefit extensions had a contemporaneous output multiplier around 1 or higher.  The unemployment rate would have been as much as 0.4pp higher absent these extensions.]]></description><author>Rohan Kekre</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29505</guid></item><item><title>Sovereign Risk and Financial Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29501</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Simon Gilchrist, Bin Wei, Vivian Z. Yue, Egon Zakrajšek.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we study the interplay between sovereign risk and global financial risk. We show that a substantial portion of the comovement among sovereign spreads is accounted for by changes in global financial risk. We construct bond-level sovereign spreads for dollar-denominated bonds issued by over 50 countries from 1995 to 2020 and use various indicators to measure global financial risk. Through panel regressions and local projection analysis, we find that an increase in global financial risk causes a large and persistent widening of sovereign bond spreads. These effects are strongest when measuring global risk using the excess bond premium – a measure of the risk-bearing capacity of U.S. financial intermediaries. The spillover effects of global financial risk are more pronounced for speculative-grade sovereign bonds.]]></description><author>Simon Gilchrist, Bin Wei, Vivian Z. Yue, Egon Zakrajšek</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29501</guid></item><item><title>Skewness and Time-Varying Second Moments in a Nonlinear Production Network: Theory and Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29499</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ian Dew-Becker, Alireza Tahbaz-Salehi, Andrea Vedolin.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies asymmetry in economic activity over the business cycle. It develops a tractable multisector model of the economy in which complementarity across inputs causes aggregate activity to be left skewed with countercyclical volatility. We then examine implications of the model regarding the time-series skewness of activity at the sector level, cyclicality of dispersion and skewness across sectors, and the conditional covariances of sector growth rates, finding support for each in the data. The empirical skewness of employment growth, industrial production growth, and stock returns increases with the level of aggregation, which is consistent with the model's implication that it is the nonlinearity in the production structure of the economy that generates the skewness. Other prominent models of asymmetry are not able to simultaneously match the range of empirical facts that the production network model can.]]></description><author>Ian Dew-Becker, Alireza Tahbaz-Salehi, Andrea Vedolin</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29499</guid></item><item><title>Zero Lower Bound on Inflation Expectations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29496</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Dmitriy Sergeyev.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We document a new fact: in U.S., European and Japanese surveys, households do not expect deflation, even in environments where persistent deflation is a strong possibility. This fact stands in contrast to the standard macroeconomic models with rational expectations. We extend a New Keynesian model with a zero-lower bound on inflation expectations. Unconventional monetary policies, such as forward guidance, are weaker. In liquidity traps, the government spending output multiplier is finite, and adverse aggregate supply shocks are not expansionary. A confidence-driven liquidity trap steady state with deflation does not exist.]]></description><author>Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Dmitriy Sergeyev</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29496</guid></item><item><title>Learning About the Long Run</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29495</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leland Farmer, Emi Nakamura, Jón Steinsson.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Forecasts of professional forecasters are anomalous: they are biased, forecast errors are autocorrelated, and forecast revisions predict forecast errors. Sticky or noisy information models seem like unlikely explanations for these anomalies: professional forecasters pay attention constantly and have precise knowledge of the data in question. We propose that these anomalies arise because professional forecasters don’t know the model that generates the data. We show that Bayesian agents learning about hard-to-learn features of the data generating process (low frequency behavior) can generate all the prominent aggregate anomalies emphasized in the literature. We show this for two applications: professional forecasts of nominal interest rates for the sample period 1980-2019 and CBO forecasts of GDP growth for the sample period 1976- 2019. Our learning model for interest rates also provides an explanation for deviations from the expectations hypothesis of the term structure that does not rely on time-variation in risk premia.]]></description><author>Leland Farmer, Emi Nakamura, Jón Steinsson</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29495</guid></item><item><title>Empirical Investigation of a Sufficient Statistic for Monetary Shocks</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29490</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Fernando E. Alvarez, Andrea Ferrara, Erwan Gautier, Hervé Le Bihan, Francesco Lippi.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In a broad class of sticky price models the non-neutrality of nominal shocks is encoded by a simple sufficient statistic: the ratio of the kurtosis of the size-distribution of price changes over the frequency of price changes. We test this theoretical prediction using data for a large number of firms representative of the French economy. We use the micro data to measure the cross sectional moments, including kurtosis and frequency, for about 120 PPI industries and 220 CPI categories. We use a Factor Augmented VAR to measure the sectoral responses to a monetary shock, as summarized by the cumulative impulse response of sectoral prices (CIRP ), under three alternative identification schemes. The estimated CIRP correlates with the kurtosis and the frequency consistently with the prediction of the theory (i.e. they enter the relationship as a ratio). The analysis also shows that other moments not suggested by the theory, such as the mean, standard deviation and skewness of the size-distribution of price changes, are not correlated with the CIR . Several robustness checks are discussed]]></description><author>Fernando E. Alvarez, Andrea Ferrara, Erwan Gautier, Hervé Le Bihan, Francesco Lippi</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29490</guid></item><item><title>Central Bank Digital Currencies and The Emerging Markets: The Currency Substitution Challenge</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29489</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sebastian Edwards.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, I discuss the implications for emerging countries of the adoption of central bank digital currencies (CBDCs) in advanced jurisdictions, such as the United States, the United Kingdom, and the Euro Zone. The analysis identifies benefits as well as costs. Among the former, one of the most important is lower costs for migrants’ remittances. Some of the costs of global CBDCs are associated with currency substitution, sudden currency depreciations, and lower seigniorage. At the global level, a smooth rollout of CBDCs in center countries requires international coordination. In addition, emerging countries will benefit from the implementation of stronger macroprudential regulations]]></description><author>Sebastian Edwards</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29489</guid></item><item><title>Converging to Convergence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29484</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Kremer, Jack Willis, Yang You.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Empirical tests in the 1990s found little evidence of poor countries catching up with rich - unconditional convergence - since the 1960s, and divergence over longer periods. This stylized fact spurred several developments in growth theory, including AK models, poverty trap models, and the concept of convergence conditional on determinants of steady-state income. We revisit these findings, using the subsequent 25 years as an out-of-sample test, and document a trend towards unconditional convergence since 1990 and convergence since 2000, driven by both faster catch-up growth and slower growth of the frontier. During the same period, many of the correlates of growth - human capital, policies, institutions, and culture - also converged substantially and moved in the direction associated with higher income. Were these changes related? Using the omitted variable bias formula, we decompose the gap between unconditional and conditional convergence as the product of two cross-sectional slopes. First, correlate-income slopes, which remained largely stable since 1990. Second, growth-correlate slopes controlling for income - the coefficients of growth regressions - which remained stable for fundamentals of the Solow model (investment rate, population growth, and human capital) but which flattened substantially for other correlates, leading unconditional convergence to converge towards conditional convergence.]]></description><author>Michael Kremer, Jack Willis, Yang You</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29484</guid></item><item><title>Labor Market Dynamics When Ideas are Harder to Find</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29479</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal, Niklas Engbom, Simon Mongey, Giovanni L. Violante.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper evaluates the impact of slowing economic growth on labor market dynamism and misallocation. It provides a model of endogenous growth via imitation in a frictional labor market. The framework accounts for rich data on worker job-to-job transitions as well as stochastic and lifecycle properties of firm growth and job reallocation. High productivity entrants gradually replace obsolescing incumbents by poaching their workers, a process that is intermediated via a frictional labor market. When the likelihood of entrants imitating technologies in the tail of the distribution falls (ideas are harder to find), so does growth. Consistent with US data over the past 30 years, firm entry, incumbents’ employment response to productivity shocks, and job-to-job transitions decline, while the share of old firms increases. With lower imitation, however, there is less misallocation, because the slower aggregate rate of obsolescence induces productive firms to invest more in costly hiring and grow faster to their optimal size.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal, Niklas Engbom, Simon Mongey, Giovanni L. Violante</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29479</guid></item><item><title>Optimal Bank Reserve Remuneration and Capital Control Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29473</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Chun-Che Chi, Stephanie Schmitt-Grohé, Martín Uribe.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies optimal capital-control and bank-reserve remuneration policy in an open economy with a banking channel and a collateral constraint that limits household debt by a fraction of income. It finds that the unregulated economy borrows too little relative to what is optimal (underborrowing). This finding contrasts with the standard overborrowing result obtained in the absence of a banking channel. Under optimal policy, the central bank injects bank reserves during recessions. In this way, the monetary authority is able to uncouple household deleveraging from economy-wide deleveraging, thereby ameliorating the severity of the financial crisis. The paper documents that in emerging and developed economies the lending spread (lending rate minus deposit rate) displayed a muted response during the 2007-2009 financial crisis. This fact is consistent with a decline in the demand rather than in the supply of loans and gives credence to models in which the collateral constraint is placed at the level of the nonfinancial sector as opposed to at the level of the bank.]]></description><author>Chun-Che Chi, Stephanie Schmitt-Grohé, Martín Uribe</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29473</guid></item><item><title>AI-tocracy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29466</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Beraja, Andrew Kao, David Y. Yang, Noam Yuchtman.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Can frontier innovation be sustained under autocracy? We argue that innovation and autocracy can be mutually reinforcing when: (i) the new technology bolsters the autocrat’s power; and (ii) the autocrat’s demand for the technology stimulates further innovation in applications beyond those benefiting it directly. We test for such a mutually reinforcing relationship in the context of facial recognition AI in China. To do so, we gather comprehensive data on AI firms and government procurement contracts, as well as on social unrest across China during the last decade. We first show that autocrats benefit from AI: local unrest leads to greater government procurement of facial recognition AI, and increased AI procurement suppresses subsequent unrest. We then show that AI innovation benefits from autocrats’ suppression of unrest: the contracted AI firms innovate more both for the government and commercial markets. Taken together, these results suggest the possibility of sustained AI innovation under the Chinese regime: AI innovation entrenches the regime, and the regime’s investment in AI for political control stimulates further frontier innovation.]]></description><author>Martin Beraja, Andrew Kao, David Y. Yang, Noam Yuchtman</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29466</guid></item><item><title>FinTech as a Financial Liberator</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Greg Buchak, Jiayin Hu, Shang-Jin Wei.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> A binding interest rate cap on household savings is a common form of financial repression in developing economies and typically benefits banks. Using proprietary data from a leading Chinese FinTech company, we study Fintech's role in ending financial repression in China through the introduction of a money market fund with deposit-like features available through an already widely-adopted household payment platform.  Cities and banks whose depositor base is more exposed to FinTech see greater deposit outflows. Importantly, exposed banks respond to FinTech competition by offering competing products with market interest rates. FinTech thus facilitates a bottom-up interest rate liberalization.]]></description><author>Greg Buchak, Jiayin Hu, Shang-Jin Wei</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</guid></item><item><title>A Temporary VAT Cut as Unconventional Fiscal Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We exploit the unexpected announcement of an immediate, temporary VAT cut in Germany in the second half of 2020 as a natural experiment to study the spending response to unconventional fiscal policy. We use survey and scanner data on households’ consumption expenditures and their perceived pass-through of the tax change into prices to quantify its effects. The temporary VAT cut led to a substantial relative increase in durable spending of 36% for individuals with a high perceived pass-through. Semi- and non-durable spending also increased. According to our preferred estimates, the VAT policy increased aggregate consumption spending by 34 billion Euros.]]></description><author>Ruediger Bachmann, Benjamin Born, Olga Goldfayn-Frank, Georgi Kocharkov, Ralph Luetticke, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29442</guid></item><item><title>Macroprudential Policies and The Covid-19 Pandemic: Risks and Challenges For Emerging Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29441</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sebastian Edwards.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper deals with COVID and macroprudential regulations in emerging markets. I document the build-up of a sturdy macroprudential structure during 2009-2019, and the relaxation of regulations in 2020-2021, as part of the effort to deal with the sanitary emergency. I show that in every country, regulatory forbearance played a key role in the response to COVID. I discuss capital controls as macroprudential instruments. I argue that rebuilding the macroprudential fabric is important to reduce the costs of future systemic shocks. I maintain that post-COVID regulations should incorporate the risks associated with digital currencies.]]></description><author>Sebastian Edwards</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29441</guid></item><item><title>The Debt Capacity of a Government</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Bernard Dumas, Paul Ehling, Chunyu Yang.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In a deterministic overlapping-generations economy with production and physical capital, the price of debt can be positive without any budget surpluses being in the offing, because debt incorporates a rational bubble. Yet the dynamics of debt remain a function of the dynamics of the primary budget deficit. As a way to study their joint behavior, we endogenize a structural deficit in the form of an underfunded social-security scheme. We define debt capacity as the level of debt that can be just sustained without a change of policy all the way to an unstable steady state. When it starts below the capacity, the debt converges to a stable steady state, in which the bubble is sustained. Above capacity the bubble unravels and the deficit cannot be financed. In several realistic scenarios occurring in economies, we calculate the needed policy response, which is the true "fiscal cost" of exceeding debt capacity.]]></description><author>Bernard Dumas, Paul Ehling, Chunyu Yang</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29434</guid></item><item><title>"Potential Capital”, Working From Home, and Economic Resilience</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29431</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Janice C. Eberly, Jonathan Haskel, Paul Mizen.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The impact of an economic shock depends both on its severity and the resilience of the economic response. Resilience can include the ability to relocate factors, for example, even when new technologies or skills are not yet at the ready. This resilience per se buffers production and has an economic value, which we estimate. The COVID-19 pandemic caused a widespread decline in recorded GDP. Yet, as catastrophic as the collapse was, it was buffered by an unprecedented and spontaneous deployment of what we call “Potential Capital,” the dwelling/residential capital and connective technologies used alongside working from home. Together potential capital and labor working from home provided additional output margins and capacity. We estimate the contribution of this capital, and the remote work that it facilitated, to have roughly halved the decline in GDP in the US reducing the fall in GDP to 9.4 log points in 2020Q2 at the trough of the recession. Similar effects are seen in the 6 OECD countries for which data are available, output fell by 14 log points, but would have fallen by 26 log points had only workplace inputs been available. Accounting for the contribution of “Potential Capital” also revises downwards estimated total productivity gains in the business sector during the pandemic from 8 log points to 5 log points in 2020Q2. We also find an output elasticity of domestic non-dwellings capital to be similar to that of workplace ICT capital, reflecting its role as productive capital. Turning to the future, changes in working from home depend upon relative costs, relative technologies and, crucially, the elasticity of substitution between home and work tasks. We estimate that that elasticity to be more than unity, meaning that the growth of ICT will raise the share of work done remotely.]]></description><author>Janice C. Eberly, Jonathan Haskel, Paul Mizen</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29431</guid></item><item><title>Uncertainty and Change: Survey Evidence of Firms' Subjective Beliefs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29430</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ruediger Bachmann, Kai Carstensen, Stefan Lautenbacher, Martin Schneider.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies how managers plan under uncertainty. In a new survey panel on German manufacturing firms, we show that uncertainty reflects change: Planning incorporates higher subjective uncertainty about future sales growth when the firm has just experienced unusual growth, and more so if the experience was negative. At the quarterly frequency, subjective uncertainty closely tracks conditional volatility of shocks: Both exhibit an asymmetric V-shaped relationship with past growth. In the cross section of firms, however, subjective uncertainty differs from conditional volatility: planning in successful firms—either large or fast-growing—reflects lower subjective uncertainty than in unsuccessful firms even when the size of the shocks is the same.]]></description><author>Ruediger Bachmann, Kai Carstensen, Stefan Lautenbacher, Martin Schneider</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29430</guid></item><item><title>A Social Insurance Perspective on Pandemic Fiscal Policy: Implications for Unemployment Insurance and Hazard Pay</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper considers fiscal policy during the pandemic through the lens of optimal social insurance. We develop a simple framework to analyze how government taxes and transfers could mimic the insurance against pandemic income losses that people would like to have had. Permutations of the framework provide insight into how unemployment insurance should be structured, when and how much hazard pay is called for, and whether fiscal policy should aim just to redistribute income or also to stimulate aggregate demand during a pandemic. When we use the insights from the model to evaluate unemployment insurance measures taken during the pandemic, we find that some, but far from all, of the implications of the social insurance framework were followed. In the case of hazard pay, we find that the proposal for a national program (the never-implemented HEROES Act) was both broader and more generous than a social insurance perspective would call for. We suggest that the social insurance perspective on fiscal policy is likely to become increasingly relevant as pandemics and climate-related natural disasters become more common causes of unemployment and recessions.]]></description><author>Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29419</guid></item><item><title>Licence to Dine: 007 and the Real Exchange Rate</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29415</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Lee A. Craig, Julianne Treme, Thomas J. Weiss.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We constructed a time series of menu prices for the identifiable restaurants at which James Bond dined in France and the UK that yields one of the few international price series representing luxury services. This series enabled us to calculate a real exchange rate based on prices pertinent to international travelers. We also compiled a time series on the salary of workers in the British Civil Service at Grade 7, like Bond, from 1953 to 2019. Our results indicate that French restaurant prices increased faster than Grade 7 salaries over the entire period and changes in the British exchange rate were not favorable for British travelers. To dine weekly in France, during the 1950s and 1960s, Bond would have spent 18 percent of his salary; whereas over the course of the Euro era the same basket of luxury services would have required on average 26 percent of his salary. Finally, our data indicate a likely violation of the law of one price during both the Pound-Franc and Pound-Euro eras.]]></description><author>Lee A. Craig, Julianne Treme, Thomas J. Weiss</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29415</guid></item><item><title>Value without Employment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29414</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Simcha Barkai, Stavros Panageas.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Young firms' contribution to aggregate employment has been underwhelming. However, a similar trend is not apparent in their contribution to aggregate sales or aggregate stock market capitalization. We study the implications of the arrival of “low marginal - high average” revenue-product-of-labor firms in a stylized model of dynamic firm heterogeneity, and show that the model can account for a large number of facts related to the decline in “business dynamism”. We study the long-term implications of the decline in business dynamism on the economy by providing analytical results that connect the decline in dynamism to the eventual decline of consumption.]]></description><author>Simcha Barkai, Stavros Panageas</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29414</guid></item><item><title>On the Persistence of the China Shock</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29401</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Autor, David Dorn, Gordon H. Hanson.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Abstract We evaluate the duration of the China trade shock and its impact on a wide range of outcomes over the period 2000 to 2019. The shock plateaued in 2010, enabling analysis of its effects for nearly a decade past its culmination. Adverse impacts of import competition on manufacturing employment, overall employment-population ratios, and income per capita in more trade-exposed U.S. commuting zones are present out to 2019. Over the full study period, greater import competition implies a reduction in the manufacturing employment-population ratio of 1.54 percentage points, which is 55% of the observed change in the value, and the absorption of 86% of this net job loss via a corresponding decrease in the overall employment rate. Reductions in population headcounts, which indicate net out-migration, register only for foreign-born workers and the native-born 25-39 years old, implying that exit from work is a primary means of adjustment to trade-induced contractions in labor demand. More negatively affected regions see modest increases in the uptake of government transfers, but these transfers primarily take the form of Social Security and Medicare benefits. Adverse outcomes are more acute in regions that initially had fewer college-educated workers and were more industrially specialized. Impacts are qualitatively—but not quantitatively—similar to those caused by the decline of employment in coal production since the 1980s, indicating that the China trade shock holds lessons for other episodes of localized job loss. Import competition from China induced changes in income per capita across local labor markets that are much larger than the spatial heterogeneity of income effects predicted by standard quantitative trade models. Even using higher-end estimates of the consumer benefits of rising trade with China, a substantial fraction of commuting zones appears to have suffered absolute declines in average real incomes.]]></description><author>David Autor, David Dorn, Gordon H. Hanson</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29401</guid></item><item><title>The Rise of Pass-Throughs and the Decline of the Labor Share</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29400</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Matthew Smith, Danny Yagan, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the coevolution of the fall in the US corporate sector labor share and the rise of business activity in tax-preferred, pass-through form. Reallocating activity to the form it would have taken prior to the Tax Reform Act of 1986 accounts for one third of the decline in the corporate sector labor share between 1978 and 2017. Our adjustments are concentrated among mid-market firms in services, leaving a larger role for the manufacturing sector and superstar firms in driving the remaining decline in the labor share. Our findings highlight the importance of tax policy when measuring factor shares.]]></description><author>Matthew Smith, Danny Yagan, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29400</guid></item><item><title>The Geography of Job Creation and Job Destruction</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29399</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Moritz Kuhn, Iourii Manovskii, Xincheng Qiu.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Spatial differences in labor market performance are large and highly persistent. Using data from the United States, Germany, and the United Kingdom, we document striking similarities in spatial differences in unemployment, vacancies, job finding, and job filling within each country. This robust set of facts guides and disciplines the development of a theory of local labor market performance. We find that a spatial version of a Diamond-Mortensen-Pissarides model with endogenous separations and on-the-job search quantitatively accounts for all the documented empirical regularities. The model also quantitatively rationalizes why differences in job-separation rates have primary importance in inducing differences in unemployment across space while changes in the job-finding rate are the main driver in unemployment fluctuations over the business cycle.]]></description><author>Moritz Kuhn, Iourii Manovskii, Xincheng Qiu</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29399</guid></item><item><title>The Fiscal and Welfare Effects of Policy Responses to the Covid-19 School Closures</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29398</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicola Fuchs-Schündeln, Dirk Krueger, André Kurmann, Etienne Lalé, Alexander Ludwig, Irina Popova.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Using a structural life-cycle model and data on school visits from Safegraph and school closures from Burbio, we quantify the heterogeneous impact of school closures during the Corona crisis on children affected at different ages and coming from households with different parental characteristics. Our data suggests that secondary schools were closed for in-person learning for longer periods than elementary schools (implying that younger children experienced less school closures than older children), and that private schools experienced shorter closures than public schools, and schools in poorer U.S. counties experienced shorter school closures. We then extend the structural life cycle model of private and public schooling investments studied in Fuchs-Schuendeln, Krueger, Ludwig and Popova (2021) to include the choice of parents whether to send their children to private schools, empirically discipline it with data on parental investments from the PSID, and then feed into the model the school closure measures from our empirical analysis to quantify the long-run consequences of the Covid-19 school closures on the cohorts of children currently in school. Future earnings- and welfare losses are largest for children that started public secondary schools at the onset of the Covid-19 crisis. Comparing children from the top- to children from the bottom quartile of the income distribution, welfare losses are ca. 0.8 percentage points larger for the poorer children if school closures were unrelated to income. Accounting for the longer school closures in richer counties reduces this gap by about 1/3. A policy intervention that extends schools by 3 months (6 weeks in the next two summers) generates significant welfare gains for the children and raises future tax approximately sufficient to pay for the cost of this schooling expansion.]]></description><author>Nicola Fuchs-Schündeln, Dirk Krueger, André Kurmann, Etienne Lalé, Alexander Ludwig, Irina Popova</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29398</guid></item><item><title>Bank Runs, Fragility, and Credit Easing</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29397</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Manuel Amador, Javier Bianchi.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We present a tractable dynamic macroeconomic model of self-fulfilling bank runs. A bank is vulnerable to a run when a loss of investors' confidence triggers deposit withdrawals and leads the bank to default on its obligations.  We analytically characterize how the vulnerability of an individual bank depends on macroeconomic aggregates and how the number of banks facing a run affects macroeconomic aggregates in turn. In general equilibrium, runs can be partial or complete, depending on aggregate leverage and the dynamics of asset prices. Our normative analysis shows that the effectiveness of credit easing and its welfare implications depend on whether a financial crisis is driven by fundamentals or by self-fulfilling runs.]]></description><author>Manuel Amador, Javier Bianchi</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29397</guid></item><item><title>Do Credit Conditions Move House Prices?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29391</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel L. Greenwald, Adam Guren.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> To what extent did an expansion and contraction of credit drive the 2000s housing boom and bust? The existing literature lacks consensus, with findings ranging from credit having no effect to credit driving most of the house price cycle. We show that the key difference behind these disparate results is the extent to which credit insensitive agents such as landlords and unconstrained savers absorb credit-driven demand, which depends on the degree of segmentation in housing markets. We develop a model with frictional rental markets that allows us to consider cases in between the extremes of no segmentation and perfect segmentation typically assumed in the literature. We argue that the relative elasticities of the price-rent ratio and homeownership with respect to an identified credit shock is a sufficient statistic to measure the degree of segmentation. We estimate this moment using three different credit supply instruments and use it to calibrate our model. Our results reveal that rental markets are highly frictional and closer to fully segmented, which implies large effects of credit on house prices. In particular, changes to credit standards can explain between 34% and 55% of the rise in price-rent ratios over the boom.]]></description><author>Daniel L. Greenwald, Adam Guren</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29391</guid></item><item><title>Household Credit as Stimulus? Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> From 2011 to 2014, the Brazilian government conducted a heavily advertised major credit expansion program through government banks as part of its effort to stimulate the economy. Using administrative data on individual-level borrowing and spending, we find that the program led to a substantial rise in borrowing by government employees, especially those with low financial literacy. We trace the impact of credit stimulus on borrowers' consumption through the 2011-16 business cycle, and find that the credit stimulus resulted in higher consumption volatility and lower average consumption over the cycle. Our results suggest a potential downside of using household credit as stimulus in emerging markets.]]></description><author>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</guid></item><item><title>Occupational Choice and the Intergenerational Mobility of Welfare</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29381</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Corina Boar, Danial Lashkari.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Based on responses in the General Social Survey, we construct an index that captures non-monetary qualities of occupations, such as respect, learning, and work hazards, relevant to the well-being of workers. Using the Panel Study of Income Dynamics and National Longitudinal Survey of Youth data, we document that the children of richer US parents are more likely to select into occupations that rank higher in terms of this index. We rationalize this fact by introducing occupational choice with preferences over the intrinsic qualities of occupations into a standard theory of intergenerational mobility. Estimating the model allows us to infer the equivalent monetary compensation each worker receives from the intrinsic qualities of their chosen occupation. Earnings adjusted to reflect this additional compensation show substantially larger persistence of income from parents to children. Our model further predicts that the trends in the composition of labor demand in the US over the past three decades decreased intergenerational persistence, and also led to higher growth in the welfare of the average worker than that implied by observed earnings.]]></description><author>Corina Boar, Danial Lashkari</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29381</guid></item><item><title>Firms' Inflation Expectations: New Evidence from France</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29376</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Frédérique Savignac, Erwan Gautier, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Olivier Coibion.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Using a new survey of firms’ inflation expectations in France, we provide novel evidence about the measurement and formation of inflation expectations on the part of firms. First, French firms report inflation expectations with a smaller, but still positive, bias than households and display less disagreement. Second, we characterize the extent and manner in which the wording of questions matters for the measurement of firms’ inflation expectations. Third, we document whether and how the position of the respondent within the firm affects the provided responses. Fourth, because our survey measures firms’ expectations about aggregate and firm-level wage growth along with their inflation expectations, we are able to show that expectations about wages are even more condensed than firms’ inflation expectations and almost completely uncorrelated with them, indicating that firms perceive little link between price and wage inflation. Finally, an experimental treatment indicates that an exogenous change in firms’ inflation expectations has no effect on their aggregate wage expectations.]]></description><author>Frédérique Savignac, Erwan Gautier, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Olivier Coibion</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29376</guid></item><item><title>Top Wealth in America: New Estimates and Implications for Taxing the Rich</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29374</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Matthew Smith, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses administrative tax data to estimate top wealth in the United States. We assemble new data that links people to their sources of capital income and develop new methods to estimate the degree of return heterogeneity within asset classes. Disaggregated fixed income data reveal that rich individuals earn much more of their interest income in higher-yielding forms, and have much greater exposure to credit risk. Consequently, in recent years, the interest rate on fixed income at the top is approximately three times higher than the average. Using firm-level characteristics to value firms, we find that twenty percent of total pass-through business wealth accrues to those with losses. We combine this new data on fixed income and pass-through business returns with refined estimates of C-corporation equity, housing, and pension wealth to deliver new capitalized wealth estimates. Our approach---which builds on Saez and Zucman (2016) and Bricker, Henriques, and Hansen (2018)---reduces bias because wealth and rates of return are correlated. From 1989 to 2016, the top 1%, 0.1%, and 0.01% wealth shares increased by 7.6, 5.1, and 3.0 percentage points, respectively, to 31.5%, 15.0%, and 7.0%. While these changes are less dramatic than some prior estimates, wealth is very concentrated: the top 1% holds nearly as much wealth as either the bottom 90% or the "P90-99" class. We discuss implications for income inequality measures, capital tax policy, and savings behavior.]]></description><author>Matthew Smith, Owen M. Zidar, Eric Zwick</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29374</guid></item><item><title>The Economics of Walking About and Predicting US Downturns</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29372</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Economic shocks are notoriously difficult to predict but recent research suggests qualitative metrics about economic actors’ expectations are predictive of downturns.  We show consumer expectations indices from both the Conference Board and the University of Michigan predict economic downturns up to 18 months in advance in the United States, both at national and at state-level.  All the recessions since the 1980s have been predicted by at least 10 and sometimes many more point drops in these expectations indices.  A single monthly rise of at least 0.3 percentage points in the unemployment rate also predicts recession, as does two consecutive months of employment rate declines.  The economic situation in 2021 is exceptional, however, since unprecedented direct government intervention in the labor market through furlough-type arrangements has enabled employment rates to recover quickly from the huge downturn in 2020.  However, downward movements in consumer expectations in the last six months suggest the economy in the United States is entering recession now (Autumn 2021) even though employment and wage growth figures suggest otherwise.]]></description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29372</guid></item><item><title>Falling Rates and Rising Superstars</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29368</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Thomas Kroen, Ernest Liu, Atif R. Mian, Amir Sufi.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Do low interest rates contribute to the rise in market concentration? Using data on firm financials and high frequency monetary policy shocks, we find that falling interest rates disproportionately benefit industry leaders, especially when the initial interest rate is already low. Falling rates raise the valuation of industry leaders relative to industry followers and this effect snowballs as the interest rate approaches zero. There are multiple channels through which falling rates disproportionately benefit industry leaders: (i) the cost of borrowing falls more for industry leaders, (ii) industry leaders are able to raise more debt, increase leverage, and buyback more shares, and (iii) capital investment and acquisitions increase more for industry leaders. All three of these effects also snowball as the interest rate approaches zero. The findings provide empirical support to the idea that extremely low interest rates and the rise of superstar firms are connected.]]></description><author>Thomas Kroen, Ernest Liu, Atif R. Mian, Amir Sufi</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29368</guid></item><item><title>Tax Policy Design with Low Interest Rates</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29352</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alan J. Auerbach, William Gale.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Interest rates on government debt have fallen in many countries over the last several decades, with markets indicating that rates may stay low well into the future.  It is by now well understood that sustained low interest rates can change the nature of long-run fiscal policy choices.  In this paper, we examine a related issue: the implications of sustained low interest rates for the structure of tax policy.  We show that low interest rates (a) reduce the differences between consumption and income taxes; (b) make wealth taxes less efficient relative to capital income taxes, at given rates of tax; (c) reduce the value of firm-level investment incentives, and (d) substantially raise the valuation of benefits of carbon abatement policies relative to their costs.]]></description><author>Alan J. Auerbach, William Gale</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29352</guid></item><item><title>What Drives Variation in the U.S. Debt/Output Ratio? The Dogs that Didn't Bark</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29351</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhengyang Jiang, Hanno Lustig, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh, Mindy Z. Xiaolan.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> If the U.S. is on a fiscally sustainable path, then higher U.S. government debt/output ratios should reliably predict higher future surpluses or lower real returns on Treasurys. In the post-war sample, we find no evidence for this. Neither future cash flows nor discount rates account for the variation in the current debt/output ratio. Instead, the future debt/output ratio accounts for most of the variation. Systematic surplus forecast errors can account for part of these findings. Since the start of the GFC, surplus projections have anticipated a large fiscal correction that failed to materialize.]]></description><author>Zhengyang Jiang, Hanno Lustig, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh, Mindy Z. Xiaolan</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29351</guid></item><item><title>Illuminating the Effects of the US-China Tariff War on China's Economy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29349</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Davin Chor, Bingjing Li.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> How much has the US-China tariff war impacted economic outcomes in China? We address this question using high-frequency night lights data, together with measures of the trade exposure of fine grid locations constructed from Chinese firms' geo-coordinates. Exploiting within-grid variation over time and controlling extensively for grid-specific contemporaneous trends, we find that each 1 percentage point increase in exposure to the US tariffs was associated with a 0.59% reduction in night-time luminosity. We combine these with structural elasticities that relate night lights to economic outcomes, motivated by the statistical framework of Henderson et al. (2012). The negative impact of the tariff war was highly skewed across locations: While grids with negligible direct exposure to the US tariffs accounted for up to 70% of China's population, we infer that the 2.5% of the population in grids with the largest US tariff shocks saw a 2.52% (1.62%) decrease in income per capita (manufacturing employment) relative to unaffected grids. By contrast, we do not find significant effects from China's retaliatory tariffs.]]></description><author>Davin Chor, Bingjing Li</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29349</guid></item><item><title>Outsourcing, Inequality and Aggregate Output</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Outsourced workers experience large wage declines, yet domestic outsourcing may raise aggregate productivity. To study this equity-efficiency trade-off, we contribute a framework in which firms either hire many imperfectly substitutable worker types in-house by posting wages along a job ladder, or rent labor services from contractors who hire in the same frictional labor markets. Three implications arise. First, more productive firms are more likely to outsource to save on higher wage premia. Second, outsourcing raises output at the firm level. Third, contractors endogenously locate at the bottom of the job ladder, implying that outsourced workers receive lower wages. Using firm-level instruments for outsourcing and revenue productivity, we find empirical support for all three predictions in French administrative data. After structurally estimating the model, we find that the rise in outsourcing in France between 1996 and 2007 raised aggregate output by 3% and reduced the labor share by 0.7 percentage points. A 9% minimum wage increase stabilizes the labor share and maintains two thirds of the output gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal, Hugo Lhuillier</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29348</guid></item><item><title>Rethinking Exchange Rate Regimes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29347</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ethan Ilzetzki, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper employs an updated algorithm and database for classifying exchange rate and anchor currency choice, to explore the evolution of the global exchange rate system, including parallel rates, capital controls and reserves. In line with a large recent literature, we find that the dollar has become ever-more central as the de facto anchor or reference currencies for much of the world. Our discussion encompasses the history of anchor currency choice, methods for classifying exchange rate regimes, a detailed discussion of the evolution of regimes, the growing substitution of reserves for capital controls as a tool for exchange rate stabilization, the modern Triffin dilemma, and the surprising recent trend decline in volatility of exchange rates at the core of the system. It concludes with issues surrounding the rise of China.]]></description><author>Ethan Ilzetzki, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29347</guid></item><item><title>Macroprudential Policy during COVID-19: The Role of Policy Space</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Katharina Bergant, Kristin Forbes.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper uses the initial phase of the COVID-19 pandemic to examine how macroprudential frameworks developed over the past decade performed during a period of heightened financial and economic stress. It discusses a new measure of the macroprudential stance that better captures the intensity of different policies across countries and time. Then it shows that macroprudential policy has been used countercyclically—with stances tightened during the 2010’s and eased in response to COVID-19 by more than previous risk-off periods. Countries that tightened macroprudential policy more aggressively before COVID, as well as those that eased more during the pandemic, experienced less financial and economic stress. Countries’ ability to use macroprudential policy, however, was significantly constrained by the extent of existing “policy space”, i.e., by how aggressively policy was tightened before COVID-19. The use of macroprudential tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use other policy tools (such as fiscal policy, monetary policy, FX intervention, and capital flow management measures), and the use of other tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use macroprudential policy. This suggests that although macroprudential tools are being used countercyclically and should therefore help stabilize economies and financial markets, there appears to be an opportunity to better integrate the use of macroprudential tools with other policies in the future.]]></description><author>Katharina Bergant, Kristin Forbes</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</guid></item><item><title>From Just in Time, to Just in Case, to Just in Worst-Case: Simple models of a Global Supply Chain under Uncertain Aggregate Shocks.</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29345</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Bomin Jiang, Daniel E. Rigobon, Roberto Rigobon.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Covid-19 highlighted the weaknesses in the supply chain. Many have argued that a more resilient or robust supply chain is needed. But what does a robust supply chain mean? And how do firms’ decisions change when taken that approach? This paper studies a very stylized model of a supply chain, where we study how the decision of a multinational corporation changes in the presence of uncertainty. The two standard theories of supply chain are Just-in-time and Just-in-case. Just-in-time argues in favor of pursuing efficiency, while Just-in-case studies how such decision changes when the firm faces idiosyncratic risk. We find that a robust supply chain is very different specially in the presence of systemic shocks. In this case, firms need to concentrate on the worst-case. This strategy implies a supply chain where the allocation of resources and capabilities does not correspond to the standard theories studied in economics, but follow a heuristic behavioral rule called “probability matching”. It has been found in nature and in experimental research that subjects appeal to probability matching when seeking survival. We find that a robust supply chain will reproduce this behavioral outcome. In fact, a multinational optimizing under uncertainty, follows a probability matching which leads to an allocation that is suboptimal from the individual producer point of view, but rules out the possibility of supply disruptions.]]></description><author>Bomin Jiang, Daniel E. Rigobon, Roberto Rigobon</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29345</guid></item><item><title>Business News and Business Cycles</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29344</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leland Bybee, Bryan T. Kelly, Asaf Manela, Dacheng Xiu.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We propose an approach to measuring the state of the economy via textual analysis of business news. From the full text of 800,000 Wall Street Journal articles for 1984–2017, we estimate a topic model that summarizes business news into interpretable topical themes and quantifies the proportion of news attention allocated to each theme over time. News attention closely tracks a wide range of economic activities and explains 25% of aggregate stock market returns. A text-augmented VAR demonstrates the large incremental role of news text in modeling macroeconomic dynamics. We use this model to retrieve the narratives that underlie business cycle fluctuations.]]></description><author>Leland Bybee, Bryan T. Kelly, Asaf Manela, Dacheng Xiu</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29344</guid></item><item><title>Hysteresis in Unemployment: Evidence from OECD Estimates of the Natural Rate</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29343</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Laurence M. Ball, Joern Onken.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the dynamics of unemployment (u) and its natural rate (u*), with u* measured by real-time estimates for 29 countries from the OECD. We find strong evidence of hysteresis: an innovation in u causes u* to change in the same direction, and therefore has permanent effects. For our baseline specification, a one percentage point deviation of u from u* for one year has a long-run effect of 0.16 points on both variables. When we allow asymmetry, we find, perhaps surprisingly, that decreases in u have larger long-run effects than increases in u.]]></description><author>Laurence M. Ball, Joern Onken</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29343</guid></item><item><title>Bayesian Learning</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29338</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Isaac Baley, Laura Veldkamp.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We survey work using Bayesian learning in macroeconomics, highlighting common themes and new directions. First, we present many of the common types of learning problems agents face---signal extraction problems---and trace out their effects on macro aggregates, in different strategic settings. Then we review different perspectives on how agents get their information. Models differ in their motives for information acquisition and the cost of information, or learning technology. Finally, we survey the growing literature on the data economy, where economic activity generates data and the information in data feeds back to affect economic activity.]]></description><author>Isaac Baley, Laura Veldkamp</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29338</guid></item><item><title>Decrypting New Age International Capital Flows</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29337</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clemens Graf von Luckner, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper employs high frequency transactions data on the world’s oldest and most extensive centralized peer-to-peer Bitcoin market, which enables trade in the currencies of more than 135 countries.  We develop an algorithm that allows, with high probability, the detection of “crypto vehicle transactions” in which crypto currency is used to move capital across borders or facilitate domestic transactions. In contrast to previous work which has used “on-chain” data, our approach enables one to investigate parts of the vastly larger pool of “off-chain” transactions. We find that, as a conservative lower bound, over 7 percent of the 45 million trades on the exchange we explore represent crypto vehicle transactions in which Bitcoin is used to make payment in fiat currency.  Roughly 20 percent of these represent international capital flight/flows/remittances.  Although our work cannot be used to put a price on cryptocurrencies, it provides the first systematic quantitative evidence that the transactional use of cryptocurrencies constitutes a fundamental component of their value, at least under the current regulatory regime.]]></description><author>Clemens Graf von Luckner, Carmen M. Reinhart, Kenneth S. Rogoff</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29337</guid></item><item><title>Exposure, Experience, and Expertise: Why Personal Histories Matter in Economics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ulrike Malmendier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Personal experiences of economic outcomes, from global financial crises to individual-level job losses, can shape individual beliefs, risk attitudes, and choices for years to come. A growing literature on experience effects shows that individuals act as if past outcomes that they experienced were overly likely to occur again, even if they are fully informed about the actual likelihood. This reaction to past experiences is long-lasting though it decays over time as individuals accumulate new experiences. Modern brain science helps understand these processes. Evidence on neuroplasticity reveals that personal experiences and learning alter the strength of neural connections and fine-tune the brain structure to those past experiences ("use-dependent brain"). I show that experience effects help understand belief formation and decision-making in a wide area of economic applications, including inflation, home purchases, mortgage choices, and consumption expenditures. I argue that experience-based learning is broadly applicable to economic decision-making and discuss topics for future research in education, health, race, and gender economics.]]></description><author>Ulrike Malmendier</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</guid></item><item><title>The Global Financial Cycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29327</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Silvia Miranda-Agrippino, Hélène Rey.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We review the literature on the empirical characteristics of the global financial cycle and associated stylized facts on international capital flows, asset prices, risk aversion and liquidity in the financial system. We analyse the co-movements of global factors in asset prices and capital flows with commodity prices, international trade and world output as well as the sensitivity of different parts of the world to the Global Financial Cycle.  We present evidence of the causal effects of the monetary policies of the US Federal Reserve, the European Central Bank and of the People's Bank of China on the Global Financial Cycle.  We then assess whether the 2008 financial crisis has altered the transmission channels of monetary policies on the Global Financial Cycle. Finally, we discuss the theoretical modelling of the Global Financial Cycle and avenues for future research.]]></description><author>Silvia Miranda-Agrippino, Hélène Rey</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29327</guid></item><item><title>Low Inflation Bends the Phillips Curve around the World</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29323</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kristin Forbes, Joseph Gagnon, Christopher G. Collins.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper finds strong support for a Phillips curve that becomes nonlinear when inflation is “low”—which our baseline model defines as less than 3 percent. The nonlinear curve is steep when output is above potential (slack is negative), but flat when output is below potential (slack is positive), so that further increases in economic slack have little effect on inflation. This finding is consistent with evidence of downward nominal wage and price rigidity. When inflation is high, the Phillips curve is linear and relatively steep. These results are robust to placing the threshold between the high and low inflation regimes at 2, 3, or 4 percent inflation or for a threshold based on country-specific medians of inflation. In this nonlinear model, international factors play a large role in explaining headline inflation (albeit less so for core inflation), a role that has been increasing since the global financial crisis.]]></description><author>Kristin Forbes, Joseph Gagnon, Christopher G. Collins</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29323</guid></item><item><title>Demand Composition and the Strength of Recoveries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29304</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Beraja, Christian K. Wolf.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We argue that recoveries from demand-driven recessions with expenditure cuts concentrated in services or non-durables will tend to be weaker than recoveries from recessions more biased towards durables. Intuitively, the smaller the bias towards more durable goods, the less the recovery is buffeted by pent-up demand. We show that, in a standard multi-sector business-cycle model, this prediction holds if and only if, following an aggregate demand shock to all categories of spending (e.g., a monetary shock), expenditure on more durable goods reverts back faster. This testable condition receives ample support in U.S. data. We then use (i) a semi-structural shift-share and (ii) a structural model to quantify this effect of varying demand composition on recovery dynamics, and find it to be large. We also discuss implications for optimal stabilization policy.]]></description><author>Martin Beraja, Christian K. Wolf</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29304</guid></item><item><title>The Sahm Rule and Predicting the Great Recession Across OECD Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29300</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We examine the start date of the Great Recession across OECD countries based on two successive quarters of negative GDP growth recession.  For most OECD countries this establishes the start of recession in Q22008 or Q32008.  We find that the Sahm Rule identifies the start of recession in the US to the beginning of 2008 but in other OECD countries it identifies the start in almost every case, after that identified by GDP.  But the GDP and labor market data are subject to major revisions, so the turn is not apparent in most countries for some time.  We establish our own rule for predicting recession using the fear of unemployment series to predict recession.  It involves looking for a ten-point rise in the series compared to its previous twelve month low.  These surveys are timely and have the major advantage they are not subject to revision. Across the OECD we confirm this finding with other types of qualitative data and especially so in the UK.  Qualitative surveys, we show, in the US in 2006 and 2007 predicted the subsequent recession and they did the same in Europe at the end of 2007 and in the early part of 2008.]]></description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29300</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Policy in the Age of COVID: Does it ‘Get in all of the Cracks?’</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, Ṣebnem Kalemli-Özcan, Veronika Penciakova, Nick Sander.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study the effects of fiscal policy in response to the COVID-19 pandemic at the firm, sector, country and global level. First, we estimate the impact of COVID-19 and policy responses on small and medium sized enterprise (SME) business failures. We combine firm-level financial data from 50 sectors in 27 countries, a detailed I-O network, real-time data on lockdown policies and mobility patterns, and a rich model of firm behavior that allows for several dimensions of heterogeneity. We find: (a) Absent government support, the failure rate of SMEs would have increased by 9 percentage points, significantly more so in emerging market economies (EMs). With policy support it only increased by 4.3 percentage points, and even decreased in advanced economies (AEs). (b) Fiscal policy was poorly targeted: most of the funds disbursed went to firms who did not need it. (c) Nevertheless, we find little evidence of the policy merely postponing mass business failures or creating many ‘zombie’ firms: failure rates rise only slightly in 2021 once policy support is removed. Next, we build a tractable global intertemporal general equilibrium I-O model with fiscal policy. We calibrate the model to 64 countries and 36 sectors. We find that: (d) a sizable share of the global economy is demand-constrained under COVID-19, especially so in EMs. (e) Globally, fiscal policy helped offset about 8% of the downturn in COVID, with a low ‘traditional’ fiscal multiplier. Yet it significantly reduced the share of demand- constrained sectors, preserving employment in these sectors. (f) Fiscal policy exerted small and negative spillovers to output in other countries but positive spillovers on employment. (g) A two-speed recovery would put significant upwards pressure on global interest rates which imposes an additional headwind on the EM recovery. (h) Corporate and sovereign spreads rise when global rates increase, suggesting that EM may face challenging external funding conditions as AEs economies normalize.]]></description><author>Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, Ṣebnem Kalemli-Özcan, Veronika Penciakova, Nick Sander</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</guid></item><item><title>Sorting with Team Formation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29290</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Job Boerma, Aleh Tsyvinski, Alexander P. Zimin.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We fully solve an assignment problem with heterogeneous firms and multiple heterogeneous workers whose skills are imperfect substitutes, that is, when production is submodular. We show that sorting is neither positive nor negative and is characterized sufficiently by two regions. In the first region, mediocre firms sort with mediocre workers and coworkers such that output losses are equal across all these pairings (complete mixing). In the second region, high skill workers sort with a low skill coworker and a high productivity firm, while high productivity firms employ a low skill worker and a high skill coworker (pairwise countermonotonicity). The equilibrium assignment is also necessarily characterized by product countermonotonicity, meaning that sorting is negative for each dimension of heterogeneity with the product of heterogeneity in the other dimensions. The equilibrium assignment as well as wages and firm values are completely characterized in closed form. We illustrate our theory with an application to show that our model is consistent with the observed dispersion of earnings within and across U.S. firms. Our counterfactual analysis gives evidence that the change in the firm project distribution between 1981 and 2013 has a larger effect on the observed change in earnings dispersion than the change in the worker skill distribution.]]></description><author>Job Boerma, Aleh Tsyvinski, Alexander P. Zimin</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29290</guid></item><item><title>Human Frictions in the Transmission of Economic Policies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Many consumers below the top of the distribution of a representative population by cognitive abilities barely react to  monetary and fiscal policies that aim to stimulate consumption and borrowing, even when they are financially unconstrained and despite substantial debt capacity. Differences in income, formal education levels, economic expectations, and a large set of registry-based demographics do not explain these facts. Heterogeneous cognitive abilities thus act as human frictions in the transmission of economic policies that operate through the household sector and might imply  redistribution from low- to high-cognitive-ability agents. We conclude by discussing how our findings inform the microfoundation of behavioral macroeconomic theory.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</guid></item><item><title>Diverse Policy Committees Can Reach Underrepresented Groups</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Francesco D’Acunto, Andreas Fuster, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Increasing the diversity of policy committees has taken center stage worldwide, but whether and why diverse committees are more effective is still unclear. In a randomized control trial that varies the salience of female and minority representation on the Federal Reserve’s monetary policy committee, the FOMC, we test whether diversity affects how Fed information influences consumers’ subjective beliefs. Women and Black respondents form unemployment expectations more in line with FOMC forecasts and trust the Fed more after this intervention. Women are also more likely to acquire Fed-related information when associated with a female official. White men, who are overrepresented on the FOMC, do not react negatively. Heterogeneous taste for diversity can explain these patterns better than homophily. Our results suggest more diverse policy committees are better able to reach underrepresented groups without inducing negative reactions by others, thereby enhancing the effectiveness of policy communication and public trust in the institution.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Andreas Fuster, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</guid></item><item><title>The Geography of Unemployment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adrien Bilal.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Unemployment rates differ widely across local labor markets. I offer new empirical evidence that high local unemployment emerges because of elevated local job losing rates. Local employers, rather than local workers, account for most of spatial gaps in job stability. I then propose a theory in which spatial differences in job loss arise endogenously, due to the spatial sorting of heterogeneous employers across local labor markets.  Labor market frictions induce productive employers to over-value locating close to each other. The optimal policy incentivizes them to relocate to areas with high job losing rates, providing a rationale for commonly used place-based policies. I estimate the model using French administrative data. The estimated model accounts for over three fourths of the cross-sectional dispersion in unemployment rates, as well as for the respective contributions of job losing and job finding rates. Employers' inefficient location choices amplify spatial unemployment differentials five-fold. Both real-world and optimal place-based policies can yield sizable local and aggregate welfare gains.]]></description><author>Adrien Bilal</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29269</guid></item></channel></rss>