<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Environment</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Environment</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 15:36:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Exposures and Behavioral Responses to Wildfire Smoke</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29380</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> The impacts of environmental change on human outcomes often depend on local exposures and behavioral responses that are challenging to observe with traditional administrative or sensor data. We show how data from private pollution sensors, cell phones, social media posts, and internet search activity yield new insights on exposures and behavioral responses during large wildfire smoke events across the US, a rapidly-growing environmental stressor. Health-protective behavior, mobility, and sentiment all respond to increasing ambient wildfire smoke concentrations, but responses differ by income.  Indoor pollution monitors provide starkly different estimates of likely personal exposure during smoke events than would be inferred from traditional ambient outdoor sensors, with similar outdoor pollution levels generating &gt;20x differences in average indoor PM2.5 concentrations. Our results suggest that the current policy reliance on self protection to mitigate health risks in the face of rising smoke exposure will result in modest and unequal benefits.]]></description><author>Marshall Burke, Sam Heft-Neal, Jessica Li, Anne Driscoll, Patrick W. Baylis, Matthieu Stigler, Joakim Weill, Jennifer Burney, Jeff Wen, Marissa Childs, Carlos Gould</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29380</guid></item><item><title>Economic Production and Biodiversity in the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29357</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Species extinctions and ecological degradation are accelerating to a degree unprecedented in human history. We present causal evidence on the economic drivers of biodiversity loss using a novel panel dataset on the types and quantities of wildlife at thousands of locations across the U.S. from 1960-2015. Exploiting fiscal and regulatory shocks to local economic output, we document large, negative impacts of GDP on abundance and diversity of species spanning multiple taxa. The adverse effects of production are mitigated by conservation and air emission abatement efforts, which points toward habitat losses and pollution as underlying contributors to contemporaneous biodiversity declines.]]></description><author>Yuanning Liang, Ivan J. Rudik, Eric Zou</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29357</guid></item><item><title>Environmental Drivers of Agricultural Productivity Growth: CO2 Fertilization of US Field Crops</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29320</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We assess the CO2 fertilization effect on US agriculture using spatially-varying CO2 data from NASA's Orbiting Carbon Observatory-2 (OCO-2) satellite covering the majority of US cropland under actual growing conditions. This study complements the many CO2 enrichment experiments that have found important interactions between CO2 and local environmental conditions in controlled settings.  We use three empirical strategies: (i) a panel of CO2 anomalies and county yields, (ii) a panel of spatial first-differences between neighboring counties, and (iii) a cross-sectional spatial first-difference. We find consistently high fertilization effects: a 1 ppm increase in CO2 equates to a 0.5%, 0.6%, and 0.8% yield increase for corn, soybeans, and wheat, respectively. Viewed retrospectively, 10%, 30%, and 40% of each crop's yield improvements since 1940 are attributable to rising CO2.]]></description><author>Charles A. Taylor, Wolfram Schlenker</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29320</guid></item><item><title>Social and Financial Incentives for Overcoming a Collective Action Problem</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29294</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Addressing public health externalities often requires community-level collective action. Each person’s sanitation behavior can affect the health of neighbors. We report on a cluster randomized controlled trial conducted with 19,000 households in rural Bangladesh where we randomized (1) either group financial incentives or a non-financial “social recognition” reward, and (2) asking each household to make either a private pledge or a public pledge to maintain hygienic latrines. The group financial reward has the strongest impact in the short term (3 months), inducing a 7.5-12.5 percentage point increase in hygienic latrine ownership. Getting people to publicly commit to maintaining and using a hygienic latrine in front of their neighbors induced a 4.2-6.1 percentage point increase in hygienic latrine ownership in the short term. In the medium term (15 months), the effect of the financial reward dissipates while the effect of the public commitment persists. Neither social recognition nor private commitments produce effects statistically distinguishable from zero.]]></description><author>M. Mehrab Bakhtiar, Raymond Guiteras, James A. Levinsohn, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29294</guid></item><item><title>Energy and Environmental Markets, Industrial Organization, and Regulation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29235</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This paper discusses contributions that industrial organization economists have made to our understanding of energy markets and environmental regulation. We emphasize the substantive contributions of recent papers while also highlighting how this literature has adopted and sometimes augmented theoretical and empirical tools from industrial organization. Many of the topics examined by this literature—especially auctions, investment, productivity and innovation, and regulation—also apply to a variety of settings beyond energy and the environment. We also indicate areas where future research is likely to be fruitful, with an emphasis on how industrial organization economists can help inform energy and environmental policies.]]></description><author>Ryan Kellogg, Mar Reguant</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29235</guid></item><item><title>How Economic Development Influences the Environment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29191</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Reducing global poverty and addressing climate change and other environmental crises are among the most important challenges facing humanity today. This review article discusses one way in which these problems are intertwined: economic development affects the environment. I synthesize recent microempirical research on the environmental effects of economic development in low- and middle-income countries. The studies that I discuss identify the causal effects of specific aspects of economic development such as greater household purchasing power, expanded access to credit, more secure property rights, technological progress, and stronger regulatory capacity. I conclude by outlining some gaps in the literature.]]></description><author>Seema Jayachandran</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29191</guid></item><item><title>The Value of Statistical Life: A Meta-analysis of Meta-analyses</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29185</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The Value of Statistical Life (VSL) is arguably the most important number in benefit-cost analyses of environmental, health, and transportation policies.  However, agencies have used a wide range of VSL values.  One reason may be the embarrassment of riches when it comes to VSL studies.  While meta-analysis is a standard way to synthesize information across studies, we now have multiple competing meta-analyses and reviews.  Thus, to analysts, picking one such meta-analysis may feel as hard as picking a single "best study."  This paper responds by taking the meta-analysis another step, estimating a meta-analysis (or mixture distribution) of six meta-analyses.  The baseline model yields a central VSL of $7.0m, with a 90% confidence interval of $2.4m to $11.2m.  The provided code allows users to easily change subjective weights on the studies, add new studies, or change adjustments for income, inflation, and latency.]]></description><author>H. Spencer Banzhaf</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29185</guid></item><item><title>A Watershed Moment: The Clean Water Act and Infant Health</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29152</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The Clean Water Act (CWA) significantly improved surface water quality, but at a cost exceeding the estimated benefits. We quantify the effect of the CWA on a direct measure of health and incorporate health benefits into a cost-benefit analysis. Using a difference-in-differences framework, we compare health upstream and downstream from wastewater treatment facilities before and after CWA grant receipt. Pollution only decreased downstream from facilities required to upgrade their treatment technology, and we leverage this additional variation with a triple difference. CWA grants increased average birth weight by 8 grams. A back-of-the-envelope calculation bounds infant health benefits below $29 billion.]]></description><author>Patrick Flynn, Michelle M. Marcus</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29152</guid></item><item><title>North-South Displacement Effects of Environmental Regulation: The Case of Battery Recycling</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29146</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This study examines the effect of a tightening of the U.S. air-quality standard for lead in 2009 on the relocation of battery recycling to Mexico and on infant health in Mexico. In the U.S., airborne lead dropped sharply near affected plants, most of which were battery-recycling plants. Exports of used batteries to Mexico rose markedly. In Mexico, production increased at battery-recycling plants, relative to comparable industries, and birth outcomes deteriorated within two miles of those plants, relative to areas slightly farther away. The case provides a salient example of a pollution-haven effect between a developed and a developing country.]]></description><author>Shinsuke Tanaka, Kensuke Teshima, Eric Verhoogen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29146</guid></item><item><title>What Do You Think About Climate Finance?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29136</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We survey 861 finance academics, professionals, and public sector regulators and policy economists about climate finance topics. They identify regulatory risk as the top climate risk to businesses and investors over the next five years, but they view physical risks as the top risk over the next 30 years. By an overwhelming margin, respondents believe that asset prices underestimate climate risks. We also tabulate opinions about the correlation between growth and climate change; social discount rates appropriate for projects that mitigate the effects of climate change; most influential forces for reducing climate risks; and, most important research topics.]]></description><author>Johannes Stroebel, Jeffrey Wurgler</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29136</guid></item><item><title>Soaking Up the Sun: Battery Investment, Renewable Energy, and Market Equilibrium</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29133</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We develop a dynamic competitive equilibrium model of battery adoption and operations to evaluate the social value and adoption trajectory of utility-scale batteries and examine policy counterfactuals. The first battery unit breaks even in 2027 when renewable energy share reaches 52% and expected capital costs are $259/kWh.  While the competitive market will install 10 MWh by 2030, competitive adoption does not reach 5,000 MWh until 2043 because the marginal value of investment sharply declines in aggregate capacity. California's 1,300 MW battery mandate implies subsidies of 49% and creates deadweight losses of $433 million relative to a competitive battery market.]]></description><author>R. Andrew Butters, Jackson Dorsey, Gautam Gowrisankaran</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29133</guid></item></channel></rss>