<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Market Structure and Firm Performance</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Market Structure and Firm Performance</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 17:40:00 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Electricity Price Distributions in Future Renewables-Dominant Power Grids and Policy Implications</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29510</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Future electricity systems with tight constraints on carbon emissions will rely much more on wind and solar generation, with zero marginal cost, than today. We use capacity expansion modelling of Texas in 2050 to illustrate wholesale price distributions in future energy-only, carbon-constrained grids without price caps under a range of technology/system assumptions. Tightening carbon emissions constraints dramatically increases the frequency of very low prices. The frequency of high prices also increases, and all resources earn the bulk of their energy market revenues in relatively few hours. The presence of demand response, long-duration energy storage, dispatchable low-carbon generation, or a robust market for hydrogen for non-electricity use (and for energy storage) weakens but does not undo these results. Financial instruments to hedge price volatility will consequently be more costly and it is likely that we will need to redesign capacity remuneration mechanisms to provide adequate incentives for optimal investment in VRE generation and, particularly, storage. In order to encourage economy-wide electrification, the marginal retail price of electricity should be low whenever the wholesale price is low.  With automated control of demand via demand response contracts, the risks of price volatility faced by retail customers can be mitigated without sacrificing efficiency. To encourage economy-wide electrification, the marginal retail price of electricity should be low when the wholesale spot price is low. We discuss ways of reducing consumers’ risk in this world while providing adequate investment incentives.]]></description><author>Dharik S. Mallapragada, Cristian Junge, Cathy Xun Wang, Johannes Pfeifenberger, Paul L. Joskow, Richard Schmalensee</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29510</guid></item><item><title>Organizational Structure and Pricing: Evidence from a Large U.S. Airline</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29508</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We study how organizational boundaries affect pricing decisions using comprehensive data from a large U.S. airline. We document that the firm's advanced pricing algorithm, utilizing inputs from different organizational teams, is subject to multiple biases. To quantify the impacts of these biases, we estimate a structural demand model using sales and search data. We recover the demand curves the firm believes it faces using forecasting data. In counterfactuals, we show that correcting biases introduced by organizational teams individually have little impact on market outcomes, but coordinating organizational outcomes leads to higher prices/revenues and increased dead-weight loss in the markets studied.]]></description><author>Ali Hortaçsu, Olivia R. Natan, Hayden Parsley, Timothy Schwieg, Kevin R. Williams</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29508</guid></item><item><title>Population Growth and Firm Dynamics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29424</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Population growth has declined markedly in almost all major economies since the 1970s. We argue this trend has important consequences for the process of firm dynamics and aggregate growth. We study a rich semi-endogenous growth model of firm dynamics, and show analytically that a decline in population growth reduces creative destruction, increases average firm size and concentration, raises market power and misallocation, and lowers aggregate growth in the long-run. We also show lower population growth has positive effects on the level of productivity, making the short-run welfare impacts ambiguous. In a quantitative application to the U.S, we find that the slowdown in population growth since the 1980s and the projected continuation of this trend accounts for a substantial share of the fall in the entry and exit rates and the increase in firm size. By contrast, the impact on markups is modest. The effect on aggregate growth is positive for around two decades, before turning negative thereafter.]]></description><author>Michael Peters, Conor Walsh</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29424</guid></item><item><title>Preemptive Entry and Technology Diffusion: The Market for Drive-in Theaters</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29408</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the role and incidence of entry preemption strategic motives on the dynamics of new industries, while providing an empirical test for entry preemption, and quantifying its impact on market structure. The empirical context is the evolution of the U.S. drive-in theater market between 1945 and 1957. We exploit a robust prediction of dynamic entry games to test for preemption incentives: the deterrence effect of entering early is only relevant for firms in markets of intermediate size. Potential entrants in small and large markets face little uncertainty about the actual number of firms that will eventually enter. This leads to a non-monotonic relationship between market size and the probability of observing an early entrant. We find robust empirical support for this prediction using a large cross-section of markets. We then estimate the parameters of a dynamic entry game that matches the reduced-form prediction and quantify the strength of the preemption incentive. Our counterfactual analysis shows that strategic motives can increase the number of early entrants by as much as 50 percent in mid-size markets without affecting the number of firms in the long run. By causing firms to enter the market too early, we show that strategic entry preemption leads on average to a 5% increase in entry costs and a 1% decrease in firms' expected value (relative to an environment without strategic investments).]]></description><author>Ricard Gil, Jean-François Houde, Shilong Sun, Yuya Takahashi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29408</guid></item><item><title>The Human Side of Structural Transformation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We document that nearly half of the global decline in agricultural employment during the 20th-century was driven by new cohorts entering the labor market. A newly compiled dataset of policy reforms supports an interpretation of these cohort effects as human capital. Through the lens of a model of frictional labor reallocation, we conclude that human capital growth, both as a mediating factor and as an independent driver, led to a sharp decline in the agricultural labor supply. This decline accounts, at fixed prices, for 40% of the decrease in agricultural employment. This aggregate effect is roughly halved in general equilibrium.]]></description><author>Tommaso Porzio, Federico Rossi, Gabriella V. Santangelo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29390</guid></item><item><title>School Food Policy Affects Everyone: Retail Responses to the National School Lunch Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29384</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We study the private market response to the National School Lunch Program, documenting economically meaningful spillovers to non-recipients. We focus on the Community Eligibility Provision (CEP), an expansion of the lunch program under the 2010 Healthy, Hunger-Free Kids Act. Under the CEP, participating schools offer free lunch to all students. We leverage both the staggered roll-out and eligibility criterion for the CEP, which is limited to schools where at least 40% of students participate in other means-tested welfare programs. We find that local adoption of the CEP causes households with children to reduce their grocery purchases, leading to a 10% decline in grocery sales at large retail chains. Retailers respond with chain-level price adjustments: chains with the most exposure lower prices by 2.5% across all outlets in the years following adoption, so that the program's welfare benefits propagate spatially. Using a stylized model of grocery demand, we estimate that, by 2016, the indirect benefit had reduced grocery costs for the median household by approximately 4.5%.]]></description><author>Jessie Handbury, Sarah Moshary</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29384</guid></item><item><title>From Just in Time, to Just in Case, to Just in Worst-Case: Simple models of a Global Supply Chain under Uncertain Aggregate Shocks.</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29345</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Covid-19 highlighted the weaknesses in the supply chain. Many have argued that a more resilient or robust supply chain is needed. But what does a robust supply chain mean? And how do firms’ decisions change when taken that approach? This paper studies a very stylized model of a supply chain, where we study how the decision of a multinational corporation changes in the presence of uncertainty. The two standard theories of supply chain are Just-in-time and Just-in-case. Just-in-time argues in favor of pursuing efficiency, while Just-in-case studies how such decision changes when the firm faces idiosyncratic risk. We find that a robust supply chain is very different specially in the presence of systemic shocks. In this case, firms need to concentrate on the worst-case. This strategy implies a supply chain where the allocation of resources and capabilities does not correspond to the standard theories studied in economics, but follow a heuristic behavioral rule called “probability matching”. It has been found in nature and in experimental research that subjects appeal to probability matching when seeking survival. We find that a robust supply chain will reproduce this behavioral outcome. In fact, a multinational optimizing under uncertainty, follows a probability matching which leads to an allocation that is suboptimal from the individual producer point of view, but rules out the possibility of supply disruptions.]]></description><author>Bomin Jiang, Daniel E. Rigobon, Roberto Rigobon</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29345</guid></item><item><title>Dynamics of Large Multinationals</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29317</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We develop a model of large multinational enterprises, each one producing a continuum of products. These outsized firms compete as oligopolists in a domestic and foreign market, facing competitive pressure from single-product firms that engage in monopolistic competition. The multinational enterprises invest in R&amp;D in order to expand the span of their products and in foreign direct investment (FDI) in order to expand the range of products manufactured by their foreign affiliates. We study the dynamic evolution of these markets and characterize transition dynamics and steady states. In addition to the evolution of product spans, we characterize the evolution of prices, markups, market shares, and exports relative to subsidiary sales. Furthermore, we study comparative dynamics that result from changes in trade costs, R&amp;D costs, the cost of FDI and productivity changes of the multinational firms.]]></description><author>Elhanan Helpman, Benjamin C. Niswonger</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29317</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic Strategic Corporate Finance: A Tug of War with Financial Frictions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29310</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Access to capital markets plays a key role for the evolution of an industry over time. We develop a benchmark theoretical setting that integrates core corporate finance insights about the impact of financial frictions on investment with those from industrial organization on dynamic competition and industry evolution under perfect capital markets. Using state of the art computational tools to systematically detect and evaluate multiple equilibria and to thoroughly explore the parameter space of our model, we show how, depending on key industry characteristics such as market size, financial frictions impact firms' pricing and investment strategies and the degree of industry concentration.]]></description><author>Ulrich Doraszelski, João F. Gomes, Felix Nockher</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29310</guid></item><item><title>Why Don’t Elite Colleges Expand Supply?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29309</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> While college enrollment has more-than doubled since 1970, elite colleges have barely increased supply, instead reducing admit rates. We show that straightforward reasons cannot explain this behavior. We propose a model where colleges compete on prestige, measured using relative selectivity or relative admit rates. A key comparative static of the model is that higher demand decreases [increases] the admit rate when the weight on prestige is above [below] a critical value, consistent with experience in elite [non-elite] colleges. A calibrated version of the model closely replicates the pattern in the data of declining admit rates at elite colleges while counter-factual simulations without prestige fail. Prestige competition is inefficient. Allowing elite colleges to collude on admissions strategy internalizes the non-pecuniary prestige externality and is Pareto improving.]]></description><author>Peter Q. Blair, Kent Smetters</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29309</guid></item><item><title>Technology Adoption and Market Allocation:The Case of Robotic Surgery</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29301</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> The adoption of healthcare technology is central to improving productivity in this sector. To provide new evidence on how technology affects healthcare markets, we focus on one area where adoption has been particularly rapid: surgery for prostate cancer. Over just six years, robotic surgery grew to become the dominant intensive prostate cancer treatment method. Using a difference-in-differences design, we show that adopting a robot drives prostate cancer patients to the hospital. To test whether this result reflects market expansion or business stealing, we also consider market-level effects of adoption and find they are significant but smaller, suggesting that adoption expands the market while also reallocating some patients across hospitals. Marginal patients are relatively young and healthy, inconsistent with the concern that adoption broadens the criteria for intervention to patients who would gain little from it. We conclude by discussing implications for the social value of technology diffusion in healthcare markets.]]></description><author>Danea Horn, Adam Sacarny, R. Annetta Zhou</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29301</guid></item><item><title>Structural Empirical Analysis of Contracting in Vertical Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29282</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This chapter presents an overview of advances in the structural analysis of contracting in vertical markets over the past fifteen years. We provide a discussion of theoretical models of contracting and bargaining that form the basis of recent empirical work, and then present common approaches used by researchers to take these models to the data. We also briefly survey the structural empirical literature on topics in vertical markets (including horizontal and vertical mergers, price discrimination, and nonlinear and exclusionary contracts), and conclude with a discussion of potential topics for future research.]]></description><author>Robin S. Lee, Michael D. Whinston, Ali Yurukoglu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29282</guid></item><item><title>Signaling in Online Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29268</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study how signaling affects equilibrium outcomes and welfare in an online credit market using detailed data on loan characteristics and borrower repayment. We build and estimate an equilibrium model in which a borrower may signal her default risk through the reserve interest rate. Comparing a market with and without signaling relative to the benchmark with no asymmetric information, we find that adverse selection destroys as much as 34% of total surplus, up to 78% of which can be restored with signaling. We also estimate backward-bending supply curves for some markets, consistent with the prediction of Stiglitz &amp; Weiss (1981).]]></description><author>Kei Kawai, Ken Onishi, Kosuke Uetake</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29268</guid></item><item><title>Frictions in Product Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29259</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This is an invited chapter for the forthcoming Volume 4 of the Handbook of Industrial Organization. We focus on markets with frictions, such as transaction costs, asymmetric information, search and matching frictions. We discuss how such frictions affect allocations, favor the emergence of intermediaries or dealers, and potentially create market power. Our focus is mostly on markets with many participants rather than on transactions that are bilateral or involve a small number of players.]]></description><author>Alessandro Gavazza, Alessandro Lizzeri</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29259</guid></item><item><title>Empirical Models of Demand and Supply in Differentiated Products Industries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29257</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This is an invited chapter for the forthcoming Volume 4 of the Handbook of Industrial Organization. We present empirical models of demand and supply in differentiated products industries with an emphasis on the key ideas arising from the recent applied literature. We start with a discussion of the challenges in modeling and estimation of demand for  differentiated products, and focus on discrete choice characteristics-based demand models that address these challenges while allowing enough flexibility to capture realistic substitution patterns. Our discussion emphasizes how empirical strategies can leverage different features of data depending on the sources of variation that are commonly found in applied work. Moving to the supply-side, we show how demand estimates combined with a pricing model, can be used to recover markups and marginal costs. We also show how the model of pricing can be tested. We discuss a baseline Bertrand-Nash model of competitive pricing, and expand it to cover a) coordinated pricing, b) wholesale relationships, and c) bargaining. We end the chapter with extensions of the demand model, including dynamic and continuous demand.]]></description><author>Amit Gandhi, Aviv Nevo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29257</guid></item><item><title>Hub and Spoke Cartels: Theory and Evidence from the Grocery Industry</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29253</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Numerous recently uncovered cartels operated along the supply chain, with firms at one end facilitating collusion at the other – hub-and-spoke arrangements. These cartels are hard to rationalize because they induce double marginalization and higher costs. We examine Canada’s alleged bread cartel and provide the first comprehensive analysis of hub-and-spoke collusion. We make three contributions: i) Using court documents and pricing data we provide evidence that collusion existed at both ends of the supply chain, ii) we show that collusion was effective, increasing inflation by about 40% and iii) we provide a model explaining why this form of collusion arose.]]></description><author>Robert Clark, Ignatius Horstmann, Jean-François Houde</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29253</guid></item><item><title>Harms of AI</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29247</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This essay discusses several potential economic, political and social costs of the current path of AI technologies. I argue that if AI continues to be deployed along its current trajectory and remains unregulated, it may produce various social, economic and political harms. These include: damaging competition, consumer privacy and consumer choice; excessively automating work, fueling inequality, inefficiently pushing down wages, and failing to improve worker productivity; and damaging political discourse, democracy's most fundamental lifeblood. Although there is no conclusive evidence suggesting that these costs are imminent or substantial, it may be useful to understand them before they are fully realized and become harder or even impossible to reverse, precisely because of AI's promising and wide-reaching potential. I also suggest that these costs are not inherent to the nature of AI technologies, but are related to how they are being used and developed at the moment - to empower corporations and governments against workers and citizens. As a result, efforts to limit and reverse these costs may need to rely on regulation and policies to redirect AI research. Attempts to contain them just by promoting competition may be insufficient.]]></description><author>Daron Acemoglu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29247</guid></item><item><title>Flagship Entry in Online Marketplaces</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29239</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> In the world of omnichannel retail, some brands open a flagship store at online marketplaces, while others avert it. Focusing on a large e-commerce platform, we empirically study how flagship entry affects consumers, the platform, and various sellers on the platform.<br />
We find flagship entry may benefit consumers by expanding the choice set, by intensifying price competition within the entry brand, and by improving consumer perception for parts of the platform. In the meantime, flagship entry cannibalizes the sales of same-brand sellers, while other brands may gain as the buyer base expands on the platform.<br />
Counterfactual simulation suggests that flagship entry improves the gross merchandise value (GMV) of the platform but hurts existing sellers of the entry brand. On average, the effect on consumer welfare is more positive if the flagship entry is from a non-prominent brand than from a prominent brand, because consumers tend to lower their willingness to pay for individual sellers upon a prominent flagship entry. In hypothetical scenarios where flagship entry were accompanied by constraints on other same-brand sellers, the reduced competition would benefit the flagship store but hurt consumers.]]></description><author>Ginger Zhe Jin, Zhentong Lu, Xiaolu Zhou, Lu Fang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29239</guid></item><item><title>An Industrial Organization Perspective on Productivity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29229</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This chapter overviews productivity research from an industrial organization perspective. We focus on what is known and what still needs to be learned about the productivity levels and dynamics of individual producers, but also how these interact through markets and industries to influence productivity aggregates. We overview productivity concepts, facts, data, measurement, analysis, and open questions.]]></description><author>Jan De Loecker, Chad Syverson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29229</guid></item><item><title>The Industrial Organization of Financial Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29183</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This chapter discusses recent developments in the literature involving applications of industrial organization methods to finance. We structure our discussion around a simple model of a financial intermediary that concentrates its attention either on (i) the retail market and hence engages in a traditional maturity transformation business by accepting funds that can be used to invest in risky projects (loans), or (ii) the investment business, financing its operations on the “wholesale” market and making markets or investing in higher return riskier projects. Our discussion is centered around the analysis of market structure and competition in each of these markets, focusing in turn on (i) primary and secondary markets for government and corporate debt, (ii) interbank loans, (iii) markets for retail funding, and (iv) credit markets, including mortgages.]]></description><author>Robert Clark, Jean-François Houde, Jakub Kastl</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29183</guid></item><item><title>Specialized Investments and Firms’ Boundaries: Evidence from Textual Analysis of Patents</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29174</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Inducing firms to make specialized investments through bilateral contracts can be challenging because of potential hold- up problems. Such contracting difficulties have long been argued to be an important reason for acquisitions. To evaluate the extent to which this motivation leads to mergers, we perform a textual analysis of the patents filed by the same lead inventors of the target firms before and after the mergers. We find that patents of inventors from target firms become 28.9% to 46.8% more specific to those of acquirers’ inventors following completed mergers, benchmarked against patents filed by targets and a group of counterfactual acquirers. This pattern is stronger for vertical mergers that are likely to require specialized investments. There is no change in the specificity of patents for mergers that are announced but not consummated. Overall, we provide empirical evidence that contracting issues in motivating specialized investment can be a motive for acquisitions.]]></description><author>Jan Bena, Isil Erel, Daisy Wang, Michael S. Weisbach</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29174</guid></item><item><title>Demand Shocks and Supply Chain Resilience: An Agent Based Modelling Approach and Application to the Potato Supply Chain</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29166</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The food supply chain has experienced major disruptions from both demand and supply sides during the Covid-19 pandemic. While some consequences such as food waste are directly caused by the disruption due to supply chain inefficiency, others are indirectly caused by a change in consumer’s preferences. As a result, evaluating food supply chain resilience is a difficult task. With an attempt to understand impacts of demand on the food supply chain, we developed an agent-based model based on the case of Idaho’s potato supply chain. Results showed that not only the magnitude but also the timing of the demand shock will have different impacts on various stakeholders of the supply chain. Our contribution to the literature is two-fold. First, the model helps explain why food waste and shortages may occur with dramatic shifts in consumer demand. Second, this paper provides a new angle on evaluating the various mitigation strategies and policy responses to disruptions beyond Covid-19.]]></description><author>Liang Lu, Ruby Nguyen, Md Mamunur Rahman, Jason Winfree</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29166</guid></item><item><title>Intermediaries in Bargaining: Evidence from Business-to-Business Used-Car Inventory Negotiations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29159</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We analyze data on tens of thousands of alternating-offer, business-to-business negotiations in the wholesale used-car market, with each negotiation mediated (over the phone) by a third-party company. The data shows the identity of the employee mediating the negotiations. We find that who intermediates the negotiation matters: high-performing mediators are 22.03% more likely to close a deal than low performers. Effective mediators improve bargaining outcomes by helping buyers and sellers come to agreements faster, not by pushing disagreeing parties to persist, and have real effects on efficiency for some negotiations, overcoming some of the inefficiency inherent in incomplete-information settings.]]></description><author>Bradley Larsen, Carol Hengheng Lu, Anthony Lee Zhang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29159</guid></item><item><title>Holding Up Green Energy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29154</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Green energy is produced by relationship-specific assets that are vulnerable to hold-up if contracts are not strictly enforced. I study the role of counterparty risk in the procurement of green energy using data on the universe of solar procurement auctions in India. The Indian context allows clean estimates of how risk affects procurement, because solar power plants set up in the same states, by the same firms, are procured in auctions variously intermediated by either risky states themselves or the central government. I find that: (i) the counterparty risk of an average state increases solar energy prices by 10%; (ii) the intermediation of the central government eliminates this risk premium; (iii) higher prices due to risk reduce investment, because state demand for green energy is elastic. The results suggest that the risk of hold-up places developing countries at a disadvantage in the procurement of green energy.]]></description><author>Nicholas Ryan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29154</guid></item><item><title>Industrial Organization of Health Care Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29137</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> In this paper we outline the tools that have been developed to model and analyze competition and regulation in health care markets, and describe particular papers that apply them to policy-relevant questions. We focus particularly on the I.O. models and empirical methods and analyses that researchers have formulated to address policy-relevant questions, although we also provide an overview of the institutional facts and findings that inform them. We divide the chapter into two broad sections: (i)  papers considering competition and price-setting among insurers and providers and (ii) papers focused specifically on insurance and market design. The former set of papers is largely concerned with models of oligopolistic competition; it is often focused on the US commercial insurance market where prices are market-determined rather than being set administratively. The latter focuses on insurance market design with an emphasis on issues raised by asymmetric information, leading to adverse selection and moral hazard. In addition, we discuss the literature on consumer choice frictions in this market and the significant implications of those frictions for I.O. questions.]]></description><author>Benjamin R. Handel, Kate Ho</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29137</guid></item></channel></rss>