<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER working group Risks of Financial Institutions</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER working group Risks of Financial Institutions</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 13:42:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Big Loans to Small Businesses: Predicting Winners and Losers in an Entrepreneurial Lending Experiment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</link><description>We experimentally study the impact of substantially larger enterprise loans, in collaboration with an Egyptian lender. Larger loans generate small average impacts, but machine learning using psychometric data reveals dramatic heterogeneity. Top-performers (i.e., those with the highest predicted treatment effects) substantially increase profits, whereas profits for poor-performers drop. The magnitude of this difference implies that an individual lender’s credit allocation choices matter for aggregate income. Evidence on two fronts suggests large loans would be misallocated: top-performers are predicted by loan officers to have higher default rates; and, top-performers grow less than others when given small loans, implying that allocating larger loans based on prior performance is not efficient. Our results have important implications for credit expansion policy and our understanding of entrepreneurial talent: on the former, the use of psychometric data to identify top-performers suggests a pathway towards better allocation that revolves around entrepreneurial type more than firm type; on the latter, the reversal of fortune for poor-performers, who do well with small loans but not large, indicates a type of entrepreneur that we call a “go-getter” who performs well when constrained but poorly when not.</description><author>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman</author></item><item><title>Banking-Crisis Interventions, 1257-2019</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29281</link><description>We present a new database of banking-crisis interventions since the 13th century.  The database includes 1886 interventions in 20 categories across 138 countries, covering interventions during all of the crises identified in the main banking-crisis  chronologies, while also cataloguing a large number of interventions outside of  those crises. The data show a gradual shift over the past centuries from the  traditional interventions of a lender-of-last-resort, suspensions of convertibility, and bank holidays, towards a much more prominent role for capital injections and  sweeping guarantees of bank liabilities. Furthermore, intervention frequencies and  sizes suggest that the crisis problem in the financial sector has indeed reached an  apex during the post-Bretton Woods era – but that such trends are part of a more  deeply entrenched development that saw global intervention frequencies and sizes  gradually rise since at least the late 17th century.</description><author>Andrew Metrick, Paul Schmelzing</author></item><item><title>Measuring the Welfare Cost of Asymmetric Information in Consumer Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</link><description>Information asymmetries are known in theory to lead to inefficiently low credit provision, yet empirical estimates of the resulting welfare losses are scarce. This paper leverages a randomized experiment conducted by a large fintech lender to estimate welfare losses arising from asymmetric information in the market for online consumer credit. Building on methods from the insurance literature, we show how exogenous variation in interest rates can be used to estimate borrower demand and lender cost curves and recover implied welfare losses. While asymmetric information generates large equilibrium price distortions, we find only small overall welfare losses, particularly for high-credit-score borrowers.</description><author>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis</author></item><item><title>Misdiagnosing Bank Capital Problems</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29223</link><description>Banks’ reluctance to repair their balance sheets, combined with deposit insurance and regulatory forbearance in recognizing greater risks and losses, can lead to solvency problems that look like liquidity (bank-run) crises. Regulatory forbearance incentivizes banks to both retain risky loans and reject new good opportunities. With sufficient regulatory forbearance, partially-insured banks act exactly as if they are fully insured. Stress tests certify that uninsured creditors will be paid, not that banks are solvent, and have ambiguous effects on the efficiency of investment.</description><author>Jeremy I. Bulow, Paul D. Klemperer</author></item></channel></rss>