<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Monetary Policy</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Monetary Policy</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 14:04:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Human Frictions in the Transmission of Economic Policies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>Many consumers below the top of the distribution of a representative population by cognitive abilities barely react to  monetary and fiscal policies that aim to stimulate consumption and borrowing, even when they are financially unconstrained and despite substantial debt capacity. Differences in income, formal education levels, economic expectations, and a large set of registry-based demographics do not explain these facts. Heterogeneous cognitive abilities thus act as human frictions in the transmission of economic policies that operate through the household sector and might imply  redistribution from low- to high-cognitive-ability agents. We conclude by discussing how our findings inform the microfoundation of behavioral macroeconomic theory.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber</author></item><item><title>Diverse Policy Committees Can Reach Underrepresented Groups</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>Increasing the diversity of policy committees has taken center stage worldwide, but whether and why diverse committees are more effective is still unclear. In a randomized control trial that varies the salience of female and minority representation on the Federal Reserve’s monetary policy committee, the FOMC, we test whether diversity affects how Fed information influences consumers’ subjective beliefs. Women and Black respondents form unemployment expectations more in line with FOMC forecasts and trust the Fed more after this intervention. Women are also more likely to acquire Fed-related information when associated with a female official. White men, who are overrepresented on the FOMC, do not react negatively. Heterogeneous taste for diversity can explain these patterns better than homophily. Our results suggest more diverse policy committees are better able to reach underrepresented groups without inducing negative reactions by others, thereby enhancing the effectiveness of policy communication and public trust in the institution.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Andreas Fuster, Michael Weber</author></item><item><title>Measuring Market Expectations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29232</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>Asset prices are a valuable source of information about financial market participants' expectations about key macroeconomic variables. However, the presence of time-varying risk premia requires an adjustment of market prices to obtain the market's rational assessment of future price and policy developments. This paper reviews empirical approaches for recovering market-based expectations. It starts by laying out the two canonical modeling frameworks that form the backbone for estimating risk premia and highlights the proliferation of risk pricing factors that result in a wide range of different asset-price-based expectation measures. It then describes a key methodological innovation to evaluate the empirical plausibility of risk premium estimates and to identify the most accurate market-based expectation measure. The usefulness of this general approach is illustrated for price expectations in the global oil market. Then, the paper provides an overview of the body of empirical evidence for monetary policy and inflation expectations with a special emphasis on market-specific characteristics that complicate the quest for the best possible market-based expectation measure. Finally, it discusses a number of economic applications where market expectations play a key role for evaluating economic models, guiding policy analysis, and deriving shock measures.]]></description><author>Christiane Baumeister</author></item><item><title>Stabilization with Fiscal Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29226</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>I reconsider the long-standing consensus view that macroeconomic stabilization should rely on monetary policy, not fiscal policy. I use an analytically tractable heterogeneous agent New Keynesian (HANK) model that is parameterized so as to admit a bubble in public debt. In this context, I show that it is possible to stabilize either inflation or output in response to aggregate shocks by varying only fiscal policy (that is, lump-sum uniform transfers). In contrast, when the public debt bubble is large, it is impossible to stabilize either inflation or output by varying only interest rates (monetary policy). The theoretical analysis implies that, in the presence of a large public debt bubble, fiscal policy is a more reliable stabilization tool than monetary policy.]]></description><author>Narayana R. Kocherlakota</author></item><item><title>Market Freezes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29210</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>During the financial crisis apparently centralized markets continued to function while trade in OTC markets froze. We use search-and-bargaining theory to ascertain conditions that allow trade to temporarily freeze in decentralized markets, focusing on the roles of liquidity and self-fulfilling prophecies. We show standard models can have recurrent, belief-driven hot and cold spells, but not freezes and thaws. A simple specification that has freezes assumes negative returns. A more realistic one incorporates information frictions (costly asset-quality verification). Another uses different frictions to get credit freezes. We also discuss policy implications, and go into detail on the nature of OTC markets.]]></description><author>Chao Gu, Guido Menzio, Randall Wright, Yu Zhu</author></item></channel></rss>