<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Financial Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Financial Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 22:16:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Attention, Social Interaction, and Investor Attraction to Lottery Stocks</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29543</link><description><![CDATA[<b>December 2021</b> <p> We find that among stocks dominated by retail investors, the lottery anomaly is amplified by high investor attention (proxied by high analyst coverage, salient earnings surprises, or recency of extreme positive returns) and intense social interactions (proxied by Facebook social connectedness or population density near firm headquarters). Such stocks’ lottery features attract greater Google search volume and retail net buying, followed by more negative earnings surprises and lower announcement-period returns. The findings provide insight into the roles of attention and social interaction in securities markets, and support the hypothesis that these forces contribute to investor attraction to lottery stocks.]]></description><author>Turan G. Bali, David Hirshleifer, Lin Peng, Yi Tang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29543</guid></item><item><title>Unlocking the Benefits of Credit through Saving</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29542</link><description><![CDATA[<b>December 2021</b> <p> Access to microcredit has been shown to generate only modest average benefits for recipient households. We study whether other financial market frictions—in particular, lack of access to a safe place to save—might limit credit's benefits. Working with Kenyan farmers, we cross-randomize access to a simple savings product with a harvest-time loan. Among farmers offered a loan, the additional offer of a savings lockbox increased farm investment by 11% and household consumption by 7%. Results suggest that financial market frictions can interact in important ways and that multifaceted financial access programs might unlock dynamic household gains.]]></description><author>Sanghamitra W. Mukherjee, Lauren F. Bergquist, Marshall Burke, Edward Miguel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29542</guid></item><item><title>Private or Public Equity? The Evolving Entrepreneurial Finance Landscape</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29532</link><description><![CDATA[<b>December 2021</b> <p> The U.S. entrepreneurial finance market has changed dramatically over the last two decades. Entrepreneurs raising their first round of venture capital retain 30% more equity in their firm and are more likely to control their board of directors. Late-stage startups are raising larger amounts of capital in the private markets from a growing pool of traditional and new investors. These private market changes have coincided with a sharp decline in the number of firms going public—and when firms do go public, they are older and have raised more private capital. To understand these facts, we provide a systematic description of the differences between private and public firms. Next, we review several regulatory, technological, and competitive changes affecting both startups and investors that help explain how the trade-offs between going public and staying private have changed. We conclude by listing several open research questions.]]></description><author>Michael Ewens, Joan Farre-Mensa</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29532</guid></item><item><title>The Cost of Consumer Collateral: Evidence from Bunching</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29527</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We show that borrowers are highly sensitive to the requirement of posting their homes as collateral. Using administrative loan application and performance data from the U.S. Federal Disaster Loan Program, we exploit a loan amount threshold above which households must post their residence as collateral. One-third of all borrowers select the maximum uncollateralized loan amount, and our bunching estimates suggest that the median borrower is willing to give up 40% of their loan amount to avoid collateral. Exploiting time variation in the loan amount threshold, we find that collateral causally reduces default rates by 35%. Our results help to explain high perceived default costs in the mortgage market, and uniquely quantify the extent to which collateral reduces moral hazard in consumer credit markets.]]></description><author>Benjamin L. Collier, Cameron Ellis, Benjamin J. Keys</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29527</guid></item><item><title>Sources and Transmission of Country Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29526</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We use textual analysis of earnings conference calls held by listed firms around the world to measure the amount of risk managers and investors at each firm associate with each country at each point in time. Flexibly aggregating this firm-country-quarter-level data allows us to systematically identify spikes in perceived country risk (“crises”) and document their source and pattern of transmission to foreign firms. While this pattern usually follows a gravity structure, it often changes dramatically during crises. For example, while crises originating in developed countries propagate disproportionately to foreign financial firms, emerging market crises transmit less financially and more to traditionally exposed countries. We apply our measures to show that (i) elevated perceptions of a country's riskiness, particularly those of foreign and financial firms, are associated with significant falls in local asset prices, capital outflows, and reductions in firm-level investment and employment. (ii) Risk transmitted from foreign countries affects the investment decisions of domestic firms.  (iii) Heterogeneous currency loadings on perceived global risk can help explain the cross-country pattern of interest rates and currency risk premia.]]></description><author>Tarek Alexander Hassan, Jesse Schreger, Markus Schwedeler, Ahmed Tahoun</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29526</guid></item><item><title>Mistakes in Future Consumption, High MPCs Now</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29517</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> In a canonical intertemporal consumption problem, I show how anticipation of future consumption mistakes leads to higher current marginal propensities to consume (MPCs). This result is driven by mistakes in future consumption's response to saving changes (i.e., changes in asset balances) and is independent of their specific behavioral foundations. My framework can accommodate many widely studied behavioral biases, such as inattention, present bias, diagnostic expectations, and near-rationality (epsilon-mistakes). This channel helps explain the empirical puzzle on high-liquidity consumers' high MPCs and can be significant. The same channel can also help explain other puzzles in intertemporal choices, such as violations of the fungibility principle, excess discounting of future income, and large risk aversion. Methodologically, I develop a general approach to study predictions of sophistication (i.e., the anticipation of future mistakes) independent of the underlying behavioral biases.]]></description><author>Chen Lian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29517</guid></item><item><title>An Economic Model of Consensus on Distributed Ledgers</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29515</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> In recent years, the designs of many new blockchain applications have been inspired by the Byzantine fault tolerance (BFT) problem. While traditional BFT protocols assume that most system nodes are honest (in that they follow the protocol), we recognize that blockchains are deployed in environments where nodes are subject to strategic incentives. This paper develops an economic framework for analyzing such cases. Specifically, we assume that 1) non-Byzantine nodes are rational, so we explicitly study their incentives when participating in a BFT consensus process; 2) non-Byzantine nodes are ambiguity averse, and specifically, Knightian uncertain about Byzantine actions; and 3) decisions/inferences are all based on local information. We thus obtain a consensus game with preplay communications. We characterize all equilibria, some of which feature rational leaders withholding messages from some nodes in order to achieve consensus. These findings enrich those from traditional BFT algorithms, where an honest leader always sends messages to all nodes. We also study how the progress of communication technology (i.e., potential message losses) affects the equilibrium consensus outcome.]]></description><author>Hanna Halaburda, Zhiguo He, Jiasun Li</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29515</guid></item><item><title>Is Hard and Soft Information Substitutable? Evidence from Lockdown</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29513</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We study information substitutability in the financial market through a quasi-natural experiment: the pandemic-triggered lockdown that has hampered people's physical interactions hence the ability to collect, process, and transmit soft information. Exploiting the cross- sectional and time-series variations of lockdown, we investigate how the difficulty to use soft information has prompted a switch to hard information and its implication on fund investment, performance, and risk management. We show that lockdown reduces fund investment in proximate stocks and generates a portfolio rebalancing toward distant stocks. The re- balancing negatively impacts fund performance by reducing fund raw (excess) return of an additional 0.76% (0.29%) per month during lockdown, suggesting that soft and hard information is not easily substitutable. Lastly, we show that soft information originates mainly from physical human interactions, primarily in cafés, restaurants, bars, and fitness centers; and the virtual world based on Zoom/Skype/Team fails to substitute physical interactions fully, thus cannot provide sufficient soft information.]]></description><author>Jennie Bai, Massimo Massa</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29513</guid></item><item><title>Empirical Perspectives on Auctions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29511</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> The empirical analysis of auction data has become a thriving field of research over the past thirty years. Relying on sophisticated models and advanced econometric methods, it addresses a wide range of policy questions for both public and private institutions. This chapter offers a guide to the literature by stressing how data features and policy questions have shaped research in the field. The chapter is organized by types of goods for sale and covers auctions of timber, construction and services procurement, oil and gas leases, online auctions, internet advertising, electricity, financial securities, spectrum, as well as used goods. It discusses the idiosyncrasies of each applied setting and the respective empirical findings.]]></description><author>Ali Hortaçsu, Isabelle Perrigne</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29511</guid></item><item><title>Technological Obsolescence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29504</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> This paper proposes a new measure of technological obsolescence using detailed patent data. Using this measure, we present two sets of results. First, firms' technological obsolescence foreshadows substantially lower growth, productivity, and reallocation of capital. This finding applies mainly for obsolescence of core innovation and embodied innovation, and it is stronger in competitive product markets. Second, in stock markets, high-obsolescence firms under-perform low-obsolescence firms by 7 percent annually. Using analyst forecast data, we show this is due to a systematic overestimation of future profits of obsolescent firms. The measure contains incremental information about firm innovation relative to measures focusing on new innovation.]]></description><author>Song Ma</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29504</guid></item><item><title>Buyouts: A Primer</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29502</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> This paper provides an introduction to buyouts and the academic literature about them. Buyouts are initiated by “buyout funds”, which are limited partnerships raised from mostly institutional investors. The funds earn returns for their investors by improving the operations of the firms they acquire and exiting them for a profit. Buyout funds have grown substantially and currently raise more than $400 billion annually in capital commitments. We first discuss the institutional environment that developed to foster such buyouts and to provide incentives for general partners and firm managers to earn returns for the fund’s investors. We then describe various strategies that funds use to increase the values of their portfolio companies. The paper provides up to date statistics on all aspects of the buyout industry. Finally, we present a summary of the academic literature on buyouts. This literature has paid particular attention to the extent to which buyouts earn risk-adjusted abnormal returns for their investors, as well as the sources of those returns.]]></description><author>Tim Jenkinson, Hyeik Kim, Michael S. Weisbach</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29502</guid></item><item><title>Sovereign Risk and Financial Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29501</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> In this paper, we study the interplay between sovereign risk and global financial risk. We show that a substantial portion of the comovement among sovereign spreads is accounted for by changes in global financial risk. We construct bond-level sovereign spreads for dollar-denominated bonds issued by over 50 countries from 1995 to 2020 and use various indicators to measure global financial risk. Through panel regressions and local projection analysis, we find that an increase in global financial risk causes a large and persistent widening of sovereign bond spreads. These effects are strongest when measuring global risk using the excess bond premium – a measure of the risk-bearing capacity of U.S. financial intermediaries. The spillover effects of global financial risk are more pronounced for speculative-grade sovereign bonds.]]></description><author>Simon Gilchrist, Bin Wei, Vivian Z. Yue, Egon Zakrajšek</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29501</guid></item><item><title>Zero Lower Bound on Inflation Expectations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29496</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We document a new fact: in U.S., European and Japanese surveys, households do not expect deflation, even in environments where persistent deflation is a strong possibility. This fact stands in contrast to the standard macroeconomic models with rational expectations. We extend a standard New Keynesian model with a zero-lower bound on inflation expectations. Unconventional monetary policies, such as forward guidance, are weaker. In liquidity traps, the government spending output multiplier is finite, and adverse aggregate supply shocks are not expansionary. The possibility of confidence-driven liquidity traps is attenuated.]]></description><author>Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Dmitriy Sergeyev</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29496</guid></item><item><title>Learning About the Long Run</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29495</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Forecasts of professional forecasters are anomalous: they are biased, forecast errors are autocorrelated, and forecast revisions predict forecast errors. Sticky or noisy information models seem like unlikely explanations for these anomalies: professional forecasters pay attention constantly and have precise knowledge of the data in question. We propose that these anomalies arise because professional forecasters don’t know the model that generates the data. We show that Bayesian agents learning about hard-to-learn features of the data generating process (low frequency behavior) can generate all the prominent aggregate anomalies emphasized in the literature. We show this for two applications: professional forecasts of nominal interest rates for the sample period 1980-2019 and CBO forecasts of GDP growth for the sample period 1976- 2019. Our learning model for interest rates also provides an explanation for deviations from the expectations hypothesis of the term structure that does not rely on time-variation in risk premia.]]></description><author>Leland Farmer, Emi Nakamura, Jón Steinsson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29495</guid></item><item><title>Collateral Damage: The Impact of Shale Gas on Mortgage Lending</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29494</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We analyze mortgage lenders’ behavior with respect to shale gas risk during the period of the U.S. shale gas boom, which coincided with fluctuations in the U.S. housing market and increased scrutiny in the lending industry.  Shale gas operations have the potential to place affected houses into technical default such that government sponsored enterprises like Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac are unable to maintain them in their portfolios.  We find that lenders changed from being willing to pay $814 on average to avoid one unit of shale risk before the financial distress of 2008 and subsequent increased scrutiny, to $3,137, or 1.6% of profit earned on an average mortgage, afterwards.  Our approach provides an alternative to the traditional property value hedonic measurement of the disamenities associated with shale gas development by looking at the decisions of mortgage professionals.]]></description><author>Yanyou Chen, James W. Roberts, Christopher D. Timmins, Ashley Vissing</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29494</guid></item><item><title>The Prudential Use of Capital Controls and Foreign Currency Reserves</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29476</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We provide a simple framework to study the prudential use of capital controls and currency reserves that have been explored in the recent literature. We cover the role of both pecuniary externalities and aggregate demand externalities. The model features a central policy dilemma for emerging economies facing large capital outflows: the choice between increasing the policy rate to stabilize the exchange rate and decreasing the policy rate to stabilize employment. Ex ante capital controls and reserve accumulation can help mitigate this dilemma. We use our framework to survey the recent literature and provide an overview of recent empirical findings on the use of these policies.]]></description><author>Javier Bianchi, Guido Lorenzoni</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29476</guid></item><item><title>Intermediation and Voluntary Exposure to Counterparty Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29467</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> I study a model of the financial sector in which intermediation among debt financed banks gives rise to an endogenous core-periphery network – few highly interconnected and many sparsely connected banks. Endogenous intermediation generates excessive systemic risk in the financial network. Financial institutions have incentives to capture intermediation spreads through strategic borrowing and lending decisions. By doing so, they tilt the division of surplus along an intermediation chain in their favor, while at the same time reducing aggregate surplus. The network is inefficient relative to a constrained efficient benchmark since banks who make risky investments “overconnect”, exposing themselves to excessive counterparty risk, while banks who mainly provide funding end up with too few connections.]]></description><author>Maryam Farboodi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29467</guid></item><item><title>Scrambling for Dollars: International Liquidity, Banks and Exchange Rates</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29457</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We develop a theory of exchange rate fluctuations arising from financial institutions’ demand for dollar liquid assets. Financial flows are unpredictable and may leave banks “scrambling for dollars.” Because of settlement frictions in interbank markets, a precautionary demand for dollar reserves emerges and gives rise to an endogenous convenience yield on the dollar. We show that an increase in the dollar funding risk leads to a rise in the convenience yield and an appreciation of the dollar, as banks scramble for dollars. We present empirical evidence on the relationship between exchange rate fluctuations for the G10 currencies and the quantity of dollar liquidity, which is consistent with the theory.]]></description><author>Javier Bianchi, Saki Bigio, Charles Engel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29457</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Firm Environmental Performance to Inform Asset Management and Standardized Disclosure</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Investing according to environmental, social, and governance (ESG) criteria is gaining momentum. Most environmental performance indices focus only on the tonnage of carbon dioxide (CO₂) emissions. This paper proposes an index covering eight pollutants expressed in monetary damage. Inclusion of multiple pollutants reflects a broader range of reputational and regulatory risks. Monetization appropriately weights emissions. CO₂ dominates the mass of other pollutants, yet the marginal damages from other pollutants are larger than CO₂. In the U.S. utility sector from 2014 to 2017, indices which only track CO₂ mischaracterize firms’ environmental performance and underestimate its effect on financial outcomes relative to the multipollutant index. Dirtier firms exhibit lower share prices and higher forward returns. The effect is twice as large for the multipollutant index compared to CO₂. Analysts’ earnings forecasts for dirtier firms systematically undershoot actuals. Earnings errors are between three and five times more sensitive to the multipollutant index than to CO₂. The multipollutant index may suggest new management strategies to financial market participants relative to those based on carbon intensity. ESG disclosure standards based on the new index are more likely to affect financial outcomes, capital allocation decisions, and firm behavior than disclosure of carbon intensity.]]></description><author>Nicholas Z. Muller</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</guid></item><item><title>Momentum, Reversals, and Investor Clientele</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29453</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Different share classes on the same firms provide a natural experiment to explore how investor clienteles affect momentum and short-term reversals. Domestic retail investors have a greater presence in Chinese A shares, and foreign institutions are relatively more prevalent in B shares. These differences result from currency conversion restrictions and mandated investment quotas. We find that only B shares exhibit momentum and earnings drift, and only A shares exhibit monthly reversals. Institutional ownership strengthens momentum in B shares. These patterns accord with a setting where momentum is caused by informed investors who underreact to fundamental signals, and short-term reversals represent premia to absorb the demands of noise traders. Overall, our findings confirm that clienteles matter in generating stock return predictability from past returns.]]></description><author>Andy C.W. Chui, Avanidhar Subrahmanyam, Sheridan Titman</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29453</guid></item><item><title>FinTech as a Financial Liberator</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> A binding interest rate cap on household savings is a common form of financial repression in developing economies and typically benefits banks. Using proprietary data from a leading Chinese FinTech company, we study Fintech's role in ending financial repression in China through the introduction of a money market fund with deposit-like features available through an already widely-adopted household payment platform.  Cities and banks whose depositor base is more exposed to FinTech see greater deposit outflows. Importantly, exposed banks respond to FinTech competition by offering competing products with market interest rates. FinTech thus facilitates a bottom-up interest rate liberalization.]]></description><author>Greg Buchak, Jiayin Hu, Shang-Jin Wei</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29448</guid></item><item><title>Nonlinearities and a Pecking Order in Cross-border Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29432</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Nonlinearities arise in international investment because of a pecking order in barriers. Some severe barriers render all others meaningless, and only when they are alleviated do other barriers become important. We show, using quantile regressions designed to model relations at more points than just the conditional mean, how various investment theories hold at different points in the distribution of bilateral cross-border equity holdings. Our results reconcile a number of findings in the literature by highlighting that datasets that focus on different points of the barriers (investment) distribution can naturally lead to different results.]]></description><author>Sara B. Holland, Sergei Sarkissian, Michael Schill, Francis E. Warnock</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29432</guid></item><item><title>Loan Officers Impede Graduation from Microfinance: Strategic Disclosure in a Large Microfinance Institution</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29427</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> One of the most important puzzles in microfinance is the low rate of borrower graduation to larger, more flexible loans. Utilizing observational and experimental data from a large Chilean microfinance institution, we demonstrate that loan officers impede borrower graduation due to common features of their compensation contracts. Our partner lender offers both microloans and larger, more flexible graduation loans, and relies on loan officer endorsements to determine borrower graduation. Loan officers are rewarded for the size of their portfolio and repayment, and so are implicitly penalized when good borrowers graduate. In an experiment designed to isolate strategic disclosure, we modify compensation to reduce this implicit penalty and document that loan officers withheld endorsements of their most qualified borrowers prior to the shift. Graduated borrowers endorsed after the shift are 34% more profitable for our partner lender than those endorsed beforehand. A back-of-the- envelope calculation suggests that strategic behavior of loan officers accounts for $4.8-29.2 billion in lost social value from forgone borrower graduations in microfinance worldwide. Our experimental design may prove useful for other experiments within firms.]]></description><author>Natalia Rigol, Benjamin N. Roth</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29427</guid></item><item><title>FinTech Lending</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29421</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> In this paper, we review the growing literature on FinTech lending – the provision of credit facilitated by technology that improves the customer-lender interaction or lenders’ screening and monitoring of borrowers. FinTech lending has grown rapidly, though in developed economies like the U.S. it still only accounts for a small share of total credit. An increase in convenience and speed appears to have been more central to FinTech lending’s growth than improved screening or monitoring, though there is certainly potential for the latter, as is the case for increased financial inclusion. The COVID-19 pandemic has shown potential vulnerabilities of FinTech lenders, although in certain segments they have displayed rapid growth.]]></description><author>Tobias Berg, Andreas Fuster, Manju Puri</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29421</guid></item><item><title>Value without Employment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29414</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> Young firms' contribution to aggregate employment has been underwhelming. However, a similar trend is not apparent in their contribution to aggregate sales or aggregate stock market capitalization. We study the implications of the arrival of “low marginal - high average” revenue-product-of-labor firms in a stylized model of dynamic firm heterogeneity, and show that the model can account for a large number of facts related to the decline in “business dynamism”. We study the long-term implications of the decline in business dynamism on the economy by providing analytical results that connect the decline in dynamism to the eventual decline of consumption.]]></description><author>Simcha Barkai, Stavros Panageas</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29414</guid></item><item><title>CLO Performance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29410</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> We study the performance of collateralized loan obligations (CLOs) to understand the market imperfections giving rise to these vehicles and their corresponding economic costs. CLO equity tranches earn positive abnormal returns from the risk-adjusted price differential between leveraged loans and CLO debt tranches. Debt tranches offer higher returns than similarly rated corporate bonds, making them attractive to banks and insurers that face risk-based capital requirements. Temporal variation in equity performance highlights the resilience of CLOs to market volatility due to their closed-end structure, long-term funding, and embedded options to reinvest principal proceeds.]]></description><author>Larry Cordell, Michael R. Roberts, Michael Schwert</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29410</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Consequences of the Opium War</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29404</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the economic consequences of the West’s foray into China after the Opium War (1839-42), when Western colonial influence was introduced in dozens of so-called treaty ports. We document a turnaround during the 19th century in the nature of China’s capital markets. Whereas before the Opium War, coastal cities were of relatively minor importance, the treaty port system of the West transformed China into an economy focused on coastal areas and on international trade that aligned with the trading interests of the West. We show, first, that the West had a positive impact on China’s economy during the 19th century. It brought down local interest rates, and regions under Western influence exhibited both higher rates of industry growth and technology adoption. Second, the geographic scope of influence went far beyond the ports, impacting most of China. Interest rates fell by more than a quarter in the immediate vicinity of the ports and still by almost ten percent at distances of 450 kilometers from treaty ports. The development of China was not simply propelled by its own pre-1800 history, or by post-1978 reforms. The nearly 100 years of semi-colonization have shaped China’s economy today as one focused on the coastal areas.]]></description><author>Wolfgang Keller, Carol H. Shiue</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29404</guid></item><item><title>Bank Runs, Fragility, and Credit Easing</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29397</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We present a tractable dynamic macroeconomic model of self-fulfilling bank runs. A bank is vulnerable to a run when a loss of investors' confidence triggers deposit withdrawals and leads the bank to default on its obligations.  We analytically characterize how the vulnerability of an individual bank depends on macroeconomic aggregates and how the number of banks facing a run affects macroeconomic aggregates in turn. In general equilibrium, runs can be partial or complete, depending on aggregate leverage and the dynamics of asset prices. Our normative analysis shows that the effectiveness of credit easing and its welfare implications depend on whether a financial crisis is driven by fundamentals or by self-fulfilling runs.]]></description><author>Manuel Amador, Javier Bianchi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29397</guid></item><item><title>Blockchain Analysis of the Bitcoin Market</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29396</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> In this paper, we provide detailed analyses of the Bitcoin network and its main participants. We build a novel database using a large number of public and proprietary sources to link Bitcoin addresses to real entities and develop an extensive suite of algorithms to extract information about the behavior of the main market participants. We conduct three major pieces of analysis of the Bitcoin eco-system. First, we analyze the transaction volume and network structure of the main participants on the blockchain. Second, we document the concentration and regional composition of the miners which are the backbone of the verification protocol and ensure the integrity of the blockchain ledger. Finally, we analyze the ownership concentration of the largest holders of Bitcoin.]]></description><author>Igor Makarov, Antoinette Schoar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29396</guid></item><item><title>Do Credit Conditions Move House Prices?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29391</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> To what extent did an expansion and contraction of credit drive the 2000s housing boom and bust? The existing literature lacks consensus, with findings ranging from credit having no effect to credit driving most of the house price cycle. We show that the key difference behind these disparate results is the extent to which credit insensitive agents such as landlords and unconstrained savers absorb credit-driven demand, which depends on the degree of segmentation in housing markets. We develop a model with frictional rental markets that allows us to consider cases in between the extremes of no segmentation and perfect segmentation typically assumed in the literature. We argue that the relative elasticities of the price-rent ratio and homeownership with respect to an identified credit shock is a sufficient statistic to measure the degree of segmentation. We estimate this moment using three different credit supply instruments and use it to calibrate our model. Our results reveal that rental markets are highly frictional and closer to fully segmented, which implies large effects of credit on house prices. In particular, changes to credit standards can explain between 34% and 55% of the rise in price-rent ratios over the boom.]]></description><author>Daniel L. Greenwald, Adam Guren</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29391</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Fragility of For-profit Hospitals: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We estimate the likelihood of financial distress of U.S. hospitals in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic using AHA Annual Survey data for 2011-2019 and smartphone mobility data for 2020. We find that while the average likelihood of distress across all hospitals is 28.53 % in 2020, slightly increasing from 2019, for-profit hospitals are much more likely to be distressed. Their average likelihood of financial distress is 39.13 %---a 6.93 percentage point increase from 2019. For-profit hospitals are the main providers of specialty health care services, such as psychiatric and acute long-term care, so their increased likelihood of distress poses a risk to service provision in these specialty areas, and particularly in rural communities. Our prediction model based on mobility data performs very well in sample against actual data and can potentially help policymakers and hospital administrators to monitor financial distress in real-time when case mixes change, or other large shocks materialize.]]></description><author>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</guid></item><item><title>Household Credit as Stimulus? Evidence from Brazil</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> From 2011 to 2014, the Brazilian government conducted a heavily advertised major credit expansion program through government banks as part of its effort to stimulate the economy. Using administrative data on individual-level borrowing and spending, we find that the program led to a substantial rise in borrowing by government employees, especially those with low financial literacy. We trace the impact of credit stimulus on borrowers' consumption through the 2011-16 business cycle, and find that the credit stimulus resulted in higher consumption volatility and lower average consumption over the cycle. Our results suggest a potential downside of using household credit as stimulus in emerging markets.]]></description><author>Gabriel Garber, Atif R. Mian, Jacopo Ponticelli, Amir Sufi</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29386</guid></item><item><title>Immediate and Longer-Term Housing Market Effects of a Major U.S. Airport Closure</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29385</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> A busy airport’s closure has large effects on noise, real estate markets, and neighborhood demographics. Using a unique dataset, we examine the effects of closing Denver’s Stapleton Airport on nearby housing markets. We find evidence of immediate anticipatory price effects upon announcement, but no price changes at closing and little evidence of upward trending prices between announcement and closing. However, after the airport closure, more higher-income and fewer black households moved in, and developers built higher quality houses. Finally, post-closing, these demographic and housing stock changes had substantial housing price effects, even after restricting the sample to pre-existing housing sales.]]></description><author>Jeffrey P. Cohen, Cletus C. Coughlin, Jonas Crews, Stephen L. Ross</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29385</guid></item><item><title>Predicting the Oil Market</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29379</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We study the performance of many traditional and novel, text-based variables for in-sample and out-of-sample forecasting of oil spot, futures, and energy company stock returns, and changes in oil volatility, production, and inventories. After controlling for small-sample biases, we find evidence of in-sample predictability. Our text measures, derived using energy news articles, hold their own against traditional variables. While we cannot identify ex-ante rules for selecting successful out-of-sample forecasters, an analysis of all possible two-variable models reveals out-of-sample performance above that expected under random variation. Our findings provide new directions for identifying robust forecasting models for oil markets, and beyond.]]></description><author>Charles W. Calomiris, Harry Mamaysky, Nida Çakır Melek</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29379</guid></item><item><title>A Factor Model For Option Returns</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29369</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Due to their short lifespans and migrating moneyness, options are notoriously difficult to study with the factor models commonly used to analyze the risk-return trade-off in other asset classes. Instrumented principal components analysis solves this problem by tracking contracts in terms of their pricing-relevant characteristics via time-varying latent factor loadings. We find that a model with three latent factors prices the cross-section of option returns and explains more than 85% of the variation in a panel of monthly S&amp;P 500 option returns from 1996 to 2017. In particular, we show that the IPCA factors can be rationalized via an economically plausible three-factor model consisting of a level, slope and skew factor. Finally, out-of-sample trading strategies based on insights from the IPCA model have significant alpha over previously studied option strategies.]]></description><author>Matthias Buechner, Bryan T. Kelly</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29369</guid></item><item><title>Is Stock Index Membership for Sale?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29365</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> While major stock market indices are followed by large monetary investments, we document that membership decisions for the S&amp;P 500 index have a nontrivial amount of discretion. We show that firms’ purchases of S&amp;P ratings appear to improve their chance of entering the index (but purchases of Moody’s ratings do not). Furthermore, firms tend to purchase more S&amp;P ratings when there are openings in the index membership. Such a pattern is also confirmed by an event study that explores a rule change on index membership in 2002. Finally, discretionary additions exhibit subsequent deterioration in financial performance relative to rule-based additions.]]></description><author>Kun Li, Xin (Kelly) Liu, Shang-Jin Wei</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29365</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Access to Small Business Credit: Evidence from the Paycheck Protection Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We explore the sources of racial disparities in small business lending by studying the $806 billion Paycheck Protection Program (PPP), which was designed to support small business jobs during the COVID-19 pandemic. PPP loans were administered by private lenders but federally guaranteed, largely eliminating unobservable credit risk as a factor in explaining differential lending by race. We document that even after controlling for a firm’s zip code, industry, loan size, PPP approval date, and other characteristics, Black-owned businesses were 12.1 percentage points (70% of the mean) more likely to obtain their PPP loan from a fintech lender than a traditional bank. Among conventional lenders, smaller banks were much less likely to lend to Black-owned firms, while the Top-4 banks exhibited little to no disparity after including controls. We use novel data to show that the disparity is not primarily explained by differences in pre-existing bank or credit relationships, firm financial positions, fintech affinity, or borrower application behavior. In contrast, we document that Black-owned businesses’ higher rate of borrowing from fintechs compared to smaller banks is particularly large in places with high racial animus, pointing to a potential role for discrimination in explaining some of the racial disparities in small business lending. We find evidence that when small banks automate their lending processes, and thus reduce human involvement in the loan origination process, their rate of PPP lending to Black-owned businesses increases, with larger effects in places with more racial animus.]]></description><author>Sabrina T. Howell, Theresa Kuchler, David Snitkof, Johannes Stroebel, Jun Wong</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</guid></item><item><title>What Drives Variation in the U.S. Debt/Output Ratio? The Dogs that Didn't Bark</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29351</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> If the U.S. is on a fiscally sustainable path, then higher U.S. government debt/output ratios should reliably predict higher future surpluses or lower real returns on Treasurys. In the post-war sample, we find no evidence for this. Neither future cash flows nor discount rates account for the variation in the current debt/output ratio. Instead, the future debt/output ratio accounts for most of the variation. Systematic surplus forecast errors can account for part of these findings. Since the start of the GFC, surplus projections have anticipated a large fiscal correction that failed to materialize.]]></description><author>Zhengyang Jiang, Hanno Lustig, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh, Mindy Z. Xiaolan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29351</guid></item><item><title>Macroprudential Policy during COVID-19: The Role of Policy Space</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper uses the initial phase of the COVID-19 pandemic to examine how macroprudential frameworks developed over the past decade performed during a period of heightened financial and economic stress. It discusses a new measure of the macroprudential stance that better captures the intensity of different policies across countries and time. Then it shows that macroprudential policy has been used countercyclically—with stances tightened during the 2010’s and eased in response to COVID-19 by more than previous risk-off periods. Countries that tightened macroprudential policy more aggressively before COVID, as well as those that eased more during the pandemic, experienced less financial and economic stress. Countries’ ability to use macroprudential policy, however, was significantly constrained by the extent of existing “policy space”, i.e., by how aggressively policy was tightened before COVID-19. The use of macroprudential tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use other policy tools (such as fiscal policy, monetary policy, FX intervention, and capital flow management measures), and the use of other tools was not significantly affected by the space available to use macroprudential policy. This suggests that although macroprudential tools are being used countercyclically and should therefore help stabilize economies and financial markets, there appears to be an opportunity to better integrate the use of macroprudential tools with other policies in the future.]]></description><author>Katharina Bergant, Kristin Forbes</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29346</guid></item><item><title>Business News and Business Cycles</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29344</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We propose an approach to measuring the state of the economy via textual analysis of business news. From the full text of 800,000 Wall Street Journal articles for 1984–2017, we estimate a topic model that summarizes business news into interpretable topical themes and quantifies the proportion of news attention allocated to each theme over time. News attention closely tracks a wide range of economic activities and explains 25% of aggregate stock market returns. A text-augmented VAR demonstrates the large incremental role of news text in modeling macroeconomic dynamics. We use this model to retrieve the narratives that underlie business cycle fluctuations.]]></description><author>Leland Bybee, Bryan T. Kelly, Asaf Manela, Dacheng Xiu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29344</guid></item><item><title>Bayesian Learning</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29338</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We survey work using Bayesian learning in macroeconomics, highlighting common themes and new directions. First, we present many of the common types of learning problems agents face---signal extraction problems---and trace out their effects on macro aggregates, in different strategic settings. Then we review different perspectives on how agents get their information. Models differ in their motives for information acquisition and the cost of information, or learning technology. Finally, we survey the growing literature on the data economy, where economic activity generates data and the information in data feeds back to affect economic activity.]]></description><author>Isaac Baley, Laura Veldkamp</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29338</guid></item><item><title>Exposure, Experience, and Expertise: Why Personal Histories Matter in Economics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Personal experiences of economic outcomes, from global financial crises to individual-level job losses, can shape individual beliefs, risk attitudes, and choices for years to come. A growing literature on experience effects shows that individuals act as if past outcomes that they experienced were overly likely to occur again, even if they are fully informed about the actual likelihood. This reaction to past experiences is long-lasting though it decays over time as individuals accumulate new experiences. Modern brain science helps understand these processes. Evidence on neuroplasticity reveals that personal experiences and learning alter the strength of neural connections and fine-tune the brain structure to those past experiences ("use-dependent brain"). I show that experience effects help understand belief formation and decision-making in a wide area of economic applications, including inflation, home purchases, mortgage choices, and consumption expenditures. I argue that experience-based learning is broadly applicable to economic decision-making and discuss topics for future research in education, health, race, and gender economics.]]></description><author>Ulrike Malmendier</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</guid></item><item><title>Corporate Culture</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29322</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Corporate culture is an omnibus term that includes many elements like norms, values, knowledge, and customs that are relevant to a firm. Economists have made great progress recently in devising methods of measuring different aspects of corporate culture. These empirical measures of culture have explained mergers and acquisitions, corporate risk-taking, and unethical behaviors observed in corporations, among other topics. We argue that unpacking corporate culture into its components is the right way to research it empirically. Theories of corporate culture are still in development, and we discuss the major contributions thus far. We argue that a theory of the firm and of corporate decision-making that is based on corporate culture is more germane to the practical realities of firms’ inner workings than prevailing theories based on agency costs. Corporate culture has the potential to set the theoretical paradigm for all corporate finance research.]]></description><author>Gary B. Gorton, Jill Grennan, Alexander K. Zentefis</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29322</guid></item><item><title>Foreign Investors and U.S. Treasuries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29313</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> While foreigners are prominent in the Treasury market and in theoretical and empirical work, little is known about the nature of their Treasury portfolios. We provide novel evidence on foreigners' U.S. Treasury portfolios based on data not yet used by researchers: the security-level Treasury portfolios of foreigners and private U.S. investors. We find that private foreign investors earn above market returns and on a risk-adjusted basis both foreign private and foreign official investors outperform U.S. investors. Moreover, while foreign officials, with their broader objective functions, may well have inelastic demand, private foreign investors increase purchases of Treasuries and increase the duration of their Treasury portfolios when their sovereign yields are low or decrease relative to Treasury yields (that is, when CIP deviations decrease). Our results are so different from existing results that we close with a reconciliation exercise that provides a useful assessment of different sources of data on flows and holdings.]]></description><author>Alexandra M. Tabova, Francis E. Warnock</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29313</guid></item><item><title>Dynamic Strategic Corporate Finance: A Tug of War with Financial Frictions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29310</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Access to capital markets plays a key role for the evolution of an industry over time. We develop a benchmark theoretical setting that integrates core corporate finance insights about the impact of financial frictions on investment with those from industrial organization on dynamic competition and industry evolution under perfect capital markets. Using state of the art computational tools to systematically detect and evaluate multiple equilibria and to thoroughly explore the parameter space of our model, we show how, depending on key industry characteristics such as market size, financial frictions impact firms' pricing and investment strategies and the degree of industry concentration.]]></description><author>Ulrich Doraszelski, João F. Gomes, Felix Nockher</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29310</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Housing Returns</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29306</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> We document the existence of a racial gap in realized housing returns that is an order of magnitude larger than disparities arising from housing costs alone, and is driven almost entirely by differences in distressed home sales (i.e. foreclosures and short sales). Black and Hispanic homeowners are both more likely to experience a distressed sale and to live in neighborhoods where distressed sales erase more house value. Importantly, absent financial distress, houses owned by minorities do not appreciate at slower rates than houses owned by non-minorities. Racial differences in income stability and liquid wealth explain a large share of the differences in distress. We use quasi-experimental variation in loan modifications to show that policies that restructure mortgages for distressed minorities can increase housing returns and reduce the racial wealth gap.]]></description><author>Amir Kermani, Francis Wong</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29306</guid></item><item><title>International Reserve Management, Global Financial Shocks, and Firms’ Investment in Emerging Market Economies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29303</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We examine the effects of active international reserve management (IRM) conducted by central banks of emerging market economies (EMEs) on firm investment in the presence of global financial shocks. Using firm level data from 46 EMEs from 2000 to 2018, we document four findings. First, active IRM positively affects firm investment - the effect strengthens with the magnitude of adverse external financial shocks. Second, financially constrained firms, compared with unconstrained ones, are less responsive to active IRM. Third, our results suggest that the country credit spread is a plausible causal channel of the positive IRM effect on firm investment. Fourth, the policies of capital controls and exchange rate managements are complementary to the IRM – it is beneficial to form a macro policy mix including active IRM to safeguard firm investment against global financial shocks. Further, our results indicate the IRM effect on firm investment is both statistical and economical significance and is relevant to the aggregate economy.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yin-Wong Cheung, Xingwang Qian</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29303</guid></item><item><title>Fiscal Policy in the Age of COVID: Does it ‘Get in all of the Cracks?’</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the effects of fiscal policy in response to the COVID-19 pandemic at the firm, sector, country and global level. First, we estimate the impact of COVID-19 and policy responses on small and medium sized enterprise (SME) business failures. We combine firm-level financial data from 50 sectors in 27 countries, a detailed I-O network, real-time data on lockdown policies and mobility patterns, and a rich model of firm behavior that allows for several dimensions of heterogeneity. We find: (a) Absent government support, the failure rate of SMEs would have increased by 9 percentage points, significantly more so in emerging market economies (EMs). With policy support it only increased by 4.3 percentage points, and even decreased in advanced economies (AEs). (b) Fiscal policy was poorly targeted: most of the funds disbursed went to firms who did not need it. (c) Nevertheless, we find little evidence of the policy merely postponing mass business failures or creating many ‘zombie’ firms: failure rates rise only slightly in 2021 once policy support is removed. Next, we build a tractable global intertemporal general equilibrium I-O model with fiscal policy. We calibrate the model to 64 countries and 36 sectors. We find that: (d) a sizable share of the global economy is demand-constrained under COVID-19, especially so in EMs. (e) Globally, fiscal policy helped offset about 8% of the downturn in COVID, with a low ‘traditional’ fiscal multiplier. Yet it significantly reduced the share of demand- constrained sectors, preserving employment in these sectors. (f) Fiscal policy exerted small and negative spillovers to output in other countries but positive spillovers on employment. (g) A two-speed recovery would put significant upwards pressure on global interest rates which imposes an additional headwind on the EM recovery. (h) Corporate and sovereign spreads rise when global rates increase, suggesting that EM may face challenging external funding conditions as AEs economies normalize.]]></description><author>Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, Ṣebnem Kalemli-Özcan, Veronika Penciakova, Nick Sander</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29293</guid></item><item><title>The Asymmetry in Responsible Investing Preferences</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29288</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We design an experiment to understand how social preferences affect investment decisions through stock allocations and probability assessments. The major preference channel is asymmetric in social outcomes – although negative and positive responsible investment (RI) externalities have the same magnitudes, negative externalities have greater impact on investment choices. The effect is persistent, but heterogenous. We also find asymmetries in belief formation and learning constitute a secondary channel. Overall, our results are consistent with important stylized empirical facts and the predictions of recent RI theories that social preferences lead to different investment choices, but our analyses also suggest important future modeling directions.]]></description><author>Jacquelyn Humphrey, Shimon Kogan, Jacob Sagi, Laura Starks</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29288</guid></item><item><title>Bank Mergers, Acquirer Choice and Small Business Lending: Implications for Community Investment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29284</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We examine the effects of bank merger and local market characteristics on local small business lending.  Mergers involving small, in-state acquirers are positively associated with small business loan (SBL) originations in counties where target banks are located.  Conversely, mergers involving large, out-of-state acquirers are associated with fewer SBL originations.  The analysis suggests that the results are driven by acquirer’s choice of target.  Small and in-state acquirers target banks that focus more on SBL and targets with strong relationships while large, out-of-state acquirers pursue better performing banks with stronger balance sheets and less focus on SBL.  Results are particularly strong in counties with a large number of small firms.  Post-merger activity supports banks expanding on their acquisition strategy decisions.  The findings suggest that acquirer strategy is important for evaluating the impact of acquisitions on local community development and that one-size-fits-all policy solutions for bank mergers may not produce common local outcomes.]]></description><author>Bernadette A. Minton, Alvaro G. Taboada, Rohan Williamson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29284</guid></item><item><title>Banking-Crisis Interventions, 1257-2019</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29281</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We present a new database of banking-crisis interventions since the 13th century.  The database includes 1886 interventions in 20 categories across 138 countries, covering interventions during all of the crises identified in the main banking-crisis  chronologies, while also cataloguing a large number of interventions outside of  those crises. The data show a gradual shift over the past centuries from the  traditional interventions of a lender-of-last-resort, suspensions of convertibility, and bank holidays, towards a much more prominent role for capital injections and  sweeping guarantees of bank liabilities. Furthermore, intervention frequencies and  sizes suggest that the crisis problem in the financial sector has indeed reached an  apex during the post-Bretton Woods era – but that such trends are part of a more  deeply entrenched development that saw global intervention frequencies and sizes  gradually rise since at least the late 17th century.]]></description><author>Andrew Metrick, Paul Schmelzing</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29281</guid></item><item><title>Does Political Partisanship Cross Borders? Evidence from International Capital Flows</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29280</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Does partisan perception shape the flow of international capital? We provide evidence from two settings, syndicated corporate loans and equity mutual funds, to show that ideological alignment with foreign governments affects the cross-border capital allocation by U.S. institutional investors. Moreover, we find that ideological alignment with foreign countries also affects investments of non-U.S. investors and can explain patterns in bilateral FDI flows. Our empirical strategy ensures that direct economic effects of foreign elections or bilateral ties between countries are not driving the result. Combined, our findings imply that partisan perception is a global phenomenon and its economic effects transcend national borders.]]></description><author>Elisabeth Kempf, Mancy Luo, Larissa Schäfer, Margarita Tsoutsoura</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29280</guid></item><item><title>External Balance Sheets and the COVID-19 Crisis</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29277</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> At the onset of the COVID-19 economic crisis, as in other crisis episodes, the flight to safety was accompanied by a rapid appreciation of “safe haven” currencies. We quantify currency-induced balance sheet effects for total external positions as well as for individual asset classes using new data on the currency composition of cross-border stocks for 48 countries for the first quarter as well as for the full year 2020. We also conduct the stock-flow reconciliation of net international investment positions to measure overall valuation effects. We show that for many countries currency-induced valuation gains mitigated losses that resulted from declining asset prices in the first quarter of 2020. Moreover, for countries with excess capital out flows during this period, the impact on external balance sheet positions was mitigated by valuation gains. This is because, in contrast with past financial crises, many emerging markets did not experience negative external balance sheet effects from their currency depreciation, partly due to currency-induced valuation gains on equity positions offsetting losses on debt positions, partly due to reduced currency mismatch on their external debt positions.]]></description><author>Galina Hale, Luciana Juvenal</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29277</guid></item><item><title>Diverse Policy Committees Can Reach Underrepresented Groups</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Increasing the diversity of policy committees has taken center stage worldwide, but whether and why diverse committees are more effective is still unclear. In a randomized control trial that varies the salience of female and minority representation on the Federal Reserve’s monetary policy committee, the FOMC, we test whether diversity affects how Fed information influences consumers’ subjective beliefs. Women and Black respondents form unemployment expectations more in line with FOMC forecasts and trust the Fed more after this intervention. Women are also more likely to acquire Fed-related information when associated with a female official. White men, who are overrepresented on the FOMC, do not react negatively. Heterogeneous taste for diversity can explain these patterns better than homophily. Our results suggest more diverse policy committees are better able to reach underrepresented groups without inducing negative reactions by others, thereby enhancing the effectiveness of policy communication and public trust in the institution.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Andreas Fuster, Michael Weber</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</guid></item><item><title>Measuring the Welfare Cost of Asymmetric Information in Consumer Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Information asymmetries are known in theory to lead to inefficiently low credit provision, yet empirical estimates of the resulting welfare losses are scarce. This paper leverages a randomized experiment conducted by a large fintech lender to estimate welfare losses arising from asymmetric information in the market for online consumer credit. Building on methods from the insurance literature, we show how exogenous variation in interest rates can be used to estimate borrower demand and lender cost curves and recover implied welfare losses. While asymmetric information generates large equilibrium price distortions, we find only small overall welfare losses, particularly for high-credit-score borrowers.]]></description><author>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</guid></item><item><title>Signaling in Online Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29268</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study how signaling affects equilibrium outcomes and welfare in an online credit market using detailed data on loan characteristics and borrower repayment. We build and estimate an equilibrium model in which a borrower may signal her default risk through the reserve interest rate. Comparing a market with and without signaling relative to the benchmark with no asymmetric information, we find that adverse selection destroys as much as 34% of total surplus, up to 78% of which can be restored with signaling. We also estimate backward-bending supply curves for some markets, consistent with the prediction of Stiglitz &amp; Weiss (1981).]]></description><author>Kei Kawai, Ken Onishi, Kosuke Uetake</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29268</guid></item><item><title>New Evidence on Redlining by Federal Housing Programs in the 1930s</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29244</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We show that the Federal Housing Administration (FHA), from its inception in the 1930s, did not insure mortgages in low income urban neighborhoods where the vast majority of urban Black Americans lived.  The agency evaluated neighborhoods using block-level information collected by New Deal relief programs and the Census in many cities.  The FHA’s exclusionary pattern predates the advent of the infamous maps later made by the Home Owners’ Loan Corporation (HOLC) and shows little change after the drafting of those maps.  In contrast, the HOLC itself broadly loaned to such neighborhoods and to Black homeowners.  We conclude that the HOLC’s redlining maps had little effect on the geographic distribution of either program’s mortgage market activity, and that the FHA crafted and implemented its own redlining methodology prior to the HOLC.]]></description><author>Price V. Fishback, Jonathan Rose, Kenneth A. Snowden, Thomas Storrs</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29244</guid></item><item><title>The Flight to Safety and International Risk Sharing</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29238</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study a business cycle model of the international monetary system featuring a time-varying demand for safe dollar bonds, greater risk-bearing capacity in the U.S. than the rest of the world, and nominal rigidities.  A flight to safety generates a dollar appreciation and decline in global output.  Dollar bonds thus command a negative risk premium and the U.S. holds a levered portfolio of capital financed in dollars.  We quantify the effects of safety shocks and heterogeneity in risk-bearing capacity for global macroeconomic volatility; U.S. external adjustment; and the international transmission of monetary and fiscal policies, including dollar swap lines.]]></description><author>Rohan Kekre, Moritz Lenel</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29238</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Market Expectations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29232</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Asset prices are a valuable source of information about financial market participants' expectations about key macroeconomic variables. However, the presence of time-varying risk premia requires an adjustment of market prices to obtain the market's rational assessment of future price and policy developments. This paper reviews empirical approaches for recovering market-based expectations. It starts by laying out the two canonical modeling frameworks that form the backbone for estimating risk premia and highlights the proliferation of risk pricing factors that result in a wide range of different asset-price-based expectation measures. It then describes a key methodological innovation to evaluate the empirical plausibility of risk premium estimates and to identify the most accurate market-based expectation measure. The usefulness of this general approach is illustrated for price expectations in the global oil market. Then, the paper provides an overview of the body of empirical evidence for monetary policy and inflation expectations with a special emphasis on market-specific characteristics that complicate the quest for the best possible market-based expectation measure. Finally, it discusses a number of economic applications where market expectations play a key role for evaluating economic models, guiding policy analysis, and deriving shock measures.]]></description><author>Christiane Baumeister</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29232</guid></item><item><title>Misdiagnosing Bank Capital Problems</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29223</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Banks’ reluctance to repair their balance sheets, combined with deposit insurance and regulatory forbearance in recognizing greater risks and losses, can lead to solvency problems that look like liquidity (bank-run) crises. Regulatory forbearance incentivizes banks to both retain risky loans and reject new good opportunities. With sufficient regulatory forbearance, partially-insured banks act exactly as if they are fully insured. Stress tests certify that uninsured creditors will be paid, not that banks are solvent, and have ambiguous effects on the efficiency of investment.]]></description><author>Jeremy I. Bulow, Paul D. Klemperer</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29223</guid></item><item><title>The Effects of Going Public on Firm Performance and Commercialization Strategy: Evidence from International IPOs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29219</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the effects of going public using a unique panel of firms in 16 European countries for which we observe financial data before and after firms' initial-public-offering (IPO) attempts. We compare firms that complete their IPO with firms that withdraw their IPO. We instrument the going public decision using prior market returns. We find that firm profitability goes up after going public—contrary to previous results in the literature. We also find an post-IPO expansion in the number of subsidiaries and countries in which IPO firms operate. Our results are stronger for firms in financially dependent industries and in countries with higher investor protection consistent with going public relaxing financial constraints and with a stronger impact when agency conflicts are lower.  Overall, our results are consistent with going public inducing a shift towards a strategy of commercialization to increase profitability.]]></description><author>Borja Larrain, Gordon M. Phillips, Giorgo Sertsios, Francisco Urzúa</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29219</guid></item><item><title>Corporate Actions and the Manipulation of Retail Investors in China: An Analysis of Stock Splits</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29212</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We identify a group of “suspicious” firms that use stock splits—perhaps, along with other activities—to artificially inflate their share prices. Following the initiation of suspicious splits, share prices temporarily increase, and subsequently decline below their pre-split levels. Using account level data from the Shanghai Stock Exchange, we find that small retail investors acquire shares in firms initiating suspicious splits, while more sophisticated investors accumulate positions before suspicious split announcements and sell in the post-split period. We also find that insiders sell large blocks of shares and obtain loans using company stock as collateral around the initiation of suspicious splits.]]></description><author>Sheridan Titman, Chishen Wei. Wei, Bin Zhao</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29212</guid></item><item><title>Venture Capitalists’ Access to Finance and Its Impact on Startups</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29211</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Although an extensive literature shows that startups are financially constrained and that constraints vary by geography, the source of these constraints is still relatively unknown. We explore intermediary financing constraints, a channel studied in the banking literature, but only indirectly addressed in the venture capital (VC) literature. Our empirical setting is the VC fundraising and startup financing environment around the passage of the Volcker Rule, which restricted banks’ ability to invest in venture capital funds as limited partners (LPs). The rule change disproportionately impacted regions of the U.S. historically lacking in VC financing. We find that a one standard deviation increase in VCs’ exposure to the loss of banks as LPs led to an 18% decline in fund size and about a 10% decrease in the likelihood of raising a follow-on fund. Startups were not completely cushioned from the additional constraints on their VCs: capital raised fell and pre-money valuations declined. Overall, VC financing constraints manifest as fewer, smaller funds that change investment strategy and experience increases in bargaining power. Last, we show that the rule change increased the likelihood startups move out of impacted states, thus exacerbating the geographic disparity in high-growth entrepreneurship.]]></description><author>Jun Chen, Michael Ewens</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29211</guid></item><item><title>Market Freezes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29210</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> During the financial crisis apparently centralized markets continued to function while trade in OTC markets froze. We use search-and-bargaining theory to ascertain conditions that allow trade to temporarily freeze in decentralized markets, focusing on the roles of liquidity and self-fulfilling prophecies. We show standard models can have recurrent, belief-driven hot and cold spells, but not freezes and thaws. A simple specification that has freezes assumes negative returns. A more realistic one incorporates information frictions (costly asset-quality verification). Another uses different frictions to get credit freezes. We also discuss policy implications, and go into detail on the nature of OTC markets.]]></description><author>Chao Gu, Guido Menzio, Randall Wright, Yu Zhu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29210</guid></item><item><title>Hedging and Competition</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29207</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study how risk management through hedging impacts firms and competition among firms in the life insurance industry - an industry with over 7 Trillion in assets and over 1,000 private and public firms. We show that firms that are likely to face costly external finance increase hedging after staggered state-level financial reform that reduces the costs of hedging. Post reform impacted firms have lower risk and fewer negative income shocks. Product market competition is also impacted. Firms that previously are more likely to face costly external finance, lower price, increase policy sales and increase their market share post reform. The results are consistent with hedging allowing firms that face potential costly financial distress to decrease risk and become more competitive.]]></description><author>Erasmo Giambona, Anil Kumar, Gordon M. Phillips</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29207</guid></item><item><title>Why Did Small Business Fintech Lending Dry Up During March 2020?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29205</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> With the onset of the COVID-19 crisis in March 2020, small business lending through fintech lenders collapsed. We explore the reasons for the market shutdown using detailed data about loan applications, offers, and take-up from a major small business fintech credit platform. We document that while the number of loan applications increased sharply early in March 2020, the supply of credit collapsed as online lenders dropped from the platform and the likelihood of applicants receiving loan offers fell precipitously. Our analysis shows that the drying up of the loan supply is most consistent with fintech lenders becoming financially constrained and losing their ability to fund new loans.]]></description><author>Itzhak Ben-David, Mark J. Johnson, René M. Stulz</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29205</guid></item><item><title>Are Collateral-Constraint Models Ready for Macroprudential Policy Design?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29204</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> We study the design of macroprudential policies based on quantitative collateral-constraint models. We show that the desirability of macroprudential policies critically depends on the specific form of collateral used in debt contracts: While inefficiencies arise when current prices affect collateral---a frequent benchmark used to guide policies---they do not when only future prices affect collateral. Since the microfoundations and quantitative predictions of models with future-price collateral constraints do not appear less plausible than those using current prices, we conclude that additional empirical work is essential for the use of these models in macroprudential policy design.]]></description><author>Pablo Ottonello, Diego J. Perez, Paolo Varraso</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29204</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Channel of Wage Rigidity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29201</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> I propose a financial channel of wage rigidity. In recessions, rather than propping up marginal (new hires’) costs of labor, rigid average wages squeeze cash flows, forcing firms to cut hiring due to financial constraints. Indeed, empirical cash flows and profits would turn acyclical if wages were only moderately more procyclical. I study this channel in a search and matching model with financial constraints and rigid wages among incumbent workers, while new hires’ wages are flexible. Individually, each feature generates no amplification. By contrast, their interaction can account for much of the empirical labor market fluctuations—breaking the neutrality of incumbents’ wages for hiring, and showing that financial amplification of business cycles requires wage rigidity.]]></description><author>Benjamin Schoefer</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29201</guid></item><item><title>When Uncertainty and Volatility Are Disconnected: Implications for Asset Pricing and Portfolio Performance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29195</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We analyze an environment where the uncertainty in the equity market return and its volatility are both stochastic, and may be potentially disconnected. We solve a representative investor's optimal asset allocation and derive the resulting conditional equity premium and risk-free rate in equilibrium. Our empirical analysis shows that the equity premium appears to be earned for facing uncertainty, especially high uncertainty that is disconnected from lower volatility, rather than for facing volatility as traditionally assumed. Incorporating the possibility of a disconnect between volatility and uncertainty significantly improves portfolio performance, over and above the performance obtained by conditioning on volatility only.]]></description><author>Yacine Aït-Sahalia, Felix Matthys, Emilio Osambela, Ronnie Sircar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29195</guid></item><item><title>Young Firms, Old Capital</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29189</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Across a broad range of equipment types and industries, we document a pattern of local capital reallocation from older firms to younger firms.  Start-ups purchase a disproportionate share of old physical capital previously owned by more mature firms.  The evidence is consistent with financial constraints driving differential demand for vintage capital.  The local supply of used capital influences start-up entry, job creation, investment choices, and growth, particularly when capital is immobile.  Conversely, incumbents accelerate capital replacement in the presence of more young firms.  The evidence suggests previously undocumented benefits to co-location between old and young firms.]]></description><author>Song Ma, Justin Murfin, Ryan D. Pratt</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29189</guid></item><item><title>The Industrial Organization of Financial Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29183</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This chapter discusses recent developments in the literature involving applications of industrial organization methods to finance. We structure our discussion around a simple model of a financial intermediary that concentrates its attention either on (i) the retail market and hence engages in a traditional maturity transformation business by accepting funds that can be used to invest in risky projects (loans), or (ii) the investment business, financing its operations on the “wholesale” market and making markets or investing in higher return riskier projects. Our discussion is centered around the analysis of market structure and competition in each of these markets, focusing in turn on (i) primary and secondary markets for government and corporate debt, (ii) interbank loans, (iii) markets for retail funding, and (iv) credit markets, including mortgages.]]></description><author>Robert Clark, Jean-François Houde, Jakub Kastl</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29183</guid></item><item><title>The Affordable Care Act After a Decade: Industrial Organization of the Insurance Exchanges</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29178</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The regulated insurance exchanges set up in the Affordable Care Act (ACA) were designed to deliver affordable, efficient health coverage through private insurers. It is crucial to study the complex industrial organization (IO) of these exchanges in order to assess their impacts to date, during the first decade of the ACA, and in order to project their impacts going forward. We revisit the inherent market failures in health care markets that necessitate key ACA exchange regulations and investigate whether they have succeeded in their goals of expanding coverage, creating robust marketplaces, providing product variety, and generating innovation in health care delivery. We discuss empirical IO research to date and also highlight shortcomings in the existing research that can be addressed moving forward. We conclude with a discussion of IO research-based policy lessons for the ACA exchanges and, more generally, for managed competition of private insurance in health care.]]></description><author>Benjamin R. Handel, Jonathan T. Kolstad</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29178</guid></item><item><title>Specialized Investments and Firms’ Boundaries: Evidence from Textual Analysis of Patents</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29174</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Inducing firms to make specialized investments through bilateral contracts can be challenging because of potential hold- up problems. Such contracting difficulties have long been argued to be an important reason for acquisitions. To evaluate the extent to which this motivation leads to mergers, we perform a textual analysis of the patents filed by the same lead inventors of the target firms before and after the mergers. We find that patents of inventors from target firms become 28.9% to 46.8% more specific to those of acquirers’ inventors following completed mergers, benchmarked against patents filed by targets and a group of counterfactual acquirers. This pattern is stronger for vertical mergers that are likely to require specialized investments. There is no change in the specificity of patents for mergers that are announced but not consummated. Overall, we provide empirical evidence that contracting issues in motivating specialized investment can be a motive for acquisitions.]]></description><author>Jan Bena, Isil Erel, Daisy Wang, Michael S. Weisbach</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29174</guid></item><item><title>Competition and Selection in Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29169</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We present both theory and evidence that increased competition may decrease rather than increase consumer welfare in subprime credit markets. We present a model of lending markets with imperfect competition, adverse selection and costly lender screening. In more competitive markets, lenders have lower market shares, and thus lower incentives to monitor borrowers. Thus, when markets are competitive, all lenders face a riskier pool of borrowers, which can lead interest rates to be higher, and consumer welfare to be lower. We provide evidence for the model’s predictions in the auto loan market using administrative credit panel data.]]></description><author>Constantine Yannelis, Anthony Lee Zhang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29169</guid></item><item><title>Corrective Regulation with Imperfect Instruments</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29160</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper studies the optimal design of second-best corrective regulation, when some agents or activities cannot be perfectly regulated. We show that policy elasticities and Pigouvian wedges are sufficient statistics to characterize the marginal welfare impact of regulatory policies in a large class of environments. We show that the optimal second-best policy is determined by a subset of policy elasticities: leakage elasticities, and characterize the marginal value of relaxing regulatory constraints. We apply our results to scenarios with unregulated agents/activities and with uniform regulation across agents/activities. We illustrate our results in applications to shadow banking, scale-invariant regulation, asset substitution, and fire sales.]]></description><author>Eduardo Dávila, Ansgar Walther</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29160</guid></item><item><title>Financial crises: A survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29155</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Financial crises have large deleterious effects on economic activity, and as such have been the focus of a large body of research. This study surveys the existing literature on financial crises, exploring how crises are measured, whether they are predictable, and why they are associated with economic contractions. Historical narrative techniques continue to form the backbone for measuring crises, but there have been exciting developments in using quantitative data as well. Crises are predictable with growth in credit and elevated asset prices playing an especially important role; recent research points convincingly to the importance of behavioral biases in explaining such predictability. The negative consequences of a crisis are due to both the crisis itself but also to the imbalances that precede a crisis. Crises do not occur randomly, and, as a result, an understanding of financial crises requires an investigation into the booms that precede them.]]></description><author>Amir Sufi, Alan M. Taylor</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29155</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of a Government Risk Pool and an Opt-Out Framing on Demand for Earthquake Protection</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29144</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This paper describes the design and analysis of a web-based choice experiment that examines how the demand for earthquake protection in Quebec and British Columbia is influenced by the default option and the structure of the insurance plan. Homeowners in both provinces were given the opportunity to purchase protection against earthquake losses when presented with one of the following options: the current private insurance plan, a high deductible private insurance plan, and a proposed public-private risk pool. The default frame was changed so the homeowner could either opt-in by purchasing this coverage or opt-out of being given this protection and receiving a premium discount.  Assigning participants to a public-private risk pool rather than the current private insurance plan increases the likelihood of purchasing earthquake protection by 151%. The opt-out frame leads to a likelihood greater than 1.6 of purchasing coverage relative to the opt-in frame when given the same plan structure. The policy implications of this finding are discussed.]]></description><author>Howard Kunreuther, Lynn Conell-Price, Paul Kovacs, Katsuichiro Goda</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29144</guid></item><item><title>Regulatory Costs of Being Public: Evidence from Bunching Estimation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29143</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> The increased burden of disclosure and governance regulations is often cited as a key reason for the significant decline in the number of publicly-listed companies in the U.S. We explore the connection between regulatory costs and the number of listed firms by exploiting a regulatory quirk: many rules trigger when a firm’s public float exceeds a threshold. Consistent with firms seeking to avoid costly regulation, we document significant bunching around multiple regulatory thresholds introduced from 1992 to 2012. We present a revealed preference estimation strategy that uses this behavior to quantify regulatory costs. Our estimates show that various disclosure and internal governance rules lead to a total compliance cost of 4.1% of the market capitalization for a median U.S. public firm. Regulatory costs have a greater impact on private firms’ IPO decisions than on public firms’ going private decisions. However, heightened regulatory costs only explain a small fraction of the decline in the number of public firms.]]></description><author>Michael Ewens, Kairong Xiao, Ting Xu</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29143</guid></item><item><title>Do Lenders Still Discriminate? A Robust Approach for Assessing Differences in Menus</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29142</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Motivated by the assessment of racial discrimination in mortgage pricing, we introduce a new methodology for comparing the menus of options borrowers face based on their choices. First, we show how standard regression-based approaches for assessing discrimination in the menus context can lead to misleading and contradictory results. Second, we propose a new methodology that is robust these problems based on relatively weak economic assumptions. More specifically, we use pairwise dominance relationships in choices supplemented by restrictions on the range of plausible menus to define (1) a test statistic for equality in menus and (2) a difference in menus (DIM) metric for assessing whether one group of borrowers would prefer to switch to another group's menus. Our statistics are robust to arbitrary heterogeneity in borrower preferences across racial groups, are sharp in terms of identification, and can be efficiently computed using Optimal Transport methods. Third, we devise a new approach for inference on the value of Optimal Transport problems based on directional differentiation. Fourth, we use our methodology to estimate mortgage pricing differentials by race on a novel data set linking 2018--2019 Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) data to Optimal Blue rate locks. We find robust evidence for mortgage pricing differentials by race, particularly among Conforming mortgage borrowers who are relatively creditworthy.]]></description><author>David Hao Zhang, Paul S. Willen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29142</guid></item><item><title>The 2000s Housing Cycle With 2020 Hindsight: A Neo-Kindlebergerian View</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29140</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> With “2020 hindsight,” the 2000s housing cycle is not a boom-bust but rather a boom- bust-rebound at both the national level and across cities. We argue this pattern reflects a larger role for fundamentally-rooted explanations than previously thought. We construct a city-level long-run fundamental using a spatial equilibrium regression framework in which house prices are determined by local income, amenities, and supply. The fundamental predicts not only 1997-2019 price and rent growth but also the amplitude of the boom-bust-rebound and foreclosures. This evidence motivates our neo-Kindlebergerian model, in which an improvement in fundamentals triggers a boom-bust-rebound. Agents learn about the fundamentals by observing “dividends” but become over-optimistic due to diagnostic expectations. A bust ensues when over-optimistic beliefs start to correct, exacerbated by a price-foreclosure spiral that drives prices below their long-run level. The rebound follows as prices converge to a path commensurate with higher fundamental growth. The estimated model explains the boom-bust-rebound with a single fundamental shock and accounts quantitatively for cross-city patterns in the dynamics of prices and foreclosures.]]></description><author>Gabriel Chodorow-Reich, Adam M. Guren, Timothy J. McQuade</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29140</guid></item><item><title>What Do You Think About Climate Finance?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29136</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We survey 861 finance academics, professionals, and public sector regulators and policy economists about climate finance topics. They identify regulatory risk as the top climate risk to businesses and investors over the next five years, but they view physical risks as the top risk over the next 30 years. By an overwhelming margin, respondents believe that asset prices underestimate climate risks. We also tabulate opinions about the correlation between growth and climate change; social discount rates appropriate for projects that mitigate the effects of climate change; most influential forces for reducing climate risks; and, most important research topics.]]></description><author>Johannes Stroebel, Jeffrey Wurgler</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29136</guid></item><item><title>Can Monetary Policy Create Fiscal Capacity?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29129</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Governments around the world have gone on a massive fiscal expansion in response to the Covid crisis, increasing government debt to levels not seen in 75 years. How will this debt be repaid? What role do conventional and unconventional monetary policy play? We investigate debt sustainability in a New Keynesian model with an intermediary sector, realistic fiscal and monetary policy, endogenous convenience yields, and substantial risk premia. When conventional monetary policy is constrained by the ZLB during an economic crisis, increased government spending and lower tax revenue lead to a large rise in government debt and raise the risk of future tax increases. We find that quantitative easing (QE), forward guidance, and an expansion in government discretionary spending all contribute to lowering debt/GDP ratio and reducing this fiscal risk. A transitory QE policy deployed during a crisis stimulates aggregate demand.]]></description><author>Vadim Elenev, Tim Landvoigt, Patrick J. Shultz, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29129</guid></item><item><title>The Treasury Market in Spring 2020 and the Response of the Federal Reserve</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29128</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Treasury yields spiked during the initial phase of COVID. The 10-year yield increased by 64 bps from March 9 to 18, 2020, leading the Federal Reserve to purchase $1T of Treasuries in 2020Q1. Fed purchases were causal for reducing Treasury yields based on the timing of purchases (which increased on March 19), the timing of yield reversal and Fed purchases in the MBS market, and evidence against confounding factors. Treasury-QE worked more via purchases than announcements. The yield spike was driven by liquidity needs of mutual funds, foreign official agencies, and hedge funds that were unaffected by the March 15 Treasury-QE announcement.]]></description><author>Annette Vissing-Jorgensen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29128</guid></item><item><title>Intangibles, Markups, and the Measurement of Productivity Growth</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29109</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> In recent years, measured TFP growth in the US has declined. We argue that two forces contributed to this decline: the mismeasurement of intangible capital, and rising markups. Markups affect input shares, while intangibles omitted from measures of investment affect measured capital growth, each potentially generating downward bias in measured TFP growth. Most importantly, when both forces are simultaneously present, their effects reinforce each other and amplify the downward bias in measured TFP growth. Using input-output data, we estimate that this mechanism could account for one-third to two-thirds of the decline in measured TFP growth.]]></description><author>Nicolas Crouzet, Janice C. Eberly</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29109</guid></item></channel></rss>