<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Antitrust</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Antitrust</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 15:13:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>A New Era of Midnight Mergers: Antitrust Risk and Investor Disclosures</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29655</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John M. Barrios, Thomas G. Wollmann.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Antitrust authorities search public documents to discover anticompetitive mergers. Thus, investor disclosures may alert them to deals that would otherwise escape scrutiny, creating disincentives for managers to divulge transactions. We study this behavior in publicly traded US companies. First, we estimate a regression discontinuity that exploits mandatory disclosure thresholds stipulated by securities law. We find that releasing information to investors poses antitrust risk. Second, we present a method for measuring undisclosed merger activity that relies on financial accounting reporting requirements. We find that undisclosed mergers total $2.3 trillion between 2002 and 2016.]]></description><author>John M. Barrios, Thomas G. Wollmann</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29655</guid></item><item><title>How Do Top Acquirers Compare in Technology Mergers? New Evidence from an S&amp;P Taxonomy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29642</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ginger Zhe Jin, Mario Leccese, Liad Wagman.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Some argue that large platforms, such as Alphabet/Google, Amazon, Apple, Facebook and Microsoft (or GAFAM), are unusual in their number, pace and concentration of technology mergers, with the potential to harm market competition. Using a unique taxonomy developed by S&amp;P Global Market Intelligence, we compare the M&amp;A activities of GAFAM to other top acquirers from 2010 to 2020. We find: (i) GAFAM completed more tech acquisitions per firm than other groups of top acquirers, and acquired younger and more consumer-facing firms on average. (ii) The top 25 private equity firms outpaced GAFAM in tech acquisitions per firm since 2018. (iii) GAFAM acquisitions are less concentrated across tech categories than other top acquirer groups, due, in part, to an “acquire-adjacent-and-then-expand” strategy. (iv) Over time, more and more GAFAM and other top acquirers acquire in the same categories. (v) No evidence suggesting that a GAFAM acquisition in a category, compared to similar categories without GAFAM acquisitions, is correlated with a slowdown in the number of new acquirers acquiring in that category. Overall, we find that technology acquisitions do not shield GAFAM from competition, at least not from other GAFAM members or other firms that acquire in the same categories.]]></description><author>Ginger Zhe Jin, Mario Leccese, Liad Wagman</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29642</guid></item><item><title>Using Bid Rotation and Incumbency to Detect Collusion: A Regression Discontinuity Approach</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29625</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kei Kawai, Jun Nakabayashi, Juan M. Ortner, Sylvain Chassang.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Cartels participating in procurement auctions frequently use bid rotation or prioritize incumbents to allocate contracts. However, establishing a link between observed allocation patterns and firm conduct has been difficult: there are cost-based competitive explanations for such patterns. We show that by focusing on auctions in which the winning and losing bids are very close, it is possible to distinguish allocation patterns reflecting cost differences across firms from patterns reflecting non-competitive environments. We apply our tests to two datasets: the sample of Ohio milk auctions studied in Porter and Zona (1999), and a sample of municipal procurement auctions from Japan.]]></description><author>Kei Kawai, Jun Nakabayashi, Juan M. Ortner, Sylvain Chassang</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29625</guid></item><item><title>Empirical Perspectives on Auctions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29511</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ali Hortaçsu, Isabelle Perrigne.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The empirical analysis of auction data has become a thriving field of research over the past thirty years. Relying on sophisticated models and advanced econometric methods, it addresses a wide range of policy questions for both public and private institutions. This chapter offers a guide to the literature by stressing how data features and policy questions have shaped research in the field. The chapter is organized by types of goods for sale and covers auctions of timber, construction and services procurement, oil and gas leases, online auctions, internet advertising, electricity, financial securities, spectrum, as well as used goods. It discusses the idiosyncrasies of each applied setting and the respective empirical findings.]]></description><author>Ali Hortaçsu, Isabelle Perrigne</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29511</guid></item><item><title>Privatization of Public Goods: Evidence from the Sanitation Sector in Senegal</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29295</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua W. Deutschmann, Jared E. Gars, Jean-François Houde, Molly Lipscomb, Laura A. Schechter.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Privatization of a public good (the management of sewage treatment centers in Dakar, Senegal) leads to an increase in the productivity of downstream sewage dumping companies and a decrease in downstream prices of the services they provide to households. We use the universe of legal dumps of sanitation waste from May 2009 to November 2018 to show that legal dumping increased substantially following privatization–on average an increase of 61.7%, or an increase of about 14,000 cubic meters each month. This is due to increased productivity of all trucks, not just those associated with the company managing the treatment centers. Household-level survey data shows that prices of legal sanitary dumping decreased by ten percent following privatization, and DHS data show that diarrhea rates among children under five decreased in Dakar relative to secondary cities in Senegal following privatization with no similar effect on respiratory illness as a placebo.]]></description><author>Joshua W. Deutschmann, Jared E. Gars, Jean-François Houde, Molly Lipscomb, Laura A. Schechter</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29295</guid></item></channel></rss>