<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Market Structure and Firm Performance</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Market Structure and Firm Performance</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 14:04:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Structural Empirical Analysis of Contracting in Vertical Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29282</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>This chapter presents an overview of advances in the structural analysis of contracting in vertical markets over the past fifteen years. We provide a discussion of theoretical models of contracting and bargaining that form the basis of recent empirical work, and then present common approaches used by researchers to take these models to the data. We also briefly survey the structural empirical literature on topics in vertical markets (including horizontal and vertical mergers, price discrimination, and nonlinear and exclusionary contracts), and conclude with a discussion of potential topics for future research.]]></description><author>Robin S. Lee, Michael D. Whinston, Ali Yurukoglu</author></item><item><title>Signaling in Online Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29268</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>We study how signaling affects equilibrium outcomes and welfare in an online credit market using detailed data on loan characteristics and borrower repayment. We build and estimate an equilibrium model in which a borrower may signal her default risk through the reserve interest rate. Comparing a market with and without signaling relative to the benchmark with no asymmetric information, we find that adverse selection destroys as much as 34% of total surplus, up to 78% of which can be restored with signaling. We also estimate backward-bending supply curves for some markets, consistent with the prediction of Stiglitz &amp; Weiss (1981).]]></description><author>Kei Kawai, Ken Onishi, Kosuke Uetake</author></item><item><title>Frictions in Product Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29259</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>This is an invited chapter for the forthcoming Volume 4 of the Handbook of Industrial Organization. We focus on markets with frictions, such as transaction costs, asymmetric information, search and matching frictions. We discuss how such frictions affect allocations, favor the emergence of intermediaries or dealers, and potentially create market power. Our focus is mostly on markets with many participants rather than on transactions that are bilateral or involve a small number of players.]]></description><author>Alessandro Gavazza, Alessandro Lizzeri</author></item><item><title>Empirical Models of Demand and Supply in Differentiated Products Industries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29257</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>This is an invited chapter for the forthcoming Volume 4 of the Handbook of Industrial Organization. We present empirical models of demand and supply in differentiated products industries with an emphasis on the key ideas arising from the recent applied literature. We start with a discussion of the challenges in modeling and estimation of demand for  differentiated products, and focus on discrete choice characteristics-based demand models that address these challenges while allowing enough flexibility to capture realistic substitution patterns. Our discussion emphasizes how empirical strategies can leverage different features of data depending on the sources of variation that are commonly found in applied work. Moving to the supply-side, we show how demand estimates combined with a pricing model, can be used to recover markups and marginal costs. We also show how the model of pricing can be tested. We discuss a baseline Bertrand-Nash model of competitive pricing, and expand it to cover a) coordinated pricing, b) wholesale relationships, and c) bargaining. We end the chapter with extensions of the demand model, including dynamic and continuous demand.]]></description><author>Amit Gandhi, Aviv Nevo</author></item><item><title>Hub and Spoke Cartels: Theory and Evidence from the Grocery Industry</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29253</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>Numerous recently uncovered cartels operated along the supply chain, with firms at one end facilitating collusion at the other – hub-and-spoke arrangements. These cartels are hard to rationalize because they induce double marginalization and higher costs. We examine Canada’s alleged bread cartel and provide the first comprehensive analysis of hub-and-spoke collusion. We make three contributions: i) Using court documents and pricing data we provide evidence that collusion existed at both ends of the supply chain, ii) we show that collusion was effective, increasing inflation by about 40% and iii) we provide a model explaining why this form of collusion arose.]]></description><author>Robert Clark, Ignatius Horstmann, Jean-François Houde</author></item><item><title>Harms of AI</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29247</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>This essay discusses several potential economic, political and social costs of the current path of AI technologies. I argue that if AI continues to be deployed along its current trajectory and remains unregulated, it may produce various social, economic and political harms. These include: damaging competition, consumer privacy and consumer choice; excessively automating work, fueling inequality, inefficiently pushing down wages, and failing to improve worker productivity; and damaging political discourse, democracy's most fundamental lifeblood. Although there is no conclusive evidence suggesting that these costs are imminent or substantial, it may be useful to understand them before they are fully realized and become harder or even impossible to reverse, precisely because of AI's promising and wide-reaching potential. I also suggest that these costs are not inherent to the nature of AI technologies, but are related to how they are being used and developed at the moment - to empower corporations and governments against workers and citizens. As a result, efforts to limit and reverse these costs may need to rely on regulation and policies to redirect AI research. Attempts to contain them just by promoting competition may be insufficient.]]></description><author>Daron Acemoglu</author></item><item><title>Flagship Entry in Online Marketplaces</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29239</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>In the world of omnichannel retail, some brands open a flagship store at online marketplaces, while others avert it. Focusing on a large e-commerce platform, we empirically study how flagship entry affects consumers, the platform, and various sellers on the platform.<br />
We find flagship entry may benefit consumers by expanding the choice set, by intensifying price competition within the entry brand, and by improving consumer perception for parts of the platform. In the meantime, flagship entry cannibalizes the sales of same-brand sellers, while other brands may gain as the buyer base expands on the platform.<br />
Counterfactual simulation suggests that flagship entry improves the gross merchandise value (GMV) of the platform but hurts existing sellers of the entry brand. On average, the effect on consumer welfare is more positive if the flagship entry is from a non-prominent brand than from a prominent brand, because consumers tend to lower their willingness to pay for individual sellers upon a prominent flagship entry. In hypothetical scenarios where flagship entry were accompanied by constraints on other same-brand sellers, the reduced competition would benefit the flagship store but hurt consumers.]]></description><author>Ginger Zhe Jin, Zhentong Lu, Xiaolu Zhou, Lu Fang</author></item><item><title>An Industrial Organization Perspective on Productivity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29229</link><description><![CDATA[September 2021<p>This chapter overviews productivity research from an industrial organization perspective. We focus on what is known and what still needs to be learned about the productivity levels and dynamics of individual producers, but also how these interact through markets and industries to influence productivity aggregates. We overview productivity concepts, facts, data, measurement, analysis, and open questions.]]></description><author>Jan De Loecker, Chad Syverson</author></item></channel></rss>