<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Public Goods</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Public Goods</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:21:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Incidence of the Corporate Income Tax is Irrelevant for its (Benefit-Based) Justification</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29547</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Simon M. Naitram, Matthew C. Weinzierl.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Robust support for corporate income taxation is a puzzle for standard tax theory because the tax’s incidence is uncertain and unreliable. We propose a resolution: if the corporate tax is seen as a benefit-based tax, its normative appeal depends on the correspondence between its incidence and that of the benefit which corporations derive from the state’s activities. We show that a simple mechanism makes this correspondence exact—and the net incidence of the tax zero—when the tax base matches what we call the benefit base. As a result, the appeal of the corporate income tax is independent of incidence as conventionally understood.]]></description><author>Simon M. Naitram, Matthew C. Weinzierl</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29547</guid></item><item><title>Ambulance Taxis: The Impact of Regulation and Litigation on Health Care Fraud</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29491</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Paul J. Eliason, Riley J. League, Jetson Leder-Luis, Ryan C. McDevitt, James W. Roberts.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the relative effectiveness of administrative regulations, criminal enforcement, and civil lawsuits for combatting health care fraud. Between 2003 and 2017, Medicare spent $7.7 billion on 37.5 million regularly scheduled, non-emergency ambulance rides for patients traveling to and from dialysis facilities, with dozens of lawsuits alleging that Medicare reimbursed rides for patients who did not meet the requirements for receiving one. Using a novel data set and an identification strategy based on the staggered timing of regulations and lawsuits across the United States, we find that a regulation requiring prior authorization for ambulance reimbursements reduced spending much more than criminal and civil lawsuits did. Despite the sharp drop in both ambulance transports and the companies that provide them following prior authorization, patients’ health outcomes did not change, indicating that most rides were not medically necessary. Our results suggest that administrative actions have a much larger impact than targeted criminal enforcement, providing novel evidence that regulations may be more cost-effective than ex post ligation for preventing health care fraud.]]></description><author>Paul J. Eliason, Riley J. League, Jetson Leder-Luis, Ryan C. McDevitt, James W. Roberts</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29491</guid></item><item><title>The Economic Burden of Pension Shortfalls: Evidence from House Prices</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> U.S. state pensions are underfunded by trillions of dollars, but their economic burden is unclear. In a model of inefficient taxation, real estate fully reflects the cost of pension shortfalls when it is the only form of immobile capital. We study the effect of pension shortfalls on real estate values at state borders, where labor and physical capital could more easily relocate to a state with a smaller shortfall. Using plausibly exogenous variation driven by pension asset returns, we find that one dollar of pension underfunding reduces house prices near state borders by approximately two dollars. Our estimates imply a deadweight loss associated with addressing pension shortfalls that is consistent with prior research in settings with high returns to public spending and costs of taxation.]]></description><author>Darren Aiello, Asaf Bernstein, Mahyar Kargar, Ryan Lewis, Michael Schwert</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29405</guid></item><item><title>School Food Policy Affects Everyone: Retail Responses to the National School Lunch Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29384</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jessie Handbury, Sarah Moshary.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the private market response to the National School Lunch Program, documenting economically meaningful spillovers to non-recipients. We focus on the Community Eligibility Provision (CEP), an expansion of the lunch program under the 2010 Healthy, Hunger-Free Kids Act. Under the CEP, participating schools offer free lunch to all students. We leverage both the staggered roll-out and eligibility criterion for the CEP, which is limited to schools where at least 40% of students participate in other means-tested welfare programs. We find that local adoption of the CEP causes households with children to reduce their grocery purchases, leading to a 10% decline in grocery sales at large retail chains. Retailers respond with chain-level price adjustments: chains with the most exposure lower prices by 2.5% across all outlets in the years following adoption, so that the program's welfare benefits propagate spatially. Using a stylized model of grocery demand, we estimate that, by 2016, the indirect benefit had reduced grocery costs for the median household by approximately 4.5%.]]></description><author>Jessie Handbury, Sarah Moshary</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29384</guid></item><item><title>Charitable Giving Responses to Education Budgets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29331</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jonathan Meer, Hedieh Tajali.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Do changes in government spending affect voluntary contributions to those recipients? We examine how changes in K-12 education budgets impact donations to teachers using data from DonorsChoose.org, an online crowdfunding platform for public school teachers to raise money for their classrooms. Using a district-year panel and instruments to address the endogeneity of budgets, we find evidence for crowd-out of private giving, though the magnitudes are fairly small in this setting and do not offset a large proportion of a budget change. These results are driven by entirely teachers' posting of requests, illustrating the importance of considering the demand side of the charitable giving market.]]></description><author>Jonathan Meer, Hedieh Tajali</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29331</guid></item><item><title>Empathy and the Efficient Provision of Public Goods</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29255</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Geoffrey Heal.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> I consider the effect of empathy towards others on the internalization of interpersonal externalities and on private contributions to the provision of public goods. I show that if preferences are empathetic in the sense of depending on the well-being of others, then in an extreme case external effects are fully internalized, and private contributions to the provision of a public good will be sufficient for it to be provided at an efficient level. Furthermore I show that an increase in the level of empathy shown by any agent will lead to an increase in the level of provision of the public good, and that as empathy levels increase towards their upper bound, the level of provision of the public good converges to the efficient level. Under certain conditions an increase in empathy is Pareto improving. As it is well-documented that people display some degree of empathy, it is arguable that our failure to provide public goods at efficient levels is attributable to lack of empathy as well as to the free rider problem.]]></description><author>Geoffrey Heal</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29255</guid></item><item><title>Perceptions of Racial Gaps, their Causes, and Ways to Reduce Them</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29245</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alberto Alesina, Matteo F. Ferroni, Stefanie Stantcheva.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Using new large-scale survey and experimental data, we investigate how respondents perceive racial inequities between Black and white Americans, what they believe causes them, and what interventions, if any, they think should be implemented to reduce them. We intentionally over-sample Black respondents, cover many US cities, and survey both adults and young people of ages 13 through 17. In the experimental parts, we consider the causal impact of information on racial inequities (such as the evolution of the Black-white earnings gap or the diﬀerences in mobility for Black and white children) and explanations for these inequities (i.e., the deep-seated roots and long-lasting consequences of systemic racism) on respondents’ views. Although there is heterogeneity in how respondents perceive the magnitude of current racial gaps in economic conditions and opportunities, the biggest discrepancies are in how they explain them. There is a stark partisan gap among white respondents, particularly in the perceived causes of racial inequities and what should be done about them. White Democrats and Black respondents are much more likely to attribute racial inequities to adverse past and present circumstances and want to act on them with race-targeted and general redistribution policies. White Republicans are more likely to attribute racial gaps to individual actions. These views are already deeply entrenched in teenagers, based on their race and their parents’ political aﬃliation. A policy decomposition shows that the perceived causes of racial inequities correlate most strongly with support for race-targeted or general redistribution policies, a ﬁnding conﬁrmed by the experimental results.]]></description><author>Alberto Alesina, Matteo F. Ferroni, Stefanie Stantcheva</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29245</guid></item><item><title>Police Officer Assignment and Neighborhood Crime</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29243</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Bocar Ba, Patrick Bayer, Nayoung Rim, Roman Rivera, Modibo Sidibé.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We develop an empirical model of the mechanism used to assign police officers to Chicago districts and examine the efficiency and equity of alternative allocations. We document that the current bidding process, which grants priority based on seniority, results in the assignment of more experienced officers to less violent and high-income neighborhoods. Our empirical model combines estimates of heterogeneous officer preferences underlying the bidding process with causal estimates of the effects of officer experience on neighborhood crime. Equalizing officer seniority across districts would reduce violent crime rate by 4.6 percent and significantly decrease inequality in crime, discretionary arrests, and officer use of force across neighborhoods. Moreover, this assignment can be achieved in a revenue-neutral way while resulting in small welfare gains for police officers, implying that it is more equitable and efficient.]]></description><author>Bocar Ba, Patrick Bayer, Nayoung Rim, Roman Rivera, Modibo Sidibé</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29243</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of a Government Risk Pool and an Opt-Out Framing on Demand for Earthquake Protection</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29144</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Howard Kunreuther, Lynn Conell-Price, Paul Kovacs, Katsuichiro Goda.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> This paper describes the design and analysis of a web-based choice experiment that examines how the demand for earthquake protection in Quebec and British Columbia is influenced by the default option and the structure of the insurance plan. Homeowners in both provinces were given the opportunity to purchase protection against earthquake losses when presented with one of the following options: the current private insurance plan, a high deductible private insurance plan, and a proposed public-private risk pool. The default frame was changed so the homeowner could either opt-in by purchasing this coverage or opt-out of being given this protection and receiving a premium discount.  Assigning participants to a public-private risk pool rather than the current private insurance plan increases the likelihood of purchasing earthquake protection by 151%. The opt-out frame leads to a likelihood greater than 1.6 of purchasing coverage relative to the opt-in frame when given the same plan structure. The policy implications of this finding are discussed.]]></description><author>Howard Kunreuther, Lynn Conell-Price, Paul Kovacs, Katsuichiro Goda</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29144</guid></item><item><title>What Do You Think About Climate Finance?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29136</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Johannes Stroebel, Jeffrey Wurgler.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> We survey 861 finance academics, professionals, and public sector regulators and policy economists about climate finance topics. They identify regulatory risk as the top climate risk to businesses and investors over the next five years, but they view physical risks as the top risk over the next 30 years. By an overwhelming margin, respondents believe that asset prices underestimate climate risks. We also tabulate opinions about the correlation between growth and climate change; social discount rates appropriate for projects that mitigate the effects of climate change; most influential forces for reducing climate risks; and, most important research topics.]]></description><author>Johannes Stroebel, Jeffrey Wurgler</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29136</guid></item></channel></rss>