<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by programs: Health Economics</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by programs: Health Economics</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 23:04:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Missing Baby Bust: The Consequences of the COVID-19 Pandemic for Contraceptive Use, Pregnancy, and Childbirth among Low-Income Women</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29722</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martha J. Bailey, Lea J. Bart, Vanessa Wanner Lang.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Multiple episodes in U.S. history demonstrate that birth rates fall in response to recessions. However, the 2020 COVID-19 recession differed from earlier periods in that employment and access to contraception and abortion fell, as reproductive health centers across the country temporarily closed or reduced their capacity. This paper exploits novel survey and administrative data to examine how reductions in access to reproductive health care during 2020 affected contraceptive efficacy among low-income women. Accounting for 2020’s reductions in access to contraception and the economic slowdown, our results predict a modest decline in births of 1.1 percent in 2021 for low-income women. Further accounting for reductions in access to abortion implies that birth rates may even rise for low-income women. These results also suggest that already economically disadvantaged families disproportionately affected by the COVID-19 economy will experience a large increase in unplanned births.]]></description><author>Martha J. Bailey, Lea J. Bart, Vanessa Wanner Lang</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29722</guid></item><item><title>Lethal Unemployment Bonuses? Substitution and Income Effects on Substance Abuse, 2020-21</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29719</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Casey B. Mulligan.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Marginal prices fell, and disposable incomes increased, for drug and alcohol consumers during the pandemic.  Most of the amount, timing, and composition of the 240,000 deaths involving alcohol and drugs since early 2020 can be explained by income effects and category-specific price changes.  For alcohol, the pandemic shifted consumption from bars and restaurants to homes, where marginal money prices are lower.  For more dangerous illegal drugs like fentanyl and methamphetamine, the full price of consumption also significantly fell whenever employment became financially less attractive, as it was while unemployment bonuses were elevated.  Both the wage effect and income effects further reduced marginal opioid prices by inducing shifts toward cheap fentanyl.  Drug mortality dipped in the months between the $600 and $300 bonuses, especially for age groups participating most in UI.  A corollary to this analysis is that national employment rates will be slow to recover due to the increased prevalence of alcohol and, especially, drug addiction.]]></description><author>Casey B. Mulligan</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29719</guid></item><item><title>Have Recreational Marijuana Laws Undermined Public Health Progress on Adult Tobacco Use?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29706</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Dhaval M. Dave, Yang Liang, Michael F. Pesko, Serena Phillips, Joseph J. Sabia.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Public health experts caution that legalization of recreational marijuana may normalize smoking and undermine the decades-long achievements of tobacco control policy.  However, very little is known about the impact of recreational marijuana laws (RMLs) on adult tobacco use.  Using information from four national datasets (National Survey of Drug Use and Health, Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System, Current Population Survey-Tobacco Use Supplements, and Population Assessment of Tobacco and Health) and dynamic difference-in-differences and discrete-time hazard approaches, we find little support for the hypothesis that RML enactment leads to increases in adult tobacco use.  In the short-run, RMLs have no effect on tobacco use and in the medium-run, we find some evidence of a lagged reduction in tobacco use on the order of approximately 0.5 to 2 percentage points.  This finding generally persists across cigarettes and e-cigarettes, is robust to event-study analyses generated from estimators designed to expunge bias due to heterogeneous dynamic treatment effects, and persists in panel data-based survival analyses that account for consumption dynamics.  We conclude that fears of adult tobacco-related public health costs from RMLs are, at least in the short- and medium-run, unfounded; instead, there may be important public health benefits from reductions in adult tobacco use.]]></description><author>Dhaval M. Dave, Yang Liang, Michael F. Pesko, Serena Phillips, Joseph J. Sabia</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29706</guid></item><item><title>Does Quitting Smoking Increase Obesity? Evidence From Accounting for Misreporting</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29701</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rusty Tchernis, Keith F. Teltser, Arjun Teotia.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Smoking and obesity are the two leading causes of preventable deaths in the United States. Because smoking is subject to heavy government intervention, understanding the effect of smoking on obesity is important in determining the extent of unintended costs or benefits of such intervention. The existing literature on this question is mixed among studies using experimental and observational data, which we attempt to reconcile by accounting for misreporting in observational data. We use self-reported data from the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS), cigarette taxes to instrument for changes in smoking, and survey completion to instrument for misreporting. Starting with the baseline two-stage least squares (2SLS) estimator common in the earlier observational literature, we obtain similar estimates suggesting quitting smoking substantially reduces BMI. However, we find the results are sensitive to specification, functional form, and the presence of misreporting. We show that accounting for misreporting using the 2-step estimator developed by Nguimkeu et al. (2019) yields estimates consistent with the experimental literature; quitting smoking has a small positive effect on BMI. Our preferred estimate suggests reduced smoking accounts for 6% of the concurrent rise in obesity.]]></description><author>Rusty Tchernis, Keith F. Teltser, Arjun Teotia</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29701</guid></item><item><title>Education and Income Gradients in Longevity: The Role of Policy</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29694</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Adriana Lleras-Muney.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Education and income are strong predictors of health and longevity. In the last 20 years many efforts have been made to understand if these relationships are causal and what the possible role of policy should be as a result. The evidence from various studies is ambiguous: the effects of education and income policies on health are heterogeneous and vary over time, and across places and populations. I discuss explanations for these disparate results and suggest directions for future research.]]></description><author>Adriana Lleras-Muney</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29694</guid></item><item><title>Two-Way Fixed Effects and Differences-in-Differences with Heterogeneous Treatment Effects: A Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29691</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&#039;Haultfoeuille.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Linear regressions with period and group fixed effects are widely used to estimate policies' effects: 26 of the 100 most cited papers published by the American Economic Review from 2015 to 2019 estimate such regressions. It has recently been show that those regressions may produce misleading estimates, if the policy's effect is heterogeneous between groups or over time, as is often the case. This survey reviews a fast-growing literature that documents this issue, and that proposes alternative estimators robust to heterogeneous effects.]]></description><author>Clément de Chaisemartin, Xavier D&amp;#039;Haultfoeuille</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29691</guid></item><item><title>Vaccine Allocation Priorities Using Disease Surveillance and Economic Data</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29682</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anup Malani, Satej Soman, Sabareesh Ramachandran, Alice Chen, Darius N. Lakdawalla.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Vaccination is a critical tool, along with suppression and treatment, for controlling epidemics such as SARS-CoV-2.  To maximize the impact of vaccination, doses should be allocated to the highest value targets, accounting for health and potential economic benefits.  We examine what allocation strategy is optimal and how to translate that strategy into actionable procurement decisions in the context of India.  We compare 3 different allocation strategies (oldest first, highest contact rate first, random order) across 4 outcomes (lives saved, life-years saved, value of statistical lives saved, value of statistical life-years saved).  We make 3 methodological contributions.  First, we estimate the incremental health benefit of vaccination using novel, local seroprevalence data from India.  Second, we estimate the value of statistical life-years using disaggregated, monthly data on consumption during the pandemic.  Third, and most importantly, we estimate social demand curves for vaccines that can practically guide government procurement decisions.  Our analysis yields 4 novel findings.  First, the need to speed-up vaccination does not justify deviation from elderly-first prioritization.  Second, much of the value of vaccination comes from improvements in consumption rather than longevity.  Moreover, vaccination increases the value of a life year because it increases consumption.  Third, social demand for vaccination falls over time as natural immunity from infections increases.  Therefore, the slower a country vaccinates its population, the fewer doses it should procure.  Fourth, there is enough variation in consumption and infection risk that it makes sense to vaccinate some areas before others.  Our approach of connecting epidemiological models and data on health and consumption to economic valuation methods generalizes to other infection control strategies, such as suppression, and public health crises, such as influenza and HIV.]]></description><author>Anup Malani, Satej Soman, Sabareesh Ramachandran, Alice Chen, Darius N. Lakdawalla</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29682</guid></item><item><title>Segregation and the Initial Provision of Water in the United States</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29678</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Brian Beach, John Parman, Martin H. Saavedra.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> U.S. cities invested heavily in water and sewer infrastructure throughout the late 19th and early 20th centuries. These investments improved public health and quality of life by helping U.S. cities control typhoid fever and other waterborne diseases. We show that segregated cities invested in water infrastructure earlier but were slower to reach universal access and slower to eliminate typhoid fever. We develop a theoretical model that illustrates how segregation, by facilitating the exclusion of Black households from water and sewer systems, explains these seemingly paradoxical findings.]]></description><author>Brian Beach, John Parman, Martin H. Saavedra</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29678</guid></item><item><title>Occupational Licensing and the Healthcare Labor Market</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29665</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marcus Dillender, Anthony T. Lo Sasso, Brian J. Phelan, Michael R. Richards.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We examine the labor market impact of states easing occupational license requirements by expanding the scope of practice (SOP) for nurse practitioners (NPs), allowing them to practice without physician oversight. Using data on job postings, we find that employers increase their demand for NPs when states expand NP SOP. We then show that these laws increase NP earnings and reallocate NPs across the healthcare sector, increasing self-employment and changing industrial employment. However, we see no evidence that these laws have increased overall NP employment. Our results suggest that expanding NP SOP has the potential to increase the number of primary care providers, but inelastic labor supply for NPs is largely preventing this from occurring.]]></description><author>Marcus Dillender, Anthony T. Lo Sasso, Brian J. Phelan, Michael R. Richards</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29665</guid></item><item><title>Health Insurance for Whom? The ‘Spill-up’ Effects of Children’s Health Insurance on Mothers</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29661</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel S. Grossman ⓡ, Sebastian Tello-Trillo ⓡ, Barton Willage ⓡ.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> A rich literature documents the benefits of social safety net programs for children. This paper focuses on an unexplored margin: how children’s programs impact parents’ well-being. We explore changes in children’s public health insurance and its effects on parents’ economic and behavioral outcomes. Using a simulated eligibility for Medicaid eligibility expansions in the 1980s and 1990s, we isolate variation in children’s Medicaid eligibility due to changes in government policies. We find that increases in children’s Medicaid eligibility increases the likelihood a mother is married, decreases her labor market participation, and reduces her smoking and alcohol consumption. Our findings suggest improved maternal well-being as measured by the Center for Epidemiological Studies-Depression score, a proxy for mental health. These results uncover a new link that provides an important mechanism, parental well-being, for interpreting the literature’s findings on the long-term, short-term, and intergenerational effects of Medicaid coverage.]]></description><author>Daniel S. Grossman ⓡ, Sebastian Tello-Trillo ⓡ, Barton Willage ⓡ</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29661</guid></item><item><title>The Variability and Volatility of Sleep: An ARCHetypal Behavior</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29658</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel S. Hamermesh, Gerard A. Pfann.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Using Dutch time-diary data from 1975-2005 covering over 10,000 respondents for 7 consecutive days each, we show that individuals’ sleep time exhibits both variability and volatility characterized by stationary autoregressive conditional heteroscedasticity: The absolute values of deviations from a person’s average sleep on one day are positively correlated with those on the next day. Sleep is more variable on weekends and among people with less education, who are younger and who do not have young children at home. Volatility is greater among parents with young children, slightly greater among men than women, but independent of other demographics. A theory of economic incentives to minimize the dispersion of sleep predicts that higher-wage workers will exhibit less dispersion, a result demonstrated using extraneous estimates of earnings equations to impute wage rates. Volatility in sleep spills over onto volatility in other personal activities, with no reverse causation onto sleep. The results illustrate a novel dimension of economic inequality and could be applied to a wide variety of human behavior and biological processes.]]></description><author>Daniel S. Hamermesh, Gerard A. Pfann</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29658</guid></item><item><title>A Cross-Country Comparison of Old Age Financial Readiness in Asian Countries vs. the United States: The Case of Japan and the Republic of Korea</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29649</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Isaac Ehrlich, Yong Yin.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We pursue a cross-country comparison of relative financial readiness of older households in Japan and the Republic of Korea relative to the US.  Our comparative analysis, using macro-level and harmonized longitudinal household financial data, covers the principal financial channels of old age support: public and private pension plans, family support, and self-management of private financial portfolios. We find that while all three countries have similar public pension systems, older Americans benefit from more developed and better-funded public and private pension systems, as well as individual management of risky financial portfolios. We find that educational and health attainments of household heads and household wealth lead to a greater tendency to hold and manage risky assets. Our decomposition analysis also shows that the gap in stock ownership in Asian countries relative to the US is attributable to lower development levels of financial and pension markets. However, these gaps are shrinking more recently.]]></description><author>Isaac Ehrlich, Yong Yin</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29649</guid></item><item><title>Technology and Resilience</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29644</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Diego A. Comin, Marcio Cruz, Xavier Cirera, Kyung Min Lee, Jesica Torres.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper estimates the impact of technology sophistication pre-COVID-19 on the performance of firms during the early stages of the pandemic. We exploit a unique data covering firms from Brazil, Senegal, and Vietnam using a treatment effect mediation framework to decompose the results into a direct and an indirect effect. Increasing pre-pandemic technology sophistication by one standard deviation is associated with 3.8pp higher sales. Both effects are positive, but the direct effect is about 5 times larger than the indirect effect. The total effect on sales is markedly nonlinear with significantly smaller estimates of the reduction in sales for firms with more sophisticated pre-pandemic technology. Our results are robust to different measures of digital responses and matching estimators.]]></description><author>Diego A. Comin, Marcio Cruz, Xavier Cirera, Kyung Min Lee, Jesica Torres</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29644</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of School and Childcare Closures on Labor Market Outcomes during the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29641</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kairon Shayne D. Garcia, Benjamin W. Cowan.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> A substantial fraction of schools and childcare facilities in the United States closed their in-person operations during the COVID-19 pandemic. These closures may carry substantial costs to the families of affected children. In this paper, we examine the impact of school and childcare closures on parental labor market outcomes during the COVID-19 pandemic. In particular, we test whether COVID-19 school closures have a disproportionate impact on parents of school-age children (age 5-17 years old) and whether childcare closures affect parents of young children (age &lt;5 years old) relative to others. Our results suggest that while closures have had little impact on whether parents work at all, they have had significant effects on whether parents work full time (at least 35 hours) and the number of hours worked per week. These effects are concentrated among low-educated parents, suggesting that such individuals had a more difficult time adjusting their work life to closures.]]></description><author>Kairon Shayne D. Garcia, Benjamin W. Cowan</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29641</guid></item><item><title>Bounds, Benefits, and Bad Air: Welfare Impacts of Pollution Alerts</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29637</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael L. Anderson, Minwoo Hyun, Jaecheol Lee.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Though air-quality alert systems (AQAS) cover more than 1.7 billion people worldwide, there has been little welfare analysis of these systems. This paper presents a theoretical framework for deriving lower bounds on the net benefits of an AQAS and applies it to a South Korean system currently covering over 51 million people. Estimating a regression discontinuity design, we find that an alert issuance reduced youth respiratory expenditures by 30% and adult cardiovascular expenditures by 23%. The overall system reduced externalized health expenditures by 28.6 million dollars during 2016–2017, with a minimum benefit-cost ratio of 7.1:1. Including dynamic impacts of alerts increases the minimum benefits (benefit-cost ratio) to 36.7 million dollars (9.2:1). Our findings imply that the AQAS generates significant net benefits and suggests that manipulation of air quality data, which has been observed in other contexts, may negatively impact social welfare.]]></description><author>Michael L. Anderson, Minwoo Hyun, Jaecheol Lee</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29637</guid></item><item><title>The Marginal Cost of Mortality Risk Reduction: Evidence from Housing Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29622</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kelly Bishop, Nicolai V. Kuminoff, Sophie Mathes, Alvin Murphy.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We provide the first evidence that spatial variation in all-cause mortality risk is capitalized into US housing prices. Using a hedonic framework, we recover the annual implicit cost of a 0.1 percentage-point reduction in mortality risk among older Americans and find that this figure is both relatively low and decreasing in age, from $1,346 for a 67 year old to $246 for an 87 year old. These estimates are one-fifth of the size of comparable estimates found in the labor market, suggesting that the housing market provides an alternative, substantially cheaper channel to reducing mortality risk.]]></description><author>Kelly Bishop, Nicolai V. Kuminoff, Sophie Mathes, Alvin Murphy</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29622</guid></item><item><title>Estimating the Effects of Milk Inspections on Infant and Child Mortality, 1880-1910</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29620</link><description><![CDATA[<i>D. Mark Anderson, Kerwin Kofi Charles, Michael McKelligott, Daniel I. Rees.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> In the mid-19th century, the urban milk supply in the United States was regularly skimmed or diluted with water, reducing its nutritional value. At the urging of public health experts, cities across the country hired milk inspectors, who were tasked with collecting and analyzing milk samples with the goal of preventing adulteration and skimming. Using city-level data for the period 1880-1910, we explore the effects of milk inspections on infant mortality and mortality among children under the age of 5. Event-study estimates are small and statistically insignificant, providing little evidence of post-treatment reductions in either infant or child mortality.]]></description><author>D. Mark Anderson, Kerwin Kofi Charles, Michael McKelligott, Daniel I. Rees</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29620</guid></item><item><title>Physician Group Influences on Treatment Intensity and Health: Evidence from Physician Switchers</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29613</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joseph J. Doyle Jr., Becky Staiger.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Treatment intensity varies remarkably across physicians, yet the key drivers are not well understood. Meanwhile, the organization of healthcare is undergoing a secular transformation as physicians increasingly work in groups. This paper tests whether physicians' group affiliation matters for practice styles and patient health. Using Medicare inpatient claims data, we compare these outcomes before and after physicians switch between groups of varying treatment intensity while remaining in the same hospital to control for practice setting. Event studies show that internists who join more-intensive groups immediately increase their own treatment intensity, with an elasticity of approximately 0.3; the opposite is found for internists who switch to groups that are less intensive. This change in Medicare spending largely stems from greater quantities of care provided, with some evidence of a change in coding behavior.  We do not detect a change in health outcomes, suggesting that treatment intensity induced by group affiliation may not be productive.]]></description><author>Joseph J. Doyle Jr., Becky Staiger</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29613</guid></item><item><title>Does Physician-Hospital Vertical Integration Signal Care-Coordination? Evidence from Mover-Stayer Analyses of Commercially Insured Enrollees</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29599</link><description><![CDATA[<i>William Encinosa, Avi Dor, PhuongGiang Nguyen.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We examine the impacts of physician-hospital integration on care fragmentation and other measures of care-coordination using a dynamic model of movers and stayers in commercially insured plans. Although recent growth in the share of practicing physicians belonging to these vertical organizations has sparked considerable policy debate, there is a paucity of evidence on the merits of vertical integration in the private segment of the market. We fill the gap by focusing on care-coordination in the relatively open plans that dominate commercial insurance, namely Preferred Provider Organizations (PPOs). We exploit the fact that physician-hospital integration levels vary dramatically across MSA and focus on orthogonal employment-based transfers for identification. We track 415,000 beneficiaries with 17 million claims between 2010 and 2016. We find that standard two-way fixed effect mover-stayer models produce biased estimates since there are heterogeneous effects of integration. Extending the dynamic event study design of Sun and Abraham (2021) to mover-stayer analyses, we are able to avoid these biases. We find that a move from the 10th to 90th percentile of physician integration level causes a 20% relative decrease in a care fragmentation index; similar declines are found in independent markers of fragmentation such as use of out-of-network and single-service facilities. Vertical integration of either primary care physicians or specialists reduced fragmentation significantly. However, only vertical integration of specialists led to significant reductions in medical spending. Our results are robust when adjusting for moves associated with alternative contractual arrangements among providers that do not require outright ownership.]]></description><author>William Encinosa, Avi Dor, PhuongGiang Nguyen</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29599</guid></item><item><title>Labor Reallocation and Remote Work During COVID-19: Real-time Evidence from GitHub</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29598</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Grant R. McDermott, Benjamin Hansen.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on labor activity using real-time data from millions of GitHub users around the world. We show that the pandemic triggered a sharp pattern of labor reallocation at both the global and regional level. Users were more likely to work on weekends and outside of traditional 9 am to 6 pm hours, especially during the early phase of the pandemic. We also document considerable heterogeneity between different user groups and locations. Some locations show a steady reversion back to historical work patterns, while others have experienced persistent trend deviations in the wake of COVID-19. The pattern of labor reallocation is slightly more pronounced among males in our sample, suggesting that men may have benefited more from the increased flexibility provided by remote work than women. Finally, we show that the pattern of reallocation was accompanied by a simultaneous increase in overall activity, though this effect is more transient. We discuss several potential mechanisms and draw tentative conclusions for broader workplace trends given our study population.]]></description><author>Grant R. McDermott, Benjamin Hansen</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29598</guid></item><item><title>Inequality in India Declined During COVID</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29597</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Arpit Gupta, Anup Malani, Bartosz Woda.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We use a large, representative panel data set from India with monthly data on household finances to examine the incidence of economic harms during the COVID pandemic.  We observe a sharp spike in poverty, peaking during India's sharp but short lockdown.  However, there was a striking decrease in income inequality outside the lockdown.  There was a smaller decrease in consumption inequality, likely due to consumption smoothing.  Evidence supports two mechanisms for the decline in income inequality: the capital income of top-quartile earners covaries more with aggregate income, and demand for labor fell more for higher quartiles.]]></description><author>Arpit Gupta, Anup Malani, Bartosz Woda</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29597</guid></item><item><title>Behavioral Responses to Supply-Side Drug Policy During the Opioid Epidemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29596</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Simone Balestra, Helge Liebert, Nicole Maestas, Tisamarie B. Sherry.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We investigate behavioral responses to a staggered disruption in the supply of prescription opioids across U.S. states: the introduction of electronic Prescription Drug Monitoring Programs (PDMPs). Using administrative datasets, we find PDMPs curtail the proliferation of prescription opioids. Physicians respond to monitoring on the extensive margin, limiting the number of patients to whom they prescribe opioids without adjusting dosage or duration. This decreases supply to long-term opioid users, who evade the restrictions by acquiring prescriptions from out-of-state prescribers and by substituting to heroin. This causes a surge in heroin overdoses, which offsets reductions in hospitalizations and deaths from prescription opioids.]]></description><author>Simone Balestra, Helge Liebert, Nicole Maestas, Tisamarie B. Sherry</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29596</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of the COVID-19 Vaccine Distribution on Mental Health Outcomes</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29593</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Virat Agrawal, Jonathan H. Cantor, Neeraj Sood, Christopher M. Whaley.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic has led to a “second pandemic” of anxiety and depression. While vaccines are primarily aimed at reducing COVID-19 transmission and mortality risks, they may have important secondary benefits. We use data from U.S. Census Bureau’s Household Pulse Survey merged to state-level COVID-19 vaccination eligibility data to estimate the secondary benefits of COVID-19 vaccination on mental health outcomes. To address endogenous COVID-19 vaccination, we leverage state-level variation in the timing of when age groups are eligible for vaccination. We estimate that COVID-19 vaccination reduces anxiety and depression symptoms by nearly 30%. Nearly all the benefits are private benefits, and we find little evidence of spillover effects, that is, increases in community vaccination rates are not associated with improved anxiety or depression symptoms among the unvaccinated. We find that COVID-19 vaccination is associated with larger reductions in anxiety or depression symptoms among individuals with lower education levels, who rent their housing, who are not able to telework, and who have children in their household. The economic benefit of reductions in anxiety and depression are approximately $350 billion. Our results highlight an important, but understudied, secondary benefit of COVID-19 vaccinations.]]></description><author>Virat Agrawal, Jonathan H. Cantor, Neeraj Sood, Christopher M. Whaley</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29593</guid></item><item><title>The COVID-19 Pandemic Disrupted Both School Bullying and Cyberbullying</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29590</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andrew Bacher-Hicks, Joshua Goodman, Jennifer G. Green, Melissa Holt.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> One-fifth of U.S. high school students report being bullied each year. We use internet search data for real-time tracking of bullying patterns as COVID-19 disrupted in-person schooling. We first show that, prepandemic, internet searches contain useful information about actual bullying behavior. We then show that searches for school bullying and cyberbullying dropped 30-35 percent as schools shifted to remote learning in spring 2020. The gradual return to in-person instruction starting in fall 2020 partially returns bullying searches to pre-pandemic levels. This rare positive effect may partly explain recent mixed evidence on the pandemic’s impact on students’ mental health and well-being.]]></description><author>Andrew Bacher-Hicks, Joshua Goodman, Jennifer G. Green, Melissa Holt</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29590</guid></item><item><title>Taking the Pulse of Nations: a Biometric Measure of Well-being</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29587</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> A growing literature identifies associations between subjective and biometric indicators of wellbeing.  These associations, together with the ability of subjective wellbeing (SWB) metrics to predict health and behavioral outcomes, have spawned increasing interest in SWB as an important concept in its own right.  However, some social scientists continue to question the usefulness of SWB metrics.  We contribute to this literature in three ways.  First, we introduce a biometric measure of wellbeing – pulse – which has been largely overlooked.  Using nationally representative data on 165,000 individuals from the Health Survey for England (HSE) and Scottish Health Surveys (SHeS) we show that its correlates are similar in a number of ways to those for SWB, and that it is highly correlated with SWB metrics, as well as self-assessed health.  Second, we examine the determinants of pulse rates in mid-life (age 42) among the 9,000 members of the National Child Development Study (NCDS), a birth cohort born in a single week in 1958 in Britain.  Third, we track the impact of pulse measured in mid-life (age 42) on health and labor market outcomes at age 50 in 2008 and age 55 in 2013.  The probability of working at age 55 is negatively impacted by pulse rate a decade earlier.  The pulse rate has an impact over and above chronic pain measured at age 42.  General health at 55 is lower the higher the pulse rate at age 42, while those with higher pulse rates at 42 also express lower life satisfaction and more pessimism about the future at age 50.  Taken together, these results suggest social scientists can learn a great deal by adding pulse rates to the metrics they use when evaluating people’s wellbeing.]]></description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29587</guid></item><item><title>Effect of Health Insurance in India: A Randomized Controlled Trial</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29576</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anup Malani, Phoebe Holtzman, Kosuke Imai, Cynthia Kinnan, Morgen Miller, Shailender Swaminathan, Alessandra Voena, Bartosz Woda, Gabriella Conti.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We report on a large randomized controlled trial of hospital insurance for above-poverty-line Indian households.  Households were assigned to free insurance, sale of insurance, sale plus cash transfer, or control.  To estimate spillovers, the fraction of households offered insurance varied across villages.  The opportunity to purchase insurance led to 59.91% uptake and access to free insurance to 78.71% uptake.  Access increased insurance utilization. Positive spillover effects on utilization suggest learning from peers.  Many beneficiaries were unable to use insurance, demonstrating hurdles to expanding access via insurance.  Across a range of health measures, we estimate no significant impacts on health.]]></description><author>Anup Malani, Phoebe Holtzman, Kosuke Imai, Cynthia Kinnan, Morgen Miller, Shailender Swaminathan, Alessandra Voena, Bartosz Woda, Gabriella Conti</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29576</guid></item><item><title>Peltzman Revisited: Quantifying 21st Century Opportunity Costs of FDA Regulation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29574</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Casey B. Mulligan.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> This paper revisits Peltzman (1973) in light of two recent opportunities to quantitatively assess tradeoffs in drug regulation.  First, reduced regulatory barriers to drug manufacturing associated with the 2017 reauthorization of Generic Drug User Fee Amendments were followed by significantly more entry and lower consumer prices for prescription drugs.  Using a simple and versatile industry model and historical data on entry, I find that easing generic restrictions discourages innovation, but this welfare cost is more than offset by consumer benefits from enhanced competition, especially after 2016.  Second, accelerated vaccine approval in 2020 had unprecedented net benefits as it not only improved health but substantially changed the trajectory of the wider economy.  The evidence suggests that cost-benefit analysis of FDA regulation is incomplete without accounting for substitution toward potentially unsafe and ineffective treatments that are both outside FDA jurisdiction and heavily utilized prior to FDA approval.  Moreover, the policy processes initiating these 21st century regulatory changes show a clear influence of Peltzman’s 1973 findings.]]></description><author>Casey B. Mulligan</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29574</guid></item><item><title>Randomization for Causality, Ethnography for Mechanisms: Illiquid Savings for Liquor in an Autarkic Society</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29566</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ricardo Godoy, Dean Karlan, Jonathan Zinman.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> What should researchers do when confronted with surprising results? Financial access innovations usually leave “temptation” spending unaffected or reduced. However, we found that promotion of savings lockboxes in a largely autarkic society increased alcohol consumption and blood pressure, despite no one reporting intentions to save for alcohol. To probe mechanisms that could explain this pattern, we then used ethnographic methods, including direct observations of drinking (“scans”) and debriefing interviews to discuss the earlier trial results. We learn that sponsoring drinks confers prestige, but the stigma attached to drinking by outsiders likely discouraged reporting intentions to save for it.]]></description><author>Ricardo Godoy, Dean Karlan, Jonathan Zinman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29566</guid></item><item><title>When (and Why) Providers Do Not Respond to Changes in Reimbursement Rates</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29564</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marcus Dillender, Lu G. Jinks, Anthony T. Lo Sasso.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> High health care prices contribute to the United States spending more on health care than any other country, but policies that reduce health care payments have the potential to lead to health care access issues if providers reduce their supply in response to reimbursement rate reductions.  In this paper, we examine the impact of reimbursement rates on health care supply by studying a policy that reduced reimbursement rates by 30% in one of the highest-reimbursing workers' compensation insurance systems in the nation. Despite the large decrease in reimbursement rates, we find no evidence that the policy affected the amount of health care that injured workers receive or recoveries after injuries. Our estimates suggest that the policy reduced annual workers' compensation medical costs by over $400 million and indicate that providers may be operating on the inelastic portion of the supply curve for care paid for by high-reimbursing payers.]]></description><author>Marcus Dillender, Lu G. Jinks, Anthony T. Lo Sasso</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29564</guid></item><item><title>COVID-19 Vaccination Mandates and Vaccine Uptake</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29563</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexander Karaivanov, Dongwoo Kim, Shih En Lu, Hitoshi Shigeoka.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We evaluate the impact of government mandated proof of vaccination requirements for access to public venues and non-essential businesses on COVID-19 vaccine uptake. We find that the announcement of a mandate is associated with a rapid and significant surge in new vaccinations (more than 60\% increase in weekly first doses) using the variation in the timing of these measures across Canadian provinces in a difference-in-differences approach. Time-series analysis for each province and for France, Italy and Germany corroborates this finding, and we estimate cumulative gains of up to 5 percentage points in provincial vaccination rates and 790,000 or more first doses for Canada as a whole as of October 31, 2021 (5 to 13 weeks after the provincial mandate announcements). We also find large vaccination gains in France (3 to 5 mln first doses), Italy (around 6 mln) and Germany (around 3.5 mln) 11 to 16 weeks after the proof of vaccination mandate announcements.]]></description><author>Alexander Karaivanov, Dongwoo Kim, Shih En Lu, Hitoshi Shigeoka</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29563</guid></item><item><title>Researchers' Degrees-of-Flexibility and the Credibility of Difference-in-Differences Estimates: Evidence From the Pandemic Policy Evaluations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29550</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joakim A. Weill, Matthieu Stigler, Olivier Deschenes, Michael R. Springborn.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic brought unprecedented policy responses and a large literature evaluating their impacts. This paper re-examines this literature and investigates the role of researchers' degrees-of-flexibility on the estimated effects of mobility-reducing policies on social-distancing behavior. We find that two-way fixed effects estimates are not robust to minor changes in usually-unexplored dimensions of the degree-of-flexibility space. While standard robustness tests based on the sequential addition of covariates are very stable, small changes in the outcome variable and its transformation lead to large and sometimes contradictory changes in the estimates, where the same policy can be found to significantly increase or decrease mobility. Yet, due to the large number of degrees-of-flexibility, one can focus on a set of results that appears stable, while ignoring problematic ones. We show that recently developed heterogeneity-robust difference-in-differences estimators only partially mitigate these issues, and discuss how a strategy of identifying the point at which a sequence of ever more-stringent robustness tests eventually fail could increase the credibility of policy evaluations.]]></description><author>Joakim A. Weill, Matthieu Stigler, Olivier Deschenes, Michael R. Springborn</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29550</guid></item><item><title>Did the Hospital Readmissions Reduction Program Reduce Readmissions? An Assessment of Prior Evidence and New Estimates</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29545</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Engy Ziedan, Robert Kaestner.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> In this article, we provide a comprehensive, empirical assessment of the hypothesis that the Hospital Readmissions Reduction Program (HRRP) affected hospital readmissions. In doing so, we provide evidence as to the validity of prior empirical approaches used to evaluate the HRRP and we present results from a previously unused approach to study this research question—a regression-kink design. Results of our analysis document that the empirical approaches used in most prior research assessing the efficacy of the HRRP often lack internal validity. Therefore, results from these studies may not be informative about the causal consequences of the HRRP. Results from our regression-kink analysis, which we validate, suggest that the HRRP had little effect on hospital readmissions. This finding contrasts with the results of most prior studies, which report that the HRRP significantly reduced readmissions. Our finding is consistent with conceptual considerations related to the assumptions underlying HRRP penalty; in particular, the difficulty of identifying preventable readmissions, the highly imperfect risk adjustment that affects the penalty determination and the absence of proven tools to reduce readmissions.]]></description><author>Engy Ziedan, Robert Kaestner</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29545</guid></item><item><title>Gender Differences in Medical Evaluations: Evidence from Randomly Assigned Doctors</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29541</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marika Cabral, Marcus Dillender.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> While a growing body of evidence documents large gender disparities in health care and related social insurance programs, little is known about what drives these disparities.  We leverage administrative data and random assignment of doctors to patients inherent within the workers’ compensation insurance claim dispute resolution process to study the impact of gender match between doctors and patients on medical evaluations and subsequent social insurance benefits received. Compared to differences among their male patient counterparts, female patients randomly assigned a female doctor rather than a male doctor are 5.0% more likely to be evaluated as disabled and receive 8.5% more subsequent cash benefits on average. There is no analogous gender-match effect for male patients. The magnitude of these effects implies that having female doctors evaluate patients entirely offsets the observed gender gap in the likelihood of being evaluated as disabled when male doctors evaluate patients. We explore mechanisms through further analysis of the administrative data and complementary survey evidence. In addition, we present broader evidence on gender gaps in workers' compensation insurance and gender homophily in patients' selections of doctors in settings where patients have choice. Combining this evidence, we conduct policy counterfactuals illustrating how policies increasing gender diversity among doctors or increasing gender homophily in patient-doctor matches may impact gender gaps in evaluated disability. Our findings indicate that policies increasing the share of female patients evaluated by female doctors may substantially shrink gender gaps in medical evaluations and associated outcomes.]]></description><author>Marika Cabral, Marcus Dillender</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29541</guid></item><item><title>The Effects of Becoming a Physician on Prescription Drug Use and Mental Health Treatment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29536</link><description><![CDATA[<i>D. Mark Anderson, Ron Diris, Raymond Montizaan, Daniel I. Rees.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> There is evidence that physicians disproportionately suffer from substance use disorder and mental health problems.  It is not clear, however, whether these phenomena are causal.  We use data on Dutch medical school applicants to examine the effects of becoming a physician on prescription drug use and the receipt of treatment from a mental health facility.  Leveraging variation from lottery outcomes that determine admission into medical schools, we find that becoming a physician increases the use of antidepressants, opioids, anxiolytics, and sedatives, especially for female physicians. Among female applicants towards the bottom of the GPA distribution, becoming a physician increases the likelihood of receiving treatment from a mental health facility.]]></description><author>D. Mark Anderson, Ron Diris, Raymond Montizaan, Daniel I. Rees</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29536</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of Health and Education on Labor Force Participation in Aging Societies – Projections for the United States and Germany from a Dynamic Microsimulation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29534</link><description><![CDATA[<i>René Böheim, Thomas Horvath, Thomas Leoni, Martin Spielauer.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Using a highly stylized dynamic microsimulation model, we project the labor force of the United States up to the year 2060 and contrast these projections with projections for Germany to assess differential effects on outcomes The projections are consistent with the U S Census Bureau’s and Eurostat’s demographic projections. Our modeling approach allows to show and quantify how policy changes the future size of the labor force, which we assess with a series of what-if scenarios.<br />
Both the US and Germany are expected to undergo demographic aging, but their demographic fundamentals differ starkly. This has strong implications for their labor force developments. According to our microsimulation, the US labor force will, despite population aging, increase by 16.2 percent in the age groups 15 to 74 (corresponding to 25.2 million workers) between 2020 and 2060, while Germany will experience a decline by 10.7 percent (4.4 million workers). In these baseline projections, improvements in the education structure will add about two million persons to the US labor force and about half a million persons to the German labor force by 2060.<br />
In the what-if scenarios, we examine the implications of improvements in the educational structure of the population and of policies which address the health impediments for labor force participation. Of the educational scenarios that we evaluate, increasing the number of persons who achieve more than lower education has the strongest positive impact on labor force participation, relative to the number of additional years of schooling implied by the various scenarios. Shifting people from intermediate to higher education levels also increases labor force participation in higher age groups, however, this is partially offset by lock in effects at younger ages.<br />
Our projections highlight that improvements in the labor market integration of people with health limitations provide a particularly promising avenue to increase labor force participation rates and thus help to address the challenges posed by demographic aging. If the health gap in participation rates in the United States were similar to that currently observed in Sweden, the labor force in 2060 would be larger by about 14.9 million persons.]]></description><author>René Böheim, Thomas Horvath, Thomas Leoni, Martin Spielauer</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29534</guid></item><item><title>Causes and Consequences of Illicit Drug Epidemics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29528</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Timothy J. Moore, Rosalie Liccardo Pacula.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Large and rapid upswings in illicit drug use display similar properties to infectious disease epidemics. In this chapter, we review research to understand what causes drug epidemics and how they end. Drug market actors are subject to both positive and negative reinforcement that lead to rapid, nonlinear increases and decreases in drug market activity. There is evidence that drug epidemics cause serious problems, including drug overdoses, adverse birth outcomes, homicides, lower educational attainment, and migration from neighborhoods subject to intense drug market activity. Many of these costs are borne by those who do not consume or sell drugs. Given the frequency, size, and impacts of illicit drug epidemics, they deserve more attention by researchers and policy-makers.]]></description><author>Timothy J. Moore, Rosalie Liccardo Pacula</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29528</guid></item><item><title>Germs in the Family: The Long-Term Consequences of Intra-Household Endemic Respiratory Disease Spread</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29524</link><description><![CDATA[<i>N. Meltem Daysal, Hui Ding, Maya Rossin-Slater, Hannes Schwandt.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> While the COVID-19 pandemic has laid bare the large costs of infectious diseases, less attention has been paid to the impacts of more common, endemic respiratory viruses that frequently circulate in the population, especially when it comes to their potential long-term consequences for population health, human capital, and economic outcomes. This paper uses Danish population-level administrative data on 35 birth cohorts of children to provide a comprehensive analysis of both the mechanisms through which infants become infected by respiratory illnesses, as well as the consequences of early-life respiratory disease exposure for their later outcomes. First, we document a striking difference in the likelihood of severe respiratory illness by birth order: younger siblings have two to three times higher rates of hospitalization for respiratory conditions before age one than older siblings at the same age. We argue that the family unit is central in virus transmission, with older children "bringing home" the virus to their younger siblings. We then combine the birth order variation with within-municipality variation in respiratory disease prevalence among preschool-aged children to identify differential long-term impacts of early-life respiratory illness between younger and older siblings. We find that moving from the 25th to the 75th percentile in the local disease prevalence distribution ("disease index") is associated with a 30.9 percent differential increase in the number of respiratory illness hospitalizations in the first year of life for younger compared to older siblings. In the long term, for younger relative to older siblings, we find a 0.5 percent differential reduction in the likelihood of high school graduation, and a 1.3 percent additional reduction in age-30 earnings.]]></description><author>N. Meltem Daysal, Hui Ding, Maya Rossin-Slater, Hannes Schwandt</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29524</guid></item><item><title>Immigrant Labor and the Institutionalization of the U.S.-born Elderly</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29520</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kristin F. Butcher, Kelsey Moran, Tara Watson.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> The U.S. population is aging. We examine whether immigration causally affects the likelihood that the U.S.-born elderly live in institutional settings. Using a shift-share instrument to identify exogenous variation in immigration, we find that a 10 percentage point increase in the less-educated foreign-born labor force share in a local area reduces institutionalization among the elderly by 1.5 and 3.8 percentage points for those aged 65+ and 80+, a 26-29 percent effect relative to the mean. The estimates imply that a typical U.S-born individual over age 65 in the year 2000 was 0.5 percentage points (10 percent) less likely to be living in an institution than would have been the case if immigration had remained at 1980 levels. We show that immigration affects the availability and cost of home services, including those provided by home health aides, gardeners and housekeepers, and other less-educated workers, reducing the cost of aging in the community.]]></description><author>Kristin F. Butcher, Kelsey Moran, Tara Watson</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29520</guid></item><item><title>Excess Deaths in the United States During the First Year of COVID-19</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29503</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher J. Ruhm.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Accurately determining the number of excess deaths caused by the COVID-19 pandemic is hard. The most important challenge is accurately estimating the counterfactual count of baseline deaths that would have occurred in its absence. This analysis used new methods to: estimate this baseline metric; calculate excess deaths during the first year of the U.S. COVID-19 pandemic; and examine plausibility of the excess death estimates obtained in this and prior analyses. Total, group-specific and cause-specific excess deaths in the U.S. from March 2020 through February 2021 were calculated using publicly available data covering all deaths from March 2009 through December 2019 and provisional data from January 2020 through February 2021. The estimates indicate that there were 646,514 (95% CI: 597,514 to 695,520) excess deaths in the U.S. during this period, with 83.4% (95% CI: 77.5% - 90.2%) of these attributed directly to COVID-19. There were substantial differences across population groups and causes in the ratio of actual-to-baseline deaths, and in the contribution of COVID-19 to excess mortality. Prior research has frequently underestimated baseline deaths and so has overstated excess mortality and the percentage of it attributed to non-COVID-19 causes.]]></description><author>Christopher J. Ruhm</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29503</guid></item><item><title>International Evidence on Vaccines and the Mortality to Infections Ratio</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29498</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Aizenman, Alex Cukierman, Yothin Jinjarak, Weining Xin.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Recent observations on countries like the UK that have accumulated a large fraction of inoculated individuals suggest that, although initially, vaccines have little effect on new infections they strongly reduce the share of mortality out of a given pool of infections. This paper examines the extent to which this phenomenon is more general by testing the hypothesis that the ratio of current mortality to lagged infections is decreasing in the total number of vaccines per one hundred individuals. This is done in a pooled time-series, cross-section sample with weekly observations for up to 208 countries. The main conclusion from the statistical analysis is that, passed a certain threshold, vaccines moderate the share of mortality from a given pool of lagged infections. This is essentially a favorable shift in the tradeoff between life preservation and economic performance. Controlling for income per capita, stringency of containment measures, and the fraction of recovered and old individuals, estimation is carried out by linear least squares, with standard errors clustered by country and region. The main result is robust to sensitivity analysis with a logarithmic specification. The practical lesson is that, in the presence of a sufficiently high share of inoculated individuals, governments can shade down containment measures, even as infections are still rampant, without significant adverse effects on mortality.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Alex Cukierman, Yothin Jinjarak, Weining Xin</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29498</guid></item><item><title>Ambulance Taxis: The Impact of Regulation and Litigation on Health Care Fraud</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29491</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Paul J. Eliason, Riley J. League, Jetson Leder-Luis, Ryan C. McDevitt, James W. Roberts.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the relative effectiveness of administrative regulations, criminal enforcement, and civil lawsuits for combatting health care fraud. Between 2003 and 2017, Medicare spent $7.7 billion on 37.5 million regularly scheduled, non-emergency ambulance rides for patients traveling to and from dialysis facilities, with dozens of lawsuits alleging that Medicare reimbursed rides for patients who did not meet the requirements for receiving one. Using a novel data set and an identification strategy based on the staggered timing of regulations and lawsuits across the United States, we find that a regulation requiring prior authorization for ambulance reimbursements reduced spending much more than criminal and civil lawsuits did. Despite the sharp drop in both ambulance transports and the companies that provide them following prior authorization, patients’ health outcomes did not change, indicating that most rides were not medically necessary. Our results suggest that administrative actions have a much larger impact than targeted criminal enforcement, providing novel evidence that regulations may be more cost-effective than ex post ligation for preventing health care fraud.]]></description><author>Paul J. Eliason, Riley J. League, Jetson Leder-Luis, Ryan C. McDevitt, James W. Roberts</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29491</guid></item><item><title>Modeling to Inform Economy-Wide Pandemic Policy: Bringing Epidemiologists and Economists Together</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29475</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael E. Darden, David Dowdy, Lauren Gardner, Barton Hamilton, Karen Kopecky, Melissa Marx, Nicholas W. Papageorge, Daniel Polsky, Kimberly Powers, Elizabeth Stuart, Matthew Zahn.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Facing unprecedented uncertainty and drastic trade-offs between public health and other forms of human well-being, policy makers during the Covid-19 pandemic have sought the guidance of epidemiologists and economists. Unfortunately, while both groups of scientists use many of the same basic mathematical tools, the models they develop to inform policy tend to rely on different sets of assumptions and, thus, often lead to different policy conclusions. This divergence in policy recommendations can lead to uncertainty and confusion, opening the door to disinformation, distrust of institutions, and politicization of scientific facts. Unfortunately, to date, there have not been widespread efforts to build bridges and find consensus or even to clarify sources of differences across these fields, members of whom often continue to work within their traditional academic silos. In response to this “crisis of communication,” we convened a group of scholars from epidemiology, economics, and related fields (e.g., statistics, engineering, and health policy) to discuss approaches to modeling economy-wide pandemics. We summarize these conversations by providing a consensus view of disciplinary differences (including critiques) and working through a specific policy example. Thereafter, we chart a path forward for more effective synergy between disciplines, which we hope will lead to better policies as the current pandemic evolves and future pandemics emerge.]]></description><author>Michael E. Darden, David Dowdy, Lauren Gardner, Barton Hamilton, Karen Kopecky, Melissa Marx, Nicholas W. Papageorge, Daniel Polsky, Kimberly Powers, Elizabeth Stuart, Matthew Zahn</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29475</guid></item><item><title>The Impact of Provider Payments on Health Care Utilization: Evidence from Medicare and Medicaid</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29471</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marika Cabral, Colleen Carey, Sarah Miller.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Provider payments are the key determinant of insurance generosity within many health insurance programs covering low-income populations. This paper analyzes the effects of a large, federally-mandated provider payment increase for primary care services provided to low-income elderly and disabled individuals.  Drawing upon comprehensive administrative payment and utilization data, we leverage variation across beneficiaries and across providers in the policy-induced payment increase in difference-in-differences and triple differences research designs. The estimates indicate that the provider payment reform led to a 6.3% increase in the targeted services provided to eligible beneficiaries, indicating an implied payment elasticity of 1.3.  Further, the provider payment reform decreased the fraction of low-income beneficiaries with no primary care visit in a year by 9%, completely closing the gap relative to higher-income beneficiaries with the same observable characteristics. Additionally, the results indicate that the payment reform caused an increase in established patient visits, with no increase in new patient visits. Heterogeneity analysis indicates that the payment increase led to an expansion of utilization for many subgroups, with somewhat larger effects among beneficiaries who are younger, are white, and live in areas with many primary care providers per capita.]]></description><author>Marika Cabral, Colleen Carey, Sarah Miller</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29471</guid></item><item><title>Office-Based Mental Healthcare and Juvenile Arrests</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29465</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Monica Deza, Thanh Lu, Johanna Catherine Maclean.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We estimate the effect of local access to office-based mental healthcare on juvenile arrest outcomes. We leverage variation in the number of mental healthcare offices within a county over the period 1999 to 2016 in a two-way fixed-effects model. Office-based treatment is the most common modality of mental healthcare received by juveniles. We find that ten additional office-based mental healthcare providers in a county leads a decrease of 2.3% to 2.6% in the per capita costs to society of juvenile arrest. Findings are similar for arrest rates although often less precise, which suggests that accounting for social costs is empirically important. Crime imposes substantial costs on society and individuals, and interventions during early life can have more pronounced effects than those received at later stages, therefore our results imply increased juvenile access to mental healthcare may have an unintended benefit for the current and future generations.]]></description><author>Monica Deza, Thanh Lu, Johanna Catherine Maclean</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29465</guid></item><item><title>A Simple Model of Social Distancing and Vaccination</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29463</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher Avery.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper analyzes a simple model of infectious disease where the incentives for individuals to reduce risks through endogenous social distancing take straightforward cost-benefit form. Since disease is transmitted through social interactions, the threat of spread of infection poses a collective action problem. Policy interventions such as lockdowns, testing, and mask-wearing serve, in part, as substitutes for social distancing. Provision of a vaccination is the only intervention that unambiguously reduces both the peak infection level and the herd immunity level of infection. Adoption of vaccination remains limited in a decentralized equilibrium, with resulting reproductive rate of disease Rt &gt; 1 at the conclusion of vaccination. Vaccine mandates yield increases in vaccination rates and corresponding reductions in future infection rates but do not increase expected payoffs to individuals.]]></description><author>Christopher Avery</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29463</guid></item><item><title>Depression and Shopping Behavior</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29462</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Katherine Meckel, Bradley Shapiro.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Using a large survey panel that connects household shopping behavior with individual health information, this paper documents correlations between self reported depression and the size and composition of shopping baskets. First, we find that roughly 16% of individuals report suffering from depression and over 30% of households have at least one member who reports suffering from depression. Households with a member suffering from depression exhibit striking differences in shopping behavior: they spend less overall, visit grocery stores less and convenience stores more frequently and spend a smaller share of their baskets on fresh produce and alcohol but a larger share on tobacco. They spend similar shares on unhealthy foods like cakes, candy, and salty snacks. These cross-sectional correlations hold within counties, suggesting that they are not driven by region specific demographics or preferences that are incidentally correlated with depression status. They also hold when considering only single-member households. However, we rule out large differences in shopping behavior within households as they change depression status. Further, using the take-up of antidepressants as an event, we document little change in shopping in response to treatment. With our results, we discuss takeaways for the economic impact of depression and for decision modeling.]]></description><author>Katherine Meckel, Bradley Shapiro</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29462</guid></item><item><title>Which Beliefs? Behavior-Predictive Beliefs are Inconsistent with Information-Based Beliefs: Evidence from COVID-19</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29452</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ori Heffetz, Guy Ishai.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the relationship between (a) official information on COVID-19 infection and death case counts; (b) beliefs about such case counts, at present and in the future; (c) beliefs about average infection chance—in principle, directly calculable from (b); and (d) self-reported health-protective behavior. We elicit (b), (c), and (d) with a daily online survey in the US from March to August 2020 (N ≈ 13,900).<br />
We have three main findings: (1) beliefs elicited as infection case counts are closely related to present and future official case-count information; however (2) beliefs elicited as risk perceptions—i.e., the chance to get infected—are inconsistent with those case-count beliefs, even when mathematically, they should be identical; notably, (3) it is the latter—the risk perceptions—that are significantly better predictors of reported behavior than the former.<br />
Together, these findings suggest that researchers and policymakers, who increasingly engage in direct elicitation and communication of numeric measures of uncertainty, may get very different outcomes, depending on which measures they use. We discuss potential implications for public communication of health-risk information.]]></description><author>Ori Heffetz, Guy Ishai</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29452</guid></item><item><title>Bad Lighting: Effects of Youth Indoor Tanning Prohibitions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29443</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher S. Carpenter, Brandyn F. Churchill, Michelle M. Marcus.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Indoor tanning beds (ITBs) emit UV light at high intensity and have been classified as carcinogenic to humans by the World Health Organization since 2009. We are the first to study the role of state laws prohibiting youths from indoor tanning using a difference-in-differences research design. We find that youth ITB prohibitions reduced population search intensity for tanning-related information. Among white teen girls, ITB prohibitions reduced self-reported indoor tanning and increased sun protective behaviors. We also find that youth ITB prohibitions significantly reduced the size of the indoor tanning market by increasing tanning salon closures and reducing tanning salon sales.]]></description><author>Christopher S. Carpenter, Brandyn F. Churchill, Michelle M. Marcus</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29443</guid></item><item><title>The Economics of Medical Procedure Innovation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29438</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Dranove, Craig Garthwaite, Christopher Heard, Bingxiao Wu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper explores the economic incentives for medical procedure innovation. Using a proprietary dataset on billing code applications for emerging medical procedures, we highlight two mechanisms that could hinder innovation. First, the administrative hurdle of securing permanent, reimbursable billing codes substantially delays innovation diffusion. We find that Medicare utilization of innovative procedures increases nearly nine-fold after the billing codes are promoted to permanent (reimbursable) from provisional (non-reimbursable). However, only 29 percent of the provisional codes are promoted within the five-year probation period. Second, medical procedures lack intellectual property rights, especially those without patented devices. When appropriability is limited, specialty medical societies lead the applications for billing codes. We indicate that the ad hoc process for securing billing codes for procedure innovations creates uncertainty about both the development process and the allocation and enforceability of property rights. This stands in stark contrast to the more deliberate regulatory oversight for pharmaceutical innovations.]]></description><author>David Dranove, Craig Garthwaite, Christopher Heard, Bingxiao Wu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29438</guid></item><item><title>Effects of COVID-19 Shutdowns on Domestic Violence in US Cities</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29429</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Amalia R. Miller, Carmit Segal, Melissa K. Spencer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We empirically investigate the impact of COVID-19 shutdowns on domestic violence using incident-level data on both domestic-related calls for service and crime reports of domestic violence assaults from the 18 major US police departments for which both types of records are available. Although we confirm prior reports of an increase in domestic calls for service at the start of the pandemic, we find that the increase preceded mandatory shutdowns, and there was an incremental decline following the government imposition of restrictions. We find no evidence that domestic violence crimes increased. Rather, domestic violence assaults declined significantly during the initial shutdown period and there was no significant change in intimate partner homicides in these months. Nationwide intimate partner violence rates in the National Crime Victimization Survey, including crimes not reported to police, were also lower during shutdown months. Our results fail to support claims that shutdowns increased domestic violence and suggest caution before drawing inference or basing policy on calls data alone.]]></description><author>Amalia R. Miller, Carmit Segal, Melissa K. Spencer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29429</guid></item><item><title>The Effects of Education on Mortality: Evidence Using College Expansions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29423</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jason Fletcher, Hamid Noghanibehambari.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper explores the long-run health benefits of education for longevity. Using mortality data from the Social Security Administration (1988-2005) linked to geographic locations in the 1940-census data, we exploit changes in college availability across cohorts in local areas. We estimate an intent to treat effect of exposure to an additional 4-year college around age 17 of increasing longevity by 0.13 months; treatment on the treated calculations suggest increases in longevity between 1-1.6 years. Some further analyses suggest the results are not driven by pre-tends, endogenous migration, and other time-varying local confounders. This paper adds to the literature on the health and social benefits of education.]]></description><author>Jason Fletcher, Hamid Noghanibehambari</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29423</guid></item><item><title>Does Research Save Lives? The Local Spillovers of Biomedical Research on Mortality</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29420</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Rebecca McKibbin, Bruce A. Weinberg.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper investigates the local impact of biomedical research on mortality in the USA. Causally estimating the marginal value of biomedical research is challenging due to a lack of micro data linking health outcomes to plausibly exogenous variation in research. We create a new linkage between a research database (PubMed) and administrative death records that enables research to be related to mortality at the geographic, disease and time level. We then estimate the marginal impact of biomedical research on mortality using hospital market (HRR) level shocks to research activity by disease. Our identification strategy builds on the literature on the dissemination of knowledge, specifically that of local knowledge spillovers. By utilizing variation across diseases, time and distance from research we control for additional trends relative to the current literature. Our results show that an additional research publication on average reduces local mortality from a disease by 0.35%. Our results also provide novel evidence that there are health benefits to the local communities (local spillovers) in which biomedical research is conducted.]]></description><author>Rebecca McKibbin, Bruce A. Weinberg</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29420</guid></item><item><title>One Instrument to Rule Them All: The Bias and Coverage of Just-ID IV</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29417</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Angrist, Michal Kolesár.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Two-stage least squares estimates in heavily over-identified instrumental variables (IV) models can be misleadingly close to the corresponding ordinary least squares (OLS) estimates when many instruments are weak. Just-identified (just-ID) IV estimates using a single instrument are also biased, but the importance of weak-instrument bias in just-ID IV applications remains contentious. We argue that in microeconometric applications, just-ID IV estimators can typically be treated as all but unbiased and that the usual inference strategies are likely to be adequate. The argument begins with contour plots for confidence interval coverage as a function of instrument strength and explanatory variable endogeneity. These show undercoverage in excess of 5% only for endogeneity beyond that seen even when IV and OLS estimates differ by an order of magnitude. Three widely cited microeconometric applications are used to explain why endogeneity is likely low enough for IV estimates to be reliable. We then show that an estimator that’s unbiased given a population first-stage sign restriction has bias exceeding that of IV when the restriction is imposed on the data. But screening on the sign of the estimated first stage is shown to halve the median bias of conventional IV without reducing coverage. To the extent that sign-screening is already part of empirical workflows, reported IV estimates enjoy the minimal bias of sign-screened just-ID IV.]]></description><author>Joshua Angrist, Michal Kolesár</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29417</guid></item><item><title>Understanding Algorithmic Discrimination in Health Economics Through the Lens of Measurement Errors</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29413</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anirban Basu, Noah Hammarlund, Sara Khor, Aasthaa Bansal.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> There is growing concern that the increasing use of machine learning and artificial intelligence-based systems may exacerbate health disparities through discrimination. We provide a hierarchical definition of discrimination consisting of algorithmic discrimination arising from predictive scores used for allocating resources and human discrimination arising from allocating resources by human decision-makers conditional on these predictive scores. We then offer an overarching statistical framework of algorithmic discrimination through the lens of measurement errors, which is familiar to the health economics audience. Specifically, we show that algorithmic discrimination exists when measurement errors exist in either the outcome or the predictors, and there is endogenous selection for participation in the observed data. The absence of any of these phenomena would eliminate algorithmic discrimination. We show that although equalized odds constraints can be employed as bias-mitigating strategies, such constraints may increase algorithmic discrimination when there is measurement error in the dependent variable.]]></description><author>Anirban Basu, Noah Hammarlund, Sara Khor, Aasthaa Bansal</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29413</guid></item><item><title>A Child Support Framework Accounting for Parenting Time and Half-Siblings</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29411</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Martin Kulldorff, Jay Bhattacharya.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In the United States, child support guidelines sometimes generate surprising and presumably unintentional child support amounts, especially in situations with extended visitation, shared parenting, and half-siblings. These are consequences of the ad-hoc mathematical formulas that are in common use to account for such situations. This paper provides ten such surprising examples from ten randomly selected states.<br />
A child support calculation framework is constructed that takes as inputs the subjective/normative decisions that the public and legislators must make regarding children's expenditures, the progressivity of the contributions between parents, and other matters. Our goal is to derive mathematical formulas for child support amounts that achieve those normative goals while satisfying basic desiderata such as supporting children in both of their families, equity between siblings, neutral medical decisions, and not requiring higher contributions from parents with a lower salary.]]></description><author>Martin Kulldorff, Jay Bhattacharya</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29411</guid></item><item><title>Financial Incentives and Other Nudges Do Not Increase COVID-19 Vaccinations among the Vaccine Hesitant</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29403</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tom Chang, Mireille Jacobson, Manisha Shah, Rajiv Pramanik, Samir B. Shah.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Can financial incentives, public health messages and other behavioral nudges –approaches deployed by state and local governments, employers, and health systems – increase SARS-CoV-2 vaccination rates among the vaccine hesitant in the US? In mid-2021, we randomly assigned unvaccinated members of a Medicaid managed care health plan to $10 or $50 financial incentives, different public health messages, a simple appointment scheduler, or control to assess impacts on SARS-CoV-2 vaccination intentions and vaccine uptake within 30 days of intervention. While messages increased vaccination intentions, none of the treatments increased overall vaccination rates. Consistent with backlash concerns, financial incentives and negative messages decreased vaccination rates for some subgroups. Financial incentives and other behavioral nudges do not meaningfully increase SARS-CoV-2 vaccination rates amongst the vaccine hesitant.]]></description><author>Tom Chang, Mireille Jacobson, Manisha Shah, Rajiv Pramanik, Samir B. Shah</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29403</guid></item><item><title>The Fiscal and Welfare Effects of Policy Responses to the Covid-19 School Closures</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29398</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicola Fuchs-Schündeln, Dirk Krueger, André Kurmann, Etienne Lalé, Alexander Ludwig, Irina Popova.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Using a structural life-cycle model and data on school visits from Safegraph and school closures from Burbio, we quantify the heterogeneous impact of school closures during the Corona crisis on children affected at different ages and coming from households with different parental characteristics. Our data suggests that secondary schools were closed for in-person learning for longer periods than elementary schools (implying that younger children experienced less school closures than older children), and that private schools experienced shorter closures than public schools, and schools in poorer U.S. counties experienced shorter school closures. We then extend the structural life cycle model of private and public schooling investments studied in Fuchs-Schuendeln, Krueger, Ludwig and Popova (2021) to include the choice of parents whether to send their children to private schools, empirically discipline it with data on parental investments from the PSID, and then feed into the model the school closure measures from our empirical analysis to quantify the long-run consequences of the Covid-19 school closures on the cohorts of children currently in school. Future earnings- and welfare losses are largest for children that started public secondary schools at the onset of the Covid-19 crisis. Comparing children from the top- to children from the bottom quartile of the income distribution, welfare losses are ca. 0.8 percentage points larger for the poorer children if school closures were unrelated to income. Accounting for the longer school closures in richer counties reduces this gap by about 1/3. A policy intervention that extends schools by 3 months (6 weeks in the next two summers) generates significant welfare gains for the children and raises future tax approximately sufficient to pay for the cost of this schooling expansion.]]></description><author>Nicola Fuchs-Schündeln, Dirk Krueger, André Kurmann, Etienne Lalé, Alexander Ludwig, Irina Popova</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29398</guid></item><item><title>The Effect of Free School Meals on Household Food Purchases: Evidence from the Community Eligibility Provision</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29395</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michelle M. Marcus, Katherine G. Yewell.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We find evidence that exposure to universal free school meals through the Community Eligibility Provision (CEP) had a meaningful impact on grocery spending for households with children, with monthly food purchases declining by about $11, or 5 percent. For households in zip codes with higher exposure, the decline is as high as $39 per month, or 19 percent. We also show evidence that the composition of food purchases changes, with low income households experiencing an increase in the dietary quality of their food purchases by about 3 percent after CEP. Finally, we show CEP exposure is associated with an 11 percent decline in the percent of households that ran short of money or tried to make their food money go further, and an almost 5 percent decline in households classified as food insecure. Our results on the heterogeneous effects of CEP exposure by prior free/reduced price lunch eligibility reveal large benefits in terms of both spending, dietary composition, and food insecurity for previously eligible low-income families, suggesting that the stigma of free school meals may be declining after universal access.]]></description><author>Michelle M. Marcus, Katherine G. Yewell</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29395</guid></item><item><title>It All Starts with Beliefs: Addressing the Roots of Educational Inequities by Shifting Parental Beliefs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29394</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John A. List, Julie Pernaudet, Dana Suskind.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Socioeconomic inequalities in child development crystallize at early stages, with associated disparities in parental investment in children. A key to understanding the data patterns is to document the sources underlying the observed inequalities. We first show that there are dramatic differences in parental beliefs across socioeconomic backgrounds (SES), with parents of higher SES being more likely to believe that parental investments impact child development. We then use two field experiments targeted to low-SES families to explore the mutability of such beliefs and their link to parental investments. In both cases, we find that parental beliefs about child development are malleable. The less intensive version of the program based on educational videos changes parental beliefs, but fails to lastingly increase parental investments and child outcomes. By contrast, in the more intensive version of our program combining home visits and feedback, the augmented beliefs are associated with enriched parent-child interactions and improved vocabulary, math, and social-emotional skills for the children. Together, these results suggest that changing parental beliefs can be an important pathway to raising parental investments and reducing socioeconomic gaps in children’s skills, but that simple informational policies may not be sufficient.]]></description><author>John A. List, Julie Pernaudet, Dana Suskind</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29394</guid></item><item><title>The Financial Fragility of For-profit Hospitals: Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We estimate the likelihood of financial distress of U.S. hospitals in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic using AHA Annual Survey data for 2011-2019 and smartphone mobility data for 2020. We find that while the average likelihood of distress across all hospitals is 28.53 % in 2020, slightly increasing from 2019, for-profit hospitals are much more likely to be distressed. Their average likelihood of financial distress is 39.13 %---a 6.93 percentage point increase from 2019. For-profit hospitals are the main providers of specialty health care services, such as psychiatric and acute long-term care, so their increased likelihood of distress poses a risk to service provision in these specialty areas, and particularly in rural communities. Our prediction model based on mobility data performs very well in sample against actual data and can potentially help policymakers and hospital administrators to monitor financial distress in real-time when case mixes change, or other large shocks materialize.]]></description><author>Ge Bai, Daniel Jiménez, Phillip Phan, Luis E. Quintero, Alessandro Rebucci, Xian Sun</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29388</guid></item><item><title>Effects of Opioid-Related Policies on Opioid Utilization, Nature of Medical Care, and Duration of Disability</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29371</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David Neumark, Bogdan Savych.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We examine the effects of must-access prescription drug monitoring programs (PDMPs) and recent regulations limiting the duration of initial opioid prescriptions on care received by patients with work-related injuries, focusing on opioid utilization and medical care related to pain management. We find that must-access PDMPs contributed to declines in opioid utilization, while regulations limiting duration of initial opioid prescriptions had little effect on whether workers receive opioids, but reduced opioid use among those with prescriptions. We find limited evidence that must-access PDMPs affected utilization of other medical care related to pain management, and that must-access PDMPs and limits on initial prescriptions had little impact on the duration of temporary disability benefits captured at 12 months of maturity.]]></description><author>David Neumark, Bogdan Savych</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29371</guid></item><item><title>The Political Economy of the COVID-19 Fiscal Stimulus Packages of 2020</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29360</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Ilan Noy.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Almost all countries announced fiscal support programs once COVID-19 hit. However, there was significant diversity in the magnitude and composition of these fiscal stimulus programs. These differences were determined by myriad political, financial, social, and economic factors - these factors are our focus. We ask what were the factors that are associated with the structure of the fiscal programs that governments chose to adopt in the early stage of the pandemic in 2020. We answer this question using details about the fiscal programs that were announced by 98 governments in the first six months of the pandemic, together with a large set of explanatory variables. Maybe not surprisingly, we find that politics played a very significant part in determining the size and composition of these fiscal programs. Governments and societies that are less polarized and more capable were able to mobilise more fiscal resources. We also find that it was governments with bigger debt loads that announced bigger programs, but that sovereign spreads were not so clearly associated with the size of these program plans. There is a limit, however, to what we can glean from these cross-country comparisons. Ultimately, the understanding of the politics and political-economy considerations that led to the specific content of each fiscal program will have to rely on information about the actual deliberations in each government’s halls of power, should these ever become public.]]></description><author>Joshua Aizenman, Yothin Jinjarak, Hien Nguyen, Ilan Noy</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29360</guid></item><item><title>Probabilistic Prediction for Binary Treatment Choice: with Focus on Personalized Medicine</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29358</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Charles F. Manski.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> This paper extends my research applying statistical decision theory to treatment choice with sample data, using maximum regret to evaluate the performance of treatment rules. The specific new contribution is to study as-if optimization using estimates of illness probabilities in clinical choice between surveillance and aggressive treatment. Beyond its specifics, the paper sends a broad message. Statisticians and computer scientists have addressed conditional prediction for decision making in indirect ways, the former applying classical statistical theory and the latter measuring prediction accuracy in test samples. Neither approach is satisfactory. Statistical decision theory provides a coherent, generally applicable methodology.]]></description><author>Charles F. Manski</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29358</guid></item><item><title>A Taste of Their Own Medicine: Guideline Adherence and Access to Expertise</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29356</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Amy Finkelstein, Petra Persson, Maria Polyakova, Jesse M. Shapiro.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We use population administrative data from Sweden to study adherence to 63 medication-related guidelines. We compare the adherence of patients without personal access to medical expertise to the adherence of those with access, namely doctors and their close relatives. We estimate that, among observably similar patients, access to expertise is associated with 3.8 percentage points lower adherence, relative to a baseline adherence rate of 54.4 percent among those without access. This association is larger for recommendations with a weaker clinical motivation. Our findings suggest an important role in non-adherence for factors other than those, such as ignorance, complexity, or failures of patient-provider communication, that would be expected to diminish with access to expertise.]]></description><author>Amy Finkelstein, Petra Persson, Maria Polyakova, Jesse M. Shapiro</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29356</guid></item><item><title>Providing Vouchers and Value Information for Already Free Eye Exams Increases Uptake Among a Low-Income Minority Population: A Randomized Trial</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29355</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Seema Kacker, Mario Macis, Prateek Gajwani, David S. Friedman.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study whether vouchers with and without value information encourage completion of already free follow-up appointments in a low-income minority population in Baltimore City referred for possible eye disease. Between May 2017 and September 2018, 821 individuals referred for free follow-up from 114 screening events received 1) standard referral, 2) a voucher redeemable for free follow-up and prescription glasses, or 3) a voucher including a statement of monetary value ($250). All referred individuals received patient education, counseling, and appointment reminders. We find that vouchers without and with value information increase follow-up appointments by 12.5 and 20.3 percentage points, respectively, corresponding to a 36%-58% increase compared to the standard referral with no voucher. We conclude that reframing free targeted health service offers by providing vouchers with value information is a promising, low-cost tool to increase uptake.]]></description><author>Seema Kacker, Mario Macis, Prateek Gajwani, David S. Friedman</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29355</guid></item><item><title>The Economics of the COVID-19 Pandemic in Poor Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29339</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Edward Miguel, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The COVID-19 pandemic has upended health and living standards around the world. This article provides an interim overview of these effects, with a particular focus on low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). Economists have explained how the pandemic is likely to have differential consequences for LMICs, and demand distinct policy responses, compared to rich countries. We survey the rapidly expanding body of empirical research that documents its many adverse economic and non-economic effects in terms of living standards, education, health, and gender equality, which appear to be unprecedented in depth and scale. We also review research on successful and failed policy responses, including the failure to ensure widespread vaccine coverage in LMICs, which is needed to end the pandemic. We close with a discussion of implications for public policy in LMICs, and for the institutions of international governance, given the likelihood of future pandemics and other major shocks (e.g., climate).]]></description><author>Edward Miguel, Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29339</guid></item><item><title>Minimum Wages and Teenage Childbearing: New Estimates Using a Dynamic Difference-in-Differences Approach</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29334</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Daniel I. Rees, Joseph J. Sabia, Rebecca Margolit.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> The minimum wage is increasingly viewed as an important tool for improving public health outcomes, including reducing childbearing among teenagers. Taken at face value, recently reported estimates suggest that raising the federal minimum wage to $15 per hour could reduce the number of teenage births by 35,000 per year. Using an event study framework that accounts for dynamic and heterogeneous treatment effects, we find little evidence that minimum wages are causally related to teenage childbearing. Moreover, the estimated effects of minimum wages on teenage sexual behaviors, including contraception use, abstinence, and number of partners are consistently small and statistically insignificant.]]></description><author>Daniel I. Rees, Joseph J. Sabia, Rebecca Margolit</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29334</guid></item><item><title>Mortality Rates by College Degree Before and During COVID-19</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29328</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anne Case, Angus Deaton.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> It is now established that mortality and excess mortality from COVID-19 differed across racial and ethnic groups in 2020. Less is known about educational differences in mortality during the pandemic. We examine mortality rates by BA status within sex, age, and race/ethnic groups comparing 2020 with 2019. Mortality rates have increasingly differed by BA status in the US in recent years and there are good reasons to expect the gap to have widened further during the pandemic. Using publicly available provisional data from the National Center for Health Statistics we find that mortality rates increased in 2020 over 2019 for those with and without a BA, irrespective of age, sex, or race/ethnicity. Although mortality rates increased by more for those without a BA, the ratio of mortality rates for those with and without a BA changed surprisingly little from 2019 to 2020. The BA was protective against mortality prior to the pandemic, and it was equally protective during the pandemic. Among 60 groups (sex by race/ethnicity by age) that are available in the data, the ratio of mortality rates of those without a BA to those with a BA fell for more than half of the groups. Our results suggest that differences in the risk of infection were less important in structuring mortality by education than differences in the risk of death conditional on infection.]]></description><author>Anne Case, Angus Deaton</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29328</guid></item><item><title>Exposure to Cigarette Taxes as a Teenager and the Persistence of Smoking into Adulthood</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29325</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andrew I. Friedson, Moyan Li, Katherine Meckel, Daniel I. Rees, Daniel W. Sacks.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Are teenage and adult smoking causally related?  Recent anti-tobacco policy is predicated on the assumption that preventing teenagers from smoking will ensure that fewer adults smoke, but direct evidence in support of this assumption is scant.  Using data from three nationally representative sources and cigarette taxes experienced as a teenager as an instrument, we document a strong, positive relationship between teenage and adult smoking: specifically, deterring 10 teenagers from smoking through raising cigarette taxes roughly translates into 5 or 6 fewer eventual adult smokers.  We conclude that efforts to reduce teenage smoking can have important, long-lasting consequences on smoking participation and, presumably, health.]]></description><author>Andrew I. Friedson, Moyan Li, Katherine Meckel, Daniel I. Rees, Daniel W. Sacks</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29325</guid></item><item><title>The Causal Effects of Place on Health and Longevity</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29321</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Tatyana Deryugina, David Molitor.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Life expectancy varies substantially across local regions within a country, raising conjectures that place of residence affects health. However, population sorting and other confounders make it difficult to disentangle the effects of place on health from other geographic differences in life expectancy. Recent studies have overcome such challenges to demonstrate that place of residence substantially influences health and mortality. Whether policies that encourage people to move to places that are better for their health or that improve areas that are detrimental to health are desirable depends on the mechanisms behind place effects, yet these mechanisms remain poorly understood.]]></description><author>Tatyana Deryugina, David Molitor</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29321</guid></item><item><title>Recovery from the COVID-19 Recession: Uneven Effects among Young Workers?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29307</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pinka Chatterji, Yue Li.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We test for heterogeneity in the effects of the COVID-19 recession on young workers by estimating month-by-month effects of the pandemic on labor market outcomes among workers aged 15-19 and aged 20-24. We use CPS data from January 2016 to June 2021, limiting the sample to childless individuals who lack a college degree. In the younger group (aged 15-19), we observe the expected sharp reduction in outcomes at the start of the pandemic, followed by a return to pre-pandemic levels of work hours, employment, and labor force participation starting in September 2020, with outcomes even surpassing pre-pandemic levels in April and May 2021. In the older age group (20-24-year-olds), however, work hours, employment, and labor force participation were still lagging below pre-pandemic levels as of June 2021. As of June 2021, weekly earnings and hourly wages were higher than typical pre-pandemic levels for that month for both age groups. Although we cannot test directly whether enhanced UI programs have played a role in these differences by age group, our findings show that within the 15-24-year-old age group, there is significant heterogeneity in labor market recovery from the COVID-19 recession.]]></description><author>Pinka Chatterji, Yue Li</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29307</guid></item><item><title>Marijuana Liberalization Policies and Perinatal Health</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29296</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Angélica Meinhofer, Allison E. Witman, Jesse M. Hinde, Kosali I. Simon.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We studied the effect of marijuana liberalization policies on perinatal health with a multiperiod difference-in-differences estimator that exploited variation in effective dates of medical marijuana laws (MML) and recreational marijuana laws (RML). We found that the proportion of maternal hospitalizations with marijuana use disorder increased by 23% (0.3 percentage points) in the first three years after RML implementation, with larger effects in states authorizing commercial sales of marijuana. This growth was accompanied by a 7% (0.4 percentage points) decline in tobacco use disorder hospitalizations, yielding a net zero effect over all substance use disorder hospitalizations. RMLs were not associated with changes in newborn health. MMLs had no significant effect on maternal substance use disorder hospitalizations nor on newborn health and fairly small effects could be ruled out. In absolute numbers, our findings implied modest or no adverse effects of marijuana liberalization policies on the array of perinatal outcomes considered.]]></description><author>Angélica Meinhofer, Allison E. Witman, Jesse M. Hinde, Kosali I. Simon</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29296</guid></item><item><title>Effect of the Jamaica Early Childhood Stimulation Intervention on Labor Market Outcomes at Age 31</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29292</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Paul Gertler, James J. Heckman, Rodrigo Pinto, Susan M. Chang, Sally Grantham-McGregor, Christel Vermeersch, Susan Walker, Amika Wright.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We report the labor market effects of the Jamaica Early Childhood Stimulation intervention at age 31. The study is a small-sample randomized early childhood education stimulation intervention targeting stunted children living in the poor neighborhoods of Kingston, Jamaica. Implemented in 1987-1989, treatment consisted of a two-year home-based intervention designed to improve nutrition and the quality of mother-child interactions to foster cognitive, language and psycho-social skills. The original sample is 127 stunted children between 9 and 24 months old. Our study is able to track and interview 75% of the original sample 30 years after the intervention, both still living in Jamaica and migrated abroad. We find large and statistically significant effects on income and schooling; the treatment group had 43% higher hourly wages and 37% higher earnings than the control group. This is a substantial increase over the treatment effect estimated for age 22 where we observed a 25% increase in earnings. The Jamaican Study is a rare case of a long-term follow up for an early childhood development (ECD) intervention implemented in a less-developed country. Our results confirm large economic returns to an early childhood intervention that targeted disadvantaged families living in poverty in the poor neighborhoods of Jamaica. The Jamaican intervention is being replicated around the world. Our analysis provides justification for expanding ECD interventions targeting disadvantaged children living in poor countries around the world.]]></description><author>Paul Gertler, James J. Heckman, Rodrigo Pinto, Susan M. Chang, Sally Grantham-McGregor, Christel Vermeersch, Susan Walker, Amika Wright</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29292</guid></item><item><title>Is Healthcare Employment Resilient and “Recession Proof”?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29287</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marcus Dillender, Andrew I. Friedson, Cong T. Gian, Kosali I. Simon.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Conventional wisdom often holds that the healthcare sector fares better than other sectors during economic downturns. However, little research has examined the relationship between local economic conditions and healthcare employment. Understanding how the healthcare sector responds to economic conditions is important for policy makers seeking to ensure an adequate supply of healthcare workers, as well as for those directing displaced workers into new jobs. We examine the impact of macroeconomic conditions on both the healthcare labor market and the pipeline of healthcare workers receiving healthcare degrees during a pre-COVID time period, 2005-2017. Our results indicate that the healthcare sector is stable across past business cycles. If anything, when areas experience more severe local economic downturns, healthcare employment increases. Much remains unknown about the adjustments and lasting impacts for the healthcare sector associated with the COVID era. Our study represents an important backdrop as policy makers consider ways to sustain the healthcare sector during economic and public health turbulence.]]></description><author>Marcus Dillender, Andrew I. Friedson, Cong T. Gian, Kosali I. Simon</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29287</guid></item><item><title>The Puzzle of Falling US Birth Rates Since the Great Recession</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29286</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Melissa Schettini Kearney, Phillip B. Levine, Luke W. Pardue.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> This paper documents a set of facts about the dramatic decline in birth rates in the United States between 2007 and 2020 and explores possible explanations. The overall reduction in the birth rate reflects declines across many groups of women, including women who differ by race and ethnicity, age, and level of education. The Great Recession contributed to the decline in the early part of this period, but we are unable to identify any other economic, policy, or social factor that has changed since 2007 that is responsible for much of the decline beyond that. Mechanically, the falling birth rate can be attributed to changes in birth patterns across recent cohorts of women moving through childbearing age. We conjecture that the “shifting priorities” of more recent cohorts, reflecting changes in preferences for having children, aspirations for life, and parenting norms, may be responsible. We conclude with a brief discussion about the societal consequences for a declining birth rate and what the United States might do about it.]]></description><author>Melissa Schettini Kearney, Phillip B. Levine, Luke W. Pardue</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29286</guid></item><item><title>The Consequences of Chronic Pain in Mid-Life: Evidence from the National Child Development Survey</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29278</link><description><![CDATA[<i>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Using data from all those born in a single week in 1958 in Britain we track the consequences of short pain and chronic pain in mid-life (age 44) on health, wellbeing and labor market outcomes in later life.  We examine data taken at age 50 in 2008, when the Great Recession hit and then five years later at age 55 in 2013.  We find those suffering both short-term and chronic pain at age 44 continue to report pain and poor general health in their 50s.  However, the associations are much stronger for those with chronic pain.  Furthermore, chronic pain at age 44 is associated with a range of poor mental health outcomes, pessimism about the future and joblessness at age 55 whereas short-duration pain at age 44 is not.  Uniquely, we also show that pain experienced in childhood, at ages 11 and 16, reported by a parent and a teacher respectively, collected decades earlier, predicts pain in mid-life, indicating just how persistent pain can be over the life-course.]]></description><author>David G. Blanchflower, Alex Bryson</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29278</guid></item></channel></rss>