<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Firm Behavior</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Firm Behavior</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 15:48:20 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Absenteeism, Productivity, and Relational Contracts Inside the Firm</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29581</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Achyuta Adhvaryu, Jean-François Gauthier, Anant Nyshadham, Jorge A. Tamayo.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study relational contracts among managers using unique data that tracks transfers of workers across teams in Indian ready-made garment factories. We focus on how relational contracts help managers cope with worker absenteeism shocks, which are frequent, often large, weakly correlated across teams, and which substantially reduce team productivity. Together these facts imply gains from sharing workers. We show that managers respond to shocks by lending and borrowing workers in a manner consistent with relational contracting, but many potentially beneficial transfers are unrealized. This is because managers’ primary relationships are with a very small subset of potential partners. A borrowing event study around main trading partners’ separations from the firm reinforces the importance of relationships. We show robustness to excluding worker moves least likely to reflect relational borrowing responses to idiosyncratic absenteeism shocks. Counterfactual simulations reveal large gains to reducing costs associated with forming and maintaining additional relationships among managers.]]></description><author>Achyuta Adhvaryu, Jean-François Gauthier, Anant Nyshadham, Jorge A. Tamayo</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29581</guid></item><item><title>Organizational Frictions and Increasing Returns to Automation: Lessons from AT&amp;T in the Twentieth Century</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29580</link><description><![CDATA[<i>James J. Feigenbaum, Daniel P. Gross.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> AT&amp;T was the largest U.S. firm for most of the 20th century. Telephone operators once comprised over 50% of its workforce, but in the late 1910s it initiated a decades-long process of automating telephone operation with mechanical call switching—a technology first invented in the 1880s. We study what drove AT&amp;T to do so, and why it took one firm nearly a century to automate this one basic function. Interdependencies between operators and nearly every other part of the business were obstacles: the manual switchboard was the fulcrum of a complex system which had developed around it, and automation only began after the firm and automatic technology were adapted to work together. Even then, automatic switching was only profitable for AT&amp;T in larger markets—hence diffusion expanded as costs declined and service areas grew. We show that automation supported AT&amp;T's continued growth, generating a positive feedback loop between scale and automation that reinforced AT&amp;T's high market share in local markets.]]></description><author>James J. Feigenbaum, Daniel P. Gross</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29580</guid></item><item><title>Labor Productivity Growth and Industrialization in Africa</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29570</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Margaret S. McMillan, Albert Zeufack.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Manufacturing has made an important contribution to raising living standards in many parts of the world. Concerns about premature deindustrialization have made some observers skeptical about the potential for manufacturing to play this role in Africa. But employment in African manufacturing has grown rapidly over the past 20 years. These employment gains have been accompanied by: (i) large increases in the number of small manufacturing firms; (ii) limited employment gains in large firms; and (iii) robust labor productivity growth in Africa’s large firms. Limited employment growth in Africa’s large manufacturing firms is partly a result of the capital intensity of the manufacturing sub-sectors in which African countries are most engaged – the processing of resources, and partly a result of rising capital intensity in manufacturing. The potential for manufacturing to raise living standards in Africa depends on indirect job creation by large firms through backward and forward linkages and increasing labor productivity in small firms.]]></description><author>Margaret S. McMillan, Albert Zeufack</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29570</guid></item><item><title>Cross-Product and Cross-Market Adjustments Within Multiproduct Firms: Evidence from Antidumping Actions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29521</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Xiaohua Bao, Bruce A. Blonigen, Zhi Yu.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Multiproduct firms are responsible for the vast majority of global trade. A prior literature examines how multiproduct firms respond to trade liberalizations that simultaneously affect all of the firms' products and inputs.  In contrast, our study uses Chinese firm-product-level export data to examine how an AD action, a very targeted trade policy against a specific product in a specific export destination, affects a multiproduct firms' price and quantity decisions across its other products and export destinations.  We find robust evidence for a new phenomenon we call within-firm cross-product trade deflection whereby an AD duty against one of the firm's products in one of its export destinations is associated with reduced prices and increased sales of its other products across all markets. This type of effect depends on increasing costs from joint production within multiproduct firms, something that is often assumed away in many models of the multiproduct firm.  We also document for the first time a within-firm chilling effect whereby an AD action in one export destination on a product leads the firm to raise price and lower quantity of the product in other export destinations to lower the risk of AD actions in these other markets.]]></description><author>Xiaohua Bao, Bruce A. Blonigen, Zhi Yu</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29521</guid></item><item><title>Who Benefits from Online Gig Economy Platforms?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29477</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Christopher T. Stanton, Catherine Thomas.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper estimates the magnitude and distribution of surplus from the knowledge worker gig economy using data from an online labor market. Labor demand elasticities determine workers’ wages, and buyers’ past market experience shapes both their job posting frequency and hiring rates. We ﬁnd that workers on the supply side capture around 40% of the surplus from ﬁlled jobs. Under counterfactual policies that resemble traditional employment regulation, buyers post fewer online jobs and ﬁll posted jobs less often, reducing expected surplus for all market participants. We ﬁnd negligible substitution on the demand side between online and oﬄine jobs by assessing how changes in local oﬄine minimum wages aﬀect online hiring. The results suggest that neither online or oﬄine knowledge workers will beneﬁt from applying traditional employment regulation to the online gig economy.]]></description><author>Christopher T. Stanton, Catherine Thomas</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29477</guid></item><item><title>Firm-Level Upgrading in Developing Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29461</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Eric Verhoogen.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In principle, firms in developing countries benefit from the fact that advanced technologies and products have already been developed in industrialized countries and can simply be adopted, a process often referred to as industrial upgrading. But for many firms this advantage remains elusive. What is getting in the way? This paper reviews recent firm-level empirical research on the determinants of upgrading in developing countries. The first part focuses on how to define and measure various dimensions of upgrading --- learning, quality upgrading, technology adoption, and product innovation. The second part takes stock of recent micro-empirical evidence on the drivers of upgrading, classifying them as output-side drivers, input-side drivers, or drivers of know-how. The review concludes with some thoughts about promising directions for research in the area.]]></description><author>Eric Verhoogen</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29461</guid></item><item><title>Technology Transfer and Early Industrial Development: Evidence from the Sino-Soviet Alliance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29455</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michela Giorcelli, Bo Li.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper studies the causal effect of technology and knowledge transfers on early industrial development. Between 1950 and 1957, the Soviet Union supported the “156 Projects” in China for the construction of technologically advanced, large-scale, capital-intensive industrial facilities. We exploit idiosyncratic delays in project completion and the unexpected end of the Sino-Soviet Alliance, due to which some projects received Soviet technology embedded in capital goods and know-how, while others were eventually realized by China alone using domestic technology. We find that receiving both Soviet technology and know-how had large, persistent effects on plant performance, while the effects of receiving only Soviet capital goods were short-lived. The intervention generated horizontal and vertical spillovers, as well as production reallocation from state-owned to privately owned companies since the late 1990s.]]></description><author>Michela Giorcelli, Bo Li</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29455</guid></item><item><title>Moment Inequalities and Partial Identification in Industrial Organization</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29409</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Brendan Kline, Ariel Pakes, Elie Tamer.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We review approaches to identification and inference on models in Industrial Organization with partial identification and/or moment inequalities. Often, such approaches are intentionally built directly on assumptions of optimizing behavior that are credible in Industrial Organization settings, while avoiding the use of strong modeling and measurement assumptions that may not be warranted. The result is an identified set for the object of interest, reflecting what the econometrician can learn from the data and assumptions. The chapter formally defines identification, reviews the assumptions underlying the identification argument, and provides examples of their use in Industrial Organization settings. We then discuss the corresponding statistical inference problem paying particular attention to practical implementation issues.]]></description><author>Brendan Kline, Ariel Pakes, Elie Tamer</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29409</guid></item><item><title>Corporate Culture</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29322</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gary B. Gorton, Jill Grennan, Alexander K. Zentefis.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Corporate culture is an omnibus term that includes many elements like norms, values, knowledge, and customs that are relevant to a firm. Economists have made great progress recently in devising methods of measuring different aspects of corporate culture. These empirical measures of culture have explained mergers and acquisitions, corporate risk-taking, and unethical behaviors observed in corporations, among other topics. We argue that unpacking corporate culture into its components is the right way to research it empirically. Theories of corporate culture are still in development, and we discuss the major contributions thus far. We argue that a theory of the firm and of corporate decision-making that is based on corporate culture is more germane to the practical realities of firms’ inner workings than prevailing theories based on agency costs. Corporate culture has the potential to set the theoretical paradigm for all corporate finance research.]]></description><author>Gary B. Gorton, Jill Grennan, Alexander K. Zentefis</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29322</guid></item><item><title>Dynamics of Large Multinationals</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29317</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Elhanan Helpman, Benjamin C. Niswonger.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We develop a model of large multinational enterprises, each one producing a continuum of products. These outsized firms compete as oligopolists in a domestic and foreign market, facing competitive pressure from single-product firms that engage in monopolistic competition. The multinational enterprises invest in R&amp;D in order to expand the span of their products and in foreign direct investment (FDI) in order to expand the range of products manufactured by their foreign affiliates. We study the dynamic evolution of these markets and characterize transition dynamics and steady states. In addition to the evolution of product spans, we characterize the evolution of prices, markups, market shares, and exports relative to subsidiary sales. Furthermore, we study comparative dynamics that result from changes in trade costs, R&amp;D costs, the cost of FDI and productivity changes of the multinational firms.]]></description><author>Elhanan Helpman, Benjamin C. Niswonger</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29317</guid></item><item><title>Task Allocation and On-the-job Training</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29312</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Mariagiovanna Baccara, SangMok Lee, Leeat Yariv.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study dynamic task allocation when providers' expertise evolves endogenously through training. We characterize optimal assignment protocols and compare them to discretionary procedures, where it is the clients who select their service providers. Our results indicate that welfare gains from centralization are greater when tasks arrive more rapidly, and when training technologies improve. Monitoring seniors' backlog of clients always increases welfare but may decrease training. Methodologically, we explore a matching setting with endogenous types, and illustrate useful adaptations of queueing theory techniques for such environments.]]></description><author>Mariagiovanna Baccara, SangMok Lee, Leeat Yariv</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29312</guid></item><item><title>Big Loans to Small Businesses: Predicting Winners and Losers in an Entrepreneurial Lending Experiment</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We experimentally study the impact of substantially larger enterprise loans, in collaboration with an Egyptian lender. Larger loans generate small average impacts, but machine learning using psychometric data reveals dramatic heterogeneity. Top-performers (i.e., those with the highest predicted treatment effects) substantially increase profits, whereas profits for poor-performers drop. The magnitude of this difference implies that an individual lender’s credit allocation choices matter for aggregate income. Evidence on two fronts suggests large loans would be misallocated: top-performers are predicted by loan officers to have higher default rates; and, top-performers grow less than others when given small loans, implying that allocating larger loans based on prior performance is not efficient. Our results have important implications for credit expansion policy and our understanding of entrepreneurial talent: on the former, the use of psychometric data to identify top-performers suggests a pathway towards better allocation that revolves around entrepreneurial type more than firm type; on the latter, the reversal of fortune for poor-performers, who do well with small loans but not large, indicates a type of entrepreneur that we call a “go-getter” who performs well when constrained but poorly when not.]]></description><author>Gharad T. Bryan, Dean Karlan, Adam Osman</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29311</guid></item><item><title>Foundations of Demand Estimation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29305</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Steven T. Berry, Philip A. Haile.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Demand elasticities and other features of demand are critical determinants of the answers to most positive and normative questions about market power or the functioning of markets in practice. As a result, reliable demand estimation is an essential input to many types of research in Industrial Organization and other fields of economics. This chapter presents a discussion of some foundational issues in demand estimation. We focus on the distinctive challenges of demand estimation and  strategies one can use  to overcome them. We cover core models, alternative data settings, common estimation approaches, the role and choice of instruments, and nonparametric identification.]]></description><author>Steven T. Berry, Philip A. Haile</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29305</guid></item></channel></rss>