<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER program Technical Working Papers</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER program Technical Working Papers</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 17:56:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Understanding Algorithmic Discrimination in Health Economics Through the Lens of Measurement Errors</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29413</link><description><![CDATA[<b>November 2021</b> <p> There is growing concern that the increasing use of machine learning and artificial intelligence-based systems may exacerbate health disparities through discrimination. We provide a hierarchical definition of discrimination consisting of algorithmic discrimination arising from predictive scores used for allocating resources and human discrimination arising from allocating resources by human decision-makers conditional on these predictive scores. We then offer an overarching statistical framework of algorithmic discrimination through the lens of measurement errors, which is familiar to the health economics audience. Specifically, we show that algorithmic discrimination exists when measurement errors exist in either the outcome or the predictors, and there is endogenous selection for participation in the observed data. The absence of any of these phenomena would eliminate algorithmic discrimination. We show that although equalized odds constraints can be employed as bias-mitigating strategies, such constraints may increase algorithmic discrimination when there is measurement error in the dependent variable.]]></description><author>Anirban Basu, Noah Hammarlund, Sara Khor, Aasthaa Bansal</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29413</guid></item><item><title>Economic Data Engineering</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29378</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Economic data engineering deliberately designs novel forms of data to solve fundamental identification problems associated with economic models of choice. I outline three diverse applications: to the economics of information; to life-cycle employment, earnings, and spending; and to public policy analysis. In all three cases one and the same fundamental identification problem is driving data innovation: that of separately identifying appropriately rich preferences and beliefs. In addition to presenting these conceptually linked examples, I provide a general overview of the engineering process, outline important next steps, and highlight larger opportunities.]]></description><author>Andrew Caplin</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29378</guid></item><item><title>Probabilistic Prediction for Binary Treatment Choice: with Focus on Personalized Medicine</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29358</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> This paper extends my research applying statistical decision theory to treatment choice with sample data, using maximum regret to evaluate the performance of treatment rules. The specific new contribution is to study as-if optimization using estimates of illness probabilities in clinical choice between surveillance and aggressive treatment. Beyond its specifics, the paper sends a broad message. Statisticians and computer scientists have addressed conditional prediction for decision making in indirect ways, the former applying classical statistical theory and the latter measuring prediction accuracy in test samples. Neither approach is satisfactory. Statistical decision theory provides a coherent, generally applicable methodology.]]></description><author>Charles F. Manski</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29358</guid></item><item><title>Refining Set-Identification in VARs through Independence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29316</link><description><![CDATA[<b>October 2021</b> <p> Identification in VARs has traditionally mainly relied on second moments. Some researchers have considered using higher moments as well, but there are concerns about the strength of the identification obtained in this way. In this paper, we propose refining existing identification schemes by augmenting sign restrictions with a requirement that rules out shocks whose higher moments significantly depart from independence. This approach does not assume that higher moments help with identification; it is robust to weak identification. In simulations we show that it controls coverage well, in contrast to approaches that assume that the higher moments deliver point-identification. However, it requires large sample sizes and/or considerable non-normality to reduce the width of confidence intervals by much. We consider some empirical applications.  We find that it can reject many possible rotations. The resulting confidence sets for impulse responses may be non-convex, corresponding to disjoint parts of the space of rotation  matrices. We show that in this case, augmenting sign and magnitude restrictions with an independence requirement can yield bigger gains.]]></description><author>Thorsten Drautzburg, Jonathan H. Wright</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29316</guid></item><item><title>Empirical Models of Demand and Supply in Differentiated Products Industries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29257</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> This is an invited chapter for the forthcoming Volume 4 of the Handbook of Industrial Organization. We present empirical models of demand and supply in differentiated products industries with an emphasis on the key ideas arising from the recent applied literature. We start with a discussion of the challenges in modeling and estimation of demand for  differentiated products, and focus on discrete choice characteristics-based demand models that address these challenges while allowing enough flexibility to capture realistic substitution patterns. Our discussion emphasizes how empirical strategies can leverage different features of data depending on the sources of variation that are commonly found in applied work. Moving to the supply-side, we show how demand estimates combined with a pricing model, can be used to recover markups and marginal costs. We also show how the model of pricing can be tested. We discuss a baseline Bertrand-Nash model of competitive pricing, and expand it to cover a) coordinated pricing, b) wholesale relationships, and c) bargaining. We end the chapter with extensions of the demand model, including dynamic and continuous demand.]]></description><author>Amit Gandhi, Aviv Nevo</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29257</guid></item><item><title>Community Colleges and Upward Mobility</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29254</link><description><![CDATA[<b>September 2021</b> <p> Two-year community colleges enroll nearly half of all first-time undergraduates in the United States, but to ambiguous effect: low persistence rates and the potential for diverting students from 4-year institutions cast ambiguity over 2-year colleges' contributions to upward mobility. This paper develops a new instrumental variables approach to identifying causal effects along multiple treatment margins, and applies it to linked education and earnings registries to disentangle the net impacts of 2-year college access into two competing causal margins: significant value-added for 2-year entrants who otherwise would not have attended college, but negative impacts on students diverted from immediate 4-year entry.]]></description><author>Jack Mountjoy</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29254</guid></item><item><title>How Well Does Bargaining Work in Consumer Markets? A Robust Bounds Approach</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29202</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> This study provides a structural analysis of detailed, alternating-offer bargaining data from eBay, deriving bounds on buyers and sellers private value distributions using a range of assumptions on behavior. These assumptions range from very weak (assuming only that acceptance and rejection decisions are rational) to less weak (e.g., assuming that bargaining offers are weakly increasing in players' private values). We estimate the bounds and show what they imply for consumer negotiation behavior in theory and practice. For the median product, bargaining ends in impasses in 43% of negotiations even when the buyer values the good more than the seller.]]></description><author>Joachim Freyberger, Bradley Larsen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29202</guid></item><item><title>Visualization, Identification, and Estimation in the Linear Panel Event-Study Design</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29170</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> Linear panel models, and the "event-study plots" that often accompany them, are popular tools for learning about policy effects.  We discuss the construction of event-study plots and suggest ways to make them more informative. We examine the economic content of different possible identifying assumptions. We explore the performance of the corresponding estimators in simulations, highlighting that a given estimator can perform well or poorly depending on the economic environment. An accompanying Stata package, -xtevent-, facilitates adoption of our suggestions.]]></description><author>Simon Freyaldenhoven, Christian Hansen, Jorge Pérez Pérez, Jesse M. Shapiro</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29170</guid></item><item><title>Intermediaries in Bargaining: Evidence from Business-to-Business Used-Car Inventory Negotiations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29159</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We analyze data on tens of thousands of alternating-offer, business-to-business negotiations in the wholesale used-car market, with each negotiation mediated (over the phone) by a third-party company. The data shows the identity of the employee mediating the negotiations. We find that who intermediates the negotiation matters: high-performing mediators are 22.03% more likely to close a deal than low performers. Effective mediators improve bargaining outcomes by helping buyers and sellers come to agreements faster, not by pushing disagreeing parties to persist, and have real effects on efficiency for some negotiations, overcoming some of the inefficiency inherent in incomplete-information settings.]]></description><author>Bradley Larsen, Carol Hengheng Lu, Anthony Lee Zhang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29159</guid></item><item><title>Exploring Spatial Price Relationships: The Case of African Swine Fever in China</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29141</link><description><![CDATA[<b>August 2021</b> <p> We use a temporary ban on inter-province shipping of live hogs induced by the 2018 outbreak of African Swine Fever (ASF) in China as a natural experiment to study spatial mechanisms behind the dynamics of market integration. With a unique dataset of weekly provincial hog prices, we employ a novel spatial network model to estimate the strength of price co-movement across provinces pre and post the ban. Results indicate that, in the highly integrated national market prior to the ban, longer geographical distances between two provinces did not weaken the strength of their price linkage. The ban broken down spatial integration. Longer distances became a significant obstacle to spatial price linkage in the post-ban periods, implying faster re-integration of hog prices between proximate provinces than remote ones. The negative effect of distance can be rationalized by the interplay between arbitrage opportunities and imperfect information. Our findings highlight information transparency as a key to market integration post shipping bans used to curb animal pandemics like ASF.]]></description><author>Michael S. Delgado, Meilin Ma, H. Holly Wang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29141</guid></item></channel></rss>