<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Economics of Information</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Economics of Information</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 09:02:29 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Unemployment-Inflation Trade-off Revisited: The Phillips Curve in COVID Times</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29785</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Richard K. Crump, Stefano Eusepi, Marc Giannoni, Ayşegül Şahin.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We estimate the natural rate of unemployment, often referred to as u*, in the United States using data on labor market flows, short-term and long-term inflation expectations and a forward-looking New-Keynesian Phillips curve for the 1960-2021 period. The natural rate of unemployment was at around 4.5% before the onset of the pandemic and increased to 5.9% by the end of 2021. This pronounced rise was primarily informed by strong wage growth rather than changes in inflation expectations. Despite the rise in the natural rate of unemployment, the secular trend of unemployment continued to fall and stands at around 4.2% reflecting  ongoing secular developments which have been pushing down the unemployment rate over the last 30 years. Our model forecasts strong wage growth to moderate only sluggishly continuing to put upward pressure on inflation in the medium-run. We project underlying inflation to remain 0.5 percentage points above its long-run trend by the end of 2023 even if long-run inflation expectations remain well anchored.<br />
Given the importance of wage growth for the inflation outlook, we examine detailed micro data on job-filling rates, posted wages for vacant positions, and workers' reservation wages.  In particular, we construct a composition-bias free measure of wage growth at the employer-job level using Burning Glass Technologies data and document strong wage growth for both teleworkable and non-teleworkable jobs. Moreover, we find that workers' reservation wages increased substantially after the pandemic. Our empirical analysis suggests that the strong wage growth is likely not a one-time adjustment of additional compensation for jobs that pose health risks to workers but rather reflects a tight labor market accompanied with a changing work-leisure trade-off.]]></description><author>Richard K. Crump, Stefano Eusepi, Marc Giannoni, Ayşegül Şahin</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29785</guid></item><item><title>A Solomonic Solution to Ownership Disputes: An Application to Blockchain Front-Running</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29780</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Joshua S. Gans, Richard T. Holden.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Blockchain front-running involves multiple agents, other than the legitimate agent, claiming a payment from performing a contract. It arises because of the public nature of blockchain transactions and potential network congestion. This paper notes that disputes over payments are similar to classic ownership disputes (such as King Solomon's dilemma). We propose a simultaneous report mechanism that resolves Solomon's dilemma (using only ordinal preference information) and also eliminates blockchain front-running. In each case, the mechanism relies on threats to remove ownership from all claimants and preferences from the legitimate claimant over allocations to other agents.]]></description><author>Joshua S. Gans, Richard T. Holden</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29780</guid></item><item><title>Dampening General Equilibrium: Incomplete Information and Bounded Rationality</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29776</link><description><![CDATA[<i>George-Marios Angeletos, Chen Lian.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We review how realistic frictions in information and/or rationality arrest general equilibrium (GE) feedbacks. In one specification, we maintain rational expectations but remove common knowledge of aggregate shocks. In another, we replace rational expectations with Level-k Thinking or a smooth variant thereof. Two other approaches, heterogeneous priors and cognitive discounting, capture the same essence while offering a gain in tractability. Relative to the full-information rational-expectation (FIRE) benchmark, all these modifications amount to attenuation of GE effects, especially in the short run. This in turn translates to either under- or over-reaction in aggregate outcomes, depending on whether GE feedbacks are positive or negative in the first place. We review a few applications, with emphasis on monetary and fiscal policy. We finally discuss how the available evidence on expectations, along with other considerations, can help guide the choice among the various alternatives, as well as between them and FIRE.]]></description><author>George-Marios Angeletos, Chen Lian</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29776</guid></item><item><title>Survey Experiments on Economic Expectations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29750</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andreas Fuster, Basit Zafar.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> In this chapter, we discuss field experiments in surveys that are conducted with the purpose of learning about expectation formation and the link between expectations and behavior. We begin by reviewing the rationale for conducting experiments within surveys, rather than just relying on observational survey data. We then outline the most commonly used experimental paradigm, randomized information provision, along with some examples. Next, we outline a few methodological issues that are important to consider in the design of such experiments. We also provide a discussion of existing extensions of this paradigm, as well as of alternative approaches.]]></description><author>Andreas Fuster, Basit Zafar</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29750</guid></item><item><title>From Anti-vax Intentions to Vaccination: Panel and Experimental Evidence from Nine Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29741</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Vincenzo Galasso, Vincent Pons, Paola Profeta, Michael Becher, Sylvain Brouard, Martial Foucault.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Millions of people refuse COVID-19 vaccination. Using original data from two surveys in nine OECD countries, we analyze the determinants of anti-vax intentions in December 2020 and show that half of the anti-vax individuals were vaccinated by summer 2021. Vaccinations were more likely among individuals aged 50+, exposed to COVID-19, compliant with public restrictions, more informed on traditional media, trusting scientists, and less concerned about vaccines’ side effects. We run a survey experiment with informational messages. In EU countries, a message about protecting health largely increases vaccinations, even among anti-vax individuals. In the U.K. and U.S., a message about protecting the economy generates similar effects. Our findings suggest that informational campaigns should adopt adequate narratives and address concerns about vaccines’ side effects.]]></description><author>Vincenzo Galasso, Vincent Pons, Paola Profeta, Michael Becher, Sylvain Brouard, Martial Foucault</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29741</guid></item><item><title>Justifying Dissent</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29730</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leonardo Bursztyn, Georgy Egorov, Ingar K. Haaland, Aakaash Rao, Christopher Roth.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> Dissent plays an important role in any society, but dissenters are often silenced through social sanctions. Beyond their persuasive effects, rationales providing arguments supporting dissenters' causes can increase the public expression of dissent by providing a “social cover” for voicing otherwise-stigmatized positions. Motivated by a simple theoretical framework, we experimentally show that liberals are more willing to post a Tweet opposing the movement to defund the police, are seen as less prejudiced, and face lower social sanctions when their Tweet implies they had first read scientific evidence supporting their position. Analogous experiments with conservatives demonstrate that the same mechanisms facilitate anti-immigrant expression. Our findings highlight both the power of rationales and their limitations in enabling dissent and shed light on phenomena such as social movements, political correctness, propaganda, and anti-minority behavior.]]></description><author>Leonardo Bursztyn, Georgy Egorov, Ingar K. Haaland, Aakaash Rao, Christopher Roth</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29730</guid></item><item><title>Consumer Reviews and Regulation: Evidence from NYC Restaurants</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29715</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Chiara Farronato, Georgios Zervas.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We investigate the informativeness of hygiene signals in online reviews, and their effect on consumer choice and restaurant hygiene. We first extract signals of hygiene from Yelp. Among all dimensions that regulators monitor through mandated restaurant inspections, we find that reviews are more informative about hygiene dimensions that consumers directly experience - food temperature and pests - than other dimensions. Next, we find causal evidence that consumer demand is sensitive to these hygiene signals. We also find suggestive evidence that restaurants that are more exposed to Yelp are cleaner along dimensions for which online reviews are more informative.]]></description><author>Chiara Farronato, Georgios Zervas</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29715</guid></item><item><title>State-Level Economic Policy Uncertainty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29714</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Scott R. Baker, Steven J. Davis, Jeffrey A. Levy.</i> <p> <b>February 2022.</b> <p> We quantify and study state-level economic policy uncertainty. Tapping digital archives for nearly 3,500 local newspapers, we construct three monthly indexes for each state: one that captures state and local sources of policy uncertainty (EPU-S), one that captures national and international sources (EPU-N), and a composite index that captures both. EPU-S rises around gubernatorial elections and own-state episodes like the California electricity crisis of 2000-01 and the Kansas tax experiment of 2012. EPU-N rises around presidential elections and in response to 9-11, Gulf Wars I and II, the 2011 debt-ceiling crisis, the 2012 fiscal cliff episode, and federal government shutdowns. Close elections elevate policy uncertainty much more than the average election. The COVID-19 pandemic drove huge increases in policy uncertainty and unemployment, more so in states with stricter government-mandated lockdowns. VAR models fit to pre-COVID data imply that upward shocks to own-state EPU foreshadow weaker economic activity in the state.]]></description><author>Scott R. Baker, Steven J. Davis, Jeffrey A. Levy</author><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29714</guid></item><item><title>Waiting for Capital: Dynamic Intermediation in Illiquid Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29712</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Barney Hartman-Glaser, Simon Mayer, Konstantin Milbradt.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We consider a firm with infrequent access to capital markets, continuous access to financing by a risk-averse intermediary, and a cost of holding cash. The intermediary absorbs a fraction of cash-flow risk that decreases with the firm’s liquidity reserves and acquires a stake in the firm under distress. Implementing the optimal contract suggests an overlapping pecking order. The firm simultaneously finances shortfalls with cash reserves and a credit line and sells equity to the intermediary when it runs out of cash. The model helps explain empirical facts and trends in financial intermediation, such as the rise of private equity.]]></description><author>Barney Hartman-Glaser, Simon Mayer, Konstantin Milbradt</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29712</guid></item><item><title>Expectations Formation and Forward Information</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29711</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nathan Goldstein, Yuriy Gorodnichenko.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We propose a model where forecasters have access to noisy signals about the future (forward information). In this setting, information varies not only across agents but also across horizons. As a result, estimated persistence of forecasts deviates from persistence of fundamentals and the ability of forecasts at shorter horizons to explain forecasts at longer horizons is limited. These properties tend to diminish as the forecast horizon increases. We document that this novel pattern is consistent with survey data for professional forecasters. We provide further evidence that time-series and cross-sectional variation in professional forecasts is driven by forward information. We propose a simple method for extracting the forward information component from survey and provide several applications of forward information.]]></description><author>Nathan Goldstein, Yuriy Gorodnichenko</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29711</guid></item><item><title>When Do Informational Interventions Work? Experimental Evidence from New York City High School Choice</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29690</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sarah Cohodes, Sean Corcoran, Jennifer Jennings, Carolyn Sattin-Bajaj.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> This paper reports the results of a large, school-level randomized controlled trial evaluating a set of three informational interventions for young people choosing high schools in 473 middle schools, serving over 115,000 8th graders. The interventions differed in their level of customization to the student and their mode of delivery (paper or online); all treated schools received identical materials to scaffold the decision-making process. Every intervention reduced likelihood of application to and enrollment in schools with graduation rates below the city median (75 percent). An important channel is their effect on reducing nonoptimal first choice application strategies. Providing a simplified, middle-school specific list of relatively high graduation rate schools had the largest impacts, causing students to enroll in high schools with 1.5-percentage point higher graduation rates. Providing the same information online, however, did not alter students’ choices or enrollment. This appears to be due to low utilization. Online interventions with individual customization, including a recommendation tool and search engine, induced students to enroll in high schools with 1-percentage point higher graduation rates, but with more variance in impact. Together, these results show that successful informational interventions must generate engagement with the material, and this is possible through multiple channels.]]></description><author>Sarah Cohodes, Sean Corcoran, Jennifer Jennings, Carolyn Sattin-Bajaj</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29690</guid></item><item><title>Designing Quality Certificates: Insights from eBay</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29674</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Xiang Hui, Ginger Zhe Jin, Meng Liu.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Quality certification is a common tool to reduce asymmetric information and enhance trust in marketplaces. Should the certificate focus on seller inputs such as fast shipping, or include output measures such as consumer ratings? In theory, incorporating output measures makes the certificate more relevant for consumer experience, but doing so may discourage seller effort because outputs can be driven by random factors out of seller control. To understand this tradeoff, we study a major redesign of eBay's Top Rated Seller (eTRS) program in 2016, which removed most consumer reports from the eTRS criteria and added direct measures of seller inputs. This change generates immediate selection on certified sellers, and homogenizes the share of certified sellers across product categories of different criticalness in consumer ratings. Post the regime change, sellers improve in the input measures highlighted in the new certificate. These effects are more conspicuous in categories that had less critical consumer ratings, in part because the new algorithm automatically removes the potential negative bias for sellers in critical markets and a clearer threshold motivates sellers to just reach the threshold. The new regime also makes sales more concentrated towards large sellers, especially in the categories that face more critical consumers.]]></description><author>Xiang Hui, Ginger Zhe Jin, Meng Liu</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29674</guid></item><item><title>Trade Policy Uncertainty</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29672</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kyle Handley, Nuno Limão.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> Trade policy uncertainty (TPU) has become an important source of economic uncertainty and research. We review the main sources and measures of TPU. We then provide a conceptual framework for modeling TPU and methods of estimating and quantifying its effects. We analyze its role in trade agreements and discuss open questions for future research.]]></description><author>Kyle Handley, Nuno Limão</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29672</guid></item><item><title>Intermediation via Credit Chains</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29632</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhiguo He, Jian Li.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> The modern financial system features complicated financial intermediation chains, with each layer performing a certain degree of credit/maturity transformation. We develop a dynamic model in which an entrepreneur borrows from overlapping-generation households via layers of funds, forming a credit chain. Each intermediary fund in the chain faces rollover risks from its lenders, and the optimal debt contracts among layers are time invariant and layer independent. The model delivers new insights regarding the benefits of intermediation via layers: the chain structure insulates interim negative fundamental shocks and protects the underlying cash flows from being discounted heavily during bad times, resulting in a greater borrowing capacity. We show that the equilibrium chain length minimizes the run risk for any given contract and find that restricting credit chain length can improve total welfare once the available funding from households has been endogenized.]]></description><author>Zhiguo He, Jian Li</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29632</guid></item><item><title>Vertical Differentiation in Frictional Product Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29618</link><description><![CDATA[<i>James Albrecht, Guido Menzio, Susan Vroman.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We consider a version of the imperfect competition model of Butters (1977), Varian (1980) and Burdett and Judd (1983) in which sellers make an ex-ante investment in the quality of their variety of the product. Equilibrium exists, is unique and is efficient. In equilibrium, search frictions not only cause sellers to offer different surpluses to buyers but also cause sellers to choose different qualities for their varieties. That is, equilibrium involves endogenous vertical differentiation. As search frictions decline, the market becomes more and more unequal as a smaller and smaller fraction of sellers produces varieties of increasing quality, offers increasing surplus to their customers, and captures an increasing share of the market, while a growing fraction of sellers produces varieties of decreasing quality. Gains from trade and welfare grow. Under some conditions, the growth rate of gains from trade and welfare is constant.]]></description><author>James Albrecht, Guido Menzio, Susan Vroman</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29618</guid></item><item><title>Information, Intermediaries, and International Migration</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29588</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Samuel Bazzi, Lisa Cameron, Simone G. Schaner, Firman Witoelar.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Job seekers often face substantial information frictions related to potential job quality. This is especially true in international labor markets, where intermediaries match prospective migrants with employers abroad. We conducted a randomized trial in Indonesia to explore how information about intermediary quality shapes migration choices and outcomes. Information reduces the migration rate, lowering use of low-quality intermediaries. However, workers who migrate receive better pre-departure preparation and have higher-quality job experiences abroad, despite no change in occupation or destination. Information does not change intentions to migrate or beliefs about the return to migration or intermediary quality. Nor does selection explain the improved outcomes for workers who choose to migrate with the information. Together, our findings are consistent with an increase in the option value of search: with better ability to differentiate offer quality, workers become choosier and ultimately have better migration experiences. This offers a new perspective on the importance of information and matching frictions in global labor markets.]]></description><author>Samuel Bazzi, Lisa Cameron, Simone G. Schaner, Firman Witoelar</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29588</guid></item><item><title>Inattention and Inequity in School Matching</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29586</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stefan F. Bucher, Andrew Caplin.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The attractive properties of the Deferred Acceptance (DA) algorithm rest on the assumption of perfect information. Yet field studies of school matching show that information is imperfect, particularly for disadvantaged students. We model costly strategic learning when schools are ex ante symmetric, agree on their ranking of students, and learning is rationally inattentive. Our analytic solution quantifies how each student’s rank, learning costs and prior beliefs interact to determine their gross and net welfare as well as the extent and form of mistakes they make. In line with the evidence, we find that lower-ranked students are affected disproportionately more by information costs, generally suffering a larger welfare loss than higher-ranked students. Interactions between mechanism design, inattention and inequity are thus of first order importance.]]></description><author>Stefan F. Bucher, Andrew Caplin</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29586</guid></item><item><title>The Rise, Fall and Stabilization of U.S. Inflation: Shifting Regimes and Evolving Reputation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29585</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Robert G. King, Yang K. Lu.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The rise, fall, and stabilization of US inflation between 1969 and 2005 is consistent with a model of shifting policy regimes that features a forward-looking New Keynesian Phillips curve, policymakers that can or cannot commit, and private sector learning about policymaker type. Using model-implied inflation forecasting rules to extract state variables from the inflation forecasts in the Survey of Professional Forecasters, we provide evidence that policy regimes without commitment prevailed before 1980 and regimes with commitment prevailed afterward. With theory and quantification, we find that evolution of reputational capital is central to understanding the behavior of inflation.]]></description><author>Robert G. King, Yang K. Lu</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29585</guid></item><item><title>Absenteeism, Productivity, and Relational Contracts Inside the Firm</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29581</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Achyuta Adhvaryu, Jean-François Gauthier, Anant Nyshadham, Jorge A. Tamayo.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study relational contracts among managers using unique data that tracks transfers of workers across teams in Indian ready-made garment factories. We focus on how relational contracts help managers cope with worker absenteeism shocks, which are frequent, often large, weakly correlated across teams, and which substantially reduce team productivity. Together these facts imply gains from sharing workers. We show that managers respond to shocks by lending and borrowing workers in a manner consistent with relational contracting, but many potentially beneficial transfers are unrealized. This is because managers’ primary relationships are with a very small subset of potential partners. A borrowing event study around main trading partners’ separations from the firm reinforces the importance of relationships. We show robustness to excluding worker moves least likely to reflect relational borrowing responses to idiosyncratic absenteeism shocks. Counterfactual simulations reveal large gains to reducing costs associated with forming and maintaining additional relationships among managers.]]></description><author>Achyuta Adhvaryu, Jean-François Gauthier, Anant Nyshadham, Jorge A. Tamayo</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29581</guid></item><item><title>Individual and Collective Information Acquisition: An Experimental Study</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29557</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pëllumb Reshidi, Alessandro Lizzeri, Leeat Yariv, Jimmy H. Chan, Wing Suen.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> Many committees—juries, political task forces, etc.—spend time gathering costly information before reaching a decision. We report results from lab experiments focused on such information-collection processes. We consider decisions governed by individuals and groups and compare how voting rules affect outcomes. We also contrast static information collection, as in classical hypothesis testing, with dynamic collection, as in sequential hypothesis testing. Several insights emerge. Static information collection is excessive, and sequential information collection is non-stationary, producing declining decision accuracies over time. Furthermore, groups using majority rule yield especially hasty and inaccurate decisions. Nonetheless, sequential information collection is welfare enhancing relative to static collection, particularly when unanimous rules are used.]]></description><author>Pëllumb Reshidi, Alessandro Lizzeri, Leeat Yariv, Jimmy H. Chan, Wing Suen</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29557</guid></item><item><title>Capital Return Jumps and Wealth Distribution</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29544</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jess Benhabib, Wei Cui, Jianjun Miao.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> The distributions of wealth in the US and many other countries are strikingly concentrated on the top and skewed to the right. To explain the income and wealth inequality, we provide a tractable heterogeneous-agent model with incomplete markets in continuous time. We separate illiquid capital assets from liquid bond assets and introduce capital return jump risks. Under recursive utility, we derive optimal consumption and wealth in closed form and show that the stationary wealth distribution has an exponential right tail. Our calibrated model can match the income and wealth distributions in the US data including the extreme right tail. We also study the effect of taxes on the distribution of wealth.]]></description><author>Jess Benhabib, Wei Cui, Jianjun Miao</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29544</guid></item><item><title>Attention, Social Interaction, and Investor Attraction to Lottery Stocks</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29543</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Turan G. Bali, David Hirshleifer, Lin Peng, Yi Tang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We find that among stocks dominated by retail investors, the lottery anomaly is amplified by high investor attention (proxied by high analyst coverage, salient earnings surprises, or recency of extreme positive returns) and intense social interactions (proxied by Facebook social connectedness or population density near firm headquarters). Such stocks’ lottery features attract greater Google search volume and retail net buying, followed by more negative earnings surprises and lower announcement-period returns. The findings provide insight into the roles of attention and social interaction in securities markets, and support the hypothesis that these forces contribute to investor attraction to lottery stocks.]]></description><author>Turan G. Bali, David Hirshleifer, Lin Peng, Yi Tang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29543</guid></item><item><title>The Cost of Consumer Collateral: Evidence from Bunching</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29527</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Benjamin L. Collier, Cameron Ellis, Benjamin J. Keys.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We show that borrowers are highly sensitive to the requirement of posting their homes as collateral. Using administrative loan application and performance data from the U.S. Federal Disaster Loan Program, we exploit a loan amount threshold above which households must post their residence as collateral. One-third of all borrowers select the maximum uncollateralized loan amount, and our bunching estimates suggest that the median borrower is willing to give up 40% of their loan amount to avoid collateral. Exploiting time variation in the loan amount threshold, we find that collateral causally reduces default rates by 35%. Our results help to explain high perceived default costs in the mortgage market, and uniquely quantify the extent to which collateral reduces moral hazard in consumer credit markets.]]></description><author>Benjamin L. Collier, Cameron Ellis, Benjamin J. Keys</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29527</guid></item><item><title>An Economic Model of Consensus on Distributed Ledgers</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29515</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Hanna Halaburda, Zhiguo He, Jiasun Li.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In recent years, the designs of many new blockchain applications have been inspired by the Byzantine fault tolerance (BFT) problem. While traditional BFT protocols assume that most system nodes are honest (in that they follow the protocol), we recognize that blockchains are deployed in environments where nodes are subject to strategic incentives. This paper develops an economic framework for analyzing such cases. Specifically, we assume that 1) non-Byzantine nodes are rational, so we explicitly study their incentives when participating in a BFT consensus process; 2) non-Byzantine nodes are ambiguity averse, and specifically, Knightian uncertain about Byzantine actions; and 3) decisions/inferences are all based on local information. We thus obtain a consensus game with preplay communications. We characterize all equilibria, some of which feature rational leaders withholding messages from some nodes in order to achieve consensus. These findings enrich those from traditional BFT algorithms, where an honest leader always sends messages to all nodes. We also study how the progress of communication technology (i.e., potential message losses) affects the equilibrium consensus outcome.]]></description><author>Hanna Halaburda, Zhiguo He, Jiasun Li</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29515</guid></item><item><title>COVID-19, Government Performance, and Democracy: Survey Experimental Evidence from 12 Countries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29514</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Michael Becher, Nicolas Longuet Marx, Vincent Pons, Sylvain Brouard, Martial Foucault, Vincenzo Galasso, Eric Kerrouche, Sandra León Alfonso, Daniel Stegmueller.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Beyond its immediate impact on public health and the economy, the COVID-19 pandemic has put democracy under stress. While a common view is that people should blame the government rather than the political system for bad crisis management, an opposing view is that dissatisfaction with government performance may cause deeper dissatisfaction with democracy even in consolidated democratic regimes. We use a pre-registered survey and experiment covering 12 countries and 22,500 respondents to examine the impact of the pandemic on public attitudes about incumbent governments, the functioning of democracy and support for different types of regimes. To estimate causal effects, we leverage experimental treatments using an instrumental variable design. We find that dissatisfaction with the government, which is equally driven by economic and health considerations, decreases satisfaction with how democracy works. However, it does not translate into an embrace of non-democratic regime types.]]></description><author>Michael Becher, Nicolas Longuet Marx, Vincent Pons, Sylvain Brouard, Martial Foucault, Vincenzo Galasso, Eric Kerrouche, Sandra León Alfonso, Daniel Stegmueller</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29514</guid></item><item><title>Learning versus Unlearning: An Experiment on Retractions</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29512</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Duarte Gonçalves, Jonathan Libgober, Jack Willis.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Widely discredited ideas nevertheless persist. Why do we fail to "unlearn"? We study one explanation: beliefs are resistant to retractions (the revoking of earlier information). Our experimental design allows us to identify updating from retractions - unlearning - and to compare it with updating from equivalent new information - learning. Across different kinds of retractions - for instance, those consistent or contradictory with the prior, or those occurring when prior beliefs are either extreme or moderate - subjects do not fully unlearn from retractions and update approximately one-third less from them than from equivalent new information. While we document a number of well-known biases in belief updating in our data, our results are inconsistent with any explanation that does not treat retractions as inherently different. Instead, our analysis suggests that retractions are harder to process, for instance, due to the intimate reliance on conditional reasoning.]]></description><author>Duarte Gonçalves, Jonathan Libgober, Jack Willis</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29512</guid></item><item><title>The Hot Hand in the NBA 3-Point Contest: The Importance of Location, Location, Location</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29468</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Robert M. Lantis, Erik T. Nesson.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Do basketball players exhibit a hot hand? Results from controlled shooting situations suggest the answer is yes, while results from in-game shooting are mixed. Are the differing results because a hot hand is only present in similar shots or because testing for the hot hand in game situations is difficult? Combining repeated shots in a location and shots across locations, the NBA 3-Point Contests mimics game situations without many of the confounding factors. Using data on the 1986-2019 contests, we find a hot hand, but only within shot locations. Shooting streaks increase a hot hand only if a player makes his previous shot and only within locations. Even making three shots in a row has no effect on making the next shot if a player moves locations. Our results suggest that any hot hand in basketball is only present in extremely similar shooting situations and likely not in the run-of-play.]]></description><author>Robert M. Lantis, Erik T. Nesson</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29468</guid></item><item><title>Intermediation and Voluntary Exposure to Counterparty Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29467</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Maryam Farboodi.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> I study a model of the financial sector in which intermediation among debt financed banks gives rise to an endogenous core-periphery network – few highly interconnected and many sparsely connected banks. Endogenous intermediation generates excessive systemic risk in the financial network. Financial institutions have incentives to capture intermediation spreads through strategic borrowing and lending decisions. By doing so, they tilt the division of surplus along an intermediation chain in their favor, while at the same time reducing aggregate surplus. The network is inefficient relative to a constrained efficient benchmark since banks who make risky investments “overconnect”, exposing themselves to excessive counterparty risk, while banks who mainly provide funding end up with too few connections.]]></description><author>Maryam Farboodi</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29467</guid></item><item><title>Which Beliefs? Behavior-Predictive Beliefs are Inconsistent with Information-Based Beliefs: Evidence from COVID-19</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29452</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ori Heffetz, Guy Ishai.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We investigate the relationship between (a) official information on COVID-19 infection and death case counts; (b) beliefs about such case counts, at present and in the future; (c) beliefs about average infection chance—in principle, directly calculable from (b); and (d) self-reported health-protective behavior. We elicit (b), (c), and (d) with a daily online survey in the US from March to August 2020 (N ≈ 13,900).<br />
We have three main findings: (1) beliefs elicited as infection case counts are closely related to present and future official case-count information; however (2) beliefs elicited as risk perceptions—i.e., the chance to get infected—are inconsistent with those case-count beliefs, even when mathematically, they should be identical; notably, (3) it is the latter—the risk perceptions—that are significantly better predictors of reported behavior than the former.<br />
Together, these findings suggest that researchers and policymakers, who increasingly engage in direct elicitation and communication of numeric measures of uncertainty, may get very different outcomes, depending on which measures they use. We discuss potential implications for public communication of health-risk information.]]></description><author>Ori Heffetz, Guy Ishai</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29452</guid></item><item><title>Herding with Heterogeneous Ability: An Application to Organ Transplantation</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29412</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Stephanie C. De Mel, Kaivan Munshi, Soenje Reiche, Hamid Sabourian.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> There are many economic environments in which an object is offered sequentially to prospective buyers. It is often observed that once the object for sale is turned down by one or more agents, those that follow do the same. One explanation that has been proposed for this phenomenon is that agents making choices further down the line rationally ignore their own assessment of the object's quality and herd behind their predecessors. Our research adds a new dimension to the canonical herding model by allowing agents to differ in their ability to assess the quality of the offered object. We develop novel tests of herding based on this ability heterogeneity and also examine its efficiency consequences, applied to organ transplantation in the U.K. We find that herding is common but that the information lost due to herding does not substantially increase false discards of good organs or false acceptances of bad organs. Our counter-factual analysis indicates that this is due (in part) to the high degree of heterogeneity in ability across transplant centers. In other settings, such as the U.S., where organ transplantation is organized very differently and the ability distribution will not be the same, the inefficiencies due to herding might well be substantial.]]></description><author>Stephanie C. De Mel, Kaivan Munshi, Soenje Reiche, Hamid Sabourian</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29412</guid></item><item><title>Policy Experimentation in China: the Political Economy of Policy Learning</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29402</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Shaoda Wang, David Y. Yang.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Many governments have engaged in policy experimentation in various forms to resolve uncertainty and facilitate learning. However, little is understood about the characteristics of policy experimentation, and how the structure of experimentation may affect policy learning and policy outcomes. We aim to describe and understand China’s policy experimentation since 1980, among the largest and most systematic in recent history. We collect comprehensive data on policy experimentation conducted in China over the past four decades. We find three main results. First, more than 80% of the experiments exhibit positive sample selection in terms of a locality’s economic development, and much of this can be attributed to misaligned incentives across political hierarchies. Second, local politicians allocate more resources to ensure the experiments’ success, and such effort is not replicable when policies roll out to the entire country. Third, the presence of sample selection and strategic effort is not fully accounted for by the central government, thus affecting policy learning and distorting national policies originating from the experimentation. Taken together, these results suggest that while China’s bureaucratic and institutional conditions make policy experimentation at such scale possible, the complex political environments can also limit the scope and bias the direction of policy learning.]]></description><author>Shaoda Wang, David Y. Yang</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29402</guid></item><item><title>It All Starts with Beliefs: Addressing the Roots of Educational Inequities by Shifting Parental Beliefs</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29394</link><description><![CDATA[<i>John A. List, Julie Pernaudet, Dana Suskind.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Socioeconomic inequalities in child development crystallize at early stages, with associated disparities in parental investment in children. A key to understanding the data patterns is to document the sources underlying the observed inequalities. We first show that there are dramatic differences in parental beliefs across socioeconomic backgrounds (SES), with parents of higher SES being more likely to believe that parental investments impact child development. We then use two field experiments targeted to low-SES families to explore the mutability of such beliefs and their link to parental investments. In both cases, we find that parental beliefs about child development are malleable. The less intensive version of the program based on educational videos changes parental beliefs, but fails to lastingly increase parental investments and child outcomes. By contrast, in the more intensive version of our program combining home visits and feedback, the augmented beliefs are associated with enriched parent-child interactions and improved vocabulary, math, and social-emotional skills for the children. Together, these results suggest that changing parental beliefs can be an important pathway to raising parental investments and reducing socioeconomic gaps in children’s skills, but that simple informational policies may not be sufficient.]]></description><author>John A. List, Julie Pernaudet, Dana Suskind</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29394</guid></item><item><title>A (Dynamic) Investigation of Stereotypes, Belief-Updating, and Behavior</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29382</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Katherine B. Coffman, Paola Ugalde Araya, Basit Zafar.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Many decisions – such as what educational or career path to pursue – are dynamic in nature, with individuals receiving feedback at one point in time and making decisions later. Using a controlled experiment, with two sessions one week apart, we analyze the dynamic effects of feedback on beliefs about own performance and decision-making across two different domains (verbal skills and math). We find significant gender gaps in beliefs and choices before feedback: men are more optimistic about their performance and more willing to compete than women in both domains, but the gaps are significantly larger in math. Feedback significantly shifts individuals' beliefs and choices. Despite this, we see substantial persistence of gender gaps over time. This is particularly true among the set of individuals who receive negative feedback. We find that, holding fixed performance and decisions before feedback, women update their beliefs and choices more negatively than men do after bad news. Our results highlight the challenges involved in overcoming gender gaps in dynamic settings.]]></description><author>Katherine B. Coffman, Paola Ugalde Araya, Basit Zafar</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29382</guid></item><item><title>Economic Data Engineering</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29378</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andrew Caplin.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Economic data engineering deliberately designs novel forms of data to solve fundamental identification problems associated with economic models of choice. I outline three diverse applications: to the economics of information; to life-cycle employment, earnings, and spending; and to public policy analysis. In all three cases one and the same fundamental identification problem is driving data innovation: that of separately identifying appropriately rich preferences and beliefs. In addition to presenting these conceptually linked examples, I provide a general overview of the engineering process, outline important next steps, and highlight larger opportunities.]]></description><author>Andrew Caplin</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29378</guid></item><item><title>A Taste of Their Own Medicine: Guideline Adherence and Access to Expertise</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29356</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Amy Finkelstein, Petra Persson, Maria Polyakova, Jesse M. Shapiro.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We use population administrative data from Sweden to study adherence to 63 medication-related guidelines. We compare the adherence of patients without personal access to medical expertise to the adherence of those with access, namely doctors and their close relatives. We estimate that, among observably similar patients, access to expertise is associated with 3.8 percentage points lower adherence, relative to a baseline adherence rate of 54.4 percent among those without access. This association is larger for recommendations with a weaker clinical motivation. Our findings suggest an important role in non-adherence for factors other than those, such as ignorance, complexity, or failures of patient-provider communication, that would be expected to diminish with access to expertise.]]></description><author>Amy Finkelstein, Petra Persson, Maria Polyakova, Jesse M. Shapiro</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29356</guid></item><item><title>Circles of Trust: Rival Information in Social Networks</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29324</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Petra Persson ⓡ, Nikita Roketskiy ⓡ, Samuel Lee.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We analyze the diffusion of rival information in a social network. In our model, rational agents can share information sequentially, unconstrained by an exogenous protocol or timing. We show how to compute the set of eventually informed agents for any network, and show that it is essentially unique under altruistic preferences. The relationship between network structure and information diffusion is complex because the former shapes both the charity and confidentiality of potential senders and receivers.]]></description><author>Petra Persson ⓡ, Nikita Roketskiy ⓡ, Samuel Lee</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29324</guid></item><item><title>Human Frictions in the Transmission of Economic Policies</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Many consumers below the top of the distribution of a representative population by cognitive abilities barely react to  monetary and fiscal policies that aim to stimulate consumption and borrowing, even when they are financially unconstrained and despite substantial debt capacity. Differences in income, formal education levels, economic expectations, and a large set of registry-based demographics do not explain these facts. Heterogeneous cognitive abilities thus act as human frictions in the transmission of economic policies that operate through the household sector and might imply  redistribution from low- to high-cognitive-ability agents. We conclude by discussing how our findings inform the microfoundation of behavioral macroeconomic theory.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Daniel Hoang, Maritta Paloviita, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29279</guid></item><item><title>Diverse Policy Committees Can Reach Underrepresented Groups</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Francesco D’Acunto, Andreas Fuster, Michael Weber.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Increasing the diversity of policy committees has taken center stage worldwide, but whether and why diverse committees are more effective is still unclear. In a randomized control trial that varies the salience of female and minority representation on the Federal Reserve’s monetary policy committee, the FOMC, we test whether diversity affects how Fed information influences consumers’ subjective beliefs. Women and Black respondents form unemployment expectations more in line with FOMC forecasts and trust the Fed more after this intervention. Women are also more likely to acquire Fed-related information when associated with a female official. White men, who are overrepresented on the FOMC, do not react negatively. Heterogeneous taste for diversity can explain these patterns better than homophily. Our results suggest more diverse policy committees are better able to reach underrepresented groups without inducing negative reactions by others, thereby enhancing the effectiveness of policy communication and public trust in the institution.]]></description><author>Francesco D’Acunto, Andreas Fuster, Michael Weber</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29275</guid></item><item><title>Salience</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29274</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pedro Bordalo, Nicola Gennaioli, Andrei Shleifer.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We review the fast-growing work on salience and economic behavior. Psychological research shows that salient stimuli attract human attention “bottom up” due to their high contrast with surroundings, their surprising nature relative to recalled experiences, or their prominence. The Bordalo, Gennaioli and Shleifer (2012, 2013, 2020) models of salience show how bottom up attention can distort economic choice by distracting decision makers from their immediate goals or from certain choice attributes. We show that this approach explains many puzzles: separately treated departures from “rationality” such as probability weighting, menu effects, reference point effects, and framing, emerge as distinct manifestations of the same principle of bottom up attention to salient stimuli. We highlight new predictions and discuss open conceptual questions, as well as potential applications in finance, industrial organization, advertising, and politics.]]></description><author>Pedro Bordalo, Nicola Gennaioli, Andrei Shleifer</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29274</guid></item><item><title>Memory and Probability</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29273</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Pedro Bordalo, John J. Conlon, Nicola Gennaioli, Spencer Yongwook Kwon, Andrei Shleifer.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> People often estimate probabilities, such as the likelihood that an insurable risk will materialize or that an Irish person has red hair, by retrieving experiences from memory. We present a model of this process based on two established regularities of selective recall: similarity and interference. The model accounts for and reconciles a variety of conflicting empirical findings, such as overestimation of unlikely events when these are cued vs. neglect of non-cued ones, the availability heuristic, the representativeness heuristic, as well as over vs. underreaction to information in different situations. The model makes new predictions on how the content of a hypothesis (not just its objective probability) affects probability assessments by shaping the ease of recall. We experimentally evaluate these predictions and find strong experimental support.]]></description><author>Pedro Bordalo, John J. Conlon, Nicola Gennaioli, Spencer Yongwook Kwon, Andrei Shleifer</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29273</guid></item><item><title>Measuring the Welfare Cost of Asymmetric Information in Consumer Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Information asymmetries are known in theory to lead to inefficiently low credit provision, yet empirical estimates of the resulting welfare losses are scarce. This paper leverages a randomized experiment conducted by a large fintech lender to estimate welfare losses arising from asymmetric information in the market for online consumer credit. Building on methods from the insurance literature, we show how exogenous variation in interest rates can be used to estimate borrower demand and lender cost curves and recover implied welfare losses. While asymmetric information generates large equilibrium price distortions, we find only small overall welfare losses, particularly for high-credit-score borrowers.]]></description><author>Anthony A. DeFusco, Huan Tang, Constantine Yannelis</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29270</guid></item><item><title>Signaling in Online Credit Markets</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29268</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Kei Kawai, Ken Onishi, Kosuke Uetake.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We study how signaling affects equilibrium outcomes and welfare in an online credit market using detailed data on loan characteristics and borrower repayment. We build and estimate an equilibrium model in which a borrower may signal her default risk through the reserve interest rate. Comparing a market with and without signaling relative to the benchmark with no asymmetric information, we find that adverse selection destroys as much as 34% of total surplus, up to 78% of which can be restored with signaling. We also estimate backward-bending supply curves for some markets, consistent with the prediction of Stiglitz &amp; Weiss (1981).]]></description><author>Kei Kawai, Ken Onishi, Kosuke Uetake</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29268</guid></item></channel></rss>