<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS for NBER topic Portfolio Selection and Asset Pricing</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS for NBER topic Portfolio Selection and Asset Pricing</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 15:21:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Simple Allocation Rules and Optimal Portfolio Choice Over the Lifecycle</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29559</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Victor Duarte, Julia Fonseca, Aaron S. Goodman, Jonathan A. Parker.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We develop a machine-learning solution algorithm to solve for optimal portfolio choice in a detailed and quantitatively-accurate lifecycle model that includes many features of reality modelled only separately in previous work.  We use the quantitative model to evaluate the consumption-equivalent welfare losses from using simple rules for portfolio allocation across stocks, bonds, and liquid accounts instead of the optimal portfolio choices. We find that the consumption-equivalent losses from using an age-dependent rule as embedded in current target-date/lifecycle funds (TDFs) are substantial, around 2 to 3 percent of consumption, despite the fact that TDF rules mimic average optimal behavior by age closely until shortly before retirement. Our model recommends higher average equity shares in the second half of life than the portfolio of the typical TDF, so that the typical TDF portfolio does not improve on investing an age-independent 2/3 share in equity. Finally, optimal equity shares have substantial heterogeneity, particularly by wealth level, state of the business cycle, and dividend-price ratio, implying substantial gains to further customization of advice or TDFs in these dimensions.]]></description><author>Victor Duarte, Julia Fonseca, Aaron S. Goodman, Jonathan A. Parker</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29559</guid></item><item><title>Attention, Social Interaction, and Investor Attraction to Lottery Stocks</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29543</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Turan G. Bali, David Hirshleifer, Lin Peng, Yi Tang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We find that among stocks dominated by retail investors, the lottery anomaly is amplified by high investor attention (proxied by high analyst coverage, salient earnings surprises, or recency of extreme positive returns) and intense social interactions (proxied by Facebook social connectedness or population density near firm headquarters). Such stocks’ lottery features attract greater Google search volume and retail net buying, followed by more negative earnings surprises and lower announcement-period returns. The findings provide insight into the roles of attention and social interaction in securities markets, and support the hypothesis that these forces contribute to investor attraction to lottery stocks.]]></description><author>Turan G. Bali, David Hirshleifer, Lin Peng, Yi Tang</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29543</guid></item><item><title>Is Hard and Soft Information Substitutable? Evidence from Lockdown</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29513</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jennie Bai, Massimo Massa.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study information substitutability in the financial market through a quasi-natural experiment: the pandemic-triggered lockdown that has hampered people's physical interactions hence the ability to collect, process, and transmit soft information. Exploiting the cross- sectional and time-series variations of lockdown, we investigate how the difficulty to use soft information has prompted a switch to hard information and its implication on fund investment, performance, and risk management. We show that lockdown reduces fund investment in proximate stocks and generates a portfolio rebalancing toward distant stocks. The re- balancing negatively impacts fund performance by reducing fund raw (excess) return of an additional 0.76% (0.29%) per month during lockdown, suggesting that soft and hard information is not easily substitutable. Lastly, we show that soft information originates mainly from physical human interactions, primarily in cafés, restaurants, bars, and fitness centers; and the virtual world based on Zoom/Skype/Team fails to substitute physical interactions fully, thus cannot provide sufficient soft information.]]></description><author>Jennie Bai, Massimo Massa</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29513</guid></item><item><title>Sovereign Risk and Financial Risk</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29501</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Simon Gilchrist, Bin Wei, Vivian Z. Yue, Egon Zakrajšek.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we study the interplay between sovereign risk and global financial risk. We show that a substantial portion of the comovement among sovereign spreads is accounted for by changes in global financial risk. We construct bond-level sovereign spreads for dollar-denominated bonds issued by over 50 countries from 1995 to 2020 and use various indicators to measure global financial risk. Through panel regressions and local projection analysis, we find that an increase in global financial risk causes a large and persistent widening of sovereign bond spreads. These effects are strongest when measuring global risk using the excess bond premium – a measure of the risk-bearing capacity of U.S. financial intermediaries. The spillover effects of global financial risk are more pronounced for speculative-grade sovereign bonds.]]></description><author>Simon Gilchrist, Bin Wei, Vivian Z. Yue, Egon Zakrajšek</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29501</guid></item><item><title>Learning About the Long Run</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29495</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Leland Farmer, Emi Nakamura, Jón Steinsson.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Forecasts of professional forecasters are anomalous: they are biased, forecast errors are autocorrelated, and forecast revisions predict forecast errors. Sticky or noisy information models seem like unlikely explanations for these anomalies: professional forecasters pay attention constantly and have precise knowledge of the data in question. We propose that these anomalies arise because professional forecasters don’t know the model that generates the data. We show that Bayesian agents learning about hard-to-learn features of the data generating process (low frequency behavior) can generate all the prominent aggregate anomalies emphasized in the literature. We show this for two applications: professional forecasts of nominal interest rates for the sample period 1980-2019 and CBO forecasts of GDP growth for the sample period 1976- 2019. Our learning model for interest rates also provides an explanation for deviations from the expectations hypothesis of the term structure that does not rely on time-variation in risk premia.]]></description><author>Leland Farmer, Emi Nakamura, Jón Steinsson</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29495</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Firm Environmental Performance to Inform Asset Management and Standardized Disclosure</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicholas Z. Muller.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Investing according to environmental, social, and governance (ESG) criteria is gaining momentum. Most environmental performance indices focus only on the tonnage of carbon dioxide (CO₂) emissions. This paper proposes an index covering eight pollutants expressed in monetary damage. Inclusion of multiple pollutants reflects a broader range of reputational and regulatory risks. Monetization appropriately weights emissions. CO₂ dominates the mass of other pollutants, yet the marginal damages from other pollutants are larger than CO₂. In the U.S. utility sector from 2014 to 2017, indices which only track CO₂ mischaracterize firms’ environmental performance and underestimate its effect on financial outcomes relative to the multipollutant index. Dirtier firms exhibit lower share prices and higher forward returns. The effect is twice as large for the multipollutant index compared to CO₂. Analysts’ earnings forecasts for dirtier firms systematically undershoot actuals. Earnings errors are between three and five times more sensitive to the multipollutant index than to CO₂. The multipollutant index may suggest new management strategies to financial market participants relative to those based on carbon intensity. ESG disclosure standards based on the new index are more likely to affect financial outcomes, capital allocation decisions, and firm behavior than disclosure of carbon intensity.]]></description><author>Nicholas Z. Muller</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</guid></item><item><title>Momentum, Reversals, and Investor Clientele</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29453</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Andy C.W. Chui, Avanidhar Subrahmanyam, Sheridan Titman.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Different share classes on the same firms provide a natural experiment to explore how investor clienteles affect momentum and short-term reversals. Domestic retail investors have a greater presence in Chinese A shares, and foreign institutions are relatively more prevalent in B shares. These differences result from currency conversion restrictions and mandated investment quotas. We find that only B shares exhibit momentum and earnings drift, and only A shares exhibit monthly reversals. Institutional ownership strengthens momentum in B shares. These patterns accord with a setting where momentum is caused by informed investors who underreact to fundamental signals, and short-term reversals represent premia to absorb the demands of noise traders. Overall, our findings confirm that clienteles matter in generating stock return predictability from past returns.]]></description><author>Andy C.W. Chui, Avanidhar Subrahmanyam, Sheridan Titman</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29453</guid></item><item><title>CLO Performance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29410</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Larry Cordell, Michael R. Roberts, Michael Schwert.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We study the performance of collateralized loan obligations (CLOs) to understand the market imperfections giving rise to these vehicles and their corresponding economic costs. CLO equity tranches earn positive abnormal returns from the risk-adjusted price differential between leveraged loans and CLO debt tranches. Debt tranches offer higher returns than similarly rated corporate bonds, making them attractive to banks and insurers that face risk-based capital requirements. Temporal variation in equity performance highlights the resilience of CLOs to market volatility due to their closed-end structure, long-term funding, and embedded options to reinvest principal proceeds.]]></description><author>Larry Cordell, Michael R. Roberts, Michael Schwert</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29410</guid></item><item><title>Blockchain Analysis of the Bitcoin Market</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29396</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Igor Makarov, Antoinette Schoar.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> In this paper, we provide detailed analyses of the Bitcoin network and its main participants. We build a novel database using a large number of public and proprietary sources to link Bitcoin addresses to real entities and develop an extensive suite of algorithms to extract information about the behavior of the main market participants. We conduct three major pieces of analysis of the Bitcoin eco-system. First, we analyze the transaction volume and network structure of the main participants on the blockchain. Second, we document the concentration and regional composition of the miners which are the backbone of the verification protocol and ensure the integrity of the blockchain ledger. Finally, we analyze the ownership concentration of the largest holders of Bitcoin.]]></description><author>Igor Makarov, Antoinette Schoar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29396</guid></item><item><title>Predicting the Oil Market</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29379</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Charles W. Calomiris, Harry Mamaysky, Nida Çakır Melek.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We study the performance of many traditional and novel, text-based variables for in-sample and out-of-sample forecasting of oil spot, futures, and energy company stock returns, and changes in oil volatility, production, and inventories. After controlling for small-sample biases, we find evidence of in-sample predictability. Our text measures, derived using energy news articles, hold their own against traditional variables. While we cannot identify ex-ante rules for selecting successful out-of-sample forecasters, an analysis of all possible two-variable models reveals out-of-sample performance above that expected under random variation. Our findings provide new directions for identifying robust forecasting models for oil markets, and beyond.]]></description><author>Charles W. Calomiris, Harry Mamaysky, Nida Çakır Melek</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29379</guid></item><item><title>A Factor Model For Option Returns</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29369</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Matthias Buechner, Bryan T. Kelly.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Due to their short lifespans and migrating moneyness, options are notoriously difficult to study with the factor models commonly used to analyze the risk-return trade-off in other asset classes. Instrumented principal components analysis solves this problem by tracking contracts in terms of their pricing-relevant characteristics via time-varying latent factor loadings. We find that a model with three latent factors prices the cross-section of option returns and explains more than 85% of the variation in a panel of monthly S&amp;P 500 option returns from 1996 to 2017. In particular, we show that the IPCA factors can be rationalized via an economically plausible three-factor model consisting of a level, slope and skew factor. Finally, out-of-sample trading strategies based on insights from the IPCA model have significant alpha over previously studied option strategies.]]></description><author>Matthias Buechner, Bryan T. Kelly</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29369</guid></item><item><title>What Drives Variation in the U.S. Debt/Output Ratio? The Dogs that Didn't Bark</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29351</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Zhengyang Jiang, Hanno Lustig, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh, Mindy Z. Xiaolan.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> If the U.S. is on a fiscally sustainable path, then higher U.S. government debt/output ratios should reliably predict higher future surpluses or lower real returns on Treasurys. In the post-war sample, we find no evidence for this. Neither future cash flows nor discount rates account for the variation in the current debt/output ratio. Instead, the future debt/output ratio accounts for most of the variation. Systematic surplus forecast errors can account for part of these findings. Since the start of the GFC, surplus projections have anticipated a large fiscal correction that failed to materialize.]]></description><author>Zhengyang Jiang, Hanno Lustig, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh, Mindy Z. Xiaolan</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29351</guid></item><item><title>Exposure, Experience, and Expertise: Why Personal Histories Matter in Economics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ulrike Malmendier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Personal experiences of economic outcomes, from global financial crises to individual-level job losses, can shape individual beliefs, risk attitudes, and choices for years to come. A growing literature on experience effects shows that individuals act as if past outcomes that they experienced were overly likely to occur again, even if they are fully informed about the actual likelihood. This reaction to past experiences is long-lasting though it decays over time as individuals accumulate new experiences. Modern brain science helps understand these processes. Evidence on neuroplasticity reveals that personal experiences and learning alter the strength of neural connections and fine-tune the brain structure to those past experiences ("use-dependent brain"). I show that experience effects help understand belief formation and decision-making in a wide area of economic applications, including inflation, home purchases, mortgage choices, and consumption expenditures. I argue that experience-based learning is broadly applicable to economic decision-making and discuss topics for future research in education, health, race, and gender economics.]]></description><author>Ulrike Malmendier</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</guid></item><item><title>Foreign Investors and U.S. Treasuries</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29313</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Alexandra M. Tabova, Francis E. Warnock.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> While foreigners are prominent in the Treasury market and in theoretical and empirical work, little is known about the nature of their Treasury portfolios. We provide novel evidence on foreigners' U.S. Treasury portfolios based on data not yet used by researchers: the security-level Treasury portfolios of foreigners and private U.S. investors. We find that private foreign investors earn above market returns and on a risk-adjusted basis both foreign private and foreign official investors outperform U.S. investors. Moreover, while foreign officials, with their broader objective functions, may well have inelastic demand, private foreign investors increase purchases of Treasuries and increase the duration of their Treasury portfolios when their sovereign yields are low or decrease relative to Treasury yields (that is, when CIP deviations decrease). Our results are so different from existing results that we close with a reconciliation exercise that provides a useful assessment of different sources of data on flows and holdings.]]></description><author>Alexandra M. Tabova, Francis E. Warnock</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29313</guid></item><item><title>The Asymmetry in Responsible Investing Preferences</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29288</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jacquelyn Humphrey, Shimon Kogan, Jacob Sagi, Laura Starks.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We design an experiment to understand how social preferences affect investment decisions through stock allocations and probability assessments. The major preference channel is asymmetric in social outcomes – although negative and positive responsible investment (RI) externalities have the same magnitudes, negative externalities have greater impact on investment choices. The effect is persistent, but heterogenous. We also find asymmetries in belief formation and learning constitute a secondary channel. Overall, our results are consistent with important stylized empirical facts and the predictions of recent RI theories that social preferences lead to different investment choices, but our analyses also suggest important future modeling directions.]]></description><author>Jacquelyn Humphrey, Shimon Kogan, Jacob Sagi, Laura Starks</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29288</guid></item><item><title>Does Political Partisanship Cross Borders? Evidence from International Capital Flows</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29280</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Elisabeth Kempf, Mancy Luo, Larissa Schäfer, Margarita Tsoutsoura.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> Does partisan perception shape the flow of international capital? We provide evidence from two settings, syndicated corporate loans and equity mutual funds, to show that ideological alignment with foreign governments affects the cross-border capital allocation by U.S. institutional investors. Moreover, we find that ideological alignment with foreign countries also affects investments of non-U.S. investors and can explain patterns in bilateral FDI flows. Our empirical strategy ensures that direct economic effects of foreign elections or bilateral ties between countries are not driving the result. Combined, our findings imply that partisan perception is a global phenomenon and its economic effects transcend national borders.]]></description><author>Elisabeth Kempf, Mancy Luo, Larissa Schäfer, Margarita Tsoutsoura</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29280</guid></item><item><title>Corporate Actions and the Manipulation of Retail Investors in China: An Analysis of Stock Splits</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29212</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sheridan Titman, Chishen Wei. Wei, Bin Zhao.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We identify a group of “suspicious” firms that use stock splits—perhaps, along with other activities—to artificially inflate their share prices. Following the initiation of suspicious splits, share prices temporarily increase, and subsequently decline below their pre-split levels. Using account level data from the Shanghai Stock Exchange, we find that small retail investors acquire shares in firms initiating suspicious splits, while more sophisticated investors accumulate positions before suspicious split announcements and sell in the post-split period. We also find that insiders sell large blocks of shares and obtain loans using company stock as collateral around the initiation of suspicious splits.]]></description><author>Sheridan Titman, Chishen Wei. Wei, Bin Zhao</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29212</guid></item><item><title>Why Did Small Business Fintech Lending Dry Up During March 2020?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29205</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Itzhak Ben-David, Mark J. Johnson, René M. Stulz.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> With the onset of the COVID-19 crisis in March 2020, small business lending through fintech lenders collapsed. We explore the reasons for the market shutdown using detailed data about loan applications, offers, and take-up from a major small business fintech credit platform. We document that while the number of loan applications increased sharply early in March 2020, the supply of credit collapsed as online lenders dropped from the platform and the likelihood of applicants receiving loan offers fell precipitously. Our analysis shows that the drying up of the loan supply is most consistent with fintech lenders becoming financially constrained and losing their ability to fund new loans.]]></description><author>Itzhak Ben-David, Mark J. Johnson, René M. Stulz</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29205</guid></item><item><title>When Uncertainty and Volatility Are Disconnected: Implications for Asset Pricing and Portfolio Performance</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29195</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yacine Aït-Sahalia, Felix Matthys, Emilio Osambela, Ronnie Sircar.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> We analyze an environment where the uncertainty in the equity market return and its volatility are both stochastic, and may be potentially disconnected. We solve a representative investor's optimal asset allocation and derive the resulting conditional equity premium and risk-free rate in equilibrium. Our empirical analysis shows that the equity premium appears to be earned for facing uncertainty, especially high uncertainty that is disconnected from lower volatility, rather than for facing volatility as traditionally assumed. Incorporating the possibility of a disconnect between volatility and uncertainty significantly improves portfolio performance, over and above the performance obtained by conditioning on volatility only.]]></description><author>Yacine Aït-Sahalia, Felix Matthys, Emilio Osambela, Ronnie Sircar</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29195</guid></item><item><title>What Do You Think About Climate Finance?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29136</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Johannes Stroebel, Jeffrey Wurgler.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> We survey 861 finance academics, professionals, and public sector regulators and policy economists about climate finance topics. They identify regulatory risk as the top climate risk to businesses and investors over the next five years, but they view physical risks as the top risk over the next 30 years. By an overwhelming margin, respondents believe that asset prices underestimate climate risks. We also tabulate opinions about the correlation between growth and climate change; social discount rates appropriate for projects that mitigate the effects of climate change; most influential forces for reducing climate risks; and, most important research topics.]]></description><author>Johannes Stroebel, Jeffrey Wurgler</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29136</guid></item><item><title>Can Monetary Policy Create Fiscal Capacity?</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29129</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Vadim Elenev, Tim Landvoigt, Patrick J. Shultz, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Governments around the world have gone on a massive fiscal expansion in response to the Covid crisis, increasing government debt to levels not seen in 75 years. How will this debt be repaid? What role do conventional and unconventional monetary policy play? We investigate debt sustainability in a New Keynesian model with an intermediary sector, realistic fiscal and monetary policy, endogenous convenience yields, and substantial risk premia. When conventional monetary policy is constrained by the ZLB during an economic crisis, increased government spending and lower tax revenue lead to a large rise in government debt and raise the risk of future tax increases. We find that quantitative easing (QE), forward guidance, and an expansion in government discretionary spending all contribute to lowering debt/GDP ratio and reducing this fiscal risk. A transitory QE policy deployed during a crisis stimulates aggregate demand.]]></description><author>Vadim Elenev, Tim Landvoigt, Patrick J. Shultz, Stijn Van Nieuwerburgh</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29129</guid></item><item><title>The Treasury Market in Spring 2020 and the Response of the Federal Reserve</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29128</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Annette Vissing-Jorgensen.</i> <p> <b>August 2021.</b> <p> Treasury yields spiked during the initial phase of COVID. The 10-year yield increased by 64 bps from March 9 to 18, 2020, leading the Federal Reserve to purchase $1T of Treasuries in 2020Q1. Fed purchases were causal for reducing Treasury yields based on the timing of purchases (which increased on March 19), the timing of yield reversal and Fed purchases in the MBS market, and evidence against confounding factors. Treasury-QE worked more via purchases than announcements. The yield spike was driven by liquidity needs of mutual funds, foreign official agencies, and hedge funds that were unaffected by the March 15 Treasury-QE announcement.]]></description><author>Annette Vissing-Jorgensen</author><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29128</guid></item></channel></rss>