<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSS by topics: Behavioral Finance</title><link>a link</link><description>RSS by topics: Behavioral Finance</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 09:08:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Moral Preferences of Investors: Experimental Evidence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29647</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jean-François Bonnefon, Augustin Landier, Parinitha R. Sastry, David Thesmar.</i> <p> <b>January 2022.</b> <p> We characterize investors’ moral preferences in a parsimonious experimental setting, where we auction stocks with various ethical features. We find strong evidence that investors seek to align their investments with their social values (“value alignment”), and find no evidence of behavior driven by the social impact of investment decisions (“impact-seeking preferences”). First, the willingness to pay for a stock is a linear function of corporate externalities, and is symmetric for positive or negative externalities. Second, whether charity transfers are contingent or independent on investors buying the auctioned stock does not affect their WTP. Our results are thus compatible with a utility model where non-pecuniary benefits of firms’ externalities only accrue through stock ownership, not through the actual impact of investment decisions. Finally, non-pecuniary preferences are linear and additive: willingness to pay for social externalities is proportional to the expected sum of charity transfers made by firms (even if some of these donations are negative).]]></description><author>Jean-François Bonnefon, Augustin Landier, Parinitha R. Sastry, David Thesmar</author><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29647</guid></item><item><title>What Drives Variation in Investor Portfolios? Evidence from Retirement Plans</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29604</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Mark L. Egan, Alexander MacKay, Hanbin Yang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We study empirical patterns in investment behavior using a comprehensive data set of defined contribution plans. Using plan-level portfolio allocation data for the near universe of 401(k) plans over the period 2009-2019, we document substantial differences in investment behavior across plans. Plans with wealthier and more educated participants tend to have higher equity exposure while plans with more retirees and minorities tend to have lower equity exposure. These patterns cannot be explained by differences in 401(k) menus or participation costs. To help interpret these facts, we use a revealed preference approach to estimate investors' expectations of stock market returns and risk aversion, where we allow investors to have heterogeneous risk aversion and subjective and potentially biased beliefs. We find that there is substantial variation in both beliefs and risk aversion across investors and over time, and that both sources of variation help explain investors' portfolio decisions. We also provide new evidence to understand how investors form beliefs. We find that investors extrapolate beliefs from past fund returns even when they initially allocate portfolios in new plans. We also find that investors extrapolate beliefs about the market from the past performance of their employer, which suggests that investor experience helps shape beliefs.]]></description><author>Mark L. Egan, Alexander MacKay, Hanbin Yang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29604</guid></item><item><title>Choice Overload? Participation and Asset Allocation in French Employer-Sponsored Saving Plans</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29601</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Marie Briere, James M. Poterba, Ariane Szafarz.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> This paper employs administrative data from one of the largest plan providers in France to investigate the role of plan and default characteristics in affecting whether employees participate in the plan and whether they accept its default investment option. The dataset includes information on the saving choices of 680,392 active employees at 1,610 firms. French employers have wide discretion in structuring employee saving plans.  All plans must offer medium-term investments, which cannot be accessed for five years.  Employers may also offer long-term investments that cannot be accessed until retirement.  When plans include a long-term option, participation is lower than when the plan offers only more liquid medium term investments.  The presence of a long-term saving option also reduces the take-up of the plan’s default investment allocation, which must include a long-term component.  One interpretation of the findings, consistent with the theory of choice overload, is that some employees are unwilling to forego the liquidity of the medium-term option but find it costly to make an active election when they opt out of the default, and therefore choose not to participate in the plan at all.]]></description><author>Marie Briere, James M. Poterba, Ariane Szafarz</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29601</guid></item><item><title>Attention, Social Interaction, and Investor Attraction to Lottery Stocks</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29543</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Turan G. Bali, David Hirshleifer, Lin Peng, Yi Tang.</i> <p> <b>December 2021.</b> <p> We find that among stocks dominated by retail investors, the lottery anomaly is amplified by high investor attention (proxied by high analyst coverage, salient earnings surprises, or recency of extreme positive returns) and intense social interactions (proxied by Facebook social connectedness or population density near firm headquarters). Such stocks’ lottery features attract greater Google search volume and retail net buying, followed by more negative earnings surprises and lower announcement-period returns. The findings provide insight into the roles of attention and social interaction in securities markets, and support the hypothesis that these forces contribute to investor attraction to lottery stocks.]]></description><author>Turan G. Bali, David Hirshleifer, Lin Peng, Yi Tang</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29543</guid></item><item><title>Mistakes in Future Consumption, High MPCs Now</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29517</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Chen Lian.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> In a canonical intertemporal consumption problem, I show how anticipation of future consumption mistakes leads to higher current marginal propensities to consume (MPCs). This result is driven by mistakes in future consumption's response to saving changes (i.e., changes in asset balances) and is independent of their specific behavioral foundations. My framework can accommodate many widely studied behavioral biases, such as inattention, present bias, diagnostic expectations, and near-rationality (epsilon-mistakes). This channel helps explain the empirical puzzle on high-liquidity consumers' high MPCs and can be significant. The same channel can also help explain other puzzles in intertemporal choices, such as violations of the fungibility principle, excess discounting of future income, and large risk aversion. Methodologically, I develop a general approach to study predictions of sophistication (i.e., the anticipation of future mistakes) independent of the underlying behavioral biases.]]></description><author>Chen Lian</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29517</guid></item><item><title>Technological Obsolescence</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29504</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Song Ma.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> This paper proposes a new measure of technological obsolescence using detailed patent data. Using this measure, we present two sets of results. First, firms' technological obsolescence foreshadows substantially lower growth, productivity, and reallocation of capital. This finding applies mainly for obsolescence of core innovation and embodied innovation, and it is stronger in competitive product markets. Second, in stock markets, high-obsolescence firms under-perform low-obsolescence firms by 7 percent annually. Using analyst forecast data, we show this is due to a systematic overestimation of future profits of obsolescent firms. The measure contains incremental information about firm innovation relative to measures focusing on new innovation.]]></description><author>Song Ma</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29504</guid></item><item><title>Zero Lower Bound on Inflation Expectations</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29496</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Dmitriy Sergeyev.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> We document a new fact: in U.S., European and Japanese surveys, households do not expect deflation, even in environments where persistent deflation is a strong possibility. This fact stands in contrast to the standard macroeconomic models with rational expectations. We extend a New Keynesian model with a zero-lower bound on inflation expectations. Unconventional monetary policies, such as forward guidance, are weaker. In liquidity traps, the government spending output multiplier is finite, and adverse aggregate supply shocks are not expansionary. A confidence-driven liquidity trap steady state with deflation does not exist.]]></description><author>Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Dmitriy Sergeyev</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29496</guid></item><item><title>Measuring Firm Environmental Performance to Inform Asset Management and Standardized Disclosure</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Nicholas Z. Muller.</i> <p> <b>November 2021.</b> <p> Investing according to environmental, social, and governance (ESG) criteria is gaining momentum. Most environmental performance indices focus only on the tonnage of carbon dioxide (CO₂) emissions. This paper proposes an index covering eight pollutants expressed in monetary damage. Inclusion of multiple pollutants reflects a broader range of reputational and regulatory risks. Monetization appropriately weights emissions. CO₂ dominates the mass of other pollutants, yet the marginal damages from other pollutants are larger than CO₂. In the U.S. utility sector from 2014 to 2017, indices which only track CO₂ mischaracterize firms’ environmental performance and underestimate its effect on financial outcomes relative to the multipollutant index. Dirtier firms exhibit lower share prices and higher forward returns. The effect is twice as large for the multipollutant index compared to CO₂. Analysts’ earnings forecasts for dirtier firms systematically undershoot actuals. Earnings errors are between three and five times more sensitive to the multipollutant index than to CO₂. The multipollutant index may suggest new management strategies to financial market participants relative to those based on carbon intensity. ESG disclosure standards based on the new index are more likely to affect financial outcomes, capital allocation decisions, and firm behavior than disclosure of carbon intensity.]]></description><author>Nicholas Z. Muller</author><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29454</guid></item><item><title>Racial Disparities in Access to Small Business Credit: Evidence from the Paycheck Protection Program</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Sabrina T. Howell, Theresa Kuchler, David Snitkof, Johannes Stroebel, Jun Wong.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> We explore the sources of racial disparities in small business lending by studying the $806 billion Paycheck Protection Program (PPP), which was designed to support small business jobs during the COVID-19 pandemic. PPP loans were administered by private lenders but federally guaranteed, largely eliminating unobservable credit risk as a factor in explaining differential lending by race. We document that even after controlling for a firm’s zip code, industry, loan size, PPP approval date, and other characteristics, Black-owned businesses were 12.1 percentage points (70% of the mean) more likely to obtain their PPP loan from a fintech lender than a traditional bank. Among conventional lenders, smaller banks were much less likely to lend to Black-owned firms, while the Top-4 banks exhibited little to no disparity after including controls. We use novel data to show that the disparity is not primarily explained by differences in pre-existing bank or credit relationships, firm financial positions, fintech affinity, borrower application behavior, or racial differences in rates of fraudulent PPP applications. In contrast, we document that Black-owned businesses’ higher rate of borrowing from fintechs compared to smaller banks is particularly large in places with high anti-Black racial animus, pointing to a potential role for discrimination in explaining some of the racial disparities in small business lending. We find evidence that when small banks automate their lending processes, and thus reduce human involvement in the loan origination process, their rate of PPP lending to Black-owned businesses increases, with larger effects in places with more racial animus.]]></description><author>Sabrina T. Howell, Theresa Kuchler, David Snitkof, Johannes Stroebel, Jun Wong</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29364</guid></item><item><title>Exposure, Experience, and Expertise: Why Personal Histories Matter in Economics</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Ulrike Malmendier.</i> <p> <b>October 2021.</b> <p> Personal experiences of economic outcomes, from global financial crises to individual-level job losses, can shape individual beliefs, risk attitudes, and choices for years to come. A growing literature on experience effects shows that individuals act as if past outcomes that they experienced were overly likely to occur again, even if they are fully informed about the actual likelihood. This reaction to past experiences is long-lasting though it decays over time as individuals accumulate new experiences. Modern brain science helps understand these processes. Evidence on neuroplasticity reveals that personal experiences and learning alter the strength of neural connections and fine-tune the brain structure to those past experiences ("use-dependent brain"). I show that experience effects help understand belief formation and decision-making in a wide area of economic applications, including inflation, home purchases, mortgage choices, and consumption expenditures. I argue that experience-based learning is broadly applicable to economic decision-making and discuss topics for future research in education, health, race, and gender economics.]]></description><author>Ulrike Malmendier</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29336</guid></item><item><title>The Asymmetry in Responsible Investing Preferences</title><link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w29288</link><description><![CDATA[<i>Jacquelyn Humphrey, Shimon Kogan, Jacob Sagi, Laura Starks.</i> <p> <b>September 2021.</b> <p> We design an experiment to understand how social preferences affect investment decisions through stock allocations and probability assessments. The major preference channel is asymmetric in social outcomes – although negative and positive responsible investment (RI) externalities have the same magnitudes, negative externalities have greater impact on investment choices. The effect is persistent, but heterogenous. We also find asymmetries in belief formation and learning constitute a secondary channel. Overall, our results are consistent with important stylized empirical facts and the predictions of recent RI theories that social preferences lead to different investment choices, but our analyses also suggest important future modeling directions.]]></description><author>Jacquelyn Humphrey, Shimon Kogan, Jacob Sagi, Laura Starks</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.nber.org/papers/w29288</guid></item></channel></rss>